>>Alex Komoroske: Hi. Welcome. Thanks for
coming back after lunch. We'll get started.
I'm Alex Komoroske.
>>Matthew McNulty: And I'm Matt McNulty.
>>Alex Komoroske: And we both work on Chrome
on the Open Web Platform team.
Now, before we get really started I just want
to reiterate that this is an intermediate
level talk, so if you saw Eric's talk just
before this, before lunch, you're probably
all set. If not, there are going to be a lot
of points where you're just scratching your
head, and what you want to do is review some
of the other specs and tutorials on some of
these emerging web standards afterwards.
>>Matthew McNulty: And all children should
leave the room as well.
[ Laughter ]
>>Alex Komoroske: So if you saw Eric's talk,
you're probably thinking to yourself, you
know, "Wow, web components sounds really cool.
Specifications are being finalized. Browsers
are starting to implement them." But...
>>Matthew McNulty: But if you're a web developer,
you're thinking, "I probably can't use these
things. Call me in a few years when I actually
can and when this is actually relevant to
me."
>>Alex Komoroske: So the good news for you
is actually that this stuff works in all modern
browsers today.
>>Matthew McNulty: So here I have a version
of TODOMDC.
>>Alex Komoroske: And if you don't know what
TODOMDC is, it's just a reference application.
It's something that people use to write this
application again in their framework to compare
it and see how it feels compared to other
frameworks.
>>Matthew McNulty: But the interesting thing
about this one, if I inspect elements, is
it uses web components.
So you see the entire thing is wrapped up
in a TD dash app tag. And if I go into settings,
I can click show Shadow DOM, leave, reinspect,
and you'll see now I can actually open that
node and the grayed-out document fragment
is actually a sign that you're in Shadow DOM
now. So this entire little world inside this
tag is encapsulated from the outside world.
There's a hard border at the edge.
>>Alex Komoroske: Okay. But so that's easy
because that's Chrome, so what about something
harder?
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. In this VM which
I've paused, because that seems to be the
best way to get Windows to stay up for this
period of time &mdash;
[ Laughter ]
>>Matthew McNulty: &mdash; for purposes of this
presentation I've got it here in IE as well
in Windows 8.
>>Alex Komoroske: So it's the same code using,
again, these concepts of Shadow DOM web components
that's working in IE.
So how did we do this? How did we make this
happen? Well, the answer is that we're impatient.
We're really excited about web components
but we didn't want to wait to use them until
they were in every modern browser.
The other important thing is we work on the
Chrome team where some of the folks who are
actively standardizing the web components
stuff in the standards bodies, and when you're
designing new web standards, it's really important
to experiment with them, especially if they're
very complex.
What you don't want is you work on a specification
for a while, you build consensus, you implement
it, you ship it, and then you use it and you
go, "Oooh, wow, that's really hard to use."
And so you want to experiment with this stuff
and feed that feedback directly back into
the standardization process before it gets
locked in.
So you want to, you know, improve these standards
and not just work around them.
So we started what was kind of a crazy experiment
to see if we could make this stuff work in
modern browsers. We started a project a number
of months ago on Github doing everything fully
in public. We called it Toolkitchen until
a few days ago when we renamed it Polymer.
>>Matthew McNulty: We renamed it a few times,
actually.
>>Alex Komoroske: If you were working on it
closely, there were two renames in short succession.
We've already gotten some really good community
participation from folks who have found out
about it and provided feedback. We're really
happy about that. And we've also been able
to provide feedback back into the specification
process to help identify some areas in the
specs that we thought needed to change.
>>Matthew McNulty: So we're focused on modern
browsers for a couple of reasons. Older browsers,
you just can't polyfill some of this stuff.
And really it's &mdash; you know, it's time for
a break. We want to move forward. And we don't
want anyone who is using this stuff to be
left behind, kind of like the current older
browsers that don't update.
You know, you're headed for trouble if all
do you is stare in the rearview mirror.
So this approach is hard. We didn't know it
would work. We actually didn't really know
it would work for the first six months or
so, whether we could actually get this stuff
working in a way that really emulated the
future platform in a way that we could work
together and form a coherent system. We've
been working with all the different standards
bodies and providing feedback, as Alex said.
Yeah.
>>Alex Komoroske: But the point is actually
that it does work today and it brings you
the future and allows you to build on top
of it today.
So the way I think about this is what's actually
implemented in browsers today is like the
bedrock. It's a solid foundation but it's
kind of uneven because different browsers
have different support for different things.
The answer to this is polyfills. Not a new
concept. A polyfill is a JavaScript library
that basically mocks out a future standard
so that you can use it before it actually
is deployed in all modern browsers.
The goal with polyfills is to have really
high fidelity, so that way, later you don't
even need it.
>>Matthew McNulty: So perfect fidelity is
not always possible in some of these things.
Everyone always goes, "Oh, but what about"
and they're usually right. So things like
styling scoping, encapsulation in any real
significant way, are just not possible in
JavaScript but we've gotten pretty close.
>>Alex Komoroske: So we'll go over these polyfills
very briefly.
These are each &mdash; almost all of these are
emerging standards so we only have a chance
to say about a sentence about each one. If
you are wondering what these are, check out
the specs, check out the tutorials to learn
more about these.
>>Matthew McNulty: So mutation observers allow
for the efficient observations of DOM, so
when new nodes are added or attributes are
changed. This one is actually already shipping
in most modern browsers.
>>Alex Komoroske: So the next one is pointer
events. This is a specification that unifies
the event models for touch and mouse. It allows
you to write the same code and have it run
on mobile devices and desktop devices as well.
In fact, everything we're showing you here
today works both on desktop and on mobile
devices.
>>Matthew McNulty: So Shadow DOM is a pillar
of web components. This brings encapsulation
to the platform for the first time. Which
is really, really, really big and we'll show
that to you a little bit. It's also incredibly
complicated, especially to grasp right away,
but the big &mdash; the big point is it gives you
the ability to encapsulate things within a
tag.
And so if you need to know more about that,
I refer you to Eric's talk that happened just
before this one, or just before lunch.
>>Alex Komoroske: The next one is custom elements.
This is another pillar of web components.
It allows you to define your own tags and
have them operate just like any other tags
in the browser. It allows you to create these
elements and put whatever you want inside
of them, even ones of arbitrary complexity,
and have them treated just like any other
tag that you're familiar with, like the video
tag or Canvas or whatever.
>>Matthew McNulty: HTML imports. This one
was known as a few different things. Link
rel imports, web components itself briefly
for a little bit, but now it's HTML imports.
And the big thing with this one, it allows
you to package CSS, JavaScript, HTML, into
a single module and import it into your app
and it allows reusability across multiple
applications or multiple parts of your application.
>>Alex Komoroske: So this next one is MDV,
which stands for "model driven views." This
is the only one in this list that isn't really
an emerging standard yet although hopefully
one day it will be.
It's something that allows you to do data
binding directly in HTML. And as we've been
playing with all of these, this is one that
really allows us to eliminate a lot of boilerplate
code in practice.
>>Matthew McNulty: So web animations unifies
CSS and SVG animations and exposes the primitives
beneath those and allows you to create really
complex animation sequences separate from
the things you want to animate. It's actually
a really, really cool project. It predates
when we started working on toolkitchen, now
polymer. And actually Mozilla, Google, Adobe,
were all collaborated on that polyfill and
it's included.
>>Alex Komoroske: So together, these form
a stable foundation that allows you to pretend
like you're living in the future and build
there. So the cool thing about polyfills is
that over time as the &mdash; as browser vendors
implement these features, the need for them
goes away, and so ultimately at some point
in the future you wouldn't even need this
layer at all.
>>Matthew McNulty: So and one of the other
great things about this is we designed this
to be a la carte. So you can use each individual
&mdash; each individual polyfill or you can combine
a couple together or you can take the entire
thing, and if you want, actually, to take
the entire platform and minimize a gzip version
of that, it's actually only 31K. So think
about that. That's actually the entire future
of the web platform for about the size of
an icon.
>>Alex Komoroske: Most of the future of the
web platform.
So we've been talking about modern browsers.
Let me define that real quick. This is our
compatibility chart for our polyfills. It
includes Chrome, Firefox, IE, Safari, also
their mobile variants.
We call these the evergreen browsers. These
are browsers that are modern. They support,
many of them, the new standards. They also
importantly keep their users updated by default.
So users don't have to do anything unusual
just to stay on the newest one. So the users
aren't going to live in the past for long.
When there's a new version, they'll just come
along to the new version, which is really
important.
Okay. So web components provides &mdash; this foundation
layer provides a lot like a utility belt that
allows you to build apps but it's not everything
you need. You need some higher-level stack
pieces to fit them together and really make
them work together.
>>Matthew McNulty: We realized we needed to
build a toolkit. So this toolkit, which we
call polymer, it weaves together all of the
lower level pieces of the platform into a
whole cloth for building applications. It's
also where we express our opinion on top of
that.
>>Alex Komoroske: So this layer, unlike the
layer below it which will disappear over time,
this layer will continue to exist because
it's not part of any spec. It's our opinion
on how to use these things productively together.
Although hopefully maybe if these kinds of
patterns become popular and other libraries
use them too, maybe this is something that
could be specified in a web standard in the
future, maybe.
>>Matthew McNulty: So we started out with
some core principles to build a new kind of
toolkit, right? One with the future in mind.
So this is &mdash; you know, we're leaving behind
the past. We've got these new toys to play
with. What can we do if we actually had all
of these things and does it actually work?
>>Alex Komoroske: So these principles are
use the platform, eliminate boilerplate, and
everything is an element.
>>Matthew McNulty: So use the platform. So
this is a big change, at least for me and
others who have built JavaScript frameworks
before. You know, for the most part, the web
has been not particularly great &mdash; a great
spot to build Webapps. The platform, like
Alex said &mdash; right? &mdash; it's rocky, it's uneven
on the bottom of the.
And, you know, as a result, a lot of really,
really talented JavaScript developers have
spent their time building frameworks and building
these entire worlds and separate render trees
and doing really kind of crazy amazing things
like using iFrames to force rendering behavior
in the browser, you know, just to get around
problems &mdash; problems on the platform.
So, you know, we were tasked very specifically,
you know, no tricks. So if you hit a problem
and, you know, something doesn't work well,
you know, we're on the Chrome team so we're
actually allowed to go to the guy around the
corner in the next cube and say, "Hey, can
you fix this?"
>>Alex Komoroske: "Let's file a bug. Let's
get that fixed."
>>Matthew McNulty: A bug, yeah. So we wanted
to use the platform, not just the existing
platform but this new platform. We have all
these new toys that we're being given. We
wanted to see what we could do with them.
>>Alex Komoroske: The next one is to eliminate
boilerplate. So on this team we're very, very
adamant about that, that you should only write
the code that's unique to your app and nothing
more. You shouldn't have to be recreating
these things every single time you're writing
an app.
>>Matthew McNulty: And everything is an element.
This one is really, really important but I'm
going to hammer it home about a hundred more
times so you can not pay attention to this
one.
So the idea is every single thing is a module,
right? And you use an element. And you build
applications out of bigger and bigger elements
made &mdash; made of more and more elements, up
to and including an actual app.
By doing this, you've got all these reasonable
little portions. You keep the developer's
context really local. You reduce bugs. And
it makes it so that, you know, from the perspective
of a developer at any given time, an application
can be arbitrarily &mdash; sorry, arbitrarily simple
and complex at the same time.
So we wanted a system that weaves together
the platform to enable component-based apps.
So everything is an element and every &mdash; and
all elements have Shadow DOM encapsulating
them.
Polymer makes building elements easier, and
from the outside &mdash; you know, from the inside,
you're building your own in polymer. From
the outside, it's just an element. It looks
like every other DOM element.
>>Alex Komoroske: So just like every other
DOM element, the way you pass in configuration
is via attributes and the way you pass things
out of it is via element, so from the outside
perspective, it's just an element.
>>Matthew McNulty: So this is an example of
polymer JS element. This one is a polymer
panels element, so all custom elements need
to have a dash in the name. That's the only
requirement. It used to be an X dash. But
this allows for different vendors to provide
their own prefix to things, and namespace
to things, and it's important to note this
is not XML namespacing. There's, you know,
no collision detection or things like that.
People just have to be on good behavior.
So in this case, it's a polymer panels app
that would provide like say a series of sliding
panels or a carousel or something like that.
So one of the first big features that we add
is declarative mapping of custom and DOM events
to methods within the element. So in this
case when a select event is fired, the panel
select handler element with that method name
&mdash; this is not code that's executed &mdash; will
be rerun on the actual element.
>>Alex Komoroske: So again, this makes it
easy to behave just like any other element
and pass things out via events.
>>Matthew McNulty: Yeah. And one of the nice
things we like about this is rather than like
what's currently in vogue with add event listener
and for security reasons, we've reestablished
a way of doing it in declarative. Kind of
the whole thing we're doing here &mdash; you know,
every single thing we do, we can also do imperatively
but we like the idea of the, you know, declarative
renaissance.
So the next thing is custom attributes. So
you've got custom elements, you need custom
attributes. This is the API that your element
exposes to the world.
And then one of the big things we add is data
binding and this is powered by MDV. This radically
reduces code complexity. We'll &mdash; we're going
to demo this in a little bit so we'll get
into it more.
And there's a whole bunch more, but this is
the big picture, and if you combine all of
this with all the new platform bits, you end
up with something pretty awesome.
>>Alex Komoroske: So as we're using this,
this already made it much easier to build
apps but we weren't satisfied because we were
realizing that we were rebuilding the same
kind of UI widgets again and again. And, you
know, every framework that wants to make an
easy-to-build app, they should help you build
UIs as well. We really need to build a set
of really great widgets, and so we've just
begun that a few weeks ago.
So I want to &mdash; this is a &mdash; this is the &mdash; sort
of completing this diagram.
I want to take a moment to reflect really
quickly on our approach.
So a lot of other frameworks are sort of forced
to do everything in script. They have to do
very, very, very clever engineering to replace
the pot from below them because it doesn't
do the things they need. So they end up building
their own parallel universes that don't inter-operate
very well because they've created their own
worlds.
What we were trying to do is fix the platform
and actually provide feedback back to the
platform, use the emerging standards.
And we &mdash; actually, one thing that's cool
about web components is that your interoperability
layer is just the DOM because an element is
an element, you know how to work it. And that
means that for the first time actually it's
possible for UI elements to be interoperable.
So you'll see in this diagram &mdash; it's actually
very, very hard to see here &mdash; there's other
boxes to the right of this, because other
UI elements could be built on top of some
of these layers or the foundation and inter-operate
with them. And we'll show you a little bit
more about that later.
They're &mdash; also in polymer, we've taken a
layered approach to everything.
So if you want to use our UI elements, great,
you get the whole stack. If you just want
to use a single polyfill by itself, cool,
just take that one.
Or anything in between.
So you can sort of figure out exactly how
much of this stuff you want to use.
So we've been talking a whole lot about this.
Let's &mdash; but rather than continue to just
talk about it, let's show you how all this
stuff works.
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. So here we have
a code editor. This is actually just the ace
code editor that we threw in a browser with
some other fancy stuff, and this is an element
definition.
So if you saw this from Eric's talk, it should
be somewhat familiar. This one is, you know,
ever so slightly different because it's a
polymer element. But the basics are still
there. So you've got an element tag. In this
case, the name attribute says it's my dash
element. That means that's the tag we're going
to create. So whenever this element definition
is around, the tag that says "my element"
will include all of this stuff.
The template tag is the DOM that you want
to stamp out when this &mdash; when this tag is
used.
There's actually a whole bunch of really cool
things you can do with template and iterate
and all these other things. I'd encourage
you to go look that up after this.
And then there's the script tag which provides
the prototype for the element and various
behaviors, if you want to add. So in this
case we'll just start out really simple and
I'll add a div, "hello world."
>>Alex Komoroske: So if you can't see it &mdash; I
know this is a big room. Back there, if you
can't see it, we can zoom it a little bit
maybe, but check it out. All this stuff is
in the repo afterwards. We can provide the
you the link. Sorry about that.
>>Matthew McNulty: There you go.
So now for previews. Look at that. "Hello
world."
>>Alex Komoroske: That is amazing. Absolutely
mind blowing.
[ Laughter ]
>>Matthew McNulty: But if I look inside it,
you can see here's our element definition
that we created and right next to it is an
actual instance of my element. And inside
that is Shadow DOM, so everything is encapsulated.
And inside that, you can see our div.
>>Alex Komoroske: So if you're scratching
your head, this is the point where we remind
you this is an intermediate level talk and
if this confuses you, you should check out
&mdash; learn more about Shadow DOM.
So in fact, to see this stuff, Shadow DOM
inspector, you actually have to check an option
to see it. It's not available by default because
it's encapsulation.
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. So one of the
cool things is you don't actually have to
use just normal DOM elements in here. You
can have custom elements that include other
custom elements.
So in this case, I'm going to switch it to
one of our custom elements, G ratings. And
this element is cool for a few reasons. It's
very easy to type, so I can't mistype it here.
It doesn't need any properties or attributes
by default.
And what it gives you is a bunch of stars
you can click on. It's like a star rating
thing. Preview it, and look at that. We've
got stars.
>>Alex Komoroske: So these are just custom
elements, so if you're looking at this in
the DOM as another library, it's just an element.
You know how to work it. Attributes in, events
out.
>>Matthew McNulty: Yeah. There it is still
in my element, and then here you can start
to see Shadow DOM within Shadow DOM and all
of the markup within.
All right. So this is pretty cool but you're
like, "Oh, you've got your own little tool."
>>Alex Komoroske: "Your own little universe
that you've built."
>>Matthew McNulty: "You're probably, you know,
cheating somehow."
So we can take the source for that document
we're creating, bring it over to JS bin, and
it's the same thing.
>>Alex Komoroske: It looks like a little bit
of boilerplate here. There is only a couple
of pieces that make are actually crucial to
make this work. So the point is it is very
easy to use this within other contexts.
So we believe you.
By the way, this is all HTML. But let's go
a little bit faster so we don't bore them.
>>Matthew McNulty: So it would be boring to
sit here and watch me write HTML. So we did
something to make it a little bit faster and
more interesting.
We built an element builder. So this is just
the product of the last few weeks. We know
we are not really planning on shipping a tool
any time soon. It allows you to build elements
and bind them together into new elements and
really explore it. It is a nice little showcase
for what we have built so far and the technology
underneath.
>>Alex Komoroske: So I am going to reiterate
that. This is just a demo tool. It is not
an ID. You don't need to use this to use polymer.
It is just for playing around with the stuff
and getting a feel for it.
>>Matthew McNulty: So we can rate Alex so
far.
>>Alex Komoroske: Oh, thank you.
>>Matthew McNulty: We can change it.
>>Alex Komoroske: Not so nice. Thank you.
>>Matthew McNulty: You can see I'm changing
things in here, the number of stars selected,
the values are changing over here in the property
inspector. This tool should be &mdash; this kind
of tool is pretty familiar for a lot of people.
You have got a palette down the left-hand
side. You have got a tool bar across the top
and then a property inspector down the right-hand
side.
>>Alex Komoroske: Can you flip to the code
real quick?
>>Matthew McNulty: So it is not doing anything.
It actually just changes the attribute in
the tag.
>>Alex Komoroske: Basically all this tool
is doing is just a convenience for piping
in those attributes to save you typing yourself.
It is not doing anything magic.
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. So that's the
tool to begin with.
Let's do something more interesting with MDV.
So if I pull out a few other widgets, let's
do some tabs and a menu and a caption. This
won't make any sense, but it will show something
really kind of interesting.
So I can tap around on these things. Tap around
on them independently. If I come over to the
code, you can see that when I inserted that,
I actually just inserted a bunch of custom
tags and even some normal native DOM tags.
So the tabs takes a bunch of spans. The menu
takes a bunch of menu items. And then the
caption is actually just a div.
So one of the really cool features of this
toolkit is MDV. MDV allows you to bind elements
together and attributes together without any
actual code.
So at first I'm actually going to add a variable
to the prototype of the element here.
>>Alex Komoroske: A property you would be
able to use just like any other JavaScript
object.
>>Matthew McNulty: I can add however many
I want. And then if I come up to any attribute
within the element, in this case "selected,"
I can use this double mustache syntax which
is MDV and say &mdash;
>>Matthew McNulty: So with this G menu, the
way you specify which one is selected again
is with an attribute just like any other element.
>>Matthew McNulty: So now the tabs and the
menu in this case both have a selected attribute.
That is not at all required. It is because
they both have the concept of what's selected
in the selected index.
I come back to the code now, except for that
one.
(Chuckles.)
There we go. Just had to clear the CSS.
You can see them connected together. And you
can actually do this right in the tool as
well. So instead of just a caption, I can
click this little linked and put in the same
thing. And now they're all tied together.
Now, I can take this entire thing and say
"publish," clear the canvas, and now the whole
thing is itself a custom element that I can
drag off the palette and it still goes together.
And not only that, you can see the myselected
property that I added to the prototype and
even the foo one, even though it doesn't actually
do anything.
All right. So we built a custom element and
all without doing any JavaScript actually.
>>Alex Komoroske: It is actually kind of cool,
right? We tie these things together. If you
look in the code view for this one as well,
you will see that this is just now a my element.
The stuff inside is sort of hidden away. You
pass the myselected that we defined in the
prototype just there as an attribute. It wires
all this stuff up together for you so you
don't have to write any script to get this
kind of behavior. It is pretty cool.
>>Matthew McNulty: One of the other really
cool things is you can make your own custom
elements. And one of the other uses for that
is you can wrap up existing functionality
on the Web and put it in a single tag. And
it is encapsulated from the rest of your page,
so you don't have any conflicts or system-level
dependencies that you're creating.
In which case, we'll show you one &mdash; really
crazy one from our friends at Mozilla actually.
They built a one megabyte PDF Viewer entirely
in JavaScript.
>>Alex Komoroske: Which is crazy but awesome.
>>Matthew McNulty: We have the complete works
of Chaucer in here. If you go to the code,
you can see it is actually just a single tag.
>>Alex Komoroske: This is kind of crazy, right?
Like, you are used to including all these
scripts and having these weird dependencies
and stuff. You just write a few characters,
one include, write a few characters, and you
have a PDF Viewer directly in your page. It
really changes how you think about architecting
your applications.
>>Matthew McNulty: We have got other ones
in here that we just threw again in the last
few weeks. We've got charts and things like
that.
>>Alex Komoroske: These are just open source
libraries other people have built.
>>Matthew McNulty: Again, they are just all
wrapped into a single tag. It gives you this
almost module pattern that you can use to
combine things from different vendors.
One the other neat things you can to do is
use Web animations, which we talked about
earlier. I can actually bring out a few slightly
fancier widgets.
Let's do a clock. So just for the demo, like,
you know, tags don't actually have to have
UI, right. Like, a script tag doesn't have
anything visual about it. But just for this
demo, we came over &mdash; actually we'll do flip
&mdash; and made it so these things have a UI so
we can click on them in the canvas and do
interesting things.
In this case, it is a flip animation. And
we can say, you know, let's flip the clock.
Let's do it for a second. Now, if I come back
here and click on it. Clock flips.
>>Alex Komoroske: So behind the scenes, this
is just using Web animations. Again, another
emerging standard.
But the cool thing about thinking about animations
configured via these non-visible elements
is that you can separate the animation that
you're defining from the element itself and
just sort of point at the other one.
The elements don't have to be visual. That's
one of the cool things when everything is
an element.
>>Matthew McNulty: Yeah, so &mdash; and one of
the other really cool things that Web animations
gives you is the ability to do really long,
really complex, intricate animations and separate
from what their target is, right? And you
can just define this and drag it out however
you want. You reuse it and all of that.
So, in this case, we have a whole group. So
you can say let's bounce the clock this time.
Let's flip the weather because it is not that
nice out. And let's change up the market because
I have run out of puns.
Now if I do it, you can see they do one after
the other. Or I can actually make it happen
in parallel.
So just a little taste of what you can do
with Web animations.
Another thing we're doing is experimenting
with responsive design and building it directly
into the widgets. I can come over here. This
is another version of the Sandbox, not full
screen, so I can actually change the window
size. If I come in here and I start shrinking
this down, you can see it has got a toolbar
across the top of the drop-down menu. And
if I shrink it small enough, hey, it drops
down to the bottom and splits because it says,
Hey, it is phone or tablet size now and automatically
flips to be a little menu that pops up that's
more of a phone size, full-screen, full-bleed
kind of treatment.
So this is not just theoretical, but we really
just got it started &mdash; just getting started
with this kind of element.
And, in fact, everything you see here works
on mobile, especially because we're using
pointer events. So we're not going to put
this on the camera or anything. But you can
actually on my iPad, if I can hold it straight
&mdash; drag stuff out on the palette from my iPad
and it just works.
>>Alex Komoroske: All this stuff is really
early. We just started playing around with
this. We are approaching this entire project
with a very mobile-first perspective.
The ideal we're working towards is that as
a developer, you write your code once, you
define, okay, this is a menu or what have
you and then it automatically adjusts across
mobile or desktop or tablet to do the right
thing for you.
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. So we've shown
that you can drag a bunch of elements out
to make other elements. You can bind them
together arbitrarily. You can use third-party
code.
Let's actually try to put all of this together
into something fun. So we have a YouTube widget.
We call this the "I'm feeling lucky" YouTube
widget because all it does is take the very
first query and play it. See the little Chrome
commercial.
I also call it the "I'm feeling risky" demo
widget.
>>Alex Komoroske: That's a wholesome commercial,
though, so we're okay.
>>Matthew McNulty: This is a cat video I was
using earlier in which I discovered last night
the people in the background were cursing.
I never had the sound on. So that one went
out the window. Let's give this one a border.
>>Alex Komoroske: It is just a normal element
so you can do whatever you want.
>>Matthew McNulty: Yeah, just a normal element.
And we can actually use the speech input in
here. And we combine the YouTube query instead
of using this plain Chrome commercial query
to the input's value.
Now if I come here and the sound system and
demo gods are in alignment, I can go "cats."
And we've got all the cats.
[ Applause ]
>>Alex Komoroske: Again, if you check out
this code, there is &mdash; great, now we have
distracting cats on the screen. Thank you,
Matt.
[ Laughter ]
>>Alex Komoroske: If you check out that code,
it is just using that MDV syntax to plug those
things together. The magic isn't from the
Sandbox app. The magic is from the platform
and that layer &mdash; that sugar layer that we
call polymer.
>>Matthew McNulty: We can do multiple cats
across the screen and really annoy Alex.
>>Alex Komoroske: So all this stuff is great.
But you have seen this kind of thing before.
Other frameworks have done similar kinds of
things.
What is cool about this Web components approach
where you have actual encapsulation between
them is it allows for the first time the potential
for components from of different sets to intermingle
seamlessly.
So in this world, interoperability layer is
the DOM. And everyone knows how to use the
DOM, how to pass an attribute to receive events
out. Again, the polyfill &mdash; the polymer library
as well is layered, so you can take just the
parts you want.
>>Matthew McNulty: So one of the cool things
we have been doing lately is our friends at
Mozilla have been building X tags in their
X tags library which is similar in concept
to the polymer widgets on top of the same
foundation layer that we showed you before.
>>Alex Komoroske: They are experimenting with
using one of our polyfills in their system
as well.
>>Matthew McNulty: Yeah. So it took us no
time at all to put them in the palette, and
I can actually drag out some of their widgets
here.
>>Alex Komoroske: So let me just emphasize
this. These are widgets that come from a separate,
a different framework that are also built
on top of Web components. So we can just seamlessly
use them in the same environment, in the same
app. This is kind of mind blowing, right?
This is very new.
>>Matthew McNulty: And one of the really cool
things is because this is just Web components
and these are just elements and you can bind
them together just like any other DOM elements,
we can take our toggle button and we combine
its value to the X tag switch. Check property.
And now it will actually play together.
>>Alex Komoroske: So that's two separate libraries
playing together seamlessly. So we think that
this interoperability potential for Web components
is a really big deal.
If you think about everything as an element,
you can have small building blocks, package
them up into larger building blocks. Before
you know it, you have entire reusable applications
all in one tag.
>>Matthew McNulty: So up to and including
this entire Sandbox application, which was
built using polymer. And as a result, we put
it in the palette.
[ Laughter ]
And we can pull it out.
[ Applause ]
>>Alex Komoroske: That's cool, but we must
go deeper.
>>Matthew McNulty: All right. Everyone get
your totems ready. We have had an inception
reference.
>>Alex Komoroske: That's pretty cool. This,
in the past, would have required very careful
planning, following all the rules, all this
kind of stuff.
With Web components and polymer, you just
get this kind of encapsulation for free. It
actually &mdash; so we've started building this
app just a few weeks ago actually as the foundation
layers got pretty solid. We were amazed how
quickly we could build it because when you
are using these concepts to build elements
and then larger elements out of them, you
are so much more productive. It is like a
whole new world. It is really cool.
>>Matthew McNulty: So that's polymer and Sandbox
as it exists right now. If you are adventurous
and unafraid of living on the bleeding edge
&mdash; and I would like to emphasize "bleeding
edge" &mdash; this is a particular version of Canary
that is working right now.
We encourage you to check it out. It is all
on Github. It is all open right now.
>>Alex Komoroske: We started this as an experiment
at the beginning to see what we could do.
But the deeper we've gone, the more and more
excited we've gotten, the more that we feel
like this is sort on the cusp of something
big with Web components.
We really believe that with Web components,
developers will be in order of magnitude more
productive building more and better apps.
So we pulled together a video that we think
&mdash; that we hope will get you as excited about
this future we are going towards as we are.
[ Video playing. ]
[ Music ]
>>Alex Komoroske: So that's what we've got.
You can find all this stuff at our Web site,
polymer-project.org. Learn more, provide feedback,
please, please, please. Ask us questions.
Provide comments. File bugs. We'd love to
get your participation. Thanks.
[ Applause ]
Now we got time for questions. So...
>>> I'm curious, I'm looking at what you have
here. And I'm thinking back to MooTools and
Jquery and how we got query selector all standardized
out of that. And I'm wondering when you look
at something like Angular that has a lot of
similar concepts, how this interplays. If
you see Angular in the future as being another
sugar layer on top of something like polymer?
Or if it Web components replaces Angular?
>>Alex Komoroske: So we aren't from the Angular
team. There might be a few folks from that
team in the audience. They are aware of this
stuff. They have been playing around with
Web components, providing feedback back to
the standardization process as well.
Again, one of the approaches with polymer
that's really important is the layered approach.
That means that other frameworks could take
just one polyfill or all of them or what have
you. So I imagine that, you know, maybe that's
something that other frameworks might want
to experiment with, is building on top of
those layers, if they want. I mean...
>>> Do you see the Web components specifications
replacing the need for a lot of the &mdash; the
Embers and the Angulars and things that are
popular now?
>>Alex Komoroske: I think that's the wrong
way of thinking about it. I think that the
Web components provides a lot of the utility
belt. There is always that need for sort of
that opinion to weave all that stuff together.
And I think that frameworks will always have
a place in this world because you are going
to need it to help you build your apps.
>>> Okay.
>>Alex Komoroske: It brings you far but not
all the way.
>>Matthew McNulty: I mean, It is extremely
likely that they will have to use less code
to do what they're doing, which is great for
them, great for everyone else. But yeah.
>>Alex Komoroske: I guess we got one in the
back there.
>>> Actually, I was going to ask about Angular,
too, but I think it got answered.
So my other question would be, then, is this
something that you can &mdash; I mean, obviously
you're using Canary, you're using a very advanced
build. Is this something that you expect we'll
need to use only when we can tightly control
the environment in which it is running?
I came in a little late. So backwards compatibility
is my question.
>>Alex Komoroske: Just to reiterate actually,
the whole approach we're taking is building
a layer of polyfills that sort of mocks out
the future. Matt's using Canary so we can
show you real Shadow DOM being used. But this
stuff should work across all modern browsers,
IE, Safari, Firefox, Chrome.
And over time as they implement these standards,
that sort of foundation layer will get thinner
and thinner.
>>> So when you say "modern browsers," I assume
there will be a level that we will need to
test for and then &mdash;
>>Alex Komoroske: That's correct. One of the
goals here is to really live like we are in
the future. And if you are staring in the
rearview mirror you aren't headed for trouble.
We want to make sure we can actually assimilate
the future in a high fidelity way.
>>> When you pulled up the X code bits from
the Mozilla team, you said &mdash;
>>Alex Komoroske: X tags.
>>> Sorry?
>>> X tags. You said it was significant because
you are pulling that in from a third-party,
you know, another vendor. Where's the actual
technical significance there if they're kind
of just doing the same thing? I didn't see,
like, a threshold between polymer and X tags.
>>Matthew McNulty: So, generally, if you wanted
two libraries to play together previously,
they had to either be built very specifically
to do that and not introduced system-level
dependencies or they would collide and you
would just have to get lucky, right?
The idea is with these things being encapsulated
is that you don't have those system-level
dependencies and really the world inside of
that element, which is what's using Mozilla's
code, is completely separate from the world
outside of that element.
So you can mix and match these together things
a lot easier without having to dealing with
those collisions.
>>Alex Komoroske: Before Web components, you
had to make everything in script. So you had
conventions for what it means to be a component.
Everyone's conventions have to align for them
to be interoperable.
With Web components, people can align their
conventions on Web components, the standards,
and then that makes them interoperable much
more easily.
>>> So did you have another library you pulled
in to use those X tags? And they just co-exist
then because they are creating DOM elements
that are all happy together.
>>Alex Komoroske: Theoretically, you could
just have it as an include. You can include
a component &mdash; in the future, you can include
a component from polymer's UI library. You
can include a component from X tags. You could
intermingle the two or a third-party &mdash; or
a framework that's yet to be created.
>>Matthew McNulty: It is all in that HTML
import.
>>> So you lie an aspect that's above polymer
and everything else that was significant in
that respect to X tag versus your components?
>>Alex Komoroske: Yep.
>>> Gotcha. Thank you.
>>> So I would confirm a simple question.
This polymer also works with Chrome Packaged
Apps?
>>Matthew McNulty: Mm-hmm.
>>Alex Komoroske: Does it work right now?
>>Matthew McNulty: Right now it does not work.
The way we did the polyfill violates the SP.
>>> I see.
>>Matthew McNulty: So Chrome apps is very
specific about that.
>>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>>Matthew McNulty: But in the very near future,
once the HTML Imports feature, which is the
thing that's loading things from across domains,
is done natively, which is pretty soon, then
it will work.
>>Alex Komoroske: HTML imports is be &mdash; just
started being implemented in Chrome.
>>> (inaudible).
(Speaker off microphone.)
>>Alex Komoroske: So you can still use &mdash; as
(saying name) was pointing out, you can use
document.register even if you can't use some
of these other pieces like HTML imports.
>>> Thanks.
>>Alex Komoroske: We got one in the back.
>>> Yeah. You were talking about modern browsers.
I was wondering if you could elaborate on
mobile support.
>>Matthew McNulty: So mobile, it is mobile
Safari and Chrome, Chrome for Android.
>>> And Android browser?
>>Alex Komoroske: Chrome for Android.
>>Matthew McNulty: Chrome for Android at the
moment is the only one we're testing out.
>>> Okay, thanks.
>>Alex Komoroske: Again, it is very early
days.
>>> Several years ago there was actually a
similar technique that was to achieve the
similar level of encapsulation, which is XML
plus XSLT.
The essential of that is &mdash; the picture of
that is essentially you will create a heavy
element-focused, say, Web interface instead
of having to take care of all the underlayers.
What would you compare that to Web components?
>>Alex Komoroske: I think there's been a number
of things that are similar to Web components
in the past. None of them have really stuck
around for various reasons. There is the things
like XBL, which is still used actually in
parts of Gecko. You've got things like the
HTC stuff for Microsoft. You have got a bunch
of other things that aims to solve all similar
kinds of problems. Web components is now like
an emerging set of specs that is &mdash;
>>Matthew McNulty: So the difference here
is that you're using the same technologies
you already use on the Web today.
>>Alex Komoroske: Yes.
>>Matthew McNulty: You are using HTML, CSS
and JavaScript. There is actually nothing
new here, whereas XSLT, I did a whole framework
in XSLT years ago. And that was &mdash; to debug
that was one of the more insane things I have
ever done in my life.
>>> Great, thank you.
>>Alex Komoroske: We're actually out of time,
I believe. If you have more questions, you
can come find us up here after the talk. Thanks.
[ Applause ]