MALE SPEAKER: Thank
you very much, Andrew.
So, folks, we have the
privilege, the challenge,
and the &mdash; well, yes,
it is a challenge &mdash;
of having a very
broadly scoped topic,
but we're going to be
exciting, lively, and vibrant,
and we need you.
We need you to
participate in that.
So lots of interaction,
please, from everybody.
Let me introduce my
panel, first of all.
I'm going from the right here.
We have Andrew Spooner, who's
UX Evangelist at Microsoft.
We have Jeni Tennison, who is
CTO at the Open Data Institute.
To my left, we
have Scott Jenson,
who does user
experience at Google.
And who's next?
Oh, it's Tom over there.
Tom Ashworth is a front-end
developer over at Twitter.
And Alice on the end there
does user experience stuff
for the government
digital service.
I think we are &mdash;
ALICE: Well, I'm front-end
developer at [INAUDIBLE]
MALE SPEAKER: I'm so sorry.
Carried away in
my own excitement.
We'll probably cover some
things that have already
been covered today,
but I'm hoping
we'll cover them from a
slightly different perspective.
So we've already
talked, for example,
about varying device
sizes and so on.
But we are looking for
broadening that topic out,
I guess, and looking
to future case.
Remember, we're talking
about the future,
so every opinion is valid.
[LIGHT LAUGHTER]
Well, nearly every opinion.
I'm trying hard to let go of
that reference to being older
than Meg.
What do you think?
SCOTT JENSON: Actually,
is Gareth here?
Is he still here, the
guy who said that?
AUDIENCE: No, he ran off.
SCOTT JENSON: He ran off.
Well, collectively,
everyone here that's over 37
would wish to say,
just fuck you.
[LAUGHTER AND APPLAUSE]
MALE SPEAKER: Just to
verify my own antiquity,
I want to make sure
that you understand.
My first build system
was, in fact, a shoe box,
which helped me to keep
the punched cards in order.
[LAUGHTER]
The other thing I want to say
in this rather lengthy preamble,
before I introduce
you to Jeni, is
that you've heard
people say, when they've
been asked to ask
their questions,
oh, this isn't what I wrote.
I'm expecting that quite a few
people who I call on will say,
I have no idea what
this even means.
It bears no relation whatsoever
to what I wrote down.
Now this is not &mdash;
we did actually
try to keep it
thematically coherent,
so the people who are
asking the questions
may have some words in
there &mdash; Dan's nodding there.
There are some words
in your question, Dan,
that you did originally write.
[LAUGHTER]
Not next to each other,
and not in the same order.
Right, so Jeni, Jeni, can you
please tell us, when next?
JENI TENNISON: OK.
So can I have my
slides up, please?
This, no, maybe
it's not plugged in.
It's on the screen here.
It's just not on
the screen there.
MALE SPEAKER: Oh,
do you need to &mdash;
JENI TENNISON: Maybe
this is not plugged in?
MALE SPEAKER: Ah, yeah,
it's not plugged in.
[INAUDIBLE]
JENI TENNISON:
Thank you, Derrick.
Great, sorry for
that slight delay.
Right, so the
topic of future web
is a rather broad one &mdash;
the future being very much
longer than the past.
Hopefully.
[LAUGHTER] Oh god,
what have I done there?
Touch wood, right.
So thinking about the
future web &mdash; obviously,
the first person to ask
about where the web might go
would be &mdash; Chrome, come on.
[INAUDIBLE] This is not good.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
JENI TENNISON: I think
I might need to use it.
This is using
reveal.js, by the way.
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] We
need the future faster.
JENI TENNISON (LAUGHING): We
do need the future faster.
Sorry about this.
Derrick, [? use ?] alternative.
Ay yai yai.
DERRICK: What did you
do to my computer?
JENI TENNISON:
[GROANS HELPLESSLY] [LAUGHS]
[SCATTERED APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
We are living in the future.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
JENI TENNISON: Excellent,
that looks much better.
DERRICK: Do you wanna try?
Oh, it's not up on
the screen, now.
Here we go.
JENI TENNISON: Okey-dokey.
Right.
Yeah, it looks better.
Right, thank you.
So let's ask TimBL, now.
Of course, thinking
about asking TimBL
what the future of the
web holds &mdash; of course,
he did his Ask Me
Anything on Reddit,
where he asked what
was one of the things
that you never anticipated
about the internet,
and famously replied, kittens!
So, in terms of
predicting what's
going to happen
in the future web,
I can predict that
there will still
be kittens on the
web &mdash; and pussies, too.
[GRADUALLY MOUNTING LAUGHTER]
But &mdash; I want to focus on
three themes, three trends,
that I think are going to be
important as we go forward
as web developers, and look
at those in terms of what that
means for us when we're
developing web applications.
Those three themes
are going to be
more sensitivity around our
personal information, more data
being available, and as we've
touched on many times today,
more devices.
So, more sensitivity,
first of all.
Ed Snowden.
One of the things that
has happened recently
that has changed the way in
which we think about the web is
the revelations
around the Ed Snowden
came about what the
NSA is looking at,
what GCHQ is looking at.
And I found this on
Wikipedia, fantastic
little diagram &mdash; SSL
added and removed here.
This is the stuff
that we can get into,
guys, at the back end of Google,
where there's no encryption
and we have free reign.
What does this mean
in terms of how
we design our systems,
our web applications?
What does it mean in terms
of these revelations,
this thinking about where our
private information is going?
What does that mean for us?
Well, there's loads of policy
implications, loads of things
that we can think of at a
legislative level, or a policy
level.
But there are also
some technical ones.
I'm on the technical
architecture group at the W3C,
and one of the things that
has come up several times
without any kind of resolution
or in-depth thinking
is what we do around
permissions on the web.
How do we balance the need for
you to know that you are being
looked at through your
video camera on your laptop,
with it not being so much
in your face that you cannot
interact with whatever
the application is?
How do we balance up
the need to request,
on a case-by-case
basis, information
about your location,
with the irritation
of being requested on
a case-by-case basis
about your location?
How do we get around
these terrible kinds
of permission interfaces
that everybody
just clicks through and ignores?
Everybody being
everybody who doesn't
wear a tin foil hat, that is.
So that's one set of questions.
How do we handle
those permissions
when we have lots of
ways of tracking us?
Another area that
I wanted to raise
was, how do we move away from
these centralized services that
are so vulnerable to a single
point of failure, if you like,
in our private data?
So I'm particularly interested
in a couple of activities
that are going on around this &mdash;
around unhosted web apps.
The idea of having a web
application over here
that operates on data
over here, and you
can control how your data
gets accessed by that web app.
It doesn't actually hold
all your data itself.
And also the work
of Redecentralize,
which explores a
lot of these issues,
and I've encouraged
you to have a look at.
How do we get to a web that
isn't as centralized as it
currently is, because
of these sensitivities
that we have about
our personal data
being collected in
huge databases which
are vulnerable to attack?
So that was my first area.
Second area is about data.
Now, so far during
the day, the focus
has really been on what happens
within a browser context.
Where I work, at the Open Data
Institute, all I hear about
is data.
All I hear about is
smart cities and the data
that you can get from
devices and sensors
within a road network
in smart cities.
This is Smart City
logo land, right?
We talk about home automation
and the extra information
we can get about our homes'
interactions with home systems,
sensors &mdash; more data coming
in from our home systems.
We talk about quantified
self &mdash; wearable computing that
monitors us constantly,
that provides
streams and streams of data.
We talk about open
data, naturally,
at the Open Data
Institute, more government
data being made available.
Also, from companies,
data being made available
that we can all use.
We talk about big
data, massive amounts
of fast-moving, variable data.
I love the way that, in
my search for big data &mdash;
see that McDonald's sign?
Why?
I don't know.
Anyway, data.
So, we talk about medical
data, defense data, decadata,
whatever that is.
Morning data, noon data,
afternoon data, and night data.
Everything is data.
So, what does this
mean for the web, when
we have so much more
data being passed around?
So much more streaming
data, so much more big data.
HTTP, as a protocol, is not
good for this kind of streaming.
It's not good for these
kinds of big files.
So what other
protocols are we using?
What other protocols do we need?
And how do we make them
play nicely with the web?
How do we make them play well
with HTML pages and HTTP?
The web was made
for docu &mdash; ments.
[CHUCKLES]
So is JSON the pinnacle
of data on the web?
Is Jason really all that we need
for expressing data on the web?
I don't think so.
The other question
I'd like to raise
is what does a native
data browser look like?
What happens currently when you
have data that's made available
on the web is that you have
to create your own component,
your own kind of visualization.
We have things like this, which
are data tables, JavaScript
plugin, that makes everything &mdash;
that streams data in,
that makes it sortable,
filterable, pageable,
and so on.
But what about moving to more
integrated data and documents,
using the kinds of
technologies within D3?
What does this mean
for us on the web?
What kinds of components?
What kinds of web
components could we
build that natively
work with data?
Those are the kinds
of questions that I
think are interesting
for the future.
Third area &mdash; more devices.
This is the area that we've
touched on loads today.
So we have a browser that's
stopped working again.
Come on.
More devices.
Give me it.
Come on.
[INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
JENI TENNISON: OK, so we have
more devices that don't work.
Oh, that is completely
interaction.
[INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
DERRICK: Do you know
what number it was at?
JENI TENNISON: Yeah, it's fine.
It's fine.
I know how to get to it quickly.
OK.
More devices.
Hey!
[APPLAUSE]
All right!
Phones, tablets &mdash; yes, that's a
Windows tablet &mdash; TVs, watches,
fridges, cars.
And all of these devices have
differences in their size,
in their resolution,
in their connectivity,
in their processing power, in
their modes of interaction &mdash;
as we've already talked about &mdash;
and in their context of use.
Huge variety, massive variety,
of ways in which we as humans
will interact with the web.
And of course that means
that we need this responsive
design plus plus, right?
Not only responsive
layout, but responsive
images, responsive
interactions, changing
based on the
devices that we use.
Responsive storage &mdash;
different ways
of storing the
information, and knowing
whether you're going to go on
and offline intermittently,
or whether you're going to have
a constant internet connection,
for example, will
change the way in which
we design our web applications.
Right, and a final thought.
We're currently dominated by
four particular web browsers,
and fewer rendering engines.
[INAUDIBLE]
JENI TENNISON: Well, OK.
[LAUGHTER]
And perhaps we should be
dominated by one more,
yeah all right.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] Blink.
JENI TENNISON:
[LAUGHS] It is Blink.
It's the same &mdash; same
rendering engine.
So, my closing question
would be are we agile enough?
Right?
Have we got enough
small pieces loosely
joined to enable us to adjust
to the changing future?
Can the web that we
know be disrupted
by the next best
thing, or have we
built something that is
too big to be taken down?
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
MALE SPEAKER: Thank
you very much, Jeni.
I anticipate a future in which
Jeni will give her presentation
using web technology with fewer
than three different browsers.
[LAUGHTER]
But I don't expect
it will come soon.
Right.
Jeni, thank you, that was great.
And hopefully we can
follow up on some
of your themes through
some of the questions
that we have put
through the wringer.
For the final time today,
at least in this role,
I'm going to call
on Andrew Betts &mdash;
this time to read a question
that he had nothing to do with.
ANDREW BETTS: That it's
very true, actually.
And I have no more
questions, I promise you.
What is the role of the web
in the world of wearables
with no screen?
MALE SPEAKER: OK,
so the question
is what is the role of the
web in a world with wearables
but no screen?
This is a reference to the
fact that the web is primarily
a visual thing &mdash; in
its output, at least.
We've talked about
different input modalities.
What about different
output modalities?
Jeni, do you want to
kick us off on this one?
JENI TENNISON: [BREATHES DEEPLY]
Just recovering.
MALE SPEAKER: Oh, I'm sorry.
JENI TENNISON: It's OK.
MALE SPEAKER: Jeni, calm down.
JENI TENNISON: So,
it's one of my bugbears
that we focus on browsers.
We focus on screens,
and we don't
think about the other ways
in which all sorts of agents
might interact on the web.
And I think wearables is just
one kind of example of this,
but there are lots of
other kinds of agents
that we need to
be thinking about,
and understand that they
live on the web, too.
And they consume
web content, too.
And so, wearables &mdash; you've got
a difference in input modality,
but you've also got a difference
in output modality, which
I think changes the way in which
we need to think about how we
design our pages in the
same way as we talked
about accessibility issues
in the last session.
Sorry that wasn't very &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: No,
that was great.
Thank you.
Alice, I know that
you've done a lot of work
on the internet of things, yeah?
ALICE: Yeah.
MALE SPEAKER: How does this
strike you in that context?
ALICE: Well, I think
the web is going
to continue in the
way it currently
does in a world without
screens, because, as Jeni said,
there are already plenty of
things that don't have screens.
And there'll be new things
that don't have screens,
and some of those will be
objects that we currently
understand &mdash; like watches &mdash; that
have a sort additional &mdash; have
been elevated by having
the web put into them.
But then, there might be
some completely new invented
things &mdash; a middle ground
that you would never
have thought about
before you were
able to put the web into stuff.
And there are &mdash; I
used work for Berg,
and so we made Little
Printer, and we made a mistake
by calling it Little
Printer, because it's not.
Well, it is a printer,
but that's not
it's primary function, and
you would never really want
Little Printer
without the internet.
And in that way, it's
sort of a new product,
rather than an internet
fridge or something like that.
But Little Printer
doesn't have a screen,
unless you count
the receipts paper
that it prints on as a
screen, which we mischievously
say it is sometimes.
MALE SPEAKER: Thanks for that.
Go ahead, Scott.
SCOTT JENSON: If I
could just poke fun
at the community a
little bit, though.
Because right now, I don't think
that the web community even
could get its head wrapped
around the web on a watch &mdash;
let alone a web not
on a screen at all.
I think the web has never
recovered from the fact
that screens started
getting smaller.
They continually got bigger,
and basically just &mdash; maybe
they just didn't
worry about things.
And then when it
reversed direction,
we collectively lost our minds.
And we still haven't
recovered from that.
And so this idea that
we have to have one size
fits all works great,
as long as you're
willing to scroll
everything 20 pages.
But if you want to have &mdash;
I hate to get into the web
app versus web page thing,
because it's a waste of &mdash; you
know.
But the fact is
that we are trying
to make things that
are more interactive,
and the web has not got its head
wrapped around that quite yet.
And so I do think we have
a lot of soul-searching
to do to figure out
what interaction
means on multiple devices.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, and so to
summarize some of the points
here, what we're saying
is, we haven't even
got to grips with
what we've got.
But I would come
back and say, hey,
but you haven't
seen anything yet.
So we'd better hurry up
and make up our minds
about what we're gonna do.
I can see Remy on the queue.
Let me take Remy and
come back to you.
REMY: Yes, this
is kind of linked
to the question I
had before, but you
mentioned how to [INAUDIBLE].
I don't get how my
phone is of the web.
It could &mdash; it can, I
think, talk over TCP IP,
and it can talk to a web server,
but in a proprietary format.
There's no webiness
that I can see there.
There's no way of
me getting into it.
MALE SPEAKER: Right, I'm
going to cut you off there,
because we're going to come
back to this as a topic later.
So I'll let you back in there.
[INAUDIBLE]
MALE SPEAKER: Fascinating
though your point was,
we will be coming back to it.
Does it qualify as
a web device is not
a purely syntactic
argument, I don't think.
Tom?
TOM ASHWORTH: I think
we, as a web community,
have good things to
say to the people who
are building these
wearable devices.
We may not be able to put
our technology stuck on them.
So, you know, you're not
going to find a headless web
browser running on
a Fitbit, but we
can say if you make
URLable resources
available and connected
to each other,
we know that's a good thing.
We can point out
to the people who
are building these
things that that
has some really
positive benefits.
And if we give things URLs
and we make them addressable
and we make them accessible,
even if it's JSON and not HTML,
but we use the
principles of the web,
and to some extent,
the internet &mdash;
then I think we can have
a really positive impact,
as the web community,
on whatever comes
over the next few years in terms
of wearable devices and things
that don't have screens.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, Andrew.
ANDREW SPOONER: Yeah, I
think inherent to the web
is the presentation format.
That presentation that
says think of the web
without a screen I think
is a little bit weird.
JENI TENNISON: Completely
disagree, but carry on.
ANDREW SPOONER: That's good.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: You
yourself were talking
about music and
notation and so on.
What's wrong with
a web of music.
Nothing's wrong
with a web of music,
but I think where we've
got all of this data
in a particular format
that we can access,
and we can use web languages
in order to talk to data
and in order to talk to
devices, but I don't see it
as the web on those devices.
MALE SPEAKER: Jeni, go on.
JENI TENNISON: So,
the reason I disagree
is that for me, the main
definition of the web
is use of HTTP.
It isn't the use of HTML.
And if you count
the use of HTTP,
you can be sending
data over HTTP,
which needn't be shown
on a screen, which
could be interacted with
through a wearable device
or in any other kind of way.
If we tie the web
as only being HTML,
I think we make a mistake.
ANDREW SPOONER: Yeah.
And I'm not getting
into the protocols,
but what the web is to
me &mdash; it has a presentation,
and it's something very visual.
But we can certainly
use the content,
and we can use the
languages that we've
got in order to
interact with devices.
But maybe we're getting crossed.
MALE SPEAKER: Right, OK, I
think we could continue on this,
and I'm very sorry to put
these on the queue here.
But we are going to move
on to the next topic
now, because we've
got too much to cover.
We just have.
I'm going to call, again &mdash;
possibly for the final time
today &mdash; Christopher, you've
been an active participant.
I hope I didn't mangle your
question beyond your ability
to read it.
CHRISTOPHER: Yes, if you'll
allow me to just preface
this &mdash; the reason I'm
asking this question
is I've actually recently
had experience with this.
But also, when we
talk about the future,
we focus a little bit too
much on the text side,
and not about the audience side.
So basically my question
is, the future of the web
will see a rising
important in automizing
[INAUDIBLE] with Eastern
China and working
with their national firewall.
Many popular embeddable
services, such as YouTube,
are blocked over there.
How do we accommodate different
nationalities' to privacy,
sensitive content, and
inappropriate content,
and so on.
And there's also the
technological barriers
to think about as well.
MALE SPEAKER: Jeni, I'm going to
ask you to leap in here again,
because this is, I think,
directly keying off
one of your principle points.
JENI TENNISON: And
I think it was also
because nobody else wanted to
touch it with a barge pole.
[LAUGHTER]
So, on the internet,
then the typical way
in which we move
around those barriers
is that we subvert them.
That tends to be what happens.
We tend to work around
those kinds of issues.
And I don't have
direct experience
of the issues in China.
I can't really speak to them.
I think that the issues about
how we internationally come up
with some kind of understanding
about how &mdash; when we have lots
of different laws
around privacy,
around data
protection, and so on,
how we internationally
handle that
is a very interesting question.
I've seen people
from Africa talk
about wanting to have
legislation in their countries
that explicitly
precludes anybody looking
at data within servers
that are in their countries
to make them a more attractive
option for people who
are building web applications
to use servers in their country,
for example.
So we might start
to see an arms race
between different
nationalities as they
try to provide a
more interesting web
environment for
people to use &mdash; maybe.
The other kinds of
things that I think
are interesting to
think about &mdash; what
TimBL said at the 25th
anniversary of the web just
the other week.
Talking about a Bill of
Rights for internet users &mdash;
whether we should have a
right to use the internet,
whether we should
have a right to use it
with particular levels of
understanding about what
our privacy should
be, what access
we should have to
content on the web.
Or the other kind of idea that
I've heard floating around
is whether we should
have a Geneva Convention
type of thing, where we
know that there are going
to be states that
block us from accessing
certain kinds of content.
But should we have an
international understanding
about the limits
of that blocking
that we internationally
agree on?
I think these are all really
interesting questions.
And I think that we're only
at the beginning of starting
to have those
conversations, particularly
with policy makers,
who really don't
understand any of this at all.
MALE SPEAKER: And that's
quite scary, really, isn't it?
TOM ASHWORTH: I think we also
have to look at this question
from another point of
view, which is &mdash; actually,
this is a moot point
if the web is not
viable in any
particular country.
So, for example, in &mdash; I won't
call them developing nations,
because their economies
are bigger than the UK's.
But in countries like Brazil &mdash;
or, say, China or India &mdash;
we have to ask, is
the web actually
a viable platform
there at the moment?
If I, for example, worked
for a social network,
and let's say I work for
Facebook and I want to &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
And I want to get more
users in a country like one
of the ones I just
mentioned, I've
got a range of technologies
that are available to me.
And honestly, as web people,
we have to say, you know what?
The web does not
win in that battle.
Native wins in that battle.
Low-powered Android
wins that battle.
[GROANS]
MALE SPEAKER: Oh, dear.
No, hmm.
TOM ASHWORTH: And I'll give
you Firefox as well, but &mdash;
[CHUCKLES]
But you have to admit that,
I think, for a big company,
if you're going to invest
in a technology right now,
low-powered Android
phones &mdash; particularly
if you're heading
into those markets &mdash;
are a very good option.
We are missing certain key
elements of the technology
stack that will enable us to
make gains in those places.
There were quite a few
questions in the moderator,
actually, about &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: I'm going
to cut you off there,
because I think that you've
done your advertising spiel.
Thank you very much for that.
Can we go to Robert
Daly, who's on the queue?
ROBERT DALY: Hi.
We currently think of
one device, one user.
But with car OSes and
basically giant touch
screens that will have multiple
users using the same app
at the same time, how
do we deal with, say,
a driver and a passenger
using the same app in a car
at the same time without
switching user accounts?
Or &mdash; as in, how do we deal with
multiple people interacting
with the web?
MALE SPEAKER: Or, indeed &mdash;
ROBERT DALY: On one device.
MALE SPEAKER: Single
people on multiple devices.
That's the other side
to that proposition.
Do you want to take
that one, Scott?
SCOTT JENSON: I
actually would add
that I feel like that's exactly
the issue the web has right
now &mdash; it's that we've
been so enamored with one
device and one screen that
that's just our entire myopia.
I would go even further
that that one screen has
to, by the way, look
and feel as much
like an iPhone as possible.
I'm being a little
editorial at that point.
But I do think
that the web needs
to be exploring these
kinds of things.
So what would it mean to
have something on my watch
which then entices me
to pull out my phone
and allows me, then, to
continue the experience.
I don't think we're
considering that.
And it's something
that frankly, I
think the web is most
powerful at playing with.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, sorry, I'm
gonna have to skip to Guy,
and then we'll move
on to the next topic.
GUY: I just want to get back
to the country question,
and say that I don't think
it's a foregone conclusion
that the web needs to
adapt to those countries.
I think, to a large
extent, the countries
need to adapt to the web.
And it's sort of a force
to be reckoned with,
and Twitter and other
platforms have already
demonstrated that multiple
times over the past few years.
I think that when you talk
about the future of the web,
it's very much possible
that the future of the web
is the openness of it, and
it's kind of the government's
problem to sort of
figure out how do they
navigate within that world?
So the intent is about
getting data from one place
to the other, privacy concerns
around that, et cetera.
ANDREW SPOONER: Yeah,
I agree with that.
MALE SPEAKER: I'm really
sorry, but we were actually
going to go light on the
allotted time for that,
but we've run out of time on
it, despite thinking we were not
going to spend as much
on it as we might.
Oh, well.
Right, next topic.
Daniel Applequist, because
I'm much nicer than Christian
Heilmann, I'm going to
give you your question.
[INAUDIBLE]
[LAUGHTER]
DANIEL APPLEQUIST: OK.
Here we go.
Oh, this isn't what I wrote.
No.
[LAUGHTER]
So, in its march towards
increasing sophistication &mdash;
and I think this
question, parenthetically,
this question kind of goes
back to the more display
browser-oriented web that
we've been talking about
for &mdash; it's not to
discount the importance
of the data-oriented web, which
I think is also important.
But in its march towards
increasing sophistication,
is the web losing touch
with big easy to learn,
and therefore accessible
to a very broad authorship
community?
And I'm going to add one
more parenthetical statement.
I think this relates to
the whole meme that's
going on right now about
teaching kids to code
and getting kids, and
especially young people, engaged
in development.
How do we get them
engaged in the web easily?
MALE SPEAKER: OK,
thank you, Daniel.
I'm going re-paraphrase
your question
back to &mdash; another
fork of the question,
if you like &mdash; which is,
it used to be terribly
easy to write a basic web page.
It was pretty shit, but
it was very easy to do.
That was an Onramp.
That point has been
made earlier today.
But in order to be competitive,
or to provide a better user
experience, things have
got a lot more complicated.
Have they got disproportionately
complicated in order
to achieve the
objectives of being
more sophisticated
than they used to be?
JENI TENNISON: No.
SCOTT JENSON: No.
TOM ASHWORTH: Yeah.
MALE SPEAKER: No.
[LAUGHTER]
Right.
ALICE: Like basically,
here's the thing.
MALE SPEAKER: We
can deal with this.
No, no, no, no no.
Right.
ALICE: You can &mdash;
back in the day,
it was still quite hard to
get a web page onto a server,
and not a lot of people
are interested in doing it
proportionately, because it
was quite a lot of effort.
Because there wasn't this
sort of corpus of help
and tutorials and stuff.
And now, you can get very, very,
far, and do very cool stuff,
without knowing
basically anything.
And that may be a good
thing or a bad thing.
But to say that we've made
it too complicated for people
is really doing people
a massive disservice.
These people that
are like, oh, I
can't be bothered &mdash;
they've always existed.
And they're still around, and
they still can't be bothered.
And then there are people
who can be bothered,
and they also are still
being served by what we have.
And you can just go further,
and the people who will say, oh,
but it's possible for people
to make terrible mistakes
and do really dangerous
things &mdash; that's fine!
Those people are
going to learn really
quickly how to be better,
and that's brilliant, too.
So this kind of &mdash; yeah,
I hate this question.
MALE SPEAKER: They'll learn
really quickly, but possibly
with disastrous consequences.
ALICE: Well &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: You know,
I use this analogy, which
is putting a chainsaw in
the hands of a six-year-old.
Either they learn, or
well, you know, they don't.
TOM ASHWORTH: I teach people
every week, mostly beginners.
In fact, people who live in
London &mdash; Codebar.io, minority
people in tech, we're trying
to promote, particularly women.
So if you've got free
time on Wednesdays,
please come to that.
But I teach people
every Wednesday,
and I see this a lot.
I see people who are coming
new to HTML, and new to CSS.
And absolutely it is possible
for them to go from zero,
and in an hour and a half, have
a huge smile on their face,
because they've just
created their first website.
There's absolutely
no reason to believe
that that's fading away.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, and also,
when you started programming
and doing things &mdash;
initially, [INAUDIBLE]
And then when you want to do
anything dynamic, [INAUDIBLE]
Are you sure that
we can do anything
more dangerous than that?
MALE SPEAKER: I think
we're talking, OK &mdash;
ALICE: Yeah.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, valid.
Andrew.
ANDREW SPOONER: I think,
as any technology matures,
we realize some of
the things that we
used to do that were
quite difficult to do,
we try and simplify those.
If I think back when I
started the web, just trying
to get someone to &mdash; just
trying to get data into a form
and save that onto a
server somewhere &mdash; that's
actually quite a
complicated task.
It took us a long
time to do that.
It was a very
expensive thing to do.
There's a lot of
simple tools out there
that allow people to
do that quite easy now.
And that's an easy
thing to do, and I
think it means that some
people don't understand what
it is that they're actually &mdash;
what's actually going on
in the background.
But then, do you
need to know what's
going on in the background?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I just want to add
to that a little bit,
and say I just recently
started doing Code Club.
So I teach kids as young as &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: How
are you getting on?
No, sorry.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: One day, I hope
to make a career out of it.
But I teach kids as young as
five or six how to programming.
And the speed, the
facility, with which
they pick up quite sophisticated
concepts is incredible.
And I think with the low barrier
to entry that the web provides,
I don't think
we're in any danger
of making that too
complex at all.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
ALICE: I think Linda has
just arrived from Code Club
as we were speaking
about it, so &mdash;
LINDA: Hi, everyone.
ALICE: So without wishing
to put words in her mouth
about what the mission
of Code Club is,
I mean it really fills a gap
in education that does exist.
And there is a
problem with that.
And so when you're
talking about &mdash; maybe
you're talking about
coming to the web
as a teenager who is looking
to make their first web page.
And then there's Code Club,
who is sort of enabling kids
at a much younger age to get
involved with technology,
and think about
programming in a way
that the education
system in this country &mdash;
TOM ASHWORTH: And
since we're talking
about the future
of the web, really,
groups like Code Club
and Young Rewired State
are making the future
of the web, which
is the people who make the web.
So we should invest in those.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, thank you.
We do need to push
on here, because I
think we probably only have
got time for two more things,
if we're going to
stick to our timing.
So Daniel, no danger there.
OK?
Moving on.
From Ed S &mdash;
JENI TENNISON: Ed Snyder.
Ed Sowden.
MALE SPEAKER: Ed [INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
MALE SPEAKER: Yes, this
was a combination of yours
and someone else's.
So just to check, it
starts, "Is the web--?"
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: So, I've &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: No.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: I've been given this
to ask on behalf of Ed "So-den"
or "Sow-den," could be, but I
think it's the question that
Remy, perhaps, wanted to ask &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: That is exactly.
AUDIENCE: It's kind
of been bubbling
under a few of the
conversations as well.
It goes like this.
Is the web going
to grow into into
an all-encompassing platform
for all future computing?
Is there any area
which will be spared?
Or, by contrast, is the future
of the web just providing
APIs for native
applications to be built?
MALE SPEAKER: Thank you.
So, this is a question about,
what are the limits of the web?
What is the definition
of the word, "web?"
I don't think we probably
want to go that way,
but you guys started having
a little bit of a hammer
and tongs about that earlier.
Would you like to continue
that in the context
of this question?
So, will the web grow into an
all-encompassing computation
platform?
Jeni, you say no, because some
things are inherently web-like,
like HTTP, are not suitable.
JENI TENNISON: Yeah, so I
think that the basic &mdash; how
I would define the web, which
would be about the use of HTTP
and the use of resources
identified by URLs,
takes us a long
way, but there are
some aspects of &mdash;
particularly data
flows on the internet &mdash; that
don't use web protocols,
and should not
use web protocols.
And we need to be thinking
outside of the HTTP
as the only protocol that
we ever use on the internet.
MALE SPEAKER: Andrew.
ANDREW SPOONER: So, is
this also about languages,
and how we can extend
languages to other &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: You
can make it that.
ANDREW SPOONER: Platforms.
Thank you.
I see the web.
We've invested so
much time in it.
We've invested so much
time putting the content
into a format that
we can access.
And we can do so much more
with languages like JavaScript
nowadays.
They're actually starting to
stand up to other languages.
So the web can exist
in almost anything.
If I think about some of
the development work I do
the moment using JavaScript to
access the same APIs that I can
do through C++ &mdash; or I
could do through C#,
when creating applications
for Windows 8, for instance &mdash;
I'm using the same
web technologies,
the same web languages &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: So are you
saying that the distinction
is a bogus distinction
in some ways?
You're saying everything
flows into everything else.
ANDREW SPOONER: I
think it can exist &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
ANDREW SPOONER: In places where
we don't have it currently,
yes.
MALE SPEAKER: Remy,
I'm hoping this
was adjacent to the
point you were making.
REMY: No.
MALE SPEAKER: Absolutely
nothing to do with it.
REMY: It's not so much
I just don't think the
web will be everything,
and I don't think it will
just be the ayes [INAUDIBLE].
ALICE: So, I agree with
what you're saying.
I think there's a lot of hype
around the Internet of Things.
There's a lot of hype
around smart watches and all
that stuff.
And I think there are
a lot of companies
that are doing a
lot of figuring out
through doing, at the moment.
And what we'll find in 10
years &mdash; well no, not 10 years,
five years &mdash; is the web
will be in some stuff,
and it'll make a lot of sense.
And everybody will
be like, check out
my cool web-enabled thing.
And then it won't
be in other stuff.
And people will
be like, remember
when we tried to put the
internet into fucking fridges?
That was madness.
[LAUGHTER]
But there is a lot of hype
and a lot of marketing stuff
that makes all of this seem like
people are seriously thinking
about this, when actually
they're just figuring stuff
out.
And some of it is bad,
and some of it is &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: I
seriously challenge
that, in the sense
that &mdash; go back
to the audience in a
second &mdash; in the sense
that I'm old enough to
have said 15 years ago,
do you know what
people are going
to be using these
devices here to do?
All kinds of cool
stuff on the move.
And people said,
yeah, yeah, yeah.
We'll wait to see that.
So I think that expressing
skepticism about the direction
that these
technologies are going
is a potentially
dangerous route to take.
ALICE: Oh, well let's not
have any skepticism then.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: That
wasn't my point.
TOM ASHWORTH: I write
JavaScript all day, every day.
And quite frankly, I do not
want JavaScript on a pacemaker.
I do not want &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
I just &mdash; if you
said to me, look,
here's a web-enabled thing
that's going in your body,
I would tell you
to fuck right off.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: We actually
have &mdash; there's actually
examples of what we
tried to do once,
when there was no
[INAUDIBLE] 40 thing.
We tried to do an interpreter
for doing things running
on a device that,
basically, you couldn't even
fit a JavaScript interpreter on.
Because I don't know if you
remember about JavaScript &mdash;
apart from having obvious
limitations regarding how
we handle numbers, et cetera &mdash;
requires quite a bit of stack,
et cetera.
And we ended up doing
the first [INAUDIBLE]
thing that we built in
this company in a scheme.
In a scheme, because it was
the smaller interpreter than
could fit in like
a proximity 4k.
Right?
So there would be things,
as we were saying,
that basically you cannot
use the HTML CSS for actually
making your interface simpler.
And you've got to use
JavaScript to kind of reduce
what you have been doing,
because literally, there's
no space.
So not only because of the
whole asynchronous thing,
but because technically,
some of these things
and [INAUDIBLE]
things are not even
going to have stack
to run JavaScript on.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
Nor to use HTTP,
for that matter.
MALE SPEAKER: Chris, and you had
a word you wanted to interject,
and then we're probably
going to have to move on.
CHRIS: Yeah.
A few.
Actually, one thing
is &mdash; what amazes
me is we talk about
HTTP, but then we're
actually using a system
here that uses web sockets.
And we're using a system
that uses WebRTC and has
PO2P connections and
could even be encrypted
between two computers, so
that companies starting with N
and ending with SA couldn't
actually listen to us.
I find it also
interesting that we &mdash;
when I started on the web,
what I loved most about it
is that I can use whatever
I want to actually start
connecting with it.
And now we're talking about
smart watches, glasses
that cost $1,500, basically
toys for the Western world
to be the future of the web.
And to me, the future
of the web lies in,
as you said, emerging markets
with more people than we have.
And fixing that to gadgets that
are closed in one environment
is, to me, the wrong way of
making the future of the web.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, a closing
comment from the panel, here?
Scott, have you got
something to say about this?
SCOTT JENSON:
Well, I'm intrigued
with how we want
this future to go.
Because there's
clearly the discussion
of how the standards
bodies work.
But I would argue that the vast
majority of the conversations
that I tend to have with
people is all about &mdash; well,
how can you make this web
page scroll on a small screen.
And so, I think, to
a certain extent,
we've trapped ourselves
in our own paradigm,
which is that these are
just scrolling web pages.
And I think that there's so
much more the web can do.
For example, the previous
question about multi-displays.
I don't want to aspire what
the iPhone was five years ago.
And I think the web can
do so much more than that.
CHRIS: Isn't the
issue that we still
say it should look
the same everywhere?
That's what I always have
to fight [INAUDIBLE] &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: This is a
little off-topic, guys.
SCOTT JENSON: I don't
agree with that, but yeah.
Sorry.
MALE SPEAKER: So, I'm sorry.
But we're going to close that.
It's my job.
I quite enjoy it, actually.
[LAUGHTER]
Right.
We have a final
question, which is
going to set us &mdash; I
think down the path,
actually, that you were
on just now, Scott.
So we'll let you
continue on that one.
From Andre Barrons.
AUDIENCE: Hi, this
is Andre's question.
Web developers, and
even corporations,
that are outside the
browser-vendor community
have a feeling of being
a prisoner to decisions
others make, with
often limited means
to address certain problems.
Who should be determining the
future of the web, and how?
MALE SPEAKER: So, who
should be determining
the future of the web?
And how?
SCOTT JENSON: Well, I assume
this is the whole Extensible
Web Manifesto discussion.
MALE SPEAKER: It can be.
SCOTT JENSON: It can be.
I still feel that
our biggest issue
is our own myopia of what
we think is important.
Because the vast majority
of this community
is just trying to figure and
argue about apps versus native.
And so, to me, I would
like the web community
to start to figure out
a way to experiment
with these new things.
Like, how would
I write a web app
to work across
multiple displays?
I'd have to roll
everything from scratch.
And I just don't
think that we're
talking about ways to encourage
that kind of experimentation.
It seems to be so
standards-driven now
that we've lost the
ability to do stupid shit.
And I'd like to do more of it.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
You carry on doing
more stupid shit.
I'll talk to someone else.
Jeni, the view expressed
here is that people
don't have a sufficient
voice in the process.
JENI TENNISON: So I think
the web is what we build.
It's what we make.
It's through experimentation.
And we have a responsibility &mdash;
if we want our voice
to be heard, step up and shout.
So that in terms
of standardization,
I think the W3C has done a lot
to try and open up discussion &mdash;
through adding community
groups, for example,
over the past three years.
But I do think that
there is a massive gap
between the [INAUDIBLE]
that are in this room here,
and the majority of web
developers out there,
who probably do
feel that they have
no role in the conversation.
MALE SPEAKER: So can I just
ask for little straw poll here?
Out of everybody in this
room here, who has actually &mdash;
or who does &mdash;
participate particularly
in the W3C process?
OK.
So &mdash;
SCOTT JENSON: [INAUDIBLE],
or specifically W3C?
MALE SPEAKER:
Specifically W3C, I think,
since we're talking
about the web.
And I guess I'm making &mdash; the
web and W3C are kind of &mdash; well,
it needn't be.
So is the W3C the future
guardian of the web?
Well, that's another
question, I guess.
Someone could ask it.
What I think is the view
this is expressed here
is that that's not
working particularly well.
ANDREW SPOONER: But I think
everybody in this room &mdash;
everybody who contacts
a browser vendor
and asks them to
fix a bug, asks them
to add a feature &mdash; you've
all got a voice in this.
They're all listening.
I know that there was &mdash; I can't
remember the exact numbers &mdash; x
thousand of bugs reported to
the Internet Explorer team.
And there's a team of hundreds
of people sitting there
listening to those,
implementing those changes.
So if you're sending
your requests in,
there's people listening to it.
And ultimately, I think
everyone in this room
has a chance to input
into where it goes.
SCOTT JENSON: I would ask if
you've had experience of that.
Because just get to
give some examples,
there's a bug in Firefox
from about 2002, 2003,
to do with fragment
identifiers in iframes.
It was opened in 2003.
I bumped it a year and half ago.
Somebody else had bumped it
about three years before that.
No nothing from Mozilla.
And in terms of
Internet Explorer,
I don't know who to talk to.
I don't know how I can
get at those people.
Apple &mdash; we all know
the story there.
And, for example, when the
developer tooling guys were up,
both of the people
who represented people
who are working on
these things &mdash; when
asked, how do we
contribute, kind
of shrunk up and
wrung their hands.
I just don't think
it's true that these
are friendly environments
that we can get to.
ANDREW SPOONER:
Connect.Microsoft.com,
where you can
submit your request,
and there's people &mdash; there's
paid Microsoft employees &mdash; who
will then respond to
you and say, right, yes,
we know about this.
Or say, this isn't
a feature we're
interested in implementing.
And you'll get a response from
a human being through that,
and there's loads of people in
there who will respond to you.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, let's
go to the audience.
We've got someone at the back.
We've got Guy, and
then &mdash; hang on a second.
Let's go to the back first.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I'm kind of biased
on this, but I
think that out of the four
rendering engines that we
saw at the beginning, three
of them are open source.
So basically, people can either
work on the engines themselves
or find someone who
will do this for him.
And the reason I'm biased,
because I'm currently working &mdash;
I started a crowd
funding effort yesterday
to add feature &mdash; the
picture element to Blink.
And I think that the future
should have more of that.
More people adding features
to the open source rendering
thing.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
Coming forward in the room, Guy.
ALICE: I think that's a pretty
high barrier to entry, though,
isn't it, for most
web developers?
MALE SPEAKER: Yes, that is a &mdash;
ALICE: That, as a
suggestion, it seems &mdash;
TOM ASHWORTH: Well the
Extensible Web Manifesto
has been mentioned.
If we work towards
that ideal, where
we expose more of the kind
of primitives that are there
in the browsers but we currently
have no access to &mdash; if we
expose them to
developers, then I
think we stand a chance of
being able to at least iterate
more quickly towards an API
that we can then standardize.
ALICE: I think, given the
choice between downloading
and patching Chrome myself or
just working around a problem,
I would work around it &mdash;
like, pragmatically.
[INAUDIBLE]
[LIGHT LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: It's a little
different &mdash; in general,
the notion of [INAUDIBLE]
as the web evolved,
and I think we're losing
sight of the server side.
Like we keep talking about the
clients and those components,
but I think the
future of the web
lies a lot with the
services consumed on it.
And I think, clearly, all these
things and all these devices
are a part of the technology.
But what you can do on
the web &mdash; especially
in the developing world,
or in access to banking,
or facilities, or
payments by the phone,
or ordering your groceries,
or calling a cab &mdash; all
of those components, I
think, are a big part
of the future of the web.
So the fact that it
might still be HTML &mdash;
or maybe we're not evolving
it &mdash; is sometimes less critical
versus the creativity
or the disruptions that
happen on the business side of
it, on the server side of it.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, can we drop
on row forwards, I think?
OK, two rows.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.
In terms of having
an input, which
is what Andrew was
talking to about getting
in touch with people, I
found an inconsistency SVG.
I wrote a blog post about it.
I managed to get
in touch with one
of the editors of the SVG spec.
I showed him the thing.
He's updating SVG spec
to fix that thing.
It does happen, it does
work, it is out there,
and you can get involved in it.
MALE SPEAKER: OK Go
right to the back,
and then we'll
start to close down.
AUDIENCE: So we can
have examples of times
when community input has worked.
What we need is an example
of when it hasn't, right?
When the will of the
community has not
been exerted over
browser vendors.
So maybe an example
of that might be DRM.
An example might be DRM,
where it's going in browsers.
And generally speaking,
that's not what people want.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, fine.
I want to ask Natasha, who's
sitting right in the front
here, and put her on the spot.
Because I know that she has
something interesting to say
about when people are invited
to take part, they don't.
NATASHA: What, so
W3C in specific?
Well, I've been very fortunate
with contributing to W3C.
I co-chair a group,
and I'm actually
filling Joe's shoes right
now, which is pretty tough,
but I'm giving it all I've got.
MALE SPEAKER: And not
very pleasant, either.
NATASHA: But we need
people to help out.
And we're so grateful that
people want to help out.
And we know there's a
membership issue there,
but if you want to help out
on what we're doing in the web
group, then please
come speak to us.
There's lots of W3C guys are
moving to using open tools,
like GitHub and Twitter.
We have a Twitter account.
And of course, the
W3C is open anyway.
So if you want to
contribute, you can.
And please come and speak to me
about that later at the party.
I'd be very happy to
speak to you about that.
MALE SPEAKER: Thanks, Natasha.
OK, so the answer to
the question &mdash; Tom,
do you have something
to say about that?
TOM ASHWORTH: Yeah, the
mention of DRM is interesting.
It's not an area I
know anything about,
so I'm not going to speak
specifically to DRM.
But the idea of people who have
a vested interest in that kind
of technology encroaching on,
say, issues of net neutrality,
is something that I think
is really important for us
to talk about.
I mean, if we're talking
about the future of the web,
we're talking about
a situation where
I have to pay my ISP
for a group of websites
that I'm allowed to visit.
And I have to extend that
package for just $5.99 a month
to get access to this
other search engine,
or this website that wasn't
on their original list.
And they couldn't &mdash; there was
some kind of hostility between
the two parties or whatever.
MALE SPEAKER: There's
a bigger question
that we had to skip exactly
on this topic, I'm afraid.
TOM ASHWORTH: But there's
a bigger community
that needs to be
involved in that.
The web community
is a small part
of the group of people
who are involved
in ensuring we keep or maintain
the kind of net neutrality
that we wish to have.
And it's not my
area of expertise,
but I sometimes feel like
we sort of close ourselves
in and say, well let's keep
the web bit of this good &mdash;
the HTML CSS
JavaScript, that stack.
Let's keep this good.
As long as we look after
this, everything else be fine.
Sometimes, I wish we
could take a step back,
and say, you know what?
Maybe we could stop worrying
about that for a bit.
And say, let's get the people
who work on the networking
hardware, and who do
all these other aspects,
and bring us all
together to make
sure we can, going forward,
keep the web and the internet
in the way we'd like it to be.
MALE SPEAKER: OK, thank you.
Now, this is unscripted.
Alice and down the
line, in three words,
then, to close us out today &mdash;
what is the future of the web?
ALICE: I don't know.
[LAUGHTER AND CHEERING]
MALE SPEAKER: Tom.
[INAUDIBLE] that response.
That was brilliant.
TOM ASHWORTH: Kids,
freedom, help?
I dunno.
MALE SPEAKER: Scott.
SCOTT JENSON: Lots of arguing.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER:
Andrew, I get to give
the privilege of being last.
ANDREW SPOONER: Oh,
I'd just say connected.
MALE SPEAKER:
Connected, connected.
OK, Jeni?
JENI TENNISON:
Redecentralization,
just because I like that word.
And data.
That's only two.
MALE SPEAKER: OK.
Thank you very
much to our panel.
[APPLAUSE]