BRAD GREEN: Good
morning, everyone.
I'm Brad Green.
I'm the manager of the Angular
project here at Google.
And I'm joined by John
and Darrel from TiKL.
And they're going to
talk to us about building
Chrome Apps with AngularJS.
And I'm sorry, you guys.
For this holiday
addition, John's
actually wearing some
spectacular Christmas pants,
but you can't see it on camera.
Maybe at the end, we
can get a shot of that.
So hey guys, tell
us a little bit
about what TiKL
does before we get
into the presentation
about building apps.
DARREL SUMI: Sure.
JOHN FEIG: Sure, yeah.
We're mainly a
mobile app company.
We have several
communications apps.
We have three on Android.
And wait-- no, we
have four on Android.
DARREL SUMI: Four on
Android, two on iOS.
JOHN FEIG: Two on iOS.
So we've got TiKL, which
is like a walkie-talkie.
It works just like
a walkie-talkie.
It's pretty fun.
We have Talkray, which is
our main focus these days,
which is a unified
communications app.
You do texting, calling-- it
does groups up to 25 people.
KeeChat, which is
what we're going
to be talking about
today, which is
group texting with usernames.
And then we have a new app out
that we launched a couple weeks
ago, which is a
PTT recorded app,
so you can send voice
mails back and forth.
It's called VoMessenger.
BRAD GREEN: So you guys have
been primarily doing Java and--
DARREL SUMI: Yes.
BRAD GREEN: --maybe
Objective-C development.
And you've just recently
come into the web
way of developing things.
And so how long have
you been doing this?
DARREL SUMI: Since we
started as a company,
it's probably-- I don't
know, five months or so where
we've been kind of
jumped into this.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah, we started over
the summer doing the web stuff.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah.
I mean, both of
us have obviously
dabbled in a lot of
web stuff before.
But this is our first
real, larger project.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah, right.
Definitely the
first big project.
And the company, as a
company, doesn't really
have much experience
with web things.
TiKL was started in 2010.
They had the TiKL
app for a while.
And then we jumped into Talkray.
And that was iOS and Android.
And we've basically been
focused on mobile exclusively
until this product.
BRAD GREEN: OK, very cool.
All right.
Well, then, let's jump
into the presentation.
And tell us about
what you guys have
learned about the environment.
JOHN FEIG: Great.
So we can start with the slides.
So this is KeeChat.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah.
So these are just a
couple screenshots
of what the mobile
app looks like.
So basically, like what we said,
it's a unified messaging app.
So you can send regular
texting images to anyone
within our system.
JOHN FEIG: And we recently
built a Chrome App out of it.
We started with a
web version of this.
And then we sort of
transitioned to a Chrome App.
And we'll talk a
little bit about why
we picked Angular and Chrome.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah.
Angular really fit with, like
we said, our background in Java.
We wanted the look and
feel of the entire thing
to be very much like an
app, less a traditional web
style of doing things.
And everything, like the
MVC architecture of Angular,
really fit into the
pre-existing model
that we had built everything
around on the mobile side.
JOHN FEIG: Right.
Yeah.
It was very comfortable
for us to look at
because it just felt a lot like
being able to build an app.
And you can see
here the structure
that we chose for KeeChat,
which is basically
Angular's suggested structure
for especially large projects.
So we broke it out into
controllers and services
and models are the
main components here,
trying to pick apart
with the MVC architecture
and do this properly.
And it was really
nice to have services.
For us, coming from Java,
where they're sort of like
singletons.
They work in a similar way.
There's a lot of nice stuff.
And organizing
your code like this
really helps in larger projects.
DARREL SUMI: Yes.
So I guess one of the
reasons, or one of the things,
is why did we chose to do a
Chrome App off the Angular app.
Why not just keep it a
website kind of thing?
So obviously, the biggest
one is the Chrome Web Store.
That's a great way to get
distribution for our app.
The other one is
that, like I said,
we really wanted to make
it feel like an app.
We wanted users who
came from our mobile
to be able to experience
the same kind of experience
that we provided
on their computers.
So one of the big
things is notifications.
That makes it feel like a
much more rich experience.
And obviously, raw sockets
were pretty important for us
because we're a
communication app.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
We had played around with a
couple different socket clients
and decided that for
us to get out the door,
raw sockets was going to be the
easiest way for us to do it.
So that was something that
was available in Chrome Apps
that really you
can't do in HTML5.
There's WebSockets, but
it's not the same thing.
Java can use
WebSockets in Java 7,
but we're not running
Java 7 on the server.
DARREL SUMI: So
some of the tools
we use are-- we'll just briefly
go over this-- Yeoman, Grunt,
Bower, and Karma.
Karma's our testing suite.
The other three really help
us organize our code a lot,
bring in all the dependencies,
keep everything clean.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
It's pretty standard stuff.
And it was really nice
with Grunt, actually.
You can run Grunt server.
And it has listeners for things.
And so it was really funny.
Because when we were really
running through this stuff,
it was faster developing on the
web than it was for Android.
Because you'd change something,
and then your browser
would get updated right away.
I don't know.
It was kind of funny.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah, we're just
used to waiting, compiling,
and doing all this stuff
for Android development.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
And we didn't even have to hit
Refresh on the browser window
here.
So it's kind of nice.
DARREL SUMI: So one of the
main concerns, when you're
thinking about
building a Chrome App,
is what are all the
dependencies in your project
that you're going to need to
re-work around the Chrome Apps.
And one of them, the
big one, was RequireJS.
So we used Require a lot.
It's a great modularization tool
that you can use-- or library.
A lot of people use it.
It's a very common thing.
But they kind of
conflict a little bit
with the module
system in Angular.
They don't necessarily
directly-- they're
not against each other.
In fact, that they're
orthogonal ideas of the way
they treat modularization.
But they are going to step
over each other a little bit,
so you've got to understand
if you really need it
and how to deal with it.
JOHN FEIG: For us, we had all
these third-party libraries
that we just had to use.
And some of those
required Require.
So it's like, OK, we're
stuck using Require.
It's kind of painful to
get implemented properly
with Angular.
If you can avoid it, it's
probably better to avoid it,
but--
DARREL SUMI: But it's
still a great tool.
And if you need it, there
are several resources
online that show examples
of how exactly to do it.
So it's not-- there's
ways around it.
JOHN FEIG: And I have
read that Angular
is supposed to be getting
better about trying
to integrate with Require.
BRAD GREEN: We do want
to work on that more.
So like you say, these
are two orthogonal things.
One is about what does my
JavaScript class need in order
to run.
The other is, what order
should I load vals.
DARREL SUMI: Right.
Dependency order and then lazy
loading, and things like that.
BRAD GREEN: It would be nice
if these worked well together.
This is some future thing
we'd like to get right.
JOHN FEIG: So, yeah.
I guess now we're
just going to dive
into what the process of
converting a web Angular
app to a Chrome App was.
DARREL SUMI: So just kind
of the quick few basics
that every kind of
Chrome App needs
is that it's going to need a
manifest.json file that pretty
much describes all the
permissions and the app name
and things that
go into the store.
There's going to be a
background.js file that
describes several entry
points into the app,
like what happens
when you install
the app, what happens on launch.
And you're going to need here,
obviously, your index files,
your main index file.
But there's a trick to this
one is that it sometimes
differs from what you normally
would have in your Angular
project.
JOHN FEIG: OK.
So we can look at the manifest
here for a little demo app
that I did.
And it's really pretty basic.
You've got your
name, description.
You have the entry point of
the JavaScript for your app
to find, which is background.js.
That's a pretty standard
thing within Chrome Apps.
And then permissions--
so for example,
I need to be able to talk to
the ajax.googleapis.com site.
And I also need to have
storage permissions.
And then you also
specify your icons.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah,
pretty straightforward.
And like I said,
for the background,
you can pretty much
describe generic things
about your Chrome App.
So in this case, all we said is
the width is going to be 1,200,
the height's going to be 700.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
And then your index
is chomeindex.html.
And you can name it
whatever you want.
But I think it's easy just
to call it Chrome Index.
And your regular one's Index.
OK.
DARREL SUMI: So once you
add all these things in,
and you think, OK, this
is going to-- things
are going to look good.
And you try running it.
Of course, nothing works, right?
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
You get a lot of red.
DARREL SUMI: Right, right.
And so one of the main,
first ways to approach this
is there's a thing
called a Content Security
Policy that web
browsers implement.
It basically
restricts what you can
do so that third-party external
code doesn't maliciously
run some hacks on
your website and cause
all kinds of problems.
So this is something
that's already
out in most web browsers.
But then Chrome Apps have
a tighter restriction
on this Content Security Policy.
So the three main things that
differ from traditional web are
is that it's going to
restrict any inline scripting.
It's going to restrict
any external resources.
So if you link to some extra
library somewhere else,
you can't necessarily
just link to that
to bring that script in.
And it's going to
restrict anything
that pretty much converts
strings into JavaScript.
So things that use the eval
or new Function methods
are not going to
work in Chrome Apps.
So the second thing
that I talked about,
the external resources,
so the first thing
you're going to look at is
what third-party libraries
you bring in that
you might actually
reference from a
CDN or something.
These you can't bring
into your app directly,
so you're going to
have to download
these libraries or any
styles, or fonts, images,
any other kind of static
content that you might
be able to just bring
into your app and have it
hosted straight from there.
And so you're going to
have to modify your index
file, obviously, because that's
where all these things get
referenced.
So here's a quick example of how
the index that you might have
for your regular
Angular projects
will differ from the Chrome one.
So first one, when
we reference the app,
is going to be a ngCsp.
JOHN FEIG: I don't
think it highlights.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah,
it doesn't highlight.
There's going to
be a ngCsp Angular
tag that you're
going to put there.
What this describes
is that it tells
Angular to be in a
CSP mode, essentially.
Angular has a lot
of optimizations
that use things like the
eval and new Function,
I believe, basically
just to optimize Angular.
But for it to run
in the Chrome App,
you have to restrict
those kinds of things.
So it has a CSP mode
that'll get around that.
BRAD GREEN: It's actually
only a few little things.
You don't lose very much at all.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
Well, yeah.
Great.
BRAD GREEN: It's one
small optimization.
But yes, you do lose it.
DARREL SUMI: Right, right.
And so you do need
to specify that.
And obviously, now that
you downloaded-- say,
in this example
it's a Socket.IO.
We were referencing
it from the CDN.
And so now we just have to
bring it into your own project
and reference it that way.
Pretty straightforward.
JOHN FEIG: Yep.
And then you try running it
again, and it's still broken.
So--
DARREL SUMI: OK, so here's a
little demo-- let me switch.
Here's a little demo of
a socket app that I made.
So basically, all this is--
it's just a small little test
demo that connects
to a Node.js server.
The Node.js server
starts counting
every one, two,
three-- every second.
And it would reply
back on Socket.IO
to the client and display
what the current count is,
essentially.
Really simple-- that's
all that's happening.
And so here, you'll see that
the counter's incrementing.
But at this point,
the Angular project
doesn't know anything about
what the count was previously.
It doesn't know anything
about who its friends are.
These are all initialized and
given to us by the Node server.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
You don't want to
dive into-- OK.
DARREL SUMI: Whoa.
Whoops.
There we go.
OK.
So one of the key components to
Angular as well as Chrome Apps
is that the way you
think about web servers
traditionally is switched
to be using an API server.
So the web server you need
to treat as an API server.
And what that means is
that the web server is not
going to hand down HTML or
things like that, where it's
traditionally-- they might
have injected information, say.
You grab information
from your database,
and you put it in your friends
list or something, for example.
And it's not going to inject
[? a string ?] into the HTML
and hand you back the HTML.
Rather, all that's going to
exist in your Angular app
already.
And really, what your
server should be doing
is sending back just the data,
none of the UI components.
So in this example,
this is how the HTML
looks like for the
example I just showed you.
Pretty much all we know
on the Angular side
is that there's
going to be a count.
There's going to be
a count listed here.
Whoops.
That doesn't do that.
JOHN FEIG: [LAUGHTER] No.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
So there's going to be a
count referenced there.
And we're going to be repeating
over a list of friends.
But we don't know who the
friends are at this point.
There might be one friend.
There might be hundreds.
And we don't know.
But really, you need to
treat your web server
to give you those
things as an API server.
BRAD GREEN: And this is the
great thing about Angular
is you're going to build
your app this way anyway.
So there's not much
in the transition.
JOHN FEIG: Right.
DARREL SUMI: Exactly.
JOHN FEIG: So we're going
to look at Socket.IO here.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
JOHN FEIG: Whoops.
Uh-oh.
That's not good.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
So here is some of the
code for this example.
And this is all, by the way,
GitHub ,
so that you can look
it later on your time.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
We have links at the end.
DARREL SUMI: Right, right.
So this is the main controller
for the example I was just
[? saying ?].
So basically, there is
going to be a count that's
initialized at zero and
an empty friends list.
Like I said, you don't
really know anything
about what's happening.
And the way we
have it structured
is that initially, you
just connect to the server.
The server is, like I
said, a Node.js server
that's running locally.
And here is a service that
controls the communication
to that Node server.
So in server connect,
where you start off,
essentially we just connect
to-- I have a hard-coded thing
to look a host right here.
And at this point, we
don't know any kind
of data that's been
passed through.
We just know that we
started with nothing.
So what we do is we
tell it to connect.
And when we connect, we event
an emit back to our controller,
saying, hey, we've connected.
And at this point--
BRAD GREEN: Actually, Darrel,
maybe just bump the font
up a point or two.
DARREL SUMI: Sure.
What was it?
Command-Plus?
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
DARREL SUMI: There we go.
BRAD GREEN: That'll be good.
JOHN FEIG: Sorry about that.
DARREL SUMI: So
in our controller,
when you do connect, we're
going to tell it to initialize,
initialize our state.
So at this point,
your API server
doesn't really know anything
about where you've left off
or what it is.
It's just going to start
counting from some random--
from zero, if the server
doesn't know anything.
So it helps if you pass in some
kind of initialization data
to tell it, hey, this
is where we left off.
And this leads into
a key point of how
you want to treat
offline and online mode.
But we'll get to
that in a second.
And so we initialize it
with our current count,
which at this point is zero.
And when we get a response
back from the server here,
and it responds here,
we'll get back some data.
And in the data--
like I just know
it's going to contain the
current count and just
a list of friends, which
doesn't really change.
And then from that point
onward, the socket's
going to connect-- it's going
to listen for a counter update
event that's going to
get pushed down once
every second from
the Node server.
And it's just going emit
the count right here.
So the count is actually
incremented on the server side.
So all that kind of
logic-- obviously,
this is a contrived
example of what
you might want to pass
down, what information you
want to pass down
from your server.
But essentially,
the server's going
to be handling all that
kind of data management,
a lot of that
stuff that goes on.
But you'll notice here
that this is all just
standard Socket.IO stuff if
you have worked with it before.
[INAUDIBLE] All right.
JOHN FEIG: There we go.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
Right.
And so one of the
things that you
have to consider when you
build your Chrome app,
and for Angular as
well, is how this
is going to get treated
in an offline mode
or in a state where you're not
sure about the connectivity
of things.
So you do need to handle things
like disconnections or crappy
connections.
And a lot of that needs to go
into any kind of socket code
that you write.
So luckily, Socket.IO
handles a lot
of the disconnect and
auto-reconnect logic.
But if you're working
with raw sockets,
you're going to need to handle
these kinds of things, as well.
But more than just the
actual connectivity,
you need to think about
how your app is going
to work from the
user's standpoint
when you don't
have connectivity.
If you start up the app, will
you be showing a blank page?
If you lose connection
in the middle, what's
going to happen to, let's
say, in our example,
the counter that
you have going on?
JOHN FEIG: Right.
You don't want to just
throw up a Refresh button
and make the user
think about that stuff.
You want to handle
it in a smart way
so that it's as
automatic as it can be.
DARREL SUMI: Right, right.
So in our example-- can
we go-- what's it called?
Terminate the server.
JOHN FEIG: Oh, the-- OK.
Um, yeah.
There we go.
OK.
Server's up there.
DARREL SUMI: OK.
So we just--
JOHN FEIG: Server's dead.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah, killed
our server, essentially.
And when you go
back to this, you'll
notice that the
counter has stopped.
You'll probably
want to do something
to signify that you're in
an offline mode, maybe.
That might help,
so the user doesn't
get confused, like, why
isn't anything working?
But you notice that the count
is just stopped at here.
But if you were to
redo the server,
or reconnect it, after
some retrial logic,
it's going to
essentially start back
from where we previously
were counting.
So you don't want to
necessarily start from scratch
every time you reconnect.
You want to leave the user
off where they were before
and [? smoothen
?] the transition
between these things.
JOHN FEIG: You
can see it worked.
We were stuck at 419, and
now we're counting again.
DARREL SUMI: Right, right.
So you don't necessarily want
to start at zero every time.
JOHN FEIG: OK.
So go here.
DARREL SUMI: So
this whole example
was, [? obviously, ?] just
a regular Angular app.
And the same thing works for--
JOHN FEIG: Kill this one.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah.
Same thing works--
the transition
from bringing Socket.IO
into Chrome Apps
is really, really simple,
pretty much like what
we showed earlier where you
reference the Socket.IO, not
from CDN but from
your own project.
After you do that,
that's pretty much it.
There isn't a
whole lot of things
that you need to do to
get Socket.IO working.
It actually just
works out of the box.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah, which was
really surprising to me
because I thought that
this might be restricted
or it might be really difficult.
But Socket.IO just works.
Where do you want to go?
DARREL SUMI: Yeah, there we go.
And so on top of
Socket.IO, Chrome Apps
provides a really
great Sockets API.
It gives you access to
raw TCP and UDP sockets.
It's through the
chrome.socket API.
I have an example on the GitHub
that is the same exact demo
that we just showed but
just rewritten for TCP.
So if you want to look at
that, here's a link for that.
But we necessarily
won't go into that code.
JOHN FEIG: It's a
little bit more verbose,
but it's also a
lot more powerful.
Like I mentioned at
the top, you get access
to real raw sockets with
this, which, like I said,
we just needed for our app.
BRAD GREEN: Just so
folks can think about,
which one would I need?
What did you guys need
the raw sockets for?
JOHN FEIG: So we're sending
binary data back and forth
to the server.
Socket.IO sends back
and forth strings.
So if you want to send that
sort of data over Socket.IO,
you have to encode
it as a string first.
And then you have to decode
it on the server side.
You also have to have
server-side components that
can handle Socket.IO.
Depending on the server that
you're running the sockets,
you might have a good Socket.IO
library available to you.
Like if you're running
Node, it's really easy
to just pull in Socket.IO.
But if you're
running Java, there's
not really a great
solution for Socket.IO.
So it's a lot easier to
use raw sockets there.
DARREL SUMI: It just depends on
what your current architecture
is and structures.
For us, since we came
from a mobile app
with a pre-existing system, it
was easier to plug into that
rather than recreate everything
on a different system.
JOHN FEIG: Right.
And there's also WebSockets,
too, like we mentioned.
And those are maybe a little
bit more available on servers.
So it just depends on
what your needs are.
But it's really nice to have
Chrome sockets available.
So the next thing that
you want to think about,
in terms of how your app
behaves when it's offline,
is your local storage stuff.
And this is actually
something that I
started with in my demo,
which is a little podcast app,
before I even thought about
converting this into a Chrome
App.
The main reason is
because I wanted
it to behave like an app.
I wanted people to be able
to subscribe to podcasts
and then listen to episodes.
I wanted it to keep
track of how much they
had listened to so far.
One thing that really
drives me nuts is I
have a couple tools that
I use, aside from my app,
for listening to
podcasts, and they always
forget where I left off.
And some of the
podcasts I listen to
are multiple hours long.
And if the thing goes down or
you accidentally click Refresh,
and you start back at zero
when you're an hour and a half
in, that's not too fun .
So this stuff is
really important.
It's really useful.
And storing stuff
on the client side
in certain cases-- like
for KeeChat for example,
all of your chats are stored
locally-- your contacts list.
You want all that stuff local.
Especially if it's just
going to be for you,
there's no reason to
have it on the server.
So there are some
slight differences
between how Chrome handles
local storage versus how
HTML5 handles local storage.
And I will show you right here.
So the big difference is
that HTML5 is synchronous.
It has a synchronous API
for local storage, which
means that you can just say,
myVal equals localStorage key.
So that's just getting the
thing right off a disk.
It blocks in-line.
And so you're going to be
blocking on whatever thread
you're calling that on.
And Chrome is asynchronous.
So it's going to go
out to disk and then
return in a callback the thing.
And you can just
follow along here.
I highlighted in blue the
value that I'm trying to set.
And then orange
here is the value
that's coming back from disk.
So in the HTML5
example at the top,
that's just one line
that we have to call.
But again, it blocks there.
And then the example below
is a little bit more verbose,
but you can see we start
out with null set to that.
And then we define
a callback function
that's going to take
a single parameter
and assign it to the
value that we want set.
Oh, boy.
Ha.
There we go.
And then we do this
chrome.storage.local.get.
And then the first
parameter is the key,
which is the same key
that we have up above.
And then whatever
gets returned is
going to get passed
to a function.
And it's going to be
callback and then data, key.
So you get an object back.
And you have to pull the
value out of the object.
It's really not too tough.
It's just slightly different
because it's asynchronous.
And the big deal
here is that there
may be some third-party
libraries, especially if you're
in a larger project,
that make assumptions
about having the synchronous
API for local storage.
So there was one
library that we ran
into that was a pretty integral
part of KeeChat that just made
assumptions all over the
place about local storage
being synchronous.
And we made assumptions--
we kind of used their API
in a synchronous way because
those were synchronous calls.
So it made sense to use
it in a synchronous way.
So what happened was when we
did this change to Chrome,
we had to go through
and rewrite quite a bit
of that third-party
library to make
it function asynchronously.
That was one of the
more painful things.
It wasn't a huge deal.
And it wasn't
technically difficult.
It was just annoying because
you have this dependency.
And it's not working for you.
So that stuff you
might run into.
But--
DARREL SUMI: So pretty
much, you always want
to check and see what
kind of assumptions
any third-party banks on
the access to the APIs,
as well as the
thing like we talked
about earlier-- the
Content Security Policy.
A lot of these libraries are
going to make assumptions,
a lot of them more
towards the way web
has been done up till
now and not the Angular
way or the Chrome App way.
JOHN FEIG: And another great
way to persist data locally
is with IndexedDB,
which is an HTML5 API.
And it can actually
be a much better fit
for certain types of data.
So if you have larger data sets,
anything that's not a string,
really, you probably
want to use IndexedDB.
It's a NoSQL
database on a client.
The API's a little-- it takes
a little getting used to.
It's a little verbose.
I actually wrote
a wrapper to help
with doing things with Angular.
So it's an AngularJS
IndexedDB wrapper
so you can just inject it.
And then you just do
much simpler calls.
But here's an example
of IndexedDB Put.
So you have a datastore.
You have a database.
The storeName is
kind of like a table.
So it's like-- I mean,
it's a datastore for NoSQL.
And we're just going to put
some data, which is an object,
so it's going to be key
value pairs in that object.
And so you have a reference
to the database already.
You have to have
opened the database.
And there's a whole
process for that.
And then you get a transaction.
With the storeName, it has
to be in read-write mode
if you're going to
be persisting things.
I'm going to say objectStore,
dot put, and then your object.
And then, hopefully,
you'll go through this on,
success callback
that has your event.
And now what I'm
doing here is I'm
emitting an event through
Angular, through the Angular
scope, that this data was put,
and then on what database,
and what storeName.
And then I have a similar
event in the error case.
DARREL SUMI: And
this whole wrapper
is put as a Angular
service, right?
JOHN FEIG: Mm-hm.
Yep.
So it's a singleton.
You can call it when
you set up your app.
I tried to make it as
simple as possible.
And we actually used the
same library in KeeChat.
It cut way down on
the amount of code
that I had to write
over trying to do things
with local storage.
BRAD GREEN: And you'll be able
to share that link with us?
DARREL SUMI: Yes.
JOHN FEIG: Yep, yep.
It's at the end.
BRAD GREEN: Great.
JOHN FEIG: So I actually
also have a wrapper
for the local storage to choose
between Chrome versus the HTML5
thing.
It tests to see if
chrome.storage exists.
And if it does, it uses that.
And you can also
set it up to use
the sync, chrome.storage.sync
versus local,
which will sync any
of those strings
across multiple
instances of Chrome.
So if you're logged into
Chrome on your laptop at home
and your laptop at
work, you can actually
have that stuff synced
up, which is nice.
So back to the slide.
Angular has-- it's
just an aside,
but Angular has these
really nice event emitters.
In KeeChat, we used a
third-party event emitter
library because we had--
like I mentioned at the top,
there's some
third-party libraries
that make assumptions
about what's available.
One of those assumptions
was that event emitters
would be available.
In my podcast demo,
I didn't need that.
I didn't really use
much third-party stuff.
So I could use the
Angular event emitters,
which are really nice because
this is done on the scope,
on Angular's scope.
So Angular knows
about these things.
You don't have to
run scope.apply
to get the digest cycle going.
So when you send a controller
an event, it's going to show up.
So it's a really simple API.
You listen for-- you register
for events with scope.on.
You say, like, i_am_event
is the string that's
going to identify this.
And then the second
parameter is a function
with two parameters,
event and data.
The event I never use at all.
But data is important.
And so then you can emit
it with rootScope.emit.
And it's rootScope
because you're usually
going to be doing
this from a service.
Services can't get
scope injected.
And they probably wouldn't
be on the same scope anyway.
So rootScope is what you use.
DARREL SUMI: The syntax--
the whole notion of this
is fairly common, standard
event emitter type of paradigm
that people are probably
used to for any other system.
It's just that these events
get passed through the scope,
so you do have to understand how
it goes up and down the scope.
JOHN FEIG: Right.
Yeah.
There are a couple options here.
So it's depending on where
you're firing events from
and where you want to get
them to, you might need emit
or you might need broadcast.
And they take the
same parameters.
But broadcast basically sends
things down to children.
Emit goes up the stack.
So you have to know
which one you need.
But yeah, event emitters
are really useful.
And they really
help clean up code.
And you don't have to have
as many things explicitly
calling one another.
DARREL SUMI: It
just really helps
keep your code structured
in a really nice, clean way
and modularized that way.
JOHN FEIG: Right Yeah.
It really cuts down on
interdependency stuff.
And then I have just one other
quick example of IndexedDB Get.
So very similar to
Put, this is just
getting some item
out of the database.
This time, we're
going to just use
a key, which can be a string,
whatever the type for your key
is.
And so we have a similar thing
where we get the transaction
out of the database
with the storeName.
You don't need to be
in read-write mode.
You don't need to
pass the mode in.
The default is just read.
And then the
onsuccess case again,
we're emitting something with
Angular's rootScope emitter.
We say, we've gotten this item.
And then we're going to
pass an array of results.
So this is nice.
With IndexedDB, I like
to always pass back
the database name, the
storeName, and then the data so
that in my controller-- whatever
is getting this data, if it's
a service controller or
whatever, I can first
check to see-- OK, getitem
is pretty generic, right?
And since this is a service
library that I wrote,
I'm not going to have
dozens of different names
for these things.
If I have common
names, and I pass back
identifiers in the
data, it just helps
so that I can register the
listener with that common name
and then just inspect things
that come back on those event
listeners when I get them.
So after you do your local
storage, convert things
to IndexedDB, it's
still not going to work.
You probably have
some dynamic content
that you need to handle.
DARREL SUMI: And this goes
back to the notion of the CSP
that you can't bring
in external content
and just think it's going
to run all fine and dandy.
JOHN FEIG: Right.
So actually, this would
probably be a good time
to explain one thing here.
So this is my little
podcast app that I did.
And this is actually
the Chrome App version.
So you can see, I
launched it there.
And so this middle
section here you can see
is all pulled in
with a web request.
So this side-- the
Add Podcast and List
a Podcast side-- that's local.
And then I have
this section up top.
This-- you've got a
playlist here on the left.
That's local.
But then the content
with text that
pulls in information about
either the show or all
these episodes, that's all being
pulled in with a web request.
And you need XHR to do that.
And it's a slightly
different call
that I had to make in
the Chrome environment
versus with just the
Angular web environment.
And so here's what you can
use to get, say, an image.
And this is an example of
getting an image out of imgur.
So I am going to set it up
with just a regular HTTP.
This is Angular's
HTTP thing that
can be injected into your app.
As I said, the method's
Get-- here's the URL.
And it's going to be a blob
response so that I can actually
set it as the
source of an image.
In a success case, you
get all this stuff back.
Again, I'm going to
ignore everything
except for the data
that's coming back.
I keep scrolling.
And there.
So I'm going to ignore
everything except the data.
I have in my HTML this
image tag with an ID
that I specified, onepod_img.
So I'm going to grab
a reference to it.
And then I can set
the source with
this
window.webkitURL.createObjectURL
and then the data.
And that's going to allow me
to just take that data that's
the result of this web
request, which is-- actually,
it works the same
way as the XHR stuff.
It's just a slightly
different API.
And then set that
into the image.
And there's an error
case where it failed.
And hopefully, it
won't fail for you.
And you also have to
make sure that imgur
is in your permissions.
So this is not something
that-- it's not my server,
so I have to put it in
the permissions thing.
Once I do that, it should be OK.
DARREL SUMI: Right.
And you'll notice that
there's other things that
might need to go into
your permissions.
So any of the
Chrome Apps require
you to specify either,
like what he said,
which domains you might be
getting external content
from that you put in
your approved list.
But also things like
your storage here.
You have to tell it that
you're going to use storage.
And even for your
sockets, if you're
going to use the
Chrome Socket API,
you need to specify
that, hey, I'm
going to allow TCP connections.
JOHN FEIG: And then we're going
to keep iterating on this.
So one thing that was
interesting was-- here's
my controller to get individual
episodes of a podcast.
And this is the method
here, makeRequest,
that's going to actually get
the data for each episode--
or for each podcast, actually,
and all the episodes within it.
So I do the test up top to see.
If it's chrome.storage, then
I'm in the Chrome environment.
There's probably a
better way to do that.
But that's the
thing that I used.
And now we get this request URL,
which is a really long thing.
What's interesting
here is I'm actually
using a Google service.
So with the Content
Security Policy, again,
and since this is
a podcast app, so I
needed to go through
a single place that's
going to return
the proper headers.
So very basically, with
an RSS feed app like mine,
you want to be able to
subscribe to whoever.
And whoever may not
have a server that's
going to return you the
headers that allow you to make
requests, like cross-site
requests to it.
So what Google's
done is to set up
a service that allows you
to get these RSS feeds
from a single location.
So I can say,
ajax.googleapis.com.
I'm giving that one permission.
It returns me back
the proper header
so that the requests are valid.
And everybody's happy.
The one big difference
between the HTML5 version
and the Chrome version
is in the HTML5 version,
I can actually use this .jsonp
thing, which, basically,
this returns as a callback.
I don't really need this.
There's probably a way that
I could get rid of this
completely in and do
them both the same way.
But it's a little nicer.
This is how I was
doing things before,
where it was-- you see a
callback equals JSON_CALLBACK
and the URL here.
And that works with this API.
And then for Chrome, if you do
that, it'll throw red at you
and say, you're not
allowed to specify
callbacks and responses.
So instead, you just
do a regular HTTP get.
And then in the
success, you can still
parse the data the same way.
So that was the only
difference here, really.
And then, obviously,
the other thing
is you've got to be
able to load images.
And as I showed you
before, it's the same deal.
So yeah.
And then you just iterate until
you don't have any more red.
There probably are going to
be other issues that you'll
run into outside of this stuff.
DARREL SUMI: So just to recap.
You have to really understand
where the Content Security
Policy's coming from.
That's going to be the major
source for most of the errors.
But you have to look into each
of the third-party libraries
that you use.
A lot of them will make
assumptions of what environment
they're working in,
whether that be how they
access sockets, how they access
local storage, what they're
used to being brought in.
So if they use a AMD or Require
style of being packaged up,
you got to understand
how that's all
wrapped around those libraries.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
So I can show-- so
here's the app in Chrome.
Oh, I closed it out.
Never mind.
Yeah.
So here's the app in Chrome.
This stuff works.
It remembers where
you left off because I
saved that information
in local storage.
So I have this method,
refreshInterval.
So every-- I think it's
three seconds, until it's
done playing, I send a message
to say, update the progress
with the current time.
DARREL SUMI: And this gets
saved into the local storage.
JOHN FEIG: It gets saved
into the local storage,
whereas this data is
saved in IndexedDB.
I originally wrote it
with local storage.
And I switched it over to
IndexedDB and cut down like-- I
just deleted a third of my code.
It was really nice.
DARREL SUMI: And
just to reiterate,
the whole point of
that is to make sure
that the transition from offline
mode to online is smooth.
So if you do lose
connection, it does
remember where you left off.
And that's really important
for the whole user experience
point of view.
JOHN FEIG: Yeah.
And there's definitely
some other stuff
that I'd like to
get to in this app,
like basically downloading
the audio ahead of time.
So that if you have no
internet connection,
you can still play your stuff.
That I did not get to.
But it's still a
pretty functional tool.
It's nicer than some
of the other web tools
that I've used, which
is why I built it.
And then we've got--
just throw up some links.
We'll make the presentation
available to everybody
so that they can look at
the stuff on their own.
We have our app that we're
modeling this talk on.
This was actually--
I think, basically,
all we really needed to do to
get KeeChat up and running.
The content security stuff was
more of a minor issue for us.
And then we didn't really
have anything outside
of this that turned out
to be much a problem.
It was a pretty
straightforward conversion.
It took me very little time to
get up and running-- really,
just a couple days.
And this is a pretty
decent-size project.
So I was very surprised
at how quickly
we were able to
do the conversion.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah, definitely.
If you come from the Angular
setup, it's really easy.
JOHN FEIG: And now, we've got
Darrel's socket demo linked,
which has both the server
side and the client side
in the same project.
DARREL SUMI: Yes.
Yep, yep.
JOHN FEIG: And then
I have two versions
of the source for my app.
So I created a
couple branches so
that you can look at before
I started the Chrome App
conversion and after
it was finished.
And these specific branches
will not have any more commits,
so they'll be exactly what
I presented to you today.
And then I wrote a
couple little libraries
that work nice with Angular
and some of these APIs,
like the IndexedDB and
localStorage wrapper.
And I have to get documentation
up for those, but they work.
BRAD GREEN: Good, good.
Guys, thanks so much.
This was a really nice
introduction for Chrome Apps
and the differences between
an HTML5 app and a Chrome App.
I think it'll get people
started really quickly.
And for everyone else,
thanks for joining us today.
We will see you on the web.
We'll share all of these
links to the presentation.
We love to take questions
on Google+ and Twitter.
And we'll see you
at the next GDL.
JOHN FEIG: Thanks for having us.
DARREL SUMI: Yeah,
thanks for having us.
BRAD GREEN: Thanks, guys.