STEVE: So welcome,
everybody, back.
This is the dreaded
after-lunch event
when you're all in
a carbohydrate coma.
So hopefully you'll all wake
up with the fierce debate
that is about to
be ignited here.
The inventor of
the Onslyde system,
Wesley, assures me it's
going to be working.
So please put your hand
up and give an opinion.
You don't have to just
be putting, standing
to ask a question, stand
up, let's ask an opinion.
We want to hear what
you think as well.
Quickly introduce
you to the panel.
Actually, we'll
start from this side.
Pat Meenan from Google, the
inventor of Web Page Test,
basically the best
page load performance
testing tool out there.
Wesley Hales from
Shape Security,
front-end developer, inventor
of Onslyde and loadreport.js.
We have Luke Blaney from
the FT, did a lot of work
on speeding up the FT way back
and is a big fan of Varnish,
apparently.
We have Peter Hedenskog,
from Cybercom Group,
creator of sitespeed.io
and Browser Time.
And last, but not least, we have
Andy Davies, from NCC Group,
Web Performance Velocity
speaker, and the person who's
going to kick off
with the introduction.
Andy.
ANDY DAVIES: Yes.
OK, so Steve's already
introduced me, but I'm Andy,
and I'm frustrated.
And the reason I'm frustrated
is, the web is too slow.
Or rather, too many
sites are too slow.
Because we've been
talking about why
we need to make web pages
faster for a long time.
Steve Souders first invented
the concept back in 2006, 2007,
he wrote his book,
and we understand
how to make sites faster.
And this is one of the reasons
why I really get frustrated.
We know that to
make sites faster,
we need to minimize latency.
Whether that's using CDN
to move our content closer
to our users, whether it's
speeding up our back-ends so
the time to first
byte is quicker.
We know latency doesn't change.
It's governed by
the speed of light.
So we have to move to reduce it.
The other thing we
need to do is cut down
the number of round
trips we make,
because every round trip is
bounded by how quickly we can
make it, or the
latency involved.
And we do this by turning
on gzip to compress stuff.
We use minification.
We merge resources
together in a build system.
And one of the
reasons we do all this
is there's a tension
between how we build sites,
so how we break it down
into modular components.
And the best thought
way to get them
to the browser, for
the browser to be
able to load the page
quickly, render it quickly.
So we can minimize latency, we
can reduce the number of round
trips, and we can
minimize blocking,
because some of our
resources block.
If we've got CSS, we
have to wait for the CSS
before we can render the page.
If we've got JavaScript, we
have to wait for the JavaScript
to execute before
we can move on.
We have web fonts, and depending
on how we load web fonts,
sometimes we have to wait
for them, sometimes we don't.
The other way of
making sites load fast
is to maximize the value we
get out the first round trip.
So when you hear
Paul Irish on stage
at Fluent conference talking
about, put in the first 15K,
this is effectively
what he's talking about.
He's talking about, turn the
initial, TCP initial congestion
window up to 10.
Make, so you get a
roughly about 14.8k,
depending on how big your
TCP segments are in it,
and push that out
to the browser.
Everything you need to render
the page on that first hit.
So that's what the
[INAUDIBLE] [? might ?]
do on the mobile site.
They have the content, the
idea that they serve out
the content, which is the HTML
and CSS to render the page.
They have the
enhancements, so where
they insert JavaScript,
so swiping, and then
they have the idea of leftovers,
so advertising, analytics.
So we can make our pages faster.
But we seem to want to leave
it to the browsers to do it.
And browsers are
doing a great job,
and have done a great
job over the years
of helping us make
our pages faster.
The HTTP standard
recommends we only
have two connections, two TCP
connections to our server,
but we've moved on from that.
Typically browsers have four,
or six, or sometimes even eight.
They open TCP
connections in advance,
they speculate that we're
going to request something
from the same server.
So we open the connection,
it's there ready for us to use.
We have the preloader,
which, while we're
busy waiting for CSS, or blocked
on JavaScript to execute,
the preloader will go looking
through the rest of the page.
Picking up the
resources the page
will need to
complete, prioritizing
them and downloading them
in the most optimal order.
We've got faster
JS engines, we've
got new image formats,
faster layout engines,
browsers are doing a great job.
We also have new protocols.
HTTP doesn't fit very
well on top of TCP.
So we have SPDY now,
we have HTTP/2 coming.
And they will help improve
the performance of our sites.
On some tests I did, I got
a 30% uplift in performance
just by switching
to SPDY, and that
includes the CLS
negotiation overhead.
HTTP/2 may get rid of
some of our build stats.
It may reduce the
need to merge stuff.
We're still going to
have the challenge,
though, that we have people
on HTTP/1 as well as HTTP/2.
And we're going to have to
work out how to optimize both.
But despite all these
improvements, [INAUDIBLE]
across, we keep adding more
and more stuff to our pages.
Our pages are getting fatter.
We're relying on
browsers and networks
to overcome the
performance hurdle.
And perhaps more
worrying, is we're
including more
blocking resources.
Now, the number of times I see
a tweet going, somebody going, I
hate web fonts because this
is the experience I get
and a page with no text on it.
But yet, they've put web
fonts on their own site.
So we're making our pages
more and more complex
and delivering more and
more of a challenge.
We can automate some
of this optimization.
So we talk about merging
stuff and image optimization.
We can use things
like mod_pagespeed,
or Akamai's FEO service to take
some of these optimizations
away, to simplify
our build services.
But OK, so why aren't
we getting faster?
And my view is, we
don't measure enough.
We've got great tools.
This is sitespeed.io
that Peter wrote.
We've got things
like Web Page Test.
We can measure in the
visitor's browser.
So we can measure
the page level.
We can measure
individual resources.
We can tag the page
so we can measure
when something we're
interested in appears.
But there's a lot
of data, and we
need to move beyond which pages
are slow to why are they slow.
This is a waterfall
in Web Page Test.
There's actually some
interesting things
in this waterfall.
In the time to first byte, so
always about 200 milliseconds.
And this is because
I get did test
from Dulles in Virginia
instead of the UK by mistake.
But I ended up looking
at this for a while,
working out what was wrong
with it and took me a while.
And destined to
be a human pattern
matcher for network waterfalls
for the rest of my life,
to help make the web faster.
We need to move on
to how do we fix it.
And we know the older
browsers need resources
to be able to render a page
and get a page to a users,
but we don't really have the
tools to help us get there.
And finally, we
think of performance
as a technical
issue and it's not.
Or I would argue, there are
technical aspects to it,
but we need to go back and
think about performance
as an aspect of user experience.
We go to Fluent, or
Velocity, or Edge Conference,
and talk about page
load performance,
but we need to fit it in to
the rest of the user experience
picture.
We'll A/B test whether a
button should be green or blue,
but will we A/B test how
our performance improves
if we remove our A/B
framework, or our fonts?
We don't generally do it.
We need to design
for performance.
If it's a user
experience asset, we
need to design it info
the way we build sites.
It's just another constraint,
like time or budget.
And design.
Clear left, Tim
Kadlec put forward
the idea of a
performance budget,
so you decide how long should
your page take in slow network
conditions?
How big should it be?
And we need to, as well
as technical solutions,
we need to go and look
for the human solutions.
And we've come a long way.
We've got much faster browsers.
We've got better networks.
But we need better tools.
We need to fit performance and
look at it in holistic ways,
in the way we build websites.
And we also need to be careful
about new technologies.
We've got HTTP/2 coming.
We don't really know, we
know some of the performance
improvements it
makes, but we don't
know what other impacts
may come with it.
We've got Web Components that
we talked about this morning,
and things like the potential
blocking effect of ral
equals import.
And we need to work out if
we deploy Web Components
on a large scale, in a
blocking format, what
are the issues it brings?
And now I believe our moderator
will put to us your questions.
STEVE: So Andy's
frustrated because he's
going to spend the
rest of his career
as a human pattern matcher.
I don't think that
fits in a tweet,
but it would be
really good if it did.
OK so, kickoff, first
question is basically
one on responsive web design
from Peter O'Shaughnessy.
PETER O'SHAUGNESSY: Hi.
Using branched
loading, the Guardian
have made their new website
responsive, but 42% smaller
on mobile than on desktop.
Does this end the
performance arguments
against responsive web design?
Are there still cases when a
separate mobile site is best?
STEVE: You're the front-end
developer representative, Wes.
You want to [? touch that ?]
with this one?
WESLEY HALES: It really
depends on the goals
of the organization, I guess.
I mean, you can have a
separate team sometimes.
Like when I was at CNN, we had
an entire separate team working
on a separate mobile website
for CNN, and then we had a,
and they were
completely divided,
and it was a really
uncomfortable situation,
not being able to cross teams.
It was just the way
they had siloed it off.
So like I said, it depends
on the company, what
your goals are, but it does
make sense for like CRUD,
if you have a heavy client-side
application, single page,
whatever, then
you would not want
to try to scale that
down to put on mobile.
I mean, chances
are, unless you're
trying to achieve the
same thing on mobile,
but sometimes developers
just build for desktop first
in a lot of cases.
STEVE: Pat, you're looking
at web sites all the time,
Web Page Test.
PAT MEENAN: And I think it's
going to get interesting.
We're probaby going to
see this a lot today.
Depending on how extreme
you're trying to get,
like when we start
talking about deliver
the above-the-fold content
in the first 15K, right.
If you're going to try
and do that on mobile,
the first 15K is fairly
easy to get your one
image and your
story or whatever.
What you're trying to
deliver for your first
15K of your desktop or
your responsive site
is going to be very different.
So I think it's
going to be really
hard to do a responsive,
like uber-optimized site,
that scales for both
mobile and desktop.
You may be able to do
well enough in both cases.
ANDY DAVIES: I think
part of the question
is, we know it's
42% smaller now,
but how small could it
be if it was catered just
for that device.
And it's a compromise.
Responsive design
is about building
a site that works on as wide a
variety of devices as possible
at an achievable cost effort.
If you look at the
studies, people
build really small mobile sites.
You can build a
mobile site that's
tens of K, whereas how big is
the Guardian site, Patrick?
PATRICK HAMMOND: 700K
on the mobile site.
ANDY DAVIES: Yeah, so the
42% is still a huge chunk.
So it's a work-in-progress
as to whether the responsive
argument has gone away.
STEVE: Luke, FT, you're in
the same business, publishing.
LUKE BLANEY: Yeah, we still
have the separate mobile site,
and we have a web app as well.
But I think that's more like an
internal legacy sort of thing.
A lot of these things &mdash;
STEVE: It's an organizational
constraint, not
a technology one.
LUKE BLANEY: Yeah, it's
not a technical thing.
And on a lot of these things,
yeah, if you're starting fresh,
you do it completely different.
But if you've got this big
massive website that's already
there, just going
from that to say,
we're going to snap our
fingers and make it immediately
responsive, that's &mdash;
STEVE:
A lot of inertia.
LUKE BLANEY: Yeah,
there's a lot of that.
I think eventually, yeah, it
would be great to get there.
And I think from a performance
point of view as well.
And like, say if
you're supporting
every individual browser,
you can make something really
performant in one
browser, and make
it work in that one
use case really well.
The more and more
things you support,
the more compromises
you have to make.
That goes for just
desktop projects,
for example, you can
optimize to Chrome,
and say I'm going to make this
work really well in Chrome,
and not care about IE.
But every time you
support one extra thing,
you're going to have to make,
it might be small compromises,
it might be big, but
then, and the same
goes for saying if you
want mobile and desktop.
ANDY DAVIES: I
think it depends on
if it's good enough
for your audience.
And it's the YouTube example
of, when they shrunk YouTube,
they got new audiences.
It's whether the Guardian
feel that 700K on mobile
fits their audience.
PAT MEENAN: Well, and
I wouldn't necessarily
even look at the 700K
number, right that's all in.
It's what does it
take to deliver
your initial experience, the
visual experience, right,
and focus on that.
If you can get that small
enough on both the mobile
and the desktop sites
with one delivery,
then you're in a lot better
shape working with that.
STEVE: So we'll take a
question from Guy in a minute.
But just, it comes
back to, does it
end the performance arguments
against responsive web design?
I think we're coming to the
conclusion that that answer is
no, there's still some
arguments for and against.
So Guy, you had a question?
GUY: Well, I wanted
to comment on that.
I think it's just
fundamentally harder
to make a responsive
website faster.
That's just the reality.
So I just ran a test to look at
the top five thousand websites.
If you look at the top, the
responsive or not responsive
websites on the m.dot sites
on the top 5,000 sites,
it's almost the
responsive websites
are about three times
bigger on mobile
than those of m.dot sites.
It's just that m.dot
naturally lends
itself to be more lightweight
and fast, while in responsive,
you need to do a lot of work.
Possibly, eventually, you can
get to the same performance,
but I think we're sort of very
far from the point where it's
just as easy, or
just as implied.
PAT MEENAN: You can
also, I mean it's
not unusual for the m.dots,
especially the legacy ones,
not to be doing advertising
tracking and all sorts
of other things that the
business gets when they're
doing a responsive one, too.
So you sort of- &mdash;
GUY: It's true, and correlation
is not causation, and all that.
But the reality is
that if you are looking
at that anecdotally, it
pretty much, all of the newly
launched websites, it's hard.
Most of them would
have done very little.
At least today, we've
done a good job.
Images, responsive images,
are being tackled much more
frequently, but still,
at the end of the day,
there's just a lot more
excess, as compared
to if you were to do
something dedicated.
ANDY DAVIES: I think one
of the interesting things
is, what do we need in the way
of tools or in browser features
to be able to build sites in
the same way the Guardian have
built their sites.
To make that easy for everybody,
rather than just needing
somebody with Guardian
skill set developers.
PAT MEENAN: And I
think that's probably
the topic I'm going to touch
on most through the day.
It is damn hard to
build a fast site,
and we need it to be easy.
We need it to be
the default case.
We need it to be, especially
like with components,
you just drop them on
and they're fast, right?
Not, you have to figure out
how to cache in local storage,
or figure out how to
plug in service workers
to cache it if you're
offline, and not
to fetch it if they're not.
STEVE: We have two seconds left.
Andrew?
Quick comment?
ANDREW BATES: I think it's a
really frustrating trade-off
because you have, on the
one hand, as Luke says,
you can optimize one particular
user agent very well.
As you try to introduce
more and more,
I think it becomes more
and more of a challenge,
and I think ultimately, that's
not a scalable challenge.
Because, we'll talk
later in Future Web
about things like wearables
and non-conventional devices
and TVs and that kind of thing.
Is responsive web design going
to deliver one single solution
to all of those things, and it
could be performant as well?
I think that's
probably very unlikely.
STEVE: We need to move
on to the new topic.
The next question is
actually from Andrew Bates.
That's called a
seamless segue, people.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDREW BATES: OK, here we go.
So do concatenation and
spriting become anti-patterns
with the advent of HTTP/2?
If so, when?
STEVE: Andy's got an entire
Velocity presentation on this,
so I'll defer to you.
ANDY DAVIES: I think what
we're aware of is what we're
doing when we concatenate
and sprite stuff.
And we're merging
resources together.
So we're merging, say,
JavaScript together
that has potentially got
different rates of change.
And we're making them
more cacheable together.
So if we can split
them out, then we
can cache them individually.
So hopefully they live
longer in the cache.
When do they become
anti-patterns?
It's an interesting...
I'm going to pass
on that for now.
I'll come back to that.
Somebody else pick
it up, and I'll--.
LUKE BLANEY: I think you
could argue at the moment,
spriting already
is an anti-pattern
in some circumstances.
If you're doing it wrong,
and you could have,
forcing users to download a
whole sprite when they just
need one icon, it's
just, that's just
a waste of performance
for everybody.
So doing in the wrong way can
already been an anti-pattern.
And I think HTTP/2 just
makes that more obvious
rather than completely
changing the ball game.
STEVE: Peter?
PETER HEDENSKOG: It
will be hard for us
as developers when we need to
serve to both HTTP.1 and 2.0.
So I mean, we need to find
the best way to do it.
WESLEY HALES: Well we're
kind of doing it now,
I mean, I know I am.
At least with this site.
It runs Speedy [INAUDIBLE]
web but I don't really
care about older
browsers right now.
It's a side project.
So I mean, I could afford to--.
But I mean, the way developers
are developing sites today,
you've got a lot of
controllers or modules,
you have a lot of
different JavaScript files
that you kindof divide out
to organize your application
on the development side.
But it's a tough
question to answer.
Like how do you support both
SPDY today and the older
browsers that don't support it.
I mean, it's almost like,
I don't know, why would you
not concatenate everything?
That's going to
save your older &mdash;
But it doesn't matter
on the newer browsers.
ANDY DAVIES: I think the
challenge is actually
when you need it on the page.
In that, if you've got a web
font that's referenced in CSS,
for example, the browser
has to download the page,
so we don't know anything
about the other resources
until we download the page.
Then we start parsing the
CSS and parsing the DOM
and building a render tree,
to decide we need a web font.
And then we have to
download the web font
and wait for it to arrive.
And the question
becomes, instead
of concatenating or
in-lining stuff in CSS,
is, can we push those
resources using HTTP/2.
To say, can we push
the font object early
so the font gets
there earlier, so we
can render the
page more quickly.
PAT MEENAN: Well, and I don't
think it's even just pushing.
I mean, the big
problem we're going
to have is knowing when you
have to support both, right?
But assuming you don't
have to support both,
it's the granularity
you get by not having
to concatenate all
of that stuff, right?
You'll add all
sorts of JavaScript
into your main JavaScript
file because it's
needed on three pages or
whatever, and all of a sudden,
you're bloating it, and
when you break it out
and you don't start
concatenating,
you can granularly
just pull down
what these individual
pages need.
On the browser
side, the browsers
won't parse and evaluate the
JavaScript until it's complete,
so breaking it down into little
chunks is nice for the browser
as well.
Same thing goes for
the sprite, you'll
have like three
images on there that
are needed for some random
page somewhere else,
and you need to rebuild
the whole sprite any time
you change one of those.
LUKE BLANEY: I
think one thing that
can help with this is
rather than using a sprite
or whatever, is, if
you have something
that your client-side
application can understand
the individual parts,
like on the FT web app.
What we do for
downloading images
is we actually use JSON, and
have all these JSON images.
Then, we can, the
client-side code
can cache each of these
images separately.
And it can handle
them separately
if we need to clear the
cache or anything like that.
We don't have to download
the entire sprite again,
because it understands each
of these individual resources.
It's only for the network bit
that we actually concatenating
them and then we
split them up again.
PAT MEENAN: Right.
But this is all JSON
data URIs, local storage,
back to not making it easy for
people to do the right thing.
STEVE: We had a question
from the audience.
Jonathan Fielding?
JONATHAN FIELDING: With what
you were just talking about,
would you say that
with HTTP 1 and HTTP/2,
you will have to have different
[? application ?] assets
and it will detect
on the server side?
So that people who are
already getting HTTP 1,
they get sprites still, and
using the old anti-pattern's
[? ways, ?] and
then with HTTP/2,
where gzip [INAUDIBLE]
caching form the best it can?
By caching individual images?
STEVE: So effectively,
you're saying,
it's a bit, the same argument.
You're going to end up with
the m.dot version, which
is going to be the
HTTP/2 version.
I'm going to have a load
balancer that sends somebody
the HTTP/2 pool and somebody
still in the HTTP 1.1 pool.
WESLEY HALES: I think
you're not going
to be penalized at
all if you continue
your old ways of development.
They are anti-patterns,
and they do cause us,
as developers, more
frustration, right?
Or more work, essentially.
But I don't think
you're going to be,
actually I know you're
not going to be penalized
for concatenating versus not
concatenating on the HTTP/2
side.
ANDY DAVIES: Well, you get
penalized in cache terms,
potentially.
LUKE BLANEY: But no more so than
you get when there's a block.
WESLEY HALES: But SPDY
pushes straight to the cache,
though, right?
I mean, it pushes straight--.
Yes, there will be, possibly
a larger download, but I mean,
once SPDY, or HTTP/2, once
it opens the connection,
it will push directly
to the cache,
even if you have caching
disabled in your browser.
STEVE: So during this, I
think the issue, if I'm clear,
is, during this
intervening period,
when you have to
support both protocols,
are things going to be painful?
WESLEY HALES: Yeah, it's really,
it's more for the developers,
I think.
It's more for us to
have better workflows
and not have to jump
through so many hoops,
and that's kind of
what HTTP/2 will bring.
ANDY DAVIES: Automate it.
PAT MEENAN: I mean, you'll
have to decide at some point.
Do you have server-side
logic that detects and spits
out the HTML, because
fundamentally it
needs to be in the HTML.
Differently for SPDY or
HTTP/2 versus HTTP 1.
Or do you look at your
traffic mix, and you go, OK,
now we've got 70% of our
traffic coming in that's SPDY
or HTTP/2-capable.
It'll be slower for the older
browsers, or the smaller group,
but it doesn't break.
WESLEY HALES: Right.
It's worth it on
the business side.
PAT MEENAN: It's, you decide
at what point do I cut over?
ANDY DAVIES: Or,
you use something
like ModPageSpeed,
that's protocol-aware.
So it will do the
optimizations for HTTP 1
and it will do different
optimizations for HTTP/2.
WESLEY HALES: I know Google
had a report out last November
about using SPDY
on Maps and Drive,
and a few different properties.
And they observed like, around
a 30% increase on all those,
so, I mean, at least we
have some larger entities
leading the way there.
STEVE: We need to move
to the next topic,
but just on the HTTP/2.
I mean, the timeline,
the specification
is not even due to be
ratified until November.
You've got to get all
of the web server &mdash;
PAT MEENAN: Effectively,
SPDY's out there, right?
STEVE: SPDY's out there now.
PAT MEENAN: IE 11, Chrome,
Firefox, it's effectively,
all the capabilities
are already out there.
So it's, what's
your traffic mix,
what's your server-side
support, and what's your &mdash;
STEVE: So if you're
expecting HTTP/2
to answer all your questions,
it's probably a way away,
but you can start playing
with some of the ideas
and the technology with SPDY.
Next question.
Patrick Hammond.
PATRICK HAMMOND: Hi.
So [INAUDIBLE], as I said
in a [INAUDIBLE] last year,
that we need to move past the
on-page events and metri &mdash;
sorry, the on-load
event and metric.
And we have a lot of
us moving enhancements
to parse that load
event as well.
What is the new golden
metric, or is there one?
STEVE: Peter, I'll
throw that one to you.
You make a tool which
measures performance.
PETER HEDENSKOG: I
mean, it is Speed Index
that I have in Web
Page Test, but we
want to move it
to the other tools
and be able to use
it in RUM also.
I mean, we need to know
when the content is,
above-the-fold conten,
is in the browser.
I mean, that's the
important thing.
Or how do you guys say it?
PAT MEENAN: Yeah I mean,
it's fundamentally,
if you own the site
you're trying to measure,
instrument it.
You are the one who knows
what you care about.
So put on load handlers for
your above-the-fold images,
for example.
Tag your ads so you
know when they load.
And then beacon all
of that stuff back.
I mean, nothing is ever going
to be custom instrumentation.
Doing it generically,
that's when
you start to get into
difficult cases, right?
If you're a RUM service
offering something everyone
and trying to
automatically tell them
when their above-the-fold
content is complete,
that's a much harder,
currently unsolved problem.
Yeah, I mean, synthetic, I
like Speed Index, obviously.
But you really need
to do need to move
beyond the technical point
when everything finished,
because there is so much stuff
on pages these days that's
not user-visible.
All of the ads
tracking, the analytics,
there's even your A/V platform
testing, all sorts of stuff.
The single-page apps
that scroll down forever.
Trying to figure out a
generic complete load time
metric for pages is tough.
ANDY DAVIES: I try
to encourage people
to target start render time.
So when the visitor
actually starts
to see something in the browser.
My preferred option after
that is Speed Index,
which measures when the viewport
is complete, visually complete.
PAT MEENAN: And for
what it's worth,
there is start rendering
the RUM from IE and Chrome,
it's kind of buried in
different places like
window.performance.ms
first pane is IE's.
STEVE: But is it
real, [INAUDIBLE]
if it has a wide screen?
PAT MEENAN: Right.
So you'll want to make sure &mdash;
it's real for some sites
and it's not real for others.
So you want to actually
test the pages you're
looking at first to
see if it's actually
a useful metric for
you, before you start
basing any decisions
based on that.
STEVE: So, quick audience poll.
Who realistically,
in their websites,
are sort of using
the Page.onload event
as their most common
page load metric?
No, yes, no, not many?
ANDY DAVIES: The first
question to start
with is who actually measures
their page load times?
STEVE: OK, so only about
half the audience is actually
measuring their page load times?
Who's actually doing
custom instrumentation,
so they know exactly when
they're above the fold?
OK, and who doesn't work
for the Guardian and the FT?
So OK, Christian,
Christopher Emery, JWT?
CHRISTOPHER EMERY: Yep.
My question was
actually touching
on the meat &mdash; We're
going on about using
the page.onload event as
the kindof de facto, that's
when the page is ready.
I mean, I work for an
advertising company
and I've kindof come
to peace with that,
but actually, it brings with it
a lot of, actually, knowledge.
And actually, in
advertising, they've
actually dealt with this
problem about 10 years ago.
And actually, when you're
building adverts, specifically
digital ones, you
have polite load.
So the idea is the
minimum viable content
that you need on the page
to get it functional,
without distracting the user.
[INAUDIBLE] passive
experiences, when
they dealt with
[INAUDIBLE] page.
So the restrictions
inherent in that platform
mean that we have to be
as efficient as possible.
And actually, now, when we're
doing a lot of sites, now,
we've done actually, some very
effective responsive sites,
we take the same thing.
There's a polite load.
We actually defer
everything that we
need for about 3 seconds, when
the, after the page load event.
The idea  &mdash; that's enough time
for someone to click on a menu
button, and click deeper into
the site, should they want to.
So we're not actually
forcing them to wait.
And this is a strategy
that we're using right now,
and it actually works
quite effectively.
And it means that &mdash; it kind of
blurs the line &mdash; like the page
isn't ready, that page.onload,
but it's actually usable,
and actually, above the fold,
everything looks the same.
As soon as the JavaScript
fires, after 3 seconds,
we then hook into that,
and then all the carousels
start working, all the
interactive videos and things
like that fire up.
STEVE: Patrick, you
got a comment on that?
PATRICK HAMMOND: Just, that's
great, that's good to hear,
from an advertising company
that's actually doing that.
UNKNOWN SPEAKER: Yeah,
I was about to say.
STEVE: It means
it's not going to be
easy to get out
of the room alive
PATRICK HAMMOND: On
that note, something,
going back to
measurement and metrics.
Something that we've
been doing with adverts,
and now that Resource Priorities
API and Timing APIs is here,
we're starting to
have discussions
with our advertising suppliers.
That's so that they
can set the timing,
and allow original
flags, so that then we
will be able to
beacon and measure.
And on our RUM [? drives ?]
have the statistical data,
for the load time
of our investment.
We'll know when things are
going bad or good on that side.
Anyway, it's very pleasing to
hear advertising companies talk
about [INAUDIBLE].
STEVE: And contrary to
sort of, popular opinion,
you generally do want to
get your ads loaded early,
so your users will see
them, click on them,
and you will make money.
So it's really important
that you actually
know when your ads
are loading, though.
And I've talked to several
companies that just stopped
loading ads so that they'll
get faster page load
times, and that's the
wrong answer, right?
It's how do you get
your ads, not competing
with your content, but both
loading visually quickly
for the users, because
at the end of the day,
you still want to make money.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #1: [INAUDIBLE]
interested [INAUDIBLE]
get warning signs from
companies like you,
but you are obviously not
allowed to talk about it.
STEVE: We can talk a
little bit, but, yeah.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #1: This
is like the same problem
with Flash.
Flash solved other
problems that HTML 5 has,
but the information
never got out.
And we probably have a lot of
performance stuff in the ad
space that was never
talked about because
of competitive advantage
over other app providers.
CHRISTOPHER EMERY: If I can
just do a follow-on point?
What I mean, actually,
the previous point
we were talking about, having
a responsive, or actually,
a mobile versus a desktop site?
We're actually
fine, because we're
building, kind of,
campaign sites.
So we're doing it for brand,
it's like 3 to 6 months,
it lives, and then
it kind of dies.
A lot of those,
because they have
a lot of money thrown
at them, both in media
spend targeting to it as well
as, kind of, organic search.
We find it's kind
of a tricky road.
We're actually
finding a lot of times
that having a dedicated
mobile site works.
Because at the end
of the day, there's
like a path to purchase that
we kind of want the user to do.
And the desktop might have
that rich, immersive, kind of,
interactive visual
video experience,
whatever that might be.
But actually, on the,
when it comes to mobile,
the use case is different.
So, actually, we're
finding a lot of times,
even though we push for
responsive over time,
realistically mobile gives you
that direct path to purchase.
There's ad dollars
behind it, you've
got to get the customer's
product sold at the end of it.
STEVE: So to summary, the answer
is there a new golden metric?
No, it's the one you roll
yourself using user timing
in the navigation,
in the timing API.
UNKNOWN SPEAKER: And
beacon it back somewhere
where you actually look at it.
Don't just instrument the page.
STEVE: A bit like
bitcoining; you've
got to mine your own gold.
Right.
The next question is
from Patrick Hammond.
PATRICK HAMMOND: It's me again.
It's actually, this is
a very similar question,
but it's in a different light.
So how, we're now very
well-equipped to measure
our initial page
load performance
with great tools like Web
Page Test and things like RUM.
But yet, we're seeing a rise
in large-scale, long-living,
single-page applications.
But, so, do we need new
tools to measure these,
and new metrics and
new visualizations
to measure long-living
applications that we're
seeing on the web today?
STEVE: So performance
measurement
in single-page apps.
STEVE: User timing.
PAT MEENAN: Well.
I mean, it it's back to
instrument, instrument
it and figure it out.
I mean, you've got &mdash; hopefully
the browsers are giving you
all of the primitives you need
to understand what's going on,
especially in the
single-page apps.
As you swap in content, as
you scroll down and do stuff.
If you're not getting
the primitives you need,
I know we were talking, like
at Velocity Summit a few weeks
ago, or months
ago at this point,
about possibly adding load event
timing handlers or first paint
timing handlers, to images
and stuff like that.
To all elements, so that
you can get the primitives.
But it really does
come down to, you
know what you want
to do with your app.
Time it, beacon it back, and if
you can't get at what you need,
let us know.
WESLEY HALES: I think it becomes
more of a rendering thing, too,
right?
I mean, your page
is already set up,
so it's about image decoding,
and making AJAX requests,
and getting the images
and decoding those.
And any other transforms
you're doing to the page,
and that's really where
it comes into Jank
and other kinds of
measurements as well.
STEVE: It looks like
there's probably
some APM vendors
in the house that
would have a conversation
about &mdash; if you've
got a single-page app that
doing lots of AJAX requests
to the back end, you're sort of,
that measurement is also going
to become more inherently
related to the measurements
of that round-trip time for
that back-end AJAX request.
And you've got to start tying
those two things tighter
together for those
single-page apps.
LUKE BLANEY: I think
it also depends &mdash;
if you're waiting on all those
AJAX requests, like in our web
app.
This was because
we've gone for, we
want something
that works offline.
We try and make it
when you click stuff,
that you're never waiting
for an AJAX request, right?
We want all the content to be
there upfront and in advance.
So it really depends
on your site,
whether you're doing these
click-and-wait for the content
to come, or whether
you're doing something
else in the background.
I think that affects what
you need to measure as well.
WESLEY HALES: So, you guys
are putting everything
in local storage, right?
LUKE BLANEY: Local
storage and WebSQL or SP
depending on the
right [INAUDIBLE].
WESLEY HALES: So what
is like, your limit?
Is there a limit on the
content you download, like,
how do you--?
LUKE BLANEY: We actually have,
like, it's a bit complicated.
There's different modes,
and like, when you first
load, we try and
just get the basics.
So just the article
content, we don't
bother with all of
the images and stuff.
Because, well,
particularly old ones.
You need to press a prompt to
allow you like 50MB of storage
or whatever, and then
we'll go and start
doing all the images and stuff.
But we try to keep all that in
the background where possible.
And it should, we try not to
get in the way of the user.
They should just be able to
navigate the app and not care.
WESLEY HALES: So it comes down
to rendering at that point.
ANDY DAVIES: But are you just
generating another problem?
When they run out of
local storage and they
have to go to actually
start managing local storage
themselves.
STEVE: So if we come back
to the question about do
we need new tools, new metrics,
and new visualizations.
You're saying if a
single-page app measuring
the rendering of that thing
that I've done becomes critical,
do we have the tools?
I mean, Peter, you make tools.
Do we have the tools to
measure that right now?
And I think the answer
is probably not.
PAT MEENAN: Actually we
do, but they're manual.
I mean, you have
the timeline and dev
tools of rendering
and painting events,
but RequestAnimationFrame is
probably your best friend.
But back to, it's not easy.
I mean, figuring out if
your single-page is behaving
smoothly on the
client side in RUM
by hooking together a
bunch of [? RAF ?] calls,
and looking for jank
and that kind of stuff.
It's doable, but
it's complicated.
STEVE: The answer to
that is yes, we probably
do need new tools and images.
LUKE BLANEY: I think,
you get to a point where,
to be honest, sometimes
it's best just having
a manual tester using it and
going, that's a bit sluggish.
There's some things
that &mdash; [INAUDIBLE]
it's not the answer that
you necessarily want,
but having somebody--.
WESLEY HALES: But
then you are limited
by CPU and whatever
your system is running.
LUKE BLANEY: Yeah,
but that's what
the user is going to do
at the end of the day.
That's [INAUDIBLE]
STEVE: We've got a
hand up over here.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #2:
[INAUDIBLE] images?
Is it worth having
maybe, an attribute
for a tag which would
be like, above the fold,
or which would basically give
the browser a hint that this
is your main content that
you want to prioritize.
Or maybe, below the fold,
you'd have a lazy, old time.
UNKNOWN SPEAKER:
There's a combination &mdash;
LUKE BLANEY: It
depends on the browser
what's going to
be above the fold.
You don't know, whenever you're
sending [INAUDIBLE] stuff down,
like, where is that
fold going to be?
WESLEY HALES: There is
no fold in the browser.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #2:
Say, like on BBC,
you'd have all your main
images for your stories,
and then you've got
your sub-stories.
So, you basically want to
prioritize [INAUDIBLE].
PAT MEENAN: Yeah, so
that's not IE-specific.
IE was the first
one to implement it.
It was a W3C spec for
lazy load and, I think,
postpone is the other one.
Or, I'll probably
get the naming wrong,
but there are sort
of two of them.
One is, don't load
this until later,
and one is, I care
less about this.
And it's sort of the opposite
of saying, this is important.
But you'd have to tag
all of your content.
And it's kind of an attempt
to eliminate the js lazy load
implementations for images
while still letting the browser
know about all the content
and give it priority hints.
And so this, is
above-the-fold and important
is basically the
stuff on your page
that doesn't have
lazy load on it.
But you should start seeing it
come out to the other browsers
as part of the same group that
did the performance specs.
STEVE: Got about a minute left.
I'm going to take
one last question
from [INAUDIBLE]
in the back there.
If you can run the mike, or,
yell very loudly, all right?
UNKNOWN SPEAKER: Yeah
well for the video.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #3: So, about
the single-page app topic,
do we need new tools
and new visualizations?
Tooling-wise, so there's
a couple of RUM tools
we worked into this.
There are commercial
ones, [INAUDIBLE]
but [INAUDIBLE] the
frameworks, and I
think the story
is a two-fold one.
First of all, we need definitely
support from framework vendors,
because that's how
we made it possible.
We have to interact with them.
Because a lot of their basic
forms logic we have to follow.
Just like, typing in a keyword
that goes back with an XHR
to the server, updates a
table and then renders it
on the page.
It comes down to
framework instrumentation
that you would have
to do, or frameworks
would build this instrumentation
right into those frameworks.
That's the part
that definitely is,
I thinl, with the
framework providers.
And they have to do it because
they are the one who know best
how the frameworks
actually work.
The other piece
to it is, what we
are really missing is that
piece, like with this framework
instrumentation,
[INAUDIBLE] to the point,
like, updated the
DOM this way, knowing
when certain elements have
been painted on the screen.
That would then be something
I see in the browser.
The question, where do we
fit this instrumentation
of frameworks, on the
one hand frameworks
should build it in, for those
who have not built it in,
you would also have to have
some means in the browser
to instrument the
browser at runtime,
because that's what
you have to do today.
Because RUM tools are often
not able to instrument it
while it disseminates through
the browser, [INAUDIBLE]
and re-processing it.
But it's a tool for all
stories, a framework
story to a great extent.
And there's two
solutions to this,
and it's also a
story, really, when
it comes to rendering,
that really ties down
to the browser.
STEVE: Got to move
on to the next topic,
but just to summarize
that, I think
there was a good
point made there.
The sort of, emphasis, may
be shifting to the framework
vendors to really
help people understand
the performance and the
timing instrumentation
within that framework.
Plus, there's also
the point you're
making about the
browser vendors.
But we've got to move on.
Rich Howard?
RICH HOWARD: So my
question to both the panel
and to the audience
is, what role
will automated front-end
optimization tools
play in our increasingly
complex world?
Do they add yet another
complicated layer
of abstraction or will
they become a necessity?
STEVE: So FEO tools
like, mod_pagespeed
or Riverbed Stingray Aptimizer.
You're a fan of Varnish,
that's a reverse proxy
type [INAUDIBLE].
LUKE BLANEY: I think, I
would classify Varnish
as different than
those sorts of things,
because Varnish behaves
like an HTTP proxy.
It'll follow, by default
it'll follow HTTP headers
and it won't do anything weird.
A lot of these other
ones, I get very
hesitant about using
things that are just
going to do magic in
front of any coder, right?
WESLEY HALES: I think it's
such a large education
process for front-end
developers as well.
I mean, especially
those that might just
be entry-level to mid-level.
It's, a lot of
companies are trying
to take care of things like
performance and security
with appliances.
And plug-ins and things that
go along with the web server.
So I don't know if
it's needed or not.
I mean I don't know if
web developers should just
know the rules automatically,
or if they need the help to &mdash;
STEVE: Peter, first?
PETER HEDENSKOG: Yeah,
I mean, as a developer,
I want to know
what's happened, so I
don't like these kind of
tools, because I don't know,
like I say, the magic,
the magic things about it.
It's made me unsecure, actually.
STEVE: But as an
operations manager,
who's been waiting for
developers to speed up
the website for ages.
If I can sling
$50,000 at Riverbed,
and it makes my
site faster, that's
the cost of one developer,
well, why wouldn't I do that?
Give Andy [INAUDIBLE] a
[? comment. ?] [INAUDIBLE]
ANDY DAVIES: We're
trying to optimize
for different browsers that
behave in different ways.
Different devices over
different network conditions.
I think for a certain
number of cust &mdash; people,
I think it's the only way to go.
I think, because
we're trading off
the cost of employing
developers who may not
be doing a great job
anyway, because there
are some great
developers in the world
and there are some very
average developers.
And we see it in the
way that pages behave.
And it's, if I can deploy
an automated device that
will speed up that site and
give those visitors a better
experience, then why not?
STEVE: I I'll take
a point from Perry,
and can somebody
refresh Onslyde,
because I think it's crashed.
[AUDIENCE]: No.
We were so close.
[LAUGHTER]
So, Perry, stand up
and wait for the mike.
Let's go.
PERRY: So all I
was going to say is
I think I agree with
Steve and with Andy,
because I think we're getting
asked as developers, ops,
webops, whatever we do.
We're getting asked to do more
and more and more with less
and less and less time to do it.
And it's actually the business
that's going to dictate this,
I think.
And I think these kind of
automated tools and devices
are going to be the
only way that we're
going to be able to keep up.
So that's going to be
HTTP/2, versus HTTP 1.1.
We're already
struggling, with just
dealing with what we
have to deal with now.
It's only going to get worse.
We're talking about
later on, there's
going to be new devices,
wearable technologies, TVs
to concern ourselves with.
I just think we're
going to have to do it.
WESLEY HALES: And
for those of us
that are not in the performance
consulting ring, I guess,
it's hard to get
time in companies
to work on performance to
make your pages faster.
It's hard to sell
a lot of bosses
on doing that as developers
who work on an application,
or a site that's driven
by whatever advertising
dollars, whatever
you want to call it.
Someone else's budget
basically and they
don't want to allot for
that performance boost.
I can speak to personally.
PAT MEENAN: And I think there's
some class of optimizations
that you're going
to start getting
more comfortable
with handing off.
The one that comes to
mind, in particular,
is image transcoding
and supporting WebP.
There's a whole bunch of
things that you're not
going to want to have to
rebuild, an image server,
and you'll start pushing off
to appliances or a service
to do for you.
Because you're not going to
want to maintain libraries
of 10 different
image formats as we
get, like, WebP,
jpeg, XR, and whatever
else comes down the pike.
LUKE BLANEY: I think there's
a difference between making
a conscious decision
as a developer saying,
I want to farm this off to
somebody else who is got
to look after my iimages,
to have just some appliance
stuck in front of all your code
that does whatever it wants
because it thinks it's better.
We had problems with
mobile operators doing
this sort of thing,
where they're going,
like, oh, that
bit of JavaScript,
we can optimize that for you.
STEVE: The person who asked this
question works for Vodafone.
LUKE BLANEY: Well,
in the early days
of the web, that was one of
the things that caught us
off guard.
Because operators think that
they know things better than
you.
But if you're a developer
who knows what they're doing,
sometimes you know better
than the appliance,
and the appliance
just gets in your way.
STEVE: I think, will they become
a necessity in our increasingly
complex world, I
guess the question is,
do you see the world &mdash; we've
talked about components,
we've talked about HTTP/2.0
I don't see the world
getting less complex,
so there's only
so much complexity
that you can deal
with as a developer,
surely, before somebody's
going to say, let's hand
this off to an automated
process that does it better.
I'm sure Guy would
say that Akamai,
the next-generation CDNs &mdash;
GUY: Yes, so I'm
totally biased, here, I
work for Akamai [INAUDIBLE],
but I do think that, two things.
One, as opposed to
the carrier proxies,
the intent here
is to be something
that's an extension
of your platform.
So it's to save you time.
It operates based on
your instructions.
Granted, instead of writing
code, you're checking a box.
But you're tuning it and you're
configuring it to your needs.
So, not quite as simple as
a Varnish HTTP construction,
but not that much different
than Varnish in SI,
or the Varnish kind of,
elaborate caching policies.
So, that's just sort
of a general thought.
And yeah, and I think
the point I come back
to every time we talk
to users of this,
or people considering
using it, is
if you can automate
it, why do it manually?
So the exact range of were
the tools good enough,
or were they not good enough,
what is your level of comfort?
That's something
that as an industry
we still need to
evolve and improve.
But I think at
the end of the day
if you have a way to
do it automatically
and it encompasses knowledge
and takes away complexity,
the only reason not to
do so is that you're not
used to it, right, and
you can overcome that.
STEVE: 30 seconds if you want it
CHRISTOPHER EMERY: I
just want to add on
since I know what you're saying.
It's great to
[INAUDIBLE] yourself
to try and act as an
extension of the platform.
But actually, in my experience
with the kind of clients
I'm dealing with, our
MSAs don't actually
give us free rein
on our platform.
We have to play by their rules.
So a lot of times,
what is in our control
are things like the build
tools, optimizing things down
on our end with the [INAUDIBLE]
before we get onto that
platform.
So a lot of times, like I
say, sticking to the basics
effectively is often
the best platform.
STEVE: Go over here.
One last, very quick question.
Or very quick comment.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #4: I'm
interested in the hardware
side of this, because I
work for a hardware company.
For me, load time
is important, yes,
you need to get stuff down
as quickly as possible,
but what's more
important is how quickly
the user can see this stuff.
And that goes
through the hardware.
You were discussing stuff
like, batching is bad,
but do you consider the
hardware underlying as well.
Batching is really
good for the GPU.
PAT MEENAN: So
batching, a GPU doesn't
know how to deal with a
sprite, though, right?
So, as far as the
browser's concerned,
the GPU doesn't deal
with the sprite.
The GPU deals with the
sprite in a whole bunch
of different places
and clips it,
and doesn't deal with
it better than images.
STEVE: So I'm going
to have, I'm going
to have to cut that
one off, and you
can take it offline,
because we've
got about five minutes left and
we still have a question to go.
From [? Paul ?] Lewis, which
actually ties in very neatly
with something that was
just mentioned, actually.
PAUL LEWIS: My
question got tweeked.
Which is the topic
of the day, so I
thought I'd fight fire with
fire and tweek it back.
How should teams balance
branding and personality
against performance.
I guess I have web fonts
and images and such in mind,
and how can they
meaningfully measure
the benefits of branding
versus the benefit of speed?
And I hashtagged
#perfmatters on that.
STEVE: Hashtag
#perfmatters, always good.
I mean, you started to talk
about this in the answer
to the previous question.
You come up again, do you
think, the designers want
their cool web fonts, they don't
necessarily want performance.
WESLEY HALES: Right,
it's the same argument
as the mobile versus
desktop side, I guess.
I mean, you have to measure, the
business knows what it wants.
Whether it's a brochure site
or whether it doesn't want
it's users to drop off because
the page load time is too high.
Or whether there's a lot of
jank going on in the page,
because they can't scroll down
the page and their user base
drops because of that.
So it's about, do you
want better performance
or do you want a
better-looking site?
I guess there's a balance
somewhere in between there,
but right now, you really have
to focus on one or the other,
I think.
STEVE: So who's had
this conversation
with their business?
So who wants to stand up
and reach for the microphone
to say, we've had this
conversation with our business.
And this is how we tackled it.
Oh, Patrick, go on, you know
you want to, Or next, go on.
Tag team it.
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #5: Yeah,
we've had this conversation
quite a lot, actually.
STEVE: So what organization?
UNKNOWN AUDIENCE #5:
The Guardian, again.
So designers like their
beautiful web fonts,
but mobile users don't like to
wait for the text to show up.
So what we've found
is that maybe we
could find a compromise.
Maybe you can have the realy,
really iconic fonts in there
on mobile, but the
other fonts, maybe you
can load them only on desktops.
So that's the kind of
compromise we came up with.
ANDY DAVIES: Can I add
a support question?
Yeah, because the other,
the thing lots of people
do is, we talk about
fonts, and how many people
just chuck Open Sans
or a font on the page,
without considering all
the font glyphs in it.
So there are, even
using web fonts,
there are optimization options.
In the &mdash; take out the
glyphs we're not using.
Which takes &mdash; Open
Sans off Google,
if you start stripping
it down to just font,
the font glyphs you
need for English,
It ends up being 60%
of the original size.
Sorry, 60% reduction in size.
So you end up with
a much smaller glyph
that's quicker to download.
That you can embed
as a data URI,
so you avoid the round trip.
It's a choice.
Some brands, it's
as a brand, measure
what the impact of
performance is having.
And test whether you can
take stuff out of the page
and still keep your brand
quality, and whether that
has an impact on visits
or behavior. this
STEVE: I think maybe
the panel is still
missing the question, which is,
how do you get your business
to engage in this conversation?
And I think the
answer has to be,
you've got to be able to
measure the performance
and tie the performance back to
the measurement of your site.
Perry gave a presentation
at Velocity this year,
where he gave some
great examples.
Where they were tying
it into the analytics,
they tied it into
their Adobe Omniture,
so the marketing
people could see
very clearly that conversion
rate changed at this point
in time.
So step one is, measure
your performance.
Step two, measure the
performance with money.
Step three, start doing
A/B testing of slow
versus fast, or pretty
versus not-so-pretty.
PAT MEENAN: And
the key thing there
is make sure your
performance data is
in with the business metrics.
Having them
completely separately,
where they can't,
sort of, correlate
the two to each other.
It becomes a really big problem.
It becomes difficult to
say, the extra two seconds
is costing you 10,000
users a day kind of thing.
But if you want to
have a conversation,
just strip out
all the web fonts.
They'll come find you.
UNKNOWN SPEAKER:
If you're trying
to figure out how to
start the conversation.
CHRISTOPHER EMERY: I just want
to say, with regards to this.
I've actually had this exact
conversation with our clients.
And because the type
of company I'm in,
we actually have a
lot of media money
in terms of TV ads
pointing at web properties.
And we actually find that
a lot of the conversation
about performance is
actually being talked about
by the clients,
actually out of fear.
And it's actually two
sides of the coin.
We're talking page
load performance.
And if the server can't
handle the load coming in,
it's pointless about
fonts and stuff like that.
So, a lot of our conversations
actually start off with,
OK, well, what's the media buy?
OK, we are
expecting &mdash; it's going
to be on how many TV channels?
Stuff like that, who
are they driving to,
we have to keep the server up.
So there's that part of it.
And then on top of
that, it then becomes,
a path to purchase with
regards to buying a product,
then it becomes, OK, well,
how fast can they do that?
Not so much, if there
are different parts
of the site that load a
little bit slower, that's OK.
It depends on that
critical path in terms
of how fast they can get to
kind of click the volume button.
So in terms of the really big
brands are talking performance,
but it kind of comes
from a fear factor
that they don't want
the site to go down,
they don't want to
be a laughingstock.
And they don't want to
lose their kindof, value.
It was the performance
of metrics,
how many visitors to how
many people purchase.
STEVE: We're going to
have to wrap it up there,
I'm sorry not to be able
to get to your question.
But we've actually reached
the end of the session.
I think the message there is,
play the fear, uncertainty,
and doubt card.
And your site will crash if
you put all this stuff on it.
Which is not an argument
I like from an operations
point of view, because it's my
fault if the site goes down.
But anyway, thanks
very much, guys.
Thanks to everybody on the
panel for contributing.
Thanks, great contributions
from the floor.
And, yeah, well done.