Hi! My name is Colt MCAnlis, and I am a Developer
Advocate for Native Client. In this video,
I am going to explain how you can get started
using Native Client to create applications.
The first thing you need to do is get the
SDK and run naclsdk update. This downloads
and unpacks the up-to-date tools, headers
and libraries that you’ll need to build
Native Client applications.
Then my recommendation is to become more familiar
with Pepper. Pepper is a set of bindings that
expose the power of the web platform to C
and C++, giving your program the same capabilities
that JavaScript has. You can start by running
some of the examples and inspect their code.
Understanding the build process is also critical.
Start by running the SCons builders, and then
look at the output.
Once you familiarized yourself with Native
Client’s basic architecture, then you are
ready to build your project. If you are porting
or building your app from an existing code
base, then you’ll need to make three key
changes:
First you’ll need to make your C and C++
source code portable; for that use only the
portable dialect of C and C++.
Second you will need to use the Pepper interfaces
to access resources like graphics, audio,
and input devices. This step makes the resulting
application OS-independent, because Pepper
is an OS-independent API.
Third if your application uses hardware accelerated
graphics, you will need to adapt it to use
OpenGL ES 2.0.
Once your project is done, then you need to
package it as a Chrome Web Store app - this
way you will be able to reach more than 200
millions Chrome users.
To learn more on how to use Native Client
check out our documentation at gonacl.com.