[MUSIC PLAYING]
PETE: All right, everybody.
All right.
We're getting ready to start.
Thank you for coming out for
our performance event tonight.
And thank you for making it the
biggest one we've ever done.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: So a couple
of things to know.
The way it's going
to work tonight
is we have three speakers.
After the speakers, we're
going to have some dinner.
It's going to be tacos.
We fought for better food.
We got you better food.
After that, Colt
McAnlis from Google
is going to do something
that if you've never
seen someone do before, it's
pretty awesome to watch, which
is dissect sites for
their performance.
That's going to be great.
The first speaker tonight,
make sure you're all
on the wireless.
Did everyone see the web page
they were supposed to go to?
Jake will remind you.
This is going to be
an interactive one.
So get your phones ready
to connect to that site.
There's going to be quizzing.
There's going to be answering.
There's going to be minds blown,
like, wait, that's a thing?
Then we're going to have Eitan
talking about the "New York
Times."
And we're going to be having
Adam Grossman from Forecast.io
talking about Forecast.io
or Forecast.io?
ADAM GROSSMAN: It
is now Forecast.io.
PETE: It's Forecast.io?
ADAM GROSSMAN:
It's just Forecast.
PETE: Just Forecast.
OK.
It's just Forecast.
Sorry.
Which if you haven't looked
at, you really should.
But first, Jake
Archibald from Google
is going to give
his excellent quiz.
One more thing.
Sorry.
Bathrooms are on the
sides if you need to.
And anything else, Chris?
Did I get it?
OK.
Jake Archibald from Google.
[APPLAUSE]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So, yeah.
This is going to be a quiz.
So if you're not on the Wi-Fi,
get yourself on the Wi-Fi now.
The username and
password is on there.
And then once you've done that,
if you want to go to this URL
and make up your own
username and password.
So obviously not the same
username and password
or a bunch of you will
be on the same account.
So you won't be able
to get to that URL
if you're not on
that Wi-Fi network.
So make sure you are.
And if you're watching this
on the live stream, tough luck
I'm afraid.
You've just got to play
along using your brain.
And you can write
things down on paper
and score yourself if you want.
So the reason I'm asking
you for a username
and password is just so you can
switch devices halfway through,
in case one, your phone
starts running out of battery
and you want to
switch to your laptop.
Just use the same
username and password.
And everything will work.
The password is stored in
plain text on my machine.
So don't use your credit card
number or anything like that
unless you are intending
to make a donation.
And that will be
gratefully received.
Thank you very much.
So I'm going to assume
everyone's ready to go.
I will keep the URL in
the corner of the screen.
So if anyone loses it, you'll
be able to pick it back up.
I hacked this
together on a plane.
You could probably break
it by trying to break it.
So please, don't
try and break it.
I've made it so little
Bobby Tables can play.
That's not going to break it.
But there are
probably other things.
You could probably DOS it.
So please don't do that.
And I want to stress that
this quiz is pretty tough.
I've seen it get
the better of people
who do this kind of study of
browser quirks for a living.
So if you're the kind of
person who gets really angry
and starts flipping over
tables when you don't win,
then just maybe stay away from
the tables for a little while.
OK.
Of course, what
kind of a quiz would
be complete without a prize?
So the Chromebook Pixel
is Google's latest laptop,
featuring an i5 1.8
gigahertz dual core
processor, 4 gigabytes of RAM,
and a touchscreen with a higher
DPI than a MacBook Pro.
Couldn't get hold
of one of those.
Sorry.
They wouldn't let me.
But what I did get
is a Chromecast.
So I've got one of
those to give away
for whoever gets
the highest score.
So it's not quite a Pixel.
But it's very, very good.
So let's start.
Let's start off really simple.
And so the URL is there in
the bottom of the screen
if you need it again.
But here's a nice easy start.
You've all worked with
images in HTML, right?
OK.
So here's a DIV.
But it has a source,
like an image might.
Which browsers do
you think are going
to make a request
for that image?
Now, on your phones
or on your laptops,
you should be presented
with the option.
So you pick which ones you think
are going to make a request.
And then hit submit.
If it's not appearing
on the screen
or the icons aren't, you
can just give the page
a refresh and that
should come through.
When we're talking
about these browsers,
I mean the latest versions
of each one, so I10,
et cetera, et cetera.
You get one point if you get it
right for a particular browser.
You lose a point if you get it
wrong for a particular browser.
So there's a maximum of
four points per question
and a minimum of minus 4.
You can score negatively.
You can assume the
HTML5 doc type.
And there's nothing
hidden going on.
I'm not going to turn around
and say, oh, but there's
a base element
that's changing URLs.
There will be none of that.
It's just what's there on
the screen, that one line.
So what we're seeing here is
like a live opinion of the room
as well.
So the needle swings one way
when you're saying collectively
that yes, the browser
will make a request.
It will swing the other
way if you're saying no.
But I'm going to
randomize which way
is yes and no for each
question, so you can't just
look at the screen and
vote along with the room.
OK.
So that's probably enough time.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
OK.
So we can see from
this that your result
is saying Chrome is going
to make a request here.
You're less sure about
the other browsers.
And the answer is no.
None of the browsers are going
to make a request in this.
But it's not actually
as mad as it seems.
So this doesn't work in HTML5.
But it was proposed in XHTML2.
So XHTML2 allowed
you to do this,
put a source
attribute on anything.
And it would replace
the content with what
you had in the source.
And this was really
good, because it
meant that the old
attribute on images
became redundant
because you could
replace real semantic content.
A pretty cool idea.
But XHTML2 was
backwards incompatible.
And it carried with it XML's
draconian era handling.
And once you invite XML into
your home, it XMLs everything.
XML is all over the
floor, up the walls.
And in the same way that Smurfs
stick the word Smurf in front
of everything to make
it a Smurf thing,
XML does it with X.
You don't want HTML.
You want XHTML.
You don't want Frames.
You want XFrames.
You don't want Forms.
You want XForms.
If you let XML take
over your life,
it will turn your
boyfriend or girlfriend
into an ex-boyfriend
or girlfriend.
And XML is cool with
that, because you
don't need a partner anymore.
You've got XML to
look after you.
It seems fitting
that in 2009, XHTML
became an ex-specification.
And it was completely abandoned.
And no browsers ever implemented
that source attribute
on elements of images and
the things they work on now.
OK.
But what about this?
So here we've got
an image element.
It's got a source.
It's in the page.
But I've spelled
image incorrectly.
I've put it I-M-A-G-E
rather than I-M-G.
Does the browser treat
it as an unknown element?
Or does it make the request?
The browser only has
to make the request.
It doesn't have to
display it on the page,
in case you think that matters.
XML was too strict
to work with the web.
But is HTML this lenient?
Or are the browsers more
lenient than the spec?
Just get your
answers in quickly.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
And it's closed.
So we're edging towards
no in all of the browsers.
All of the browsers will make
a request for this image.
And they will display
it, because, in the past,
a browser decides that IMG is
quite difficult for developers
to remember so they should
support I-M-A-G-E as well.
And we've been stuck
with it ever since.
Which browser
engine do you think
we've got to thank for this?
Yep.
You've guessed it.
It is Mosaic back in 1993.
The people who
invented the image tag,
they put this alias in.
And a study in 2005
showed that 0.2% of pages
were using this
misspelled image tag.
So any browser that
wants to work on the web
that we have today has
to duplicate this alias.
The WHATWG recognized that.
And they added it to the spec.
This is the parsing spec.
It was start tag, name image,
change the token to IMG,
and reprocess it.
Don't ask, which was great.
But this was actually used
in a clever hack recently.
Alexi 10 came up with
this, which I really liked.
You would use this in place
of your image elements.
What it does is it loads an SVG
for browsers that support SVG.
And it loads a PNG for
browsers that don't.
So the way a modern browser
would parse it is it sees SVG.
And it goes, OK,
it's got a width
and height of 100%
of 100 pixels.
And it sees this.
And it sees this as
an SVG image element,
because in SVG,
images are spelled out
full rather than IMG.
It's got width and height.
And I'm going to load
this, because this
is how you define the
source of an image in SVG.
Because why have Links
when you could have XLinks?
And then it sees this.
And that doesn't mean
anything to SVG images.
So it's ignored.
So we're now showing
the SVG image.
An older browser, such as
Android 2 or IE8 and below,
they will parse it like this.
No idea what that is.
I'm going to ignore it.
I'll treat it like
an unknown element.
Oh, look, the developer
has spelled image wrong.
It's OK.
I'm going to
correct it for them.
It's 100 by 100.
No idea what that means.
So I'll ignore that.
And then, oh, there's
the source of the image.
They're going to
download the PNG.
So it's kind of nice because
it doesn't require JavaScript.
And it's a nice way
to conditionally load
the kind of file that
the browser supports.
We got quite excited about it.
And we were tweeting about it.
The mistake we made
is we did not test it.
So a few of us did just that.
And we found out
something interesting.
All of these
browsers support SVG.
But which browsers will
download the PNG as well?
And I'll give you a clue.
It's not all of them.
Not all of them get it wrong.
It's just one or
some of the browsers
that are going to
get this wrong.
And they'll end up downloading
both, both the PNG and the SVG.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
OK.
So we're saying no in all
the browsers and yes in IE.
It's almost like
you've been burned
by that browser in the past.
Well, the answer
is, you are right.
Internet Explorer will make a
request for two images here.
And it's because
all modern browsers,
they've got two parsers
built into them.
It's a relatively new
thing for them to have.
But they all have it.
One parser runs ahead.
And it goes, and it
tries and find things
like it should download,
like scripts and images
and whatever.
And the other parser comes along
and does the heavy lifting,
like building the DOM
tree, parsing scripts,
et cetera, et cetera.
And this has a
really large benefit.
A study we did at Google,
we looked at 2,000 sites.
And we added this preloader.
And we got a 20%
speed improvement
to get to DOM content loaded.
So it's really useful.
But in order to be
quick, this pre-parser
is a little bit stupid.
And in Internet Explorer, it's
a bit too stupid at the moment.
It kind of gets over excited.
It's like, oh, look, I'm
going to show this PNG.
I'm going to show this PNG.
Here I go.
Showing the PNG.
Oh, no.
Actually, I won't.
It's actually an SVG.
I'll do that instead.
So the main parser
sees the markup.
And it sees the image.
But it misses the SVG context.
And then the main parser
comes along and goes, well,
why am I downloading PNG?
And it cancels that download
and goes for the SVG instead.
But by that point, it's
made the connection.
It's probably got all of
the image by that point.
The moral here is don't
trust performance tips.
Make sure you test things.
At Chrome, we say, tools
not rules, which rhymes.
So I guess it must be true.
But always be on the lookout for
existing data or existing tests
that you can run.
One of my favorite stories
in science or a tale &mdash; I
don't know how true it is.
But it involves this
man, August Weismann.
And he wanted to disprove
that life experience was
part of evolution, like
something that happened
to you during your life would
be passed down as evolution.
So the way he was going
to disprove this is he
took two mice.
And he cut their tails off
and bred them together.
And then he took
the offspring there.
And he cut their tails off
and bred them together.
And the idea was
we shouldn't end up
with mice being born
without tails, right?
And he was running this
test for quite a while,
until one of his colleagues
pointed out, August,
you do realize that Jewish
people have been inadvertently
carrying out this experiment
a lot longer than you have.
Oh, yeah.
So he stopped his test and
just used that as evidence.
So what about this?
We've got a DIV.
It's displaying none
as an image inside it.
So the image won't be displayed.
But which browsers are
going to download it anyway?
So, yeah, it's not
going to render.
So you could say it's a
waste of bytes to do so.
Or maybe some browsers are going
to get it just in preparation,
thinking it might be shown.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So we're leaning towards
yes for every browser.
We're quite certain it's going
to happen in Internet Explorer.
The answer.
Collectively, you are correct.
Yes, all of the
browsers here are
going to download that image.
And this behavior
is part of the spec.
So in the browser, in the
beginning, there is nothing.
And then the browser gets
sprayed with HTML text.
And it will convert that
text into a tree of elements
that we know as the DOM.
When this is HTML, when a tag
is turned into an element,
the construction steps
for that element are run.
And for image, it's really
complicated, actually,
creating an image element.
But step 14 down
here at the bottom
is where it actually makes the
request and requests the image.
So visibility doesn't
matter at all.
It doesn't come into it.
And that's good, because it
means that your images can
download before your
CSS is downloaded,
before your scripts
have downloaded.
As a downside, it meant that
responsive images, polyfills,
did not work.
Because by the time your
JavaScript gets to the image,
it's already
started the download
of the thing that
was there already.
You're just going to
add a second download
by changing the source.
This won't be a problem in the
future, the resource priority
spec.
We've specified the
postpone attribute,
which tells an image
that it shouldn't display
if it's displaying
among other things.
But what if we are using CSS?
What then?
So here we've got a DIV
that's displaying none.
And inside, there's a DIV
with a background image.
So it's similar
to the image one.
But we saw that images
are ignoring CSS.
But here we're actually
in CSS land already.
So are there any browsers that
are going to download that?
Or are they just
going to ignore it?
So once again, it's not
going to be displayed.
So you could consider
it a waste of bytes.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So we're edging towards
yes in every browser.
I'm afraid not.
No browsers are going
to download it here.
Not at all.
And I suppose you could
see that as a good thing.
It's saving bytes.
But what if we did this?
Similar question.
It's a DIV, displaying none,
and it has a background image.
So the difference
in the last question
is it's all on one element.
The images isn't inside another
element that's displaying none.
Does that change things?
Once again, it's not going to
need that background image.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So we're edging towards
yes in every browser,
a little bit more
confident in Chrome.
Most browsers will.
Firefox will not.
So what's going on here?
So once the browser has
this tree of elements,
it needs to work out
what they look like
and where they go on the page.
And the first step of this
is a style calculation.
So it calculates all the styles.
It goes through the
CSS cascade, the style
attributes, the font tags
if you're from the '90s,
and works out what style
applies to each element.
But not everything gets
its style calculated.
So this DIV up at the top
turned out to be display none.
The browser stops there.
It doesn't calculate
for the children,
because those elements
have no impact
on the rendering of the page.
So it shortcuts.
So if these elements
have a background image,
the browser just never
finds out about it.
This DIV up at the top
here is displaying none.
But it did have its
style calculated in order
to find that out.
And that's when the browser will
discover the background image.
Firefox is a little bit smarter
here and avoids the download.
But if you change that to
instead of displaying none,
you use visibility
hidden or opacity zero,
Firefox would download as well.
Who's getting it right
according to the specification?
Everyone is.
The spec is really vague here.
It says the browser
may optimize,
even if the element
is just obscured.
It's underneath another one.
But no browsers are that smart.
This kind of freedom
in specifications
is good, because it
means the browser can
do the right thing given the
device, the connectivity,
maybe even the battery percent,
how much battery you've
got left.
But it's also scary, as it
means the browsers are doing
different things, as
they try new stuff
with that freedom they have.
But I think that
kind of diversity
is what makes the web great.
It's not one company driving
forward with its own interests.
It's lots of companies
driving forward
in different directions.
And we get this car crash
but with a happy ending.
And that's the web
that we have today.
If you want to avoid
downloading a CSS background,
hiding the element isn't enough.
You need to put it
inside an element that
is displaying none.
But when you do
this, you are just
relying on what
browsers do today.
It's not specified behavior.
Browsers may change.
The only sure-fire way is
make sure the browser doesn't
find out about that
background image.
Don't add the class name
that adds that background
or don't add the
element to the DOM
at all until you really need it.
OK.
Things have been
relatively easy so far
because we weren't
involving JavaScript.
So let's get
JavaScript involved.
What about this?
I'm creating an image.
I'm giving it a source.
I'm not putting it
in the document.
And I'm spelling
image incorrectly,
like we did before.
So we saw in HTML that it
was also correcting I-M-A-G-E
to I-M-G. But does it
do the same in the DOM?
Do images even download when
they're not in the document?
Because once again,
the browser doesn't
need to render this yet.
Or it can't render this yet.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So this is the point in the
quiz where the audience just
gets broken.
And the needles just drift
towards the center of I
don't know what's going on.
In this case, most
browsers will download.
Firefox won't.
And there are two parts
of this explanation.
As we saw before,
the DOM gets parsed.
And the creation steps
of the elements are run.
This animation took
me a long time,
which is why you've seen
it three times already.
But that is the last time.
But when an element is
created using DOM stuff,
it's still going to
run the creation steps.
And we saw for
images, at step 14,
that is going to be when
it downloads the image.
We can use this
to our advantage,
because this one line, you can
make a GET request to anything
that the machine can access.
And in fact, images have
their own DOM constructor,
unlike a lot of other elements.
So that tiny bit of
code, instant GET
request to anywhere else.
And this is pretty much how
Google Analytics talks back
to the server.
But we saw before that Firefox
didn't make the request.
So what's going on there?
When we create this, most
browsers &mdash; Chrome, Safari, IE &mdash;
will give us an HTML
image element back.
Whereas Firefox will
give us an HTML element.
It's not an image.
If you add it to the page,
it won't display an image.
And the interesting
thing is here,
it's the only one
getting it right.
We saw before this is
how the browser that
had the spec deals with images
that are spelled incorrectly.
But this is in the parsing spec.
And we bypassed parsing
by using create element.
We're completely
bypassing the parser.
Well, Firefox gives
us an HTML element.
It should give us an
HTML unknown element,
which it does if you
do create on Fubar.
So Firefox is doing something
special for these images.
But it's getting it more
right than other browsers.
I think I preferred it when we
were developing for browsers.
It was like there
was one bad guy.
And it was Internet
Explorer 6 or 7 or 8.
And all the other browsers
seemed perfect in comparison.
But I see the browser scape as
being like an orchestra, where
Internet Explorer
8 was just this kid
hitting two cymbals
together and screaming.
But once we finally kick
the screaming child out
of the room, and we come back
and we start conducting again,
we realize, oh,
everyone's actually
a little bit out of tune.
We just didn't realize because
of the screaming cymbal child
of Internet Explorer.
So let's get CSS involved
again but JavaScript as well.
What about this?
So I'm creating a DIV.
Giving it a background.
It's not in the document.
But everything's
spelled right and valid.
We saw images download
at this point.
But what about when
CSS is involved?
Are we going to see
things download there?
Get your answers in quickly.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So once again, the needles
drift into the middle.
The answer here is no.
No browsers will download here.
This is the same as
the display none case.
The browser won't
calculate the style
of elements that display none.
And it also won't
calculate the styles
of elements that aren't in
the document, because there's
no point.
It doesn't affect the
rendering of the page at all.
OK.
I'm going to be cruel now.
What about this?
So same again.
I'm adding it to the document.
Then I'm removing it again.
Is it in the document long
enough for the browser
to go, oh, I should download
this background image?
Or does it not get to
see it long enough?
Does it not bother?
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
OK.
So we're suggesting
yes, because yes, it
has entered the document.
I'm afraid you are all
wrong with that one, all
the people who said that.
The browser doesn't want to
think about styles or layout
until the very last moment.
And that's normally
rendering, when it actually
needs to change
pixels on the screen.
And we can't do
that or we don't do
that while we're in the
middle of JavaScript.
So the browser
actually sits back
and waits for that
JavaScript block to execute.
And then afterwards, it will
go and look at what's changed
and react to that when
it needs to render next.
But does this change that?
So same code again.
But in between adding and
removing it to the document,
I'm going to ask for the
text content of the element.
Now, the text content is
going to be an empty string
because it is an empty element.
But is just accessing
that property
going to change things?
I'm not even assigning
it to a variable.
So is it just even going to be
optimized away by JavaScript
because it has no impact?
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
Almost dead in the middle.
Excellent.
The answer is no.
No browsers will make a request.
Getting the text
content is easy.
It's just going to go through
the DOM, find the text nodes,
and catenate the
values together.
What about this?
Similar question.
But this time, enter HTML
rather than text content.
Once again, it's going to be
an empty string that comes back
there, because the
element is empty.
But does it behave
differently to text content?
Are the browsers going to
do something different?
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So we're saying no here.
You're mostly right.
Internet Explorer will
make a download here.
And the reason for that is
because in Internet Explorer &mdash;
I don't know.
I have absolutely no idea.
Some things in the world
cannot be explained.
And this is one of them, like
how it takes three attempts
to plug in a USB cable, even
though there are only two
possibilities.
Some things cannot be explained.
OK.
So on the same theme again
but this time in a text.
Once again, like
the other two, this
is going to come back as an
empty string, because it's
an empty element.
But is that going to
behave differently?
Is Internet Explorer still going
to make the request erroneously
like it did before?
Is it going to get
it correct this time?
Who knows.
I'm going to close the
question in three, two, one.
So we're edging towards no.
A little bit less sure
on Internet Explorer.
The answer &mdash; yes.
Most browsers will
make a request here.
And this actually makes
sense in an odd way.
Let's make a DIV.
It's got a background image.
And it's got some inner HTMLs.
It's got Hello World inside it.
But World is inside
a DIV of its own.
We add it to the document.
We ask for its text content.
It's Hello World.
But when we ask for the inner
text in IE, Safari, and Chrome,
it's going to return this.
It's got a line
break in the middle.
And the reason for this is inner
text isn't just a text content.
It's more like
what you would get
if you highlighted the
element and copied it.
And because of this, it's
got style information,
because the world is
on a different line,
because the DIV is block level.
Or it is by default.
And it is in this case.
So what actually happens
here is the browser,
we asked for the text content.
It just gets that back.
But when you ask for the inner
text, the browser has to go,
ah, I need to know what
the layout of this element
is in order to return this.
I need to find out if
that DIV is block level.
Where am I going to
put my line breaks?
Oh, look.
There's a background
image there.
And it downloads it,
because it forces
it to look at the styles.
Most of the time,
the browser will
defer looking at styles
as late as it can.
But here we forced it to
happen sooner because we've
asked for something
that's style dependent.
Firefox didn't make
a request because it
doesn't support inner text.
It doesn't support
the property at all.
So that's just undefined.
That was quite cruel.
But if we used any
of these properties,
like offset left,
offset parent, Firefox
would have made the
request as well.
So with ignorance of
those elements that
will require style
information, that's
one of the number one
problems with performance
that we see on the web.
But also, you can do some
nice hackery with it.
If you look at code like this,
it looks really expensive.
But it's not.
It's really cheap, because
the browser is just
going to sit back and
watch you just writing
this property to an object.
And it's not going to care
about it until that block ends.
And once that's all done, it
will just look at the results.
And in this case, there's
no pixel difference.
This can lead to some
unexpected results, not just
graphical performance.
So let's have a look
at a practical example.
Here is Paul Lewis and me.
We work together.
We want to go over there.
You can tell because
we're pointing.
But let's do it with code.
We're going to say left 0%.
We're going to set a
transition, and then left 100%.
If we run that code, off we go.
Excellent.
We win at code.
But if we run that code
again, nothing happens.
And the reason
nothing happens is
the browser is going to
batch up these style changes.
So we're saying left twice.
But the browser is only going
to listen to the last one.
And we're essentially
saying, transition to 100%.
But we're already at 100%.
So it doesn't move.
You might have
encountered this and tried
to fix it with set timeouts and
an arbitrary number in that.
But what you actually want
to do is at this point,
just after we set
the first left,
you want the browser
to look at that style
and actually think about it.
And we can actually do that by
putting one of those properties
in of set width or whatever.
And once we do that, we can
run that code as many times
as we want.
And it will work every time.
But you are relying on
unspecified behavior
when you do that.
The web animation's
API will save us there.
And just before I
get kicked off stage,
I want to go through
the bad side of that.
Normally, using things
like offset width
in the middle of your code can
lead to performance difficulty.
And here's an example of that.
So here I've got a page
with a load of paragraphs.
And what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to set Chrome's timeline
recording, which
is going to record
everything that's going on,
resize the screen box, and
I'm going to hit that button.
When I hit that button,
all of these paragraphs
are going to become the
same size as the green box.
So we do that.
Press the button.
And they all change.
And that was quite slow.
We can see in the timeline,
there's a little spike there.
And if we have a look at the
number that comes up there,
it's like 1.27 seconds.
It's very slow.
But there's this little
warning icon on there.
And if we look into that, we
get a clue of what's going on.
We get this Recalculate Style
Layout, Recalculate Style
Layout, happening
over and over again.
And that's not looking great.
The code we're using
is really simple.
We just loop through
all of those paragraphs
and set the offset width of the
green block to the paragraph.
Now, the first time we
go through this loop,
we ask the browser, what is
the size of the green box?
And it goes, oh,
I know that answer
because I've just drawn it.
Here's your answer.
Easy peasy.
And then we set the
width of the paragraph.
But the next time we
come around the loop,
we ask the browser, what's
the width of the green box?
And it's like, I used to know
the answer to that question.
But since then, you've
been playing around
with styles on the page.
So I need to go away and have a
think about what you've changed
and see if it affects the
width of the green block.
And that's going to
happen on every loop.
This is layout frashing.
This is interleaving
style reads and writes.
And it's a performance killer.
What we actually want to
do is just cache that,
do the reads first outside the
loop, get the green box width,
and then go through the loop.
And the difference is
absolutely astounding.
So recording that, changing
the width of the green box,
click the button.
It just happens instantly.
And it's a massive difference.
That was like 60 milliseconds
all in for everything
versus over a second.
So if you need to read something
that's style dependent,
do it before you start
making style changes.
Am I out of time?
Am I done?
OK.
But before we do that, we'll
have a look at the final scores
and see who managed to
win the Chromecast if I
can get the mouse
pointer over here.
Right.
A moment of tension.
Where's my mouse pointer?
Let's see if this works.
OK.
Oh, we've got a draw.
We've got one Chromecast.
We can get another one.
That's excellent.
I do have a bonus round.
But we're definitely
out of time.
Where are you two people?
Where are you?
Oh, one here.
And there.
Congratulations, guys.
A round of applause for
these guys actually.
[APPLAUSE]
JAKE ARCHIBALD: And with that,
I say, thank you very much.
And I'm going to make
way for someone else.
Thank you very much, guys.
Cheers.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: Thanks, Jake.
That was great.
All right.
And our next speaker is the
"New York Times'" own Eitan
Konigsburg.
He's a front-end architect.
And he's going to be
talking about the history
of performance at the Times.
Looks good.
OK.
EITAN KONIGSBURG: Hello?
Hey.
So hi, everybody.
My name's Eitan Konigsburg.
I'm a front-end
software architect here
at the "New York Times."
Today, I'm going to be talking
about the very real history
of our web performance efforts
here at the "New York Times."
Before I dive in, I
wanted to share with you
this tweet by Steve
Souders himself.
If you're not familiar
with Steve Souders,
it's the place to
start when you're
talking about web performance.
He tweeted, "is
performance of "the Web"
getting better or worse?
My past week was painfully
slow, marred by top sites w/ bad
#WebPerf.
Is it too hard?"
I don't know if the "New York
Times" was among these sites
that Steve was
having trouble with.
We've known that we've had a
little bit of a performance
problem.
I like to think that
he's checking our site.
And he's actually complaining
for real that our site is slow,
so that we make it fast for him.
But I'm going to get
back to this question
about whether it's too hard.
So while I was
preparing for this talk,
I was thinking that this
is a very real story.
And it reminded me of a
Geico ad from about 2006
that I just wanted
to share with you.
So just give me one sec to play.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
-Paula Sala is a real Geico
customer, not an actor.
So to help tell her story,
we hired that announcer guy
from the movies.
-When the storm hit, both our
cars were totally under water.
-In a world where both of our
-We thought it would take
forever to get some help.
-But a new wind
was about to blow.
-With Geico, we had
our check in two days.
-Payback &mdash; this
time it's for real.
-Geico.
Real service, real savings.
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
EITAN KONIGSBURG: So I thought
about doing this entire talk
in movie announcer voice.
I didn't think I'd be able to
keep it up all the way through.
Colt is actually
the expert at that.
So you should check out
his talk on National Talk
Like a Pirate Day.
That was actually really great.
Kudos.
So in a world of static
pages, pages on our website
are published basically
like you would a newspaper.
Somebody hits a button.
And the content goes
through templates
and is written to disk.
And we mix it with a
proprietary language
that we compile to give a
little bit of dynamicism
on the server side.
And it was fast.
We have about 1 million of
these static pages since 2004.
And republishing them is
really not an option for us.
If, hypothetically, it
took about five seconds
to republish one of these pages,
5 million seconds, I think,
comes out to about two months.
We can't be doing that
every time we make a change.
So what ends up happening is
it's extremely hard for us
to change markup once
it's been published.
And every time we
make a change, it's
only present from the
day we deploy it onward,
which means we have an
unknown number of permutations
of these markups to handle
and support over time.
So our front-end assets,
our JavaScript and CSS,
have to handle all of
these permutations.
And in order to be able
to change these files,
since we can't change the
asset path because the HTML is
static, we have to
keep the time to live,
the cache expiration timeout,
very low on these files, which
is a performance bad practice.
And we also don't really
know what pages on the site
call which assets in general.
So I want to talk
about our CSS history.
We didn't really
have a CSS framework
which means we have a
lot of repetitive styles.
Files were imported,
basically, as needed.
Style sheets approached the
import limits in IE &mdash; 31 total
and maybe up to three
nested levels deep.
There was inconsistent
load style.
We were using link tags in
one case, and right after it,
using a style tag with
an add import directive.
And basically, we
also have to deal
with web producers
who go through.
And they're able
to modify the look
and feel of our page on the
fly as the news happens.
So they can be dropped
into our content system
and appear anywhere on the page.
In the JavaScript department,
JavaScript was very ad hoc.
Since most of the dynamicism
was on the server side,
we basically used
JS basically as
needed to fix
cross-browser issues,
to do widgets that
respond to events
by the user in the browser.
Most of the variables
and functions are global.
Script tags are dropped
wherever they were needed.
You would define a new
DIV, leave it empty,
and you'd put a script
tag right after it.
We didn't defer execution,
another performance no-no.
We didn't have a DOM
framework to handle
any cross-browser functionality.
That framework war happened.
And we still hadn't
picked one yet.
Some words on images.
Basically, the UI images
that are part of a product
would get uploaded
individually to production.
You could easily forget
how to do that when
you were deploying.
So they would go missing
for a little while.
Our content photography
is extremely hard for us
to optimize.
We have a lot of pride
in our photography.
There's a lot of resistance
in making them smaller
and not featuring them
as largely on our pages.
We did some experiments
with lossless compression.
We actually, for
color novices, we
noticed some colors changing
in whatever these tools were.
There's a whole department here
that does color correction.
And the red walls don't
appear in their area,
so that they don't have a
little bit of red dilution
on their screens to do
this color correction.
It's basically a manual process
to re-size these images.
And we have a lot of them.
And in order for them to be
fast and have them be smaller,
people have to cut them and make
sure they don't crop something
out of the picture.
Because it's manual, it
doesn't happen a lot.
Other concerns for
the business, we
have these editorial
constraints.
Like I mentioned
earlier, producers
have a need to adjust based on
what's happening in the news.
So we use this
free-form module where
they can drop any
bit of HTML code.
It doesn't even have
to be balanced tags.
So this can easily
mess up our page.
But they have the
freedom to do that.
And we have to be able to handle
styles and scripts occurring
in them.
And ads, of course, they're
top-level objects in our DOM.
They're not treated
in any special way.
They bring their own copies
of DOM frameworks in.
We get older versions of jQuery.
We saw an ad that tried to
encapsulate Prototype &mdash; which
if you're familiar with
how Prototype JS works,
it modifies built-in
objects in the browser.
You can't actually
contain it in a box.
So it didn't really work.
Ads animate as
soon as they load.
We get a lot of painting
issues when animations
happen while the
page is loading.
And basically, they are
higher in the DOM order
as the page is loading than
our own logo on the homepage.
You'll see two ads.
And then you'll see our logo
if you look at the source.
So just to caveat
all of this history,
it wasn't really
entirely all bad.
We do use a CDN.
We've had Akamai for
a number of years.
It's been great.
We did turn gzip on in 2007.
The bandwidth savings
were actually immediate.
And there were a lot
of really happy people
as soon as we did that.
But it wasn't on previously.
And it's worth mentioning
that we did turn it on.
So a new wind for
our efforts and what
we were trying to do starting
in 2009 to make the site faster.
2009 was the year
we were focusing
on tools and libraries.
We basically built a new build
system for front-end files.
And this was our first foray
into doing automatic builds.
We used to manually
untar uncompressed files
in production.
And we were actually pulling
changes from version control,
as opposed to somebody's
home directory.
They would arrange the files the
way they wanted them to appear.
We would package them up.
And someone would
manually unpackage it.
Now, it's coming from
version control directly.
There were
semi-stateful rollbacks.
There was a rollback mechanism.
But you could really only
roll back the latest one.
If you tried to roll
back any before that,
you'd end up in
an unknown state.
And that was really bad.
But the really
exciting bit of it
was that there were
hooks for build scripts.
And we can expand
on this process,
basically, dynamically.
So we did just that for our CSS.
It was the first system
to use those new hooks.
And we wrote a bunch
of proprietary scripts
to not only unravel the ad
import directives to make
one concatenated file, we
wrote a script also trying
to remove some of the white
space and the comments.
This is all downstream from
development work, which
is also a really good point.
We didn't want our
developers to feel
that they couldn't comment
their work adequately.
While we were
doing this, we were
working on our CSS framework.
We took the concepts
from our design.
And we turned them
into these base files
that can be used
across the site.
We split code into
reusable modules
and actually tried to
reuse them in a sane way.
We aimed to have a single entry
point at the top of the page.
While we were doing
this, we were also
trying to lock down
our JS development.
We introduced a
top-level name space
called NYTD and
the module pattern
also called the Immediately
Invoked Function Expression.
This is a great way to wrap all
your variables in a closure.
Although thanks to Colt,
I'm now afraid of closures.
We introduced Prototype
JS as a DOM library.
This one bullet
point doesn't really
reflect the amount of
meetings and discussions
and debates and fights we
had over this decision.
But Prototype JS
won out in the end.
We also tried to write our
own proprietary asynchronous
JavaScript loader in the
days before RequireJS.
Any of these, LabJS,
any of these loaders,
they didn't exist.
We tried to write our own.
It didn't really work.
It became a synchronous
JavaScript loader.
So we started with
our home page.
And there's a number
of reasons why.
It's published very frequently.
So this problem
with legacy markup
really doesn't become an issue.
It gets the most traffic.
So it has the potential to save
people the most amount of time.
It has an isolated
implementation.
And basically, if
something went wrong,
nothing would go wrong on
other parts of the site.
And it's viewed very
heavily internally.
If something were really
bad, it would get noticed
before it got out
into production.
So in November 2009, we
put our CSS optimizations
on the home page.
It saved 25 HTTP connections to
what our very small CSS files.
The first pane occurred
a whole second earlier.
And the homepage
really felt faster.
And we were very happy by this.
So in 2010, we wanted to
continue these efforts.
The CSS framework
basically rolled out
to our section
and article pages.
Again, we were focusing
on the single entry point.
But we never optimized them.
There were some concerns with
these proprietary scripts.
And it turns out later
when we did an audit
that we were right
to be concerned.
There were references
to missing files.
There were ad import cycles.
A would include B,
include C, include A.
And if you're ever curious
about what the browser does
to get out of that, I still
don't know the answer.
And there were syntax
errors that there
were styles not getting
applied because they
were typed improperly.
So we decided to build a
new JS build system in 2010.
We forked the codebase.
We wanted to create
a clean build.
And only code that was
modular and name spaced
would be able to
be in this build.
Basically, we had these
manifests of files that had
an @import-like syntax
in a JS comment,
so that they would be inert
if the build process failed.
We used YUI compressor
for minification.
We no longer wanted to
write our own scripts.
This was well
supported at the time.
So why not?
We were focusing
on two build files,
one at the top,
one at the bottom.
If you're familiar with
the best practices,
they say that you're
supposed to put
your JS at the
bottom of the page.
So why did we have
them at the top?
If you remember that editors
can put JavaScript on the page,
if we wanted them to
use our frameworks,
it had to be there before they
could actually run their code.
So we put stuff at
the top to make sure
that that wouldn't
break anything.
This build process
was executed manually.
So it didn't see
widespread usage.
It's basically almost done
only on the home page.
And now, we have two codebases
and still no automatic
build process.
But when we did launch these
JS changes to the homepage,
it was pretty drastic.
We got a 50% speedup, 6
seconds, down from 12.
We were very excited by that.
So 2011 was a bit
of a slow year.
As you might remember, if you're
fans of the "New York Times,"
we introduced digital
subscriptions in 2011.
So resourcing for
this kind of work
was really hard to come by.
Oh, hello.
I don't know what I just did.
All right.
There were efforts to optimize
our analytics packaging.
We have a lot of
analytics packages.
And they were doing
some really bad stuff.
They got aborted
mostly because we
were afraid to break
these actual reports.
We wanted to make sure
that the business was
able to analyze
things correctly.
So we didn't continue that.
So we used a series of code
reviews and style guides
to make sure that
we were enforcing
good standards
and best practices
to keep the status quo.
But at the end of 2011,
we made the decision.
We decided to
replace PrototypeJS
with jQuery sitewide.
And as you can imagine,
this is really, really hard.
We needed both of them to
coexist during the transition.
We weren't going to rewrite
everything and launch
a new site on a new
framework all at once.
So we needed both of
them to, basically,
be around while we did this.
But in 2012, a group
of five developers
basically set out
to try and excise
PrototypeJS from article pages.
And we were making really,
really excellent progress.
Things were going great,
hours and hours of work.
And then we found out there
were some inline scripts that
made references to PrototypeJS.
And if you remember that we have
these static pages with markup
that we can't change,
we really have no idea
what's calling PrototypeJS
and inline scripts.
And so, therefore,
we're not ever
able to remove PrototypeJS
fully from our site.
So now we have two frameworks.
They both download.
They're both still in use.
And this actually causes
some really strange bugs.
In older IE, where you
don't have a get elements
by class name,
PrototypeJS would add one.
And jQuery will
detect it and use it.
It returns Prototype objects.
And jQuery says, I have no
idea what these are, and bails.
So 2012 also marked the end
of life for this proprietary
build system.
We basically
migrated to a system
that mirrored our entire
SVN repositories via Hudson.
We wrote a new script to
concatenate the CSS imports.
We needed feature parity
with what we had before.
So we had to write
something new to make sure
that we could handle it for the
homepage, which already had it.
It does have all these features.
Although CSSLint is
added on the list
to catch syntax errors that
didn't exist until 2012,
I believe.
It uses YUI compressor
to do minification
and also has to be run manually.
So again, it's really just
limited to the home page.
So finally, I'm going to
talk a bit about some efforts
in modern times of
what we're trying
to do to really
fix this problem.
So we were really gifted
a very rare opportunity
by the business.
In March 2013, the
"New York Times"
announced that it was going
to introduce a new article
redesign.
And for us, it's more than
just a new user interface,
a new user experience.
It's really a
technological reboot.
We've changed everything
about our systems
in order to deal with some
of these legacy issues
that we've had.
So the best thing &mdash; and I have
an exclamation point here,
and it really doesn't
represent our excitement
by this &mdash; we have
dynamic pages now.
We no longer have to deal
with an unknown number
of permutations.
We can actually
change our asset URLs
on the fly to bypass the cache
as soon as we do a deploy.
We pushed a lot of
the user customization
into the client side.
We're not doing
it on the server.
So we can actually cache our
pages better on the back end.
We introduced HTML5
Boilerplate and Modernizr
to give us a nice starting
point for these new pages.
So now, we have a modern
build system using Grunt.
It can be run both in
our Developer Sandboxes
and in Hudson to
prepare a build.
And most of these
web performance
best practices are actually
available as Grunt tasks
already, which
made it really easy
to integrate some of this
great advice for our code.
And we're using RPM
packaging for deployments.
They have very great
rollback support.
And they're really easy to use.
So for style development,
we switched to using LESS.
LESS itself handles
concatenation.
Minification is supported
by a YUI compressor
through the Grunt task.
So this is really easy
to get these two wins.
Variables and mix-ins allow us
to do some really interesting
things in CSS that we had to
do with images before &mdash; arrows,
buttons, data
URIs, and spriting.
So earlier this year,
I wrote a Grunt task
that automates the
creation of spritesheets.
I don't really know
what the diction
is around sprites
and spritesheets.
I don't know.
What do you call the individual
images on a spritesheet?
I have no idea.
So I'm making up
the terminology.
Basically, the task takes in
a bunch of images and exports
not only the combined
spritesheet but also
a bunch of mix-ins in LESS with
the background coordinates,
which makes it not
only really easy
to make these
combined images, you
don't have to maintain
them manually.
It's really easy for developers
to use them in the code.
The mix-ins are named
after the image itself.
So you just put the image
name, and you basically
get the sprite.
And the best part about it
is if the coordinates change
because we've added a new
image, and if it's alphabetical,
and you added a C, all the
images shift a little bit.
All you have to do is
rebuild the system.
And all the coordinates
are updated.
Nobody has to go in and actually
figure something out and change
anything.
And we're currently combining
I think over 100 small images
into one.
That's 99 saved requests
to very small files
that we need for our new design.
I'm not showing it here.
You can check out the marketing
page to see what it looks like.
Just a heads up.
For JavaScript, we
switched to RequireJS.
This handles, again,
concatenation and minification
in the Grunt task.
And we also get
source maps, which
is something we're
really excited to use
for our development.
We no longer need
a global namespace.
That's why the slide
is titled that we're
deleting our
Window.NYTD namespace.
We get asynchronous
loading of JavaScript.
And we, basically, decided to
focus on larger build files,
so that once you've establish
a connection on mobile,
you want to make sure
you keep the latency low.
That initial handshake
can be really high.
So we keep these large
build files around instead
of using a bunch of
individual RequireJS loads.
Since we moved a lot of
the client customization
to the browser,
we needed to make
sure we could template properly.
So we use Underscore JS
templates instead of building
with the DOM or
any HTML strings.
And it's way faster
to precompile.
You're essentially running
a JavaScript function,
which is optimized
in the browser.
Grunt can automate
this compilation.
There's a built-in
task to do it.
And we turn them into
a RequireJS module
that gets included as
part of our build process.
So we use Backbone to organize
everything into modules.
They are reusable.
And they are shared
across applications
if we would like them to be.
But the real win is
that they give us
a bunch of inherited
functionality.
So we can abstract out
touch events and analytics
or some common
element references,
so that we won't have to
look them up all the time.
And we can get this
functionality in everything
very easily.
We get event delegation,
fewer event listeners,
so things run a
little more smoothly.
And the modules communicate
with each other using events.
So you can publish events.
Or you can subscribe to
another module's events
to find out about changes.
So this is the big topic.
What did we do about ads?
We took ads out of
the critical path.
What we do is on DOM ready,
we write the ad markup
into a new Iframe.
You just take the
frames document,
and you document.write
it into the frame.
And what happens, if the ad
itself calls document.write,
you don't lose your whole page.
You would just lose the
content of the Iframe, which
is blank to begin with.
So we don't care what they
do once they're in the frame,
once they load.
If they decide to bust out
of the frame, they can.
But we have this notion of
trusted ads that aren't framed.
And trusted basically means
that they specifically
don't do things that
are bad for page speed.
And also, if there's actually a
problem, it's very easy for us
to get in touch with
them and make the change.
And this has been really,
really effective for us.
So this is the results page.
I thought it would
be great to show you
a comparative slide
of our waterfalls
to show you how really
dramatic this is.
We're not quite ready to show
you that information yet.
It's still being built.
So we're not quite
ready to do that.
But just to give
you an overview,
before starting to
render, the page
used to download
over 60 requests.
It's about 10 now,
maybe even fewer.
Before we're fully loaded, we
had to download 200 assets.
It's about 70 now.
Start render is under
one second in Chrome.
And document complete is
under three seconds in Chrome.
So this is a huge win for us.
Before, previously,
document complete
would be about nine seconds
on our article pages.
So to answer Steve's
question about
is web performance
too hard, no and yes.
It's really not that hard.
The optimization
practices are really not
that difficult to begin with.
And there is excellent tooling
that exist to make it really,
really, really easy to do.
However, there are some unique
challenges that, I think,
not just big websites,
but companies
tend to have their own
challenges that people can't
solve their problems
for them, and not
to mention any legacy
decisions, such as ours, where
we have our static pages
that was holding us back.
We found that we did this
negative feedback cycle.
We had this poor setup.
And we tried to do
this proprietary fix
to make it better.
And we found ourselves slightly
worse off than we were before,
even though we were getting
slightly faster speed.
So here's some stuff that we
learned, share some advice.
It's really worth
it to fight to solve
these big, difficult problems.
They are the 800-pound gorilla
in the room for a reason.
Fight to solve them.
Once they're out of
your way, it really
opens the path to making
this a lot simpler.
We live in a world
where you don't
have to rely on proprietary
systems anymore.
You might need some
because it's your business.
So you may need to
make sure that you
have all your requirements
taken care of.
But a lot of the tooling exists
to make this very simple.
I always say that you should
count your HTTP connections
before you count
bytes in every file.
Do the big, easy wins first.
It's really easy to
combine files together
than it is to figure
out what code is old
and needs to be removed
from your files.
And automate everything.
As soon as you introduce
manual to the equation,
it really doesn't get done.
So if you can
automate everything,
it's by far going to pave the
road and make it really easy.
So that's it.
I think I'm running out of time.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
EITAN KONIGSBURG: I don't think
I have time for questions.
But I will be around at dinner.
So if you want to
come find me, and I
can talk endlessly about this.
So please find me.
I will share all
of my knowledge.
PETE: All right.
So that's one point.
You can talk to
people at dinnertime.
We may have time for questions
at the end of the night.
We'll see.
All right.
So our next speaker is Adam
Grossman from Forecast.
Really, if you haven't looked
at this, you should look at it.
You should pull it up on your
browser, maybe right now,
and see how it is.
One quick question.
Is everyone OK on temperature?
Raise your hand if
you're too warm.
OK.
Looks good.
ADAM GROSSMAN: You'll
have to excuse me.
This is my first
time using Keynote.
All right.
Word of warning.
I'm getting over a cold.
So I'm really hoping that my
voice lasts the entire thing.
So I'll try to keep this short.
And also, full disclosure.
Right now, I'm a little
bit high on the 'Tussin.
And it turns out, I
just learned this right
before coming here,
that you're not
supposed to mix cold
medicine with whiskey.
I didn't know that.
But that train has sailed.
So we're going to
make the best of it.
I'm Adam Grossman.
I work for a tiny little
two-person company
called Dark Sky.
We make weather
prediction software.
We have an iOS app
called Dark Sky.
We have a weather API
for other developers.
And we make, more
recently, a weather website
called Forecast.
It's forecast.io.
If you want to
give us heartburn,
you can call it
"forecast-ee-oh."
And it looks like
this on the desktop.
On mobile, it looks
more like this.
That's the iPhone version.
And we really tried hard to
make the mobile experience
feel like a native app.
So you save it to
your home screen.
In fact, we require it.
And that's a very
controversial decision.
It lives on your homescreen.
It's got a little icon.
It fits in with
all the other apps.
And you launch it.
And you get something that
looks like a native app.
And when you slide
between views,
it's a nice smooth animation.
And we even got a nice,
smoothly animating radar map.
And the reason we
did this &mdash; and I
don't recommend it for all apps.
But the reason we did this is
because if you want a weather
app on your phone, and you've
got your phone and you're out
and you want to access the
weather, the last thing
you want to do is
open your web browser,
navigate to some weather
website, enter your location,
and wait for it to load.
You just want to launch an
app and get the weather.
So if we had gone the
more traditional route,
I think a lot of people
just wouldn't use it.
So that's the reason
that we did it.
Now, a lot of ink
has been spilled
on the topic of mobile
web UI performance
and the bigger picture question
of what's the future of mobile.
Is it native apps?
Or is it the mobile web?
And more recently,
the question has
been why are mobile web apps so
crummy compared to native apps?
And they are.
If you take the
average mobile web app
and you compare it to
the average native app,
it doesn't perform as well.
And of course, there
are always exceptions.
And if you do some Googling,
the general consensus,
if there is such a
thing on the web,
is that web apps are slow
because JavaScript is slow.
There was a great article,
great blog post put out
by a guy named Drew
Crawford called
"Why Mobile Web Apps Are Slow."
And he did a comparison.
He showed benchmarks of
JavaScript versus native code.
And he found, of course,
that especially on mobile,
JavaScript is way
slower than native code.
And his conclusion
is that web apps
can't compete with native
apps because they're
written in JavaScript.
And JavaScript has
to compete with,
on iOS, Objective-C,
which is nice and fast.
On Android, it's generally
Java, even BlackBerry,
presumably Fortran.
And all of these are fast.
And JavaScript is
comparatively much slower.
And that's why mobile
web apps are slow.
This is not true.
Web apps are not slow and
crummy because JavaScript slow.
And the reason is really simple.
Graphical rendering on the web
does not happen in JavaScript.
Unless you're doing
pixel-by-pixel graphics
on a canvas element, nothing
is being drawn by JavaScript.
It's all being drawn by the
engine underneath it which
has been heavily optimized.
And in fact, on iOS,
graphical rendering
is not done in Objective-C.
Most of it, at least
the heavy lifting, is
offloaded onto the GPU.
And in fact, you can
prove this yourself
with a little
thought experiment.
Imagine ripping out your GPU,
the little chip on your iPhone,
and being forced to do
everything in Objective-C.
You would get a really
crummy experience.
So really when it comes
to graphical performance,
it's not about JavaScript.
It's not about Objective-C.
So that brings us back
to the original question.
Why are mobile web apps so
crummy compared to native apps?
And to answer this
question, I think
I have to stop and give
you the two rules for how
to create performant
mobile web apps.
There's only two rules
you need to know.
And you only need to know these
two rules and nothing else.
So you might want to grab a pen.
The two rules for performant
mobile web UI, number one,
is to do stuff
that is performant.
Number two, second
rule, is avoid stuff
that performs poorly.
Now, before I continue, a
brief anecdotal interlude.
Growing up, I played baseball.
I was on the little league team.
And I had a little league coach.
That's not him.
He was much fatter.
And that's the wrong sport.
And one day, he gathered
all of us around.
And he said, kids,
I'm going to tell you
the key to winning
any baseball game.
And of course, our
ears perked up.
And we leaned in.
And he said, the key to
winning any baseball game
is to score more runs
than your opponent.
Thanks, coach.
You're a really bad coach.
And it turns out
he was a bad coach.
We lost most of the
games that year.
And I know that this rule
seems very similar in spirit
to my two rules for
performant mobile web UI.
But they're not.
They're not the same.
And I think there's
some interesting things
that we can pull from this
if we really, really try.
The first thing to notice
is that on the surface
these two rules seem like
the same rule, just worded
in two different ways, so I can
fill up two points on a slide.
But really, I think
they're different.
And one of these
rules is much harder
to accomplish than
the other rule.
And if you're going to ask
someone who is just starting up
in web development
which rule was easy
and which rule
was hard, he would
say, the hard rule is the first
one &mdash; doing stuff that performs
well, finding the
techniques that you need,
because there's lot of
stuff you need to learn.
And learning is hard.
And you may have to learn about
CSS transitions, and Appcache,
and browser compatibility,
and all of that.
And that's really hard.
Meanwhile, rule number
two &mdash; avoiding stuff.
That's easy.
That's not doing something.
And not doing something
is really easy.
And you can just try things.
And if you look on your phone
and they don't perform well,
well, you just don't include it.
And so that's really easy.
But I think true enlightenment
comes from the realization
that the situation is
reversed, that, in actuality,
the hard one is to avoid
stuff that performs poorly.
And the easy one is to do
stuff that performs well.
I need my water.
So I've been doing web
development for a while.
I was doing freelance
before I started Dark Sky.
But I'd never done any big
mobile project, like Forecast.
And I didn't know,
really, where to start.
I didn't know what the
performance bottlenecks were.
Well, what I did was
I went to Google.
And I asked Google,
hey Google, how do I
make smooth animations
in mobile web apps?
And Google said, hey,
here are some links
you might like to read.
And there's a whole
bunch of them.
And the first thing you
learn is that if you're
going to make mobile
animations that are performant,
you should use CSS transitions
and transforms because they're
hardware accelerated
and they're fast.
So I went back to Google.
And I said, tell me about CSS
transforms and transitions.
And it worked, even though
I spelled transitions wrong.
And suddenly, in
a weekend, I was
able to make my animations fast
and performant on my iPhone.
So then I went on
to the next thing.
I asked Google
about touch events.
And it told me
about touch events,
how to capture the event when
your finger touches the phone.
And suddenly, my smooth
animations were interactive.
You can interact with them.
And then I got excited.
And I went on and I asked
Google about Appcache.
It is this thing
I'd heard about.
I always heard that it
was tough and confusing.
But you ask Google about it.
And it gives you the
links, the blog posts
that you need to know.
And the Appcache is
something that, well,
it tells the browser
to cache the app,
so that next time
you go to it, you
don't have to pull in all
of the HTML and JavaScript.
And suddenly, your
interactive, smooth animations
now load quickly.
And finally, you want
to make it into an app
that you save to
your home screen.
So I asked Google, how do I save
mobile apps to the home screen,
because that would
be really awesome?
And it tells you about
metatags that you
can include in your page.
It's really easy.
And when you include
those metatags,
the Chrome disappears, the
back button and what have you.
And you now have an app
that fills the screen.
And you also find about
metatags for specifying icons.
So very little work in about
two weekends of Googling.
It's not tough.
In two weekends,
you can have an app
that lives on your home
screen, has an icon.
And when you launch the icon,
you get an app in full screen.
And it's performant.
And it's great.
And suddenly, the
"New York Times"
is asking you to
give presentations.
And I think that was the
body from someone else.
That's not my body.
So learning the techniques
that perform well
is actually pretty
straightforward.
It doesn't take that long,
especially if you're already
a web developer.
And we like to think that
web development is difficult,
because it's our jobs,
it's our livelihoods.
But in reality, the hard
part is all the stuff that
happens behind the scenes,
all the people that
work on the web kit team,
people at Google and Apple
and Mozilla, who are
making the tools,
doing the hard work to give
us the handful of tools
to make mobile apps
that perform well.
So this is easy.
And I really think that avoiding
techniques that perform poorly
is the hard part.
This is a little bit
counterintuitive,
because introducing crummy
performance on the web is
really an active endeavour.
The default is good performance.
So one of my favorite mobile
websites is Wikipedia.
And this is one of the
only content-heavy sites
where I actually prefer
their mobile site
over their desktop
site on my phone.
And it performs beautifully.
I think the most complicated
thing on the site
is an auto complete
in the search.
But they don't try
to do anything fancy.
And because of that, they
get great performance.
It scrolls beautifully.
When you click on a
sub-heading that's collapsed,
it just appears.
No jittery animations because
there aren't any animations.
So really, good
performance is the default.
And when you come
across crummy websites,
it's because someone is
actively making it crummy.
And that's a very
perplexing thing.
One example is I
was reading a blog.
And it had a mobile interface.
And I was scrolling
through it vertically.
And as you're apt to do,
because your thumb is
on a weird swivel, I couldn't
scroll perfectly up and down.
And I managed to go a
little bit sideways.
And all of a sudden, this
red semicircle appeared.
And it had this chunky animated
bitty, disgusting loading
screen.
The UI froze up.
And then a new blog post loaded.
And it was because someone tried
to get fancy with a swiping
gesture to load
up new blog posts.
And it failed miserably.
And this is someone who was
not heeding rule number two.
Another example is
on the ESPN site.
I just saw this where
you get a main headline.
And then you get one
sub-story and a more link.
And when you click that
more link, it comes up.
And you get more articles.
And when you do that, it is
this chunky, horrible animation
that's a few frames a second.
And doing this in a
way that is smooth
takes no extra work than doing
it in a way that's not smooth.
And this is a major website.
And they've failed to
heed rule number two.
There are design
examples of this too.
Any time you see
content that spills over
or nav that spills
over your content,
it's someone who has actively
incorporated crummy design.
My favorite example
is this website.
You go here.
And I exaggerated by
putting it in landscape.
But you have browser Chrome
on the top and the bottom.
And then they've introduced
a header and a footer that's
always there, fixed positioning.
And I don't understand
the share links.
It's as if you're going to get
halfway through the article,
and you just can't wait
to share it on Twitter.
So it's there and again.
So it's not just
performance in terms
of making smooth animations.
It's also the design too.
And this is someone
actively making
the design worse by doing this.
The rest of the site
looks really nice,
but this one aspect.
So why do we do it?
If it's an active
thing, it seems
like it should be
really easy to avoid.
And it seems to be a bigger
problem on the mobile web
than in native apps.
And why is that?
I think this rule &mdash;
avoid stuff that
performs poorly &mdash; I
think the key difference
between native apps and mobile
web apps is that this rule is
really easy to break on the web.
And it's really hard to break
when you make native apps.
So what do I mean by this?
On the web, you're given all
sorts of ways to do things.
And generally, the way
that you've learned them
when you're just
making static content
is not the way you
should do things
when you're trying to make
dynamic animations that
perform well.
So one example is say
you make a static page
and you want to position
something absolutely.
So you give it a CSS
position absolute.
And you said it's top
in left attributes.
And you put it somewhere.
And now, say you want
to make it dynamic.
You want to animate it.
I think the first thing we
all do is we load up jQuery.
And we animate the top and
left attributes in jQuery.
And when you try it,
historically, that
has given really poor
performance on mobile.
You should really be
using CSS transitions.
Meanwhile, on native apps &mdash; and
this is especially true in iOS.
As far as native apps go,
I'm only an iOS developer,
but I imagine this
is true on Android.
Apple makes it really hard to
do things that perform poorly.
Apple has &mdash; you do UI
kit and core animation.
And there's all sorts of juicy
things you can do with this.
And you can't find anything
in there that performs poorly.
If you try to break it and
try to do these things,
it's really hard to
do that, because Apple
has it locked down.
And they only give you
tools that perform well.
And one big example of this
is it is possible to make,
of course, iOS apps
that don't perform well.
And the biggest
way to do this is
to do custom drawing operations.
And so in the iOS world, there
are things called UI views.
And UI views, you can think of
them as DIVs in the HTML world.
They're just generic
rectangle containers
that you can put stuff in.
And you can implement
an optional method
on them called drawRect.
It's optional.
You usually don't
want to use it.
But when you implement
it, it turns a UI view
into, essentially, a
canvas element, where
you can do a canvas
drawing to it.
And actually, the syntax is
very similar to the syntax
for a canvas drawing, presumably
because canvas was originally
developed by Apple.
So Apple cares so much
about you not using this
that they'll actually
put this optional method.
When you go into Xcode
and you create a file,
they'll put this method here.
They'll comment it out.
And in the comment, they
tell you not to use it.
And I think the only
reason they actually
put this here is so that they
can tell you that it adversely
affects performance.
And so I think this is
the biggest difference
between the native
world and the web world
is that it's really
hard to break this rule.
So where do we go from here?
How do we avoid making
crummy web apps?
I think the biggest thing,
more so than on native apps,
is discipline.
We need to take
great care that we
don't introduce
poor performance.
Some things to watch out
for are &mdash; well, the biggest
thing to watch out for,
and this is something
that I fall for all the
time, is falling in love
with a bad idea.
So maybe you have an idea.
Presumably, the person
who made that blog post
with the really awful
swiping, he fell in
love with the idea of swiping to
get back and forth between blog
posts.
For me, it's been
a lot of things.
I wanted to implement
a thing in Forecast
for deleting saved
locations where
when you click that delete
button, the thing jumps up,
crinkles up, gets thrown
away into a trash bin,
and fades out.
And it's really seductive to
fall in love with an idea.
And when you test
it, it will often
work because you're testing
it in an environment that's
not a real-world environment.
And it turns out when you
actually implement it,
when it's actually interacting
with other things on the page,
sometimes it fails.
And if you fall in
love with a bad idea,
it's sometimes really
hard to let it go.
And it stays in.
And sometimes you
don't listen when
your friends try to
talk you out of it.
And they say that idea
is no good for you.
And that's fine.
Experiment.
Fool around a little bit.
We're young.
But don't settle down too
easily if it turns out
that the idea turns out
to be no good for you.
I don't know why I
used this picture
of an example of a couple
that's no good for each other.
They look really happy.
And if one of them
decides to change
their hair before the other.
Another thing to
avoid is, of course,
designer-developer disconnect.
And this tends to be true at
larger organizations, where
you have a designer
designing something
or a team of designers.
And they hand it
down to developers.
And time was you could design
something in Photoshop,
because websites were static.
And developers
could implement it.
And sometimes they had
to do disgusting things,
like chop it up into a grid
of images and use tables.
But it worked.
But now, especially
on the mobile web,
websites are dynamic.
They're animated.
And it's really hard to
design for that, especially
in Photoshop.
So designers may have
these great ideas
for how to do things, how
to interact with things.
And when it comes time
to actually develop them,
it doesn't work.
And I think that
very often developers
don't speak up about it.
And it stays in there.
So I think the way to avoid this
is to really &mdash; developers take
ownership in any design work and
any app that you're working on.
I don't know any organization
where a developer couldn't
go back to the designers
and even back to management
and say, this was a great idea.
But it turns out when we
actually implement it,
it doesn't work.
So there needs to be
this cyclical process
of development.
Another thing to avoid is
one platform preference.
I am an iPhone guy.
I love my iPhone.
I will never switch to Android.
I have a bunch of
Android phones.
And I never use them.
I have a Firefox OS device.
And I really want the Firefox
OS device to be great.
But it's not that great.
So I'm really about iOS.
And this is to the severe
detriment of Forecast
because it works way better on
iOS than it does on Android.
So this is something to avoid.
And this is the lesson
I need to learn.
But I haven't.
I can put it in a slide.
The next thing to avoid is
what I call test blindness.
And when you develop an app,
as you progress in development,
you're constantly using it.
You're constantly
interacting with it.
You're loading it on your phone.
And pretty soon, you
learn how to avoid
interacting with it in
a way that breaks it.
You know all the
little hidden gotchas.
And subconsciously,
you avoid it.
And I do this all the time.
I'll do something.
And I'll think it has no bugs.
And then I'll hand
it to my wife.
And the very first thing
she does is break it.
She'll double-tap
on things you're not
supposed to double-tap on.
She'll slide when you're
not supposed to slide.
And it completely falls apart.
And so the way I know that
I'm falling for test blindness
is when I show a new app
to someone new on my phone.
And instead of handing
it to them, I load it up.
And I show it to them.
And I show them how I'm
interacting with it.
Isn't this a great thing?
And I don't hand over my phone.
And I've seen
other developers do
this too when they're
working on something,
especially when it's in beta.
And if you're afraid to
hand over your phone,
if you try to show people it
by you interacting with it,
then you're probably
succumbing to test blindness.
So these are the
things to avoid.
And there's lots of
other things to avoid.
But it really
boils down to this.
The only way that we're going
to compete with native apps
is through unflinching
diligence to keep crumminess out
of our apps.
Native app developers
have it easy.
They got it by default.
But we have to spend every
waking minute that we're
developing a mobile
web app and make sure
that crumminess
doesn't get introduced,
because once it's there, it's
really hard to get rid of it.
Thank you.
One quick thing, I do have
one anecdotal postscript
that has nothing to do with
the mobile web UI performance.
I had one slide in
here where I was
going to talk about how web
development is so easy that you
could teach my
grandmother to do it.
So here's my
grandmother, presumably,
rocking out in BBEdit,
listening to 5by5 podcasts.
Actually, this is
not my grandmother.
I had to do a Google image
search for old ladies
on a computer.
And there's a lot of images
of old ladies on computers.
But one really strange
phenomenon is even more
than there are old
ladies on computers,
there are a bunch of old
ladies smoking cigars.
I don't understand
this phenomenon.
It's all over.
The web is filled with
old ladies smoking cigars.
This one's my favorite.
It's inexplicable.
And this may be the
Robitussin talking,
but I love that
we live in a world
where such a thing is possible.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: Thank you, Adam.
OK.
It's time for dinner.
Wait.
There is a lot of us.
There's a small space
for getting through
to food and drinks.
Food is on this side.
Drinks are on this side.
OK?
Consider taking the side you're
on to get that thing first.
We're going to have to cooperate
to get through the food
and get everyone
through and fed.
Also, consider that when
you're looking at portions.
We have more food.
But be considerate of
your fellow attendee.
We've got a little bit of time.
We have 40 &mdash; so we're
meeting back here at 8:30.
So back in your seats at 8:30.
You can eat in here.
You can eat out on the balcony.
Get to it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
PETE: All right, everybody.
You can find your seats.
We're ready to begin the second
part of our show this evening.
We've got Colt McAnlis
from Google here.
And he's going to
be doing something,
if you've never
seen it before, it's
pretty interesting to watch.
He's going to be looking
at other people's websites,
looking at them through
the lens of tooling that's
available in Chrome and his
expertise as a performance
expert, and look at performance
issues that are happening
and why they're happening.
He'll tell you more about that.
And we've also got
some stuff on mobile.
So this should be
pretty interesting.
So without further ado, Colt
McAnlis, Developer Advocate
at Google.
[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS: Are we good?
Test?
Can everybody hear me?
Can everyone see how bald I
am from where you're sitting?
Hands up if you can see
your reflection in my head.
So I have a really
tough job tonight.
My job is to try to keep
you entertained and awake
at this time of night, after
you've been fed and alcoholed.
So I'm going to try to
do that as best I can.
Let me introduce
myself really quickly.
My name is Colt McAnlis.
I'm actually the team lead
for Chrome Developer Relations
Performance.
About a year ago in
January, we actually
identified that the web
performance community
was good and doing well.
But we didn't have
someone focused
on bringing the message
to people constantly.
And as talked about in the
previous talks tonight,
it's really easy to do dumb,
slow things on the web.
And one of the first things
we need to do with that
is fix it with education.
So we defined from the
beginning that after looking
at all the education and
looking at everything out there,
they're really three
pillars of web performance.
Up until now, the web
as a whole has really
only focused on one of them.
All you've heard from
most performance experts
is, how fast does
your website load?
We've all seen the
studies that show
that one millisecond of time
actually related to $10 million
of lost revenue for
site X, Y, and Z.
And they only really
talk about network.
But in the modern age
of web applications,
we often tend to
neglect the other two
pillars of web performance &mdash;
rendering and compute.
A great part of the
Forecast.io &mdash; Forecast.io?
I wanted to see if
he was listening.
That was good.
See?
I've got to keep you awake too.
One of the great parts of
the Forecast talk, I believe,
was when he really said,
we have to actually solve
this problem of
rendering, because it
doesn't happen for free.
I think the existence of
the previous type of web,
where CSS animations
weren't something you even
had availability to, allowed
us to do really stupid things.
And the browser
kept us really fast.
But now, because we
contend our own yard,
we're running into
some problems there.
So when you think
about performance,
you should know that
network render and compute,
you can have problems
in all three of these.
And much like Jake said
earlier, a huge problem
in one of these
portions can actually
cloud out issues that are
happening in the other two.
So as you're going through your
process of finding performance
issues in your website,
you need to make sure
that you're evaluating
all three of these
with the right tools
at the right time.
And what I'm going
to do tonight is
I'm going to try to walk you
through some of the sites
that you've submitted &mdash;
ha, ha, ha, ha, ha &mdash;
and, hopefully, bruise
your ego a little bit.
No offense.
It's what we all have to do.
Quite frankly, I think one
of the big things we've
been trying to do with
the web performance
movement over the
past year is actually
bruise a lot of egos in the web,
because we're all programmers.
We're all smart.
We're too smart, quite frankly.
And we've got to be taken
down a peg, because we all
know in here, everyone in here,
think about your coworkers.
And think about what
really motivates them.
99% of the time, if you
can bruise their ego
or challenge them or tell
them they're not good enough
or the problem is
too hard, that's
what actually gets
them to move, right?
AUDIENCE: Or if
you pay them more.
COLT MCANLIS: OK.
Maybe, maybe, maybe.
If you've got Yankees
money, I guess so.
So this is the loop.
So this is what you
should all be thinking of.
Now, I've got about 10 years
of game development background
under my belt.
I'm a C++ programmer at heart.
And I'm trying to apply
a lot of the lessons we
use in game development
to web development,
because, in reality, we're both
dealing with real-time media
interfaces.
So when you guys say,
how fast can something
load off an internet site?
I'm thinking, how fast can that
stuff be streamed off a DVD?
It's the same problem we've
had, just 10 years later.
So when you're doing
your performance,
the main thing that you have to
do is follow these three steps.
The first thing is you
need to gather information.
You go open up Chrome DevTools.
You open up webpagetest.org.
This gives you information about
what is going on in your page.
From that you
actually need insight.
Because, really, what's a whole
sheet of floating point numbers
mean to you?
Nothing, right?
You need to know what those
floating point numbers mean.
And your tooling
system needs to be
able to infer what those
floating point numbers mean.
And then once you
have that insight,
you need to be able to
actually plan an action.
You have this data.
You have to then
go to your manager
and justify, please, let
me spend two weeks fixing
seven milliseconds of load
time from our website,
because it matters.
And then you need to be able
to repeat this constantly,
constantly, constantly.
You need continuous
integration tools.
You need the ability
to actually track down
whose check-in broke the build.
Quick show of hands.
How many of you in
here actually have
some continuous
integration for performance
in your suite right now?
One, two, three, four, five.
Wait.
Were you just showing
me your Pepsi can?
I mean, it's a cool can.
Bravo.
So maybe four, maybe
five of an entire room.
I've asked this question to
probably about 3,000 developers
this week while I've
been in New York
and meeting and giving talks.
And the total number of
people is close to about 15
with the five in this room.
This shows that there's a huge
problem in the web community
is that we're not actually
testing for performance
and giving it the gravitas that
we are our features and our CSS
and those pretty
little bubbly items
everywhere else on our pages.
This is why we
actually moved forward
with trying to build a
better community about this.
So for you in the audience,
this is the only slide
I want you to take
away from today.
Burn this into your retina.
Tweet it.
Blog it.
Get a tattoo of it.
If you get a tattoo
if it, tweet it to me.
And I'll send you some swag.
Please don't get a tattoo.
Anything I say is
not representative
of any organization or
Google or the lawyers that
are affiliated with me.
All comments are my own.
Please do not get a tattoo.
First off, if you're
doing performance,
go to HTML5rocks.com.
There's a landing page.
It's called performance.
You click on the button.
I'm actually the guy
that maintains that page.
If you start there,
it's going to walk you
through the three pillars
of web performance.
You're going to be able
to go step by step on how
to find and address
the largest problems
on each one of
these three pillars.
Next is you need to
be following and using
the perfmatters hashtag.
We actually started this
hashtag just earlier this year.
And we wanted to use web perf.
We really did.
We wanted to use that hashtag.
It was out there.
But we didn't feel like
it bruised enough egos.
We wanted perfmatters to
be this name, this brand,
this answer to a question.
And what we saw was,
very quickly, people
started hosting links
to their friends
websites and be
like, yo, dude, why
does it takes 15 seconds
to load your site?
Perfmatters.
We wanted it to be something
you could take to your manager
and say, hey, it
takes 15 seconds
for our site to load on mobile.
Perfmatters.
We want this to be a badge.
We are all egotistical
programmers.
Wear the badge.
Own the sticker.
Make it a part of your culture.
Make it a part of
your environment.
That's what we want.
We want attitude in that.
That's why you should
follow that hashtag.
Finally, check out the G+
web performance community.
If you're in Google+,
it's a cool place.
A lot of cool people
hang out there.
Some of them are bald.
Some of them post content.
I'm not saying who.
But you need to follow
that, because, really,
if you combine perfmatters with
the Google+ web performance
communities and the articles
coming through HTML5rocks,
you're actually going to find
an overflow of information.
I bet most of you in here
haven't actually dived into &mdash;
Here.
We'll do this.
Put your hand up if you've
read more than five articles
about performance.
OK.
Keep your hands up.
More than 10 articles?
OK.
Let's ramp this exponentially.
20?
28?
Let's go 40 articles
on performance.
OK.
For those of you who
have had your hands up,
of those 40 articles,
how many of those
things did you implement?
Maybe 5, 6, 20?
No fair if you actually
did a talk earlier tonight.
I'm not taking your input.
So the point that
we're getting at though
is that for those of you
who haven't been reading
a lot of this content,
there is actually
going to be overflow
of information.
Hopefully, you can find it.
You can guide it.
You can move through it.
What's the next one?
Yeah.
So what I'm going to do now
is with the rest of the time &mdash;
Pete, how much time do we have?
40, 60, as much as I want?
Keep talking until
people fall asleep.
Good.
I can do that.
So what we're going to do
is I'm actually only going
to load these
websites on mobile.
Quite frankly, I ran
through these earlier today.
And most of your sites actually
fell over dead on mobile.
There were some interesting
use cases on desktop.
But quite frankly,
desktop is dead.
If you're not making your
site mobile and friendly
and fast there, you're
doing it wrong, period.
Period, period, period.
Mobile is all that matters
right now. #perfmatters.
You can tweet that.
I'll give you a second.
No, go ahead.
It's OK. #perfmatters.
So we're going to take a look at
a couple of these really quick.
And I'm going to try to organize
these in terms of discussion
and pointing out
a couple things.
So if we don't get to
all of them, I apologize.
Please feel free to email
me later and curse at me.
Or do it on social media.
That's always fun too.
So what I've got here
is a little setup.
And you can actually
see my little phone,
so I can click on some stuff.
And what I'm using over here is
the Chrome Developer Tools ADB
extension.
So this is a fantastic
little &mdash; who's using this?
Anyone using this?
No fair if you're
hosting the event, dude.
God.
You guys are cheating.
So this is a fantastic
Chrome extension.
You go to the Chrome Web Store.
You can actually download
and install this extension.
Basically, what it
allows you to do
is to interface with the
Android developer tools
very easily and quickly.
So I can actually click on this
and go view inspection targets.
And you'll actually see that it
loads and shows me this Galaxy
Nexus phone that's actually
plugged in right here.
And I can actually click &mdash;
well, I'll close this,
so you can actually see
what this looks like.
I can click the inspect button.
And what this inspect
button shows is
it actually shows me what's
on my phone right now.
So this one of the sites.
I'll get to it in a little
bit deeper here in a minute.
But this is actually
what's on the phone.
You can see it's moving.
It's scrolling.
It's doing stuff.
We go over here.
And you can actually
see the network.
So if I hit reload
on my phone, you
can actually see the network
request coming through.
This is not the desktop site.
This is actually a mobile site.
This is really good, because I'm
actually testing on the device
that my users are using.
Wow.
Great comment.
#perfmatters.
One of you will
tweet it tonight.
It will happen.
I'll keep drilling it into you.
But the cool thing
is you can actually
see what's going on here.
And notice, for this
particular website,
that it's actually
not done loading yet.
You can still see the bar
moving on the side over there.
And the funny thing is if you
load this site in desktop,
you don't see that same problem.
So obviously, there's
an issue on the mobile
that is not showing
up on the desktop.
Again, we need to make sure that
we're testing things properly.
But the cool thing
is we can actually
see all the same
events, use the dev
tools in the same way minus
everything crashing because
of memory issues, which
might happen tonight.
I apologize for the live feed.
But we can actually go through
here and just record memory
and see what's
going on in memory.
And so let me show
you over here.
I can go through and actually
scroll and go back and actually
see how memory is adjusting
based on this stuff.
So if you haven't adopted
this Chrome ADB extension
into your tooling
and your testing,
you need to definitely do this.
Definitely get
this in your stuff,
because no other tool allows
you this sort of integration.
And Chrome Dev Tools are
already top of the line.
It should be part of it.
So anyhow, enough
of me babbling.
So let's start with one
of the first sites here.
Clicky, clicky.
There's a native app for you.
Slow in loading.
Forecast.io?
I'll get it right.
Sorry.
So we're going to try this
first one here, allout.org.
This was submitted.
Someone in the room
submitted this.
I don't know who it is.
Doesn't matter.
But we're going to take
a look at your site.
And hopefully, we're
going to make you upset.
So this is loading.
I'm going to show you what
the page looks like first.
So first off, we all
just watched it load.
This is on a 4G connection.
I'm not on the local Wi-Fi.
We can see that this actually
is not a mobile site.
I shouldn't have to scroll.
Oh, I can zoom.
Yay.
But most of the site
is actually eclipsed.
We've got some sort of
spinner here at the top.
It's a marquee movement.
We've got some other items
down here on the bottom.
Some stuff's going on.
So let's take a
look at what that
looks like in Chrome Dev Tools.
So I can go here.
Click inspect.
Again, native
applications &mdash; they're slow.
So let's go to the Network tab.
And I want to take a look
at how this thing loads.
So I'm going to
hit reload again.
And we're going to watch
all the assets come through.
And notice here
on the bottom here
you can see six
requests, 12 requests.
I'll keep scrolling down to
the bottom so you can see that.
Seven seconds worth of load time
before it's actually loaded.
So this down here on
the bottom tells us
that it took about six
seconds before content
complete was actually
issued, before the page load
event occurred and
7.9 seconds total.
8K actually came up.
Nope.
We're still not done.
9K came through, pardon me.
And so 34 requests.
We can actually see the
health of this object
and the health of this site.
Now, 34 requests,
that's actually nothing.
9K, that's a drop in the bucket.
The Robitussin-laced
grandmother picture from earlier
could easily load
9K very quickly.
What's important here though,
and I want to show you this,
is when we go up here and
actually sort by size,
we actually get
a different sense
of the content that's
being sent around.
So we can actually
see the images loaded.
We can actually see that most
of the large assets here, 6.4K,
512 bytes.
We can see that the
large images here.
This is actually
interesting to me.
So this is a 1,024 by 576.
It's 213K.
Quick round of applause.
Who thinks that's too
large for a mobile site?
[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS:
Here's another one.
Here's 109K.
A little bit better.
Same resolution though.
Anyone notice that?
Same resolution, half the size.
Another round of applause.
Who's written a JPEG compressor?
One guy, two guys, three guys.
We'll get some beers later.
And we'll talk about
DCT coefficients.
I've had this really
cool idea that you
can actually &mdash; you know what?
Never mind.
So notice, though, that
this image actually
has a lot more data to it.
There's a lot more edges.
There's a lot more
noise to the image.
Yet it's smaller
than this one here.
This is actually mostly pink.
There's no reason that
the image with more detail
should be less size than the
one with less detail in it.
What this tells &mdash; I know
nothing about these developers.
I know nothing about the site.
But this tells me that
they're not actually
exporting this particular image
with the right compression
settings.
So I like doing these
polls, because it's late.
And I need you all entertained.
So how many of you
actually just export
your images at some
constant format?
When you do an export from
a JPEG it's on 12 or 80
depending on what you're doing?
Everyone else hand optimizes
your exact perfect PSNR
relationship for your JPEG?
Yes?
Is that what I'm hearing?
Because I saw three hands.
So either you're all
lying to each other.
Or you have no idea the way that
your images &mdash; Round of applause
for no idea of the
compression quality.
[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS: OK.
Fantastic.
So seeing this site
actually tells us
that this is a systemic problem.
And again, the 3,000
developers I've
talked to over the past
week all see this problem.
On a couple of
the other websites
I'm going to load
tonight, you're
going to see the show
up very prevalently,
that in general, we
as a web community
do a horrible, horrible job of
optimizing images for quality
against size.
Now, in reality,
this isn't something
that's that difficult.
Most of us consider
a single-way pipe.
We have artists or designers
that are working in a vacuum.
They're trying to optimize
for the visual quality
of the image.
Meanwhile, there's
bald engineers
in a corner somewhere
going, why is my site slow?
And there's this constant back
and forth between these two
camps about size of
images versus quality
of images and load
times and all the stuff.
Let me give you a
little word of advice.
If any of you are able to
implement something like this,
it's very simple to spin
up an Amazon EC2 instance,
or even do this at your
desk, and actually run
a compressor, a command
line compressor,
like libjpeg or jpeg-turbo.
By the way, jpeg-turbo
is the actual codec
that we use inside
of Chrome for JPEGs.
And actually compress it
at various quality settings
and test the PSNR of the images.
PSNR, for those of
you who don't know,
is Peak Signal to Noise Ratio.
This is actually a
measurement of the amount
of noise and error that's
introduced to an image.
It's the blockiness
that actually
comes from the
compression format.
We actually have a
standardization process.
We call it PSNR.
And that's how we compare image
compressors to each other.
So you can actually take your
image, compress it at level 90,
see what the PSNR is.
Compress it at 80.
See what the PSNR is.
70, 60, 50, 40, 30.
If you get below 30,
you've gone too far.
Just stop at 30.
But the cool thing about
this is that you can actually
run 10,000, 20,000, 30,000
images through this process
and, for each one, find
the exact right compression
value to give you a
PSNR of around 38 to 45.
So you're not actually
just exporting
to a single compression
number, a slider
that your artists have
no idea what it does.
You can actually
programmatically
find this value by implementing
a simple iterative process
against the command
line compressor.
That's kind of cool.
Round of applause for cool?
[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS: I saw
some of you begrudgingly
go, that's not cool.
Let's save the questions
for the end if that's OK,
because, otherwise, I'm
going to stare at Putin.
And he kind of scares me.
So let's take a look at
some other things here.
So I want to go over timeline.
So that was load time.
Everyone knows
the network stuff.
If you're not using
webpagetest.org or modpagespeed
or pagespeedinsights
and all that stuff,
you need to be using all that.
So let's just take a
look at what this site is
doing while I'm doing nothing.
So now, I haven't
touched this site.
To be clear, my
phone almost actually
went locked, because
I haven't touched it.
I'm still not touching it.
But I want you to notice what
the memory is doing on the top.
Now, I'm a C++ game developer.
To me, the only thing that
matters for performance
is follow the memory.
I actually gave a talk
at Velocity yesterday,
where I, in a very
heretic fashion,
suggested that web developers
were really bad developers
because we're not
controlling our memory.
We're actually letting
JavaScript do it for us.
And because of this,
we have no idea
what's going on under the hood.
How many of you know
what your heap size is?
How many of you care?
That's another question.
I like that.
I like your outfit.
Does that have a cummerbund.
What is that?
I like that.
That's cool.
I'm going to have to
get me one of those.
Perfmatters.
I've got to get me one of those.
So again, I've touched nothing.
But notice this here on the top.
I don't know if you
guys can see it.
It's allocating between
7.5 megs and 9 megs.
I'm touching nothing.
Nothing's occurring
on the screen.
Yet two megabytes of data are
being allocated and cleared
in this environment.
Now, I can actually
figure out what's
going on with this, if
I stop my recording.
Too much information.
Let me just do a quick
record real quick,
so I can clear all that.
So we can see something
on a timeline here.
So it looks like,
first off, they've
got like two different
timers firing.
So we've got Widgets.js
and Chartbeat.
Chartbeat, I'm guessing,
is like an analytics thing.
I see this on a bunch of
sites you guys gave me.
And then widgets seems
like their things.
So I'm guessing this is that
marquee scroll at the top.
They've got some
timer that's actually
moving those images around.
What I don't like &mdash; pardon?
AUDIENCE: It's Twitter.
COLT MCANLIS: For Widgets.js?
Oh, cool.
Nice.
Widgets.js.
Twitter.
Oh, cool.
So Twitter is actually
screwing this page up.
Go, Twitter.
Is anyone here from Twitter?
Boo, Twitter.
So what we see
down here though is
we see recalculate
and paint and whatnot.
For our memory, this
view doesn't actually
tell us what's being allocated.
We can see where the events
are occurring and whatnot.
I can actually mouse over the
GCs when they actually happen.
More importantly, though,
I can actually go over here
to the Profiles
page, because I don't
like seeing that kind of memory.
And I can actually do a
record of heap applications.
So I can just hit start
and let this thing run.
And basically, what you're
seeing here is on this top,
you're seeing timeline
view plus memory
profiling at the same time.
At the top, any of
these blue lines
is when memory
allocations occur.
Now, when you see a gray
line, what the gray line means
is that memory has been freed
by a garbage collection process
somewhere.
So you can actually see a
new set that just happened.
And some of the
gray lines happened.
But these blues tend to pop
up in a very regular fashion.
Now, in this, I can
actually go through here
and change the size of
my window and actually
see exactly what was allocated.
So in this single event,
at about eight seconds
into my capture, about 3K
worth of data was allocated.
And we can see a similar
pattern over here.
l can highlight this window.
And we see about almost 3K.
And over here, a similar window.
There's about 3K plus
a lot of extra change
there that hasn't
been freed up yet.
But let me focus on
this guy really quick.
So here I can actually see that
3K came from compiled code.
So somewhere in the system,
deoptimization code came from.
Now, for those of
you who are not
versed in fast path and
slow path JavaScript,
effectively, what this
little block of data
you're seeing here &mdash; see
that deoptimization data?
The way that V8 and most modern
JavaScript VMs work is they
will actually try to optimize
your code on your behalf,
because come on, you're
a stupid programmer.
You don't know
how to write code.
Obviously, the VM
knows better than you,
because it's a machine.
And it's fast.
And it's smart.
So what it will actually
do is take a code path
that you've written.
And it will actually
optimize it.
It'll manage the memory.
It will make some fast
path optimizations.
And it will put it out
there and start running it.
Well, the problem
is that it does this
with some assumptions about
the state of the environment
that it's in.
And it'll do this.
And oftentimes it'll break.
And it'll go, whoa, whoa.
We actually caused an exception
somewhere in the stack
doing our optimization, because
we're just a stupid robot.
And we actually don't know
what we're doing either.
When this happens,
basically, Chrome
has to create this new block
of code that's parallel
to the block of code you had,
delete your block of code,
put your new block of code in
the stack, and have it execute.
When that deoptimization
occurs, because the optimization
failed, it has to take
your old block of code,
put it back in, and
delete the block of code
that it just created.
So there are specific
code paths that
generally cause this to happen.
Closures are one of them.
How many of you are using
closures in your timers?
Don't applaud.
I don't want you
to applaud that.
Closures are one
of these things.
If you actually have
a closure running,
it's very common for people to
do set interval closure, 1,000.
That closure in
that set interval
is actually causing these
sorts of memory leaks to occur.
It's a deoptimization path
that V8 can't optimize around.
And so, basically, every
single time you're doing this,
you're running into
this situation.
So let's take a look at
something else really quick.
So I want to go over
here and show you
what I'm seeing on the screen.
Now, I've turned on a couple
modes on the developer tools.
So first off, you'll see
this beautiful little &mdash;
you can't see it too well.
I wonder if I can tilt my
phone just a little bit.
You can see up at the
top that I actually
have a little graph
showing me frame rate,
as well as how much GPU
memory is being used.
Quick show of hands.
Who understands how a
web page is painted?
It's like the same guys
that wrote JPEG compilers.
So for everyone else, let
me do this really quick.
How your page is rasterized
is a delicate ballet.
Really, it's more like boxing.
It's basically two people
smashing each other's faces
in for about six
milliseconds a frame.
Effectively, what happens is
Chrome will take your web page.
And it will dice it up.
It'll create square regions
of 256 by 256 tiles.
For each one of these tiles, it
will actually spin up a thread
and actually rasterize all
of the pixels in that tile,
all of the WebKit &mdash;
well, Blink now.
Sorry.
I've got to get my terminology
right &mdash; all of the page
elements and actually composite
that to a CPU chunk of memory,
32 bits per pixel,
256 by 256 tile.
And it will rasterize
all that data in there.
Once that data is rasterized, it
will then upload it to the GPU.
When you scroll a page,
the GPU is actually
the thing that's
moving your page.
Now, some of you in here are
young, much younger than me.
You may not know this.
But back before Quake 3
was hardware accelerated,
we had something called
software rasterization.
Software rasterization?
Heretic Doom?
Quake?
Anybody?
Any other professional
gamers in the house?
Yeah.
So back then, we used a term
called software rasterization.
This was generally OK.
But once we invented
GPUs, GPUs are basically
hardware rasterization.
They're built to take pixels
and put them on the screen.
They're dedicated
silicon for this.
But Chrome is actually still
using software rasterization
to paint the pixels
on the screen.
This means that
this is a slow path.
This also means that
every one of you
right now should be
really, really scared,
because how many of you have
actually tested whether or not
those rounded corners and drop
shadows affect your render
time?
They do, actually,
quite frankly.
If you go to HTML5rocks, I
actually did a study on this.
I'm sorry.
That was a leading question.
That was mean.
I knew that you didn't
know that answer.
But basically, what
happens is your CSS effects
have to be software rasterized,
which means we have to actually
go and draw rounded rectangles
and then actually add a drop
shadow to the side of it.
And this actually
takes more time.
In fact, if you have
those two combinations
of things together,
it actually takes 4x
as long as each one of
them individually, which
means that there's
combinations of CSS properties
that hurt your rendering
performance more than others.
Hopefully, all of you
are going, dear God,
I have to test this right now.
And how you can test this
is you can actually see up
here in this frame rate meter
that as you're scrolling,
you can actually
see the milliseconds
taken to render that
part of your page.
Now, what you're
also seeing here
is notice this big red
box that keeps popping up?
This is actually a mode
in Chrome Dev Tools &mdash;
and let me show you this.
And I know I'm spending
more time on this site.
As we go to the other
sites, you actually
see this stuff play out.
But I need to test
the groundwork here.
Is that in or left?
AUDIENCE: Left.
COLT MCANLIS: Left.
Oh, wow.
I'll keep working.
So anyhow, I have show
paint rectangles on.
Basically, what this does
is when I turn this on,
it's going to show
a red rectangle
for every part of the page
that actually gets repainted.
So this actually tells
me what part of the page
is being rerasterized, which
is really cool to know,
because I'm pretty sure all
of you will look at your site
and find that you've got some
little square icon like this.
But for some reason it's
rasterizing like a 6x size
window of that that all has
to be reprocessed on the CPU.
This slows down your page.
It creates jank.
I hate that word.
Hitching, by the way,
hitching is the right term.
Every other medium &mdash;
video games, AV,
movies &mdash; it's called hitching.
Can we all agree
to use hitching?
No?
I'll get hitchfree.org later.
Anyhow, let me move
on to the next site,
because I want to make sure that
we talk about some more stuff.
But basically, you can
see that on this site,
there's a couple things.
First off, they're
sending too large images
to a mobile device.
They don't have a mobile view.
They don't have a
mindset of a viewport
for these mobile environments.
Plus, it seems like
their marquee is actually
rendering and updating
different parts of the page
at different frequencies.
They're allocating about
a meg of memory per minute
or so, when no one's
touching anything.
So if this is your
site, fix those things,
because you need to.
And also, your load time
is pretty harsh too.
So let's do this next one.
So this next one
should be pretty quick.
I just want to highlight
something really poignant here.
So I'm going to close this.
Which view are you on?
So let's show you.
So this is dosomething.org.
Cool little website.
It just encourages everyone
to do something interesting,
like small butterfly
wings change
the course of tides in
Africa and all that stuff.
But we see it's a pretty simple
website, just a little strata
of images and whatnot.
When we go over here
to Chrome Dev Tools,
let's inspect this
information here.
And I'm going to put this
back on the Network tab.
And we're going to go
ahead and reload this.
So we can actually see the
page loaded pretty quickly.
We got a lot of
information really quick,
about 2.9 seconds.
So this is a lot better
than the previous website.
We're right around that
three-second load time.
And again, this is on my 4G.
I'm not on the wireless.
So that's pretty good.
10K transferred.
That's all right.
21 requests.
Not that bad at all.
So let's, again, sort by size.
Let's see if anything's
coming up here.
I got a couple not founds.
That's not necessarily
a good idea.
A couple images here.
So this is interesting.
Again, another 106K image
that's being delivered
to a mobile screen, that,
obviously, does not need 106K.
That one's a little bit
better, well not better.
I mean that's a very
depressing image.
I didn't mean that
that was &mdash; Again,
my opinions are my
own and not that
of any organization
or secret service
that I'm influenced with.
So we can actually see
some of these images
may be a little bit
larger than others.
But for the most part,
this is actually nice.
What happened here?
This technology.
Isn't it great?
So we can actually see though
that this page is actually
a pretty good example of
what to do on a website.
If you load this on the desktop,
what you'll actually see
is that there's larger
versions of these images.
They're tiled differently
with a different layout.
There's a difference scheme.
But in the mobile
version, they really only
have one or two images
that are probably
too large for the mobile device.
But in the most
part, this actually
scrolls pretty quickly.
I know you can't see
it up at the top here,
but this is actually about
three milliseconds to five
milliseconds to actually
draw the part of the page.
And you can actually see
that as I'm scrolling,
notice that there's
no red tiles.
You don't see those
big red flashes.
What that means is this
entire page has actually
been rasterized on the CPU
and uploaded to the GPU.
And it's been cached in the GPU.
And so as you're
scrolling up and down,
the CPU doesn't
have to do any work.
So this is what you want.
You want to no red blocks
going on in your page.
So let's do another
site here really quick,
because now I'm freaking out
that I've only got 30 minutes.
MALE SPEAKER: You've
got 45 minutes.
COLT MCANLIS: Yes!
We're going all night.
Let's just open
up every website.
So this is the one we
saw a little bit earlier.
Sorry.
I don't know if my antics
distracted you all.
Let's reload this again.
Let's see how the load time is.
So notice on the top here
that it's about halfway.
So this page hasn't
unloaded yet.
Let's just be clear about
what we're looking at.
This is an instant load.
Now, we've actually gotten
to the loading part.
If this is your
website, I'm sorry.
Hopefully, you understand
there's work that needs to do.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: It might be.
Let's find out.
So again, over here,
let's go to inspect.
I wonder if I can just
catch this midstream,
if it will just tell
me what that image is
or if I have to hit reload.
It's still loading.
OK.
Here, I'll hit reload and
see what goes on here.
Oh, web fonts.
OK.
We'll take a look
at that in a second.
OK.
So I hit reload.
This is waiting to reload.
So obviously, there's already
some problems with this site.
Hopefully, someone in
here is going, please
stop clicking buttons.
Please take my website off
of your screen, you angry,
bald man.
OK.
Let's see how this
is going here.
So you can't see the screen.
It's still loading.
The fonts just now appeared.
Let's take a look at
what's going on here
and see whether or not we can
discuss some of these items.
So let's sort by size here.
This is something I want to let
everybody know, because this
is the first thing I want
to point out on this site.
This is a WOFF file.
It's a web font.
Round of applause if you're
using web fonts in your site.
[APPLAUSE]
COLT MCANLIS: Good.
Please stop.
Please, please stop.
I don't know if you saw this.
Web fonts look great.
They're awesome.
This is 38K for that web font.
And unfortunately, some
of these have been cached.
So you can't actually see the
true size of a lot of these.
But there's actually five or
six web fonts on this page.
So you guys are
getting a bum deal.
You're not seeing
how horrible this is.
But basically,
here's what happens.
When you've got five
web fonts, each one
can be somewhere between
the range of 40K and 90K
for a font.
That font is required
before text can actually
be drawn to your screen.
So pop quiz.
What happens if you're
ready to draw text,
and your CSS is down, and
your JavaScript is down,
and your images are down,
but your WOFF isn't down yet?
Good answer.
No one said anything.
Nothing.
Nothing happens.
Chrome will do nothing.
Chrome will block.
Chrome will wait.
Chrome will wait for every
single one of your WOFFs
to come down before a
single character of text
is drawn on your screen.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] render all
the text that you [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: Jake
Archibald says I'm dumb.
If that single WOFF is
visible, it'll render that one.
Now, Firefox will do it
a little bit differently.
Basically, what it will do
is it'll wait three seconds.
Right, Jake?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yeah.
COLT MCANLIS: It'll
wait three seconds.
Maybe you should &mdash; having
an awkward mic moment.
Basically, what will
happen with Firefox
is it'll start the
request for the WOFF.
If it hasn't been
downloaded in three seconds,
it'll actually keep
allowing that to download.
But it'll actually display
the font with a default.
It'll just see Arial.
So if you're actually
seeing this on Firefox,
you'll see three
seconds of nothing.
And then you'll see Arial.
And then when the
font comes in, you'll
see it pop to whatever the
font is supposed to be.
And so you see this flicker.
I see it.
You see it a lot on mobile,
because these mobile devices
are actually 6x slower in
hardware just across the board,
probably for at least
another two years,
depending on which hardware
manufacturer you're trending,
then what you're
seeing on the desktops.
Not only is it slower to
download these things,
but these WOFFs are actually
very complex spline paths
that actually can be interpreted
by these under-powered ARM
chips as well.
Anyone in here written
a software rasterizer?
Cool.
Spline paths are slow.
Anyhow, WOFFs are bad.
And you should
feel bad if you're
using them in your
websites right now.
Now, things have been
happening that are
trying to optimize this.
I know that there's
people talking
about different ways to compress
WOFFS and different ways
to use these type of
fonts in different ways.
But please note that if you
have them as part of your site,
you should feel bad.
Now, can I shift reload this?
I don't know.
I can't get the data from cache.
But we also see and here
a couple of these things.
And I can't show you this.
But these images are
actually a little bit larger
than they should be as well.
These are OK.
Is that Willie Nelson?
I don't know.
Again, there's another WOFF.
This PNG, where was
his header on that?
This one's a WebP.
Oh, fantastic.
So this guy was
actually using a WebP.
Interesting.
I don't know what that's doing.
AUDIENCE: That was
the accept header.
COLT MCANLIS: That was
the accept header, yeah.
So at least a WebP
did come down.
However, we see that &mdash;
let's go down here.
Again, 124K.
So again, you guys are
getting the bad rap,
because I'm not doing a
cached fresh reload on this.
But basically, this
site is actually
passing full megabyte,
two megabyte images down.
It's got the WOFFs in the
direct path to rendering.
And so that's going
to take a long time
before text will show up.
In fact, the image will try
to progressively load in
before all the text does.
And this will annoy
your users a lot more.
So let's try to avoid that.
Let's try another website
here really quick.
Just let me go over to this.
Is anyone sad yet about
the state of things?
Is anyone going,
wow, I wonder how
my site does under
this type of scrutiny?
If so, then yay.
I'm doing my job.
I can get paid this week.
Cool.
That was actually pretty quick.
That actually wasn't that bad.
Let me do that again.
Load, load, load.
Good.
Cool.
OK.
So this might be a good site.
Let's take a look at this one.
So we'll hit Inspect again.
We'll load it up.
Let's see here.
Scrolling actually seems
pretty smooth on this site.
It doesn't seem that bad.
We can move stuff
around pretty easily.
Let's take a look
at the Network tab.
Let's hit reload again.
Again, unfortunately,
all of this stuff
is coming from the cache now.
I should have used
my other tablet.
.com, CSS, not that bad.
22K CSS.
27K CSS.
200K.
I don't like this 192K JPEG
that's only 920 by 300.
Notice this.
So this is 192K
for an image that
is a quarter of
the size of Putin.
Quick show of hands.
Who knows what that means?
Yeah, not optimizing your JPEGs.
I think there's actually
some other bad examples here.
Here's another one, 240K.
Oh, oh, 240K, 920 by 300.
Does anyone off the
back of your hand
know what this is if it
were a raw image size?
So it's 920 times 300
times 24 bits per pixel.
Get back to me.
Jake will give you some swag.
Oh, there's a Facebook
icon, only 9K.
Yay.
100 by 100 is 9K.
That seems a little
bit excessive.
That seems like there's actually
some bloat going on there.
I wonder if there's a
negative JPEG encoder.
Make it larger.
By the way, if any of you are
going to be in San Francisco
next week or have a chance
or have the internet,
I think, definitely tune into my
talk I'm giving on compression
on the web.
And hopefully, if you've
seen my talk yesterday
about being scared of closures,
if you see my talk next week
on compression on the web,
hopefully, compression
will scare you after that.
And you'll drudge toward
that monster with a wary eye.
But anyhow, 100K
pixels is 3.9K in size.
So that actually seems a
little bit excessive there too.
Here's, again, those
are the same images.
Here's another one.
These are really large, 180K
being sent to my mobile device.
And the reason this
loaded, again, this
loaded a little fast.
This is a bias,
because I've been
testing these things all day.
And this is coming from cache.
So you're not really feeling
as much pain as you should be.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: Beautiful.
All right.
Jake Archibald for the win.
Here, let's hit reload now.
There we go.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, feel it.
Feel it.
So awkward right now.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: They kind
of should be, yeah.
No one is hiding
their face right now.
So maybe the guy who put
this site in isn't here.
Or you've got a
great poker face.
I will not bet
money against you.
OK.
AUDIENCE: And then they shrank.
COLT MCANLIS: And
then they shrank.
That's actually a great point.
I'll bring this up
really quick too.
How many of you have
responsive websites?
OK.
You're doing it wrong.
Let me ask that in a better way.
How many of your
responsive websites
will actually resize the
image that you've been given?
Jake?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: What
do you mean by resize?
COLT MCANLIS: You've
got a CSS resize, where
you're changing the
properties of it.
If it comes down as 1024
pixels by 1024 pixels
and you display it as 900 pixels
by 900 pixels or something
like that.
Anybody resizing?
You're telling me
every single one of you
gives exactly the right pixel
ratio for every single device
that loads your website?
Is that what I'm hearing?
That guy's hiding his face.
So I know he's doing it wrong.
At least you're honest, brother.
I've got some swag
for you after this.
So here's something a
lot of you don't know.
Decoding a JPEG or a PNG
or a WebP file actually
takes time from your CPU.
And in fact, you know
how I was talking
about those tiles
getting rasterized?
What happens is before a
tile can be rasterized,
Chrome actually has
to go decompress
all the images that
are in that tile.
Now, when that tile is
evicted from the cache,
we're going to have to repaint
it again sometime later.
Well, lo and behold,
there's actually
a texture decompression
cache as well.
So there's a chance, a very
high, high, high chance
on mobile devices, that we'll
actually decompress a JPEG file
and then have to resize the
uncompressed version of it.
So you're actually getting full
32-bit pixels actually being
resized from 1024 to 512.
And then the next time you
have to render that image,
you have to decompress
it and resize it again.
So if an image is split
between two tiles,
you can run into a very
awkward situation, where
you have to decode and resize
that image for each tile
that it's split in.
So if you are resizing your
images dynamically right now,
this could be a
problem for your site.
Hopefully, some of you &mdash;
AUDIENCE: So should we
not do dynamic websites?
COLT MCANLIS: Save the
questions for the end.
I said it to that guy.
I've got to say it to you too.
Was that because I
called you Forecast.io?
OK.
That's all right.
Much love.
Anyhow, so I think we see that
this website has some issues.
And most of it is
on the Network tab.
Let me go ahead and turn
on continuous show paint
rectangles as well, because
I want to show this off too.
So see that red rectangle?
You can see this little one.
Let me show it on
the screen here.
You can see this one
little pop it up.
But watch this red rectangle
happen full screen.
Did you see that?
See that again?
I see this almost on every
single site on this list.
Basically, they got
a marquee on top.
And that marquee,
for some reason,
is actually invalidating the
entire page below it as well.
So the actual DIV that's
expanding this thing, that's
getting repainted, is
touching every single pixel
on the page, which
means that even sitting
here doing nothing, where
actually the CPU is just
sitting here
spinning and spinning
and spinning and spinning
and working and working.
And that's actually going to
make scrolling not as smooth
as possible.
And you can't see it.
I can feel it a little bit here.
This is actually a
pretty janky website.
Up at the top, it says that our
average frame rate right now
is about 18 frames a
second, 17 frames a second.
I can actually really
feel this on mobile.
Now, I have 30 minutes.
Yes.
15 minutes of filler.
So obviously, this is a problem.
And because when I see
something dynamic like this,
I generally think that memory
is going wonky as well.
So let's go ahead and do a
timeline and hit record again.
Let's see what's going on.
We've seen this before.
Same pattern we saw
with the other site.
We see just memory being
allocated and allocated
and allocated and allocated.
Let's hit stop and
see if we can drill in
and see what the culprit is.
Again, I know nothing
of these websites.
I'm just a primitive
C++ developer.
Your web development
scares and confuses me.
So let's go to Profile.
And let's do a record
heap allocations.
So we can see that
memory is a problem.
Now, let's dig in a
little bit deeper.
Let's record a heap application.
OK.
Again, I'm not touching
anything on the website.
And memory, 10K, 5K, 10K, 5K.
Let's hit stop.
Let's try to drill in
here on one of these guys.
Let's just look at this one.
Compiled code.
Looks familiar again.
Oh, wow.
It's almost like we've seen
this exact three lines of code
before.
So again, I know
nothing of this website.
I haven't even looked
at the source code yet.
But something in here is
already passing a closure
to a set timeout
or a set interval.
Sorry.
Set timeout is a different
operating system.
But there's some other
stuff going on in here too.
It looks like some other
relocation info is going on.
I don't see any
injections, which is good.
No one's calling eval, because,
otherwise, we'd probably
see the 6K worth of information.
Someone laughed.
That's probably good.
Eval is bad.
And you should feel bad.
So if you're using closures
and eval, just get out.
Just get out, dude.
I'm going to see a tweet.
Colt says, use set interval
with closure and eval &mdash;
perfmatters &mdash; inside of a WOFF.
By the way, I saw
someone the other day
that actually had a WOFF
embedded inside of a CSS.
And I was like, that's just a
bad idea from all principles.
The CSS gets bloated.
And then the WOFF
has to be &mdash; Anyhow,
we see that this other
part is an array.
Now, this is interesting.
So when you see
this array object,
this means this is an
actual JavaScript array that
is allocated
somewhere on the page.
And you can see
some of it is coming
from internal with
V8, the code DOP data.
But otherwise, the
relocation info &mdash; here's
a null array is just being
created for no reason.
And no items are
being added to it.
We can go down here to string.
And we can see a GM string
has been created somewhere.
Let's scroll this up.
Do we have any information?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: Yeah.
Yeah.
That's what's going on here.
So there's a regex
occurring somewhere.
A GM is being created.
And then there's some
system-level stuff.
This is mostly
dragons and krakens
and other things going
on under the hood.
If we expand this
a little bit, we
can actually slide over and
see, again, compiled code.
There's another relocation info.
Let's see if there's
a DOP this time.
No.
That makes sense, because
the spike's not as high.
We're on this guy.
Compiled code.
Relocation.
Spike's not as high again.
So again, DOP is actually what's
causing the memory spike here.
And then, of course, that's
causing inflation in our heap.
So we can actually see
there's a couple problems.
Obviously, they're sending
too much data down the pipe.
This page is loading slowly.
The person should feel bad.
They've also got some
timers and some closures
and some memory leak
issues that are causing
some friction with their users.
Let's load another site.
Chrome always, thank you.
So let's see this one.
Who thinks this is
going to be a fast site?
Show of hands.
No hands.
Good job.
You win.
I like the spinner.
We're trying to load.
We're letting you know that
we don't know how to do this.
Sorry.
That was below the belt.
I'm sorry.
That was a good idea.
We see it in Gmail.
I don't know.
It's like, hey, we're not
ready to figure out how
to steam content yet.
We saw load.
That was good.
So let's do this again.
Actually, let me show.
Scrolling doesn't seem that bad.
Let's click on something.
That was actually pretty fast.
That was actually
a little too fast.
Hold on.
Wait a minute.
Let me go back.
I'm back to slow.
Let me click on something
else, like trust no one.
I don't trust anybody.
Wow, that actually loaded a
lot faster than the main site.
Let's drill in here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: Dude,
you're messing it up.
Jake, who's got the microphone?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I'm sorry.
COLT MCANLIS: I didn't
interrupt your talk.
So let's take a
look at this here.
So I'm going to
go to Network tab.
And I'm going to hit
reload again here.
And we're going to
take a look at this.
Let's see what's going on.
So it was really weird.
The main page loaded slow.
That was awkward.
But then all subsequent
clicks loaded actually really,
really, really
fast, which tells us
if you can't get
the main page right,
why are you getting
the sub-clicks right?
That's kind of awkward.
So we're still loading.
We're still loading.
Again, I always sort
by size, because I'm
a big dude who says that
memory is where the performance
problems are.
We can actually see
that they're loading.
And I'll give away
the punchline here.
But these images were on the
sub pages, not the main page.
But they're being
loaded on the main page.
Anyone figure it out yet?
Basically, what they're
doing is they're
loading all of the images
for all of the articles
that you would click to before
the main page is loaded.
So they're basically
trading off.
They're saying your
initial load time
is going to be really crummy.
But every click after that
is going to be golden.
So they're giving up that
initial three-second load time
to get one-second
load times later.
Maybe that's a discussion.
Again, here's a WOFF.
Anyone like WOFFs now?
The answer should be no.
But yeah, this is
really interesting
that we're seeing
some of these images.
Let me see if I
can sort this again
and see if we can't get better.
Here's another PNG.
Again, this is not
on the main page.
So let me hit back here.
Let's show you the
main page here.
Even clicking back
takes some time.
No?
Backy?
No, I guess not.
AUDIENCE: You can do it.
COLT MCANLIS: We're stuck now.
There we go.
So yeah.
So notice this right here.
So this was one of the
last things I clicked on.
And they have a
little drop-down.
So basically, each one of
these items, the images
and the extra content is
loaded in the main page, not
the subsequent page.
We're seeing that break down
in a lot of these charts here.
They have a couple lower
res versions here too.
So remember when that 100 pixel
by 100 pixel Facebook icon
was 9K?
Here's a 320 by 180 that's 10K.
So again, don't trust
your Facebook icons.
I would like to say,
don't trust Facebook.
But I'm not allowed
to say that on camera.
Shit.
Sorry.
Again, perfect.
Here's a 320 by 180
that's exactly 9.1K.
So again, I think
all of you should
be questioning how
big your images are.
But I think this Quartz site
is actually an interesting case
study, because they've
definitely traded off
one type of load time for
another type of load time.
And I'm not really
sure why or where
the justifications of that are.
But I think we
can definitely all
agree that the 20 years
that we've had on the web
have all accumulated that the
initial load time is pretty
much the most important
thing, because that's
the first thing your user feels.
None of you have seen this
site, except for the one
guy who submitted it.
And all of you felt the
pain of this site loading
for me hitting a button.
And it doesn't matter how much
the clicks after that are.
Most of us would have left the
site before we got to that.
Let me go over here too.
I want to show this.
So notice this &mdash; I moved now &mdash;
but this YouTube image here.
So if I click this
button, you'll
see the red boxes
again show up here.
So we can actually see
that that part of the page
is being re-rendered.
So you can see, again,
that it's showing &mdash; nope.
Don't care.
Don't.
No, dumb.
Stop.
Let me click.
Done.
What I'd really
like to show here,
and this isn't really showing
up on the main screen.
I'm sorry.
But can anyone see this
orange line right here?
This orange line?
So one of the other
interesting things,
there's a talk that I gave at
Google I/O this year on this.
It's called webpage design
with the GPU in mind.
So what happens is
certain elements on a page
are &mdash; Imagine your
page is a plane.
And all of your images
and all of your text
exist on this plane.
Some of those
things are actually
propagated to its own plane, so
that the webpage can actually
scroll in the background.
And this other plane can
actually scroll relative to it.
So there is relative
scrolling concept.
Let me actually show you
this on a big screen here.
Let me load up HTML5rocks.
No.
I typed in the wrong
thing, because I can type.
Who's on my internet?
Watch my Wi-Fi go down now.
We'll try that.
There we go.
So I'm going to pick a random
article with some random guy
on it, some random
good-looking guy.
I think he's pretty
good looking.
Bald is beautiful here.
So let's go ahead and turn on.
This is Chrome DevTools
on a desktop site.
I know I wasn't going
to talk about this.
But let's do forced accelerated
and show composite layer
borders.
So turning on layer
borders here shows us
what we're seeing normally.
The first thing you see is
that the blue lines here
actually represent the
tiling of the page.
And this orange line
actually represents
something that's been
promoted to its own layer.
So how many of you are
using translateZ(0)?
TranslateZ(0).
Translate3D.
This is the hardware-accelerated
fast path, the silver bullet
that makes your web fast,
because you're suddenly
using the GPU on the web.
It's so amazing.
Actually, that's
not how it works.
What happens is when you use
translateZ(0) or translate3D,
you're actually promoting
these pieces of content
to its own plane.
This is actually a
separate set of tiles.
So remember how I said
the GPU will actually
scroll your tiles on the screen?
When you actually
use translateZ(0),
you get another layer that
the GPU also controls.
Now, I'm going to
see if I can do this,
because for some reason we
get paused in the debug.
Too much clicking.
So as I scroll here, notice
how these objects on the side &mdash;
watch this.
The table of contents
has not orange.
And so once it gets
to a certain part,
it actually gets promoted
to its own layer.
The orange border represents
different layers in GPU memory.
And then as I scroll
down the page,
they actually stay static.
Any time you have relative
scrolling content on your page,
you're actually going
to want to promote it
with this translateZ(0)
or translate3D.
Now, beware that this actually
puts a lot of pressure
on your GPU.
So for all of you
who are just going
to start putting translateZ(0)
on every part of your page &mdash;
we saw this happen
a lot because it
was supposed to be
a silver bullet &mdash;
every one of these tiles,
every one of these layers,
is actually contending for
residency inside of your GPU
cache, which means the more
of these separate layers
that you've actually promoted,
the slower your website is
going to be.
So you can get an
inverse effect with it,
because, basically, your
GPU is getting overtaxed.
More tiles are being
evicted from your cache,
because more things are
fighting for residency.
It's actually going to
slow down your site,
because your CPU is
spinning out more.
Anyhow, enough with
the desktop stuff.
Desktop is dead.
No one wants desktop.
OK.
Let's go back over
here to this thing,
because the mobile web is sexy.
What was I showing off?
Yeah.
So this qz site, this
is actually a little bit
interesting, because we see
mostly that as we're scrolling,
notice the big red spots
that keep popping up.
Let me see if I can get
it to do that again.
See it?
So something's going on.
I'll spare you the
punchline here.
What's actually occurring
is that these guys
are doing something with
a scroll handler in here,
where they're actually trying
to catch what I'm doing.
They're trying to
catch my little scroll.
reposition things.
And we soon as
they touch the DOM,
the whole DOM has
to be recalculated.
As soon as the whole DOM
has to be recalculated,
all of the tiles
have to be redrawn.
So as soon as they try to
touch what I'm scrolling
and reposition things
manually, they're actually
invalidating the
hardware compositing
and the GPU scrolling that we're
trying to do on their behalf
and actually messing up
their entire frame rate.
How many of your mobile sites
are catching a user input
like this?
Yeah.
I saw that.
At least you're honest.
Forecast.io, they know
what's going on guys.
I got it right.
He didn't.
No, he still hates me.
That's OK.
All right.
Let's do some other websites.
Pete, how are we doing on time?
PETE: 15.
COLT MCANLIS: 15 minutes?
I can load all the
websites in 15 minutes.
So let's look at a
couple other ones here.
Let's see.
Let's take a look
at something good,
so that everyone
walks away from here
with feelings of
happy bunny times.
Sorry.
I just called somebody.
So this is meetup.com.
OK.
So we didn't see
a loading spinner.
That was nice.
But it did take a
little bit long to load.
In general though, let's
see how it scrolls.
That's actually pretty fast.
Let's open the DevTools again
and see what kind of red things
are occurring and what
kind of load times
we're experiencing here.
So turn on DevTools.
Let's hit reload and see
how the network performs.
Not that bad.
On the device, I'm
actually seeing
things starting
to pop up already.
I notice no WOFFs in the code.
That's really good.
Oh, there is one.
Son of a bitch.
Where did that come from?
Oh, bogus.
Well, maybe they're not using
that on something critical.
Let's sort by content here.
This is really cool to see.
A 44K JavaScript is actually
the biggest part of the page.
I'm surprised that's
not jQuery at 191K.
How many of you are using--?
You know what?
Never mind.
Just never mind.
OK.
Actually, this
image is popping up
at the top, 60K
JPEG, 320 by 226.
That's maybe a little large.
Another 60K JPEG.
Another 50K JPEG.
This is really interesting too,
because we just saw 340 by 226s
on the previous site
that were about 10K.
So again, someone's not
optimizing JPEGs the right way.
In fact, actually on the
article that I put on HTML5rocks
about image
compression &mdash; let me see
if I can type over
there really quick.
So this article that
I did was actually
image compression
for web developers.
The entire point of this article
was to talk to all of you
in a very frank way and
discuss the back story of where
image compression works.
Plus, I'm a real
big fan of parrots.
They're kind of cool, especially
the digitally pixelated ones.
Anyhow, there's some
great content down here
about JPEG information.
And it actually shows that &mdash;
here it is, right here.
Let me see if I
can zoom this in.
Nope.
Too far.
OK.
So I feel it's
important to break away
from our regular scheduled
bashing of these websites,
because that's getting a
little depressing, right?
Everyone is getting depressed.
So this is actually a test
that an external person
did on the compression
quality of images
that are being served by the
top websites of the world.
And what you're actually seeing
here is that most of them
actually just use
a standard value.
So all Window Live background
images are exactly 82.
Regardless of what the
PSNR is, they choose 82.
It's hard coded.
So they might be able on some
of the images to use a level 64
and actually reduce
the size more.
But they use 82.
Wikipedia are all 80 for
every one of their images,
regardless of the
content quality on it.
YouTube is about 70 to 82.
That's good.
It shows that they're actually
doing some dynamic scaling.
Although it's unclear
whether or not that
it's actually manually scaled,
or they have an artist actually
changing them, or they have
some sort of dynamic solution,
like I was saying.
Yahoo, 69 to 91.
Again, they may have some more
responsive version of that.
Facebook's are at 85.
And Google image
thumbnails are about 74.
Here's the really interesting.
Twitter user JPEGs are
anywhere between 30 and 100,
which means that
for some images,
they're actually doing nothing.
And some images, they're
doing everything.
This actually tells me &mdash; no one
is in here from Twitter, right?
This actually tells me that
they may have something dynamic
actually testing the noise
ratio of the compression
there and actually serving
you the most optimized JPEG
at the best image
quality possible.
So that's really cool.
That's really cool to
see that someone's is
doing that out on the web.
OK.
Back to doom and gloom.
We were over here.
So these images probably are a
little too large in megabytes.
They're probably
not optimizing it.
Nope, that's not an image.
Chances are they're just
using a standard one.
So let's hit timeline.
Let's just hit record.
Let's see what's
going on with memory.
I'm not touching anything.
Memory is increasing,
not too much, 5.5, 5.6.
Again, we've got these
timers getting fired.
fine.js.
I don't even know what this is.
Meetup script mobile find.
So apparently, it's trying
to meet me and find me.
That's kind of creepy.
Mobile base.
So that's weird.
So they've got two
separate timers
coming from their own website
doing two different things.
And again, I'm not
touching anything.
Nothing's happening.
Nothing is moving.
But we're at 5.6 megs.
So this is like a slow leak.
It looks like there's a slow
closure or something being
tossed to this.
So let's take a look at this
and see if we can't drill in.
Oh, yay.
It is a jQuery library.
Summon the power
of pretty print.
Aha.
That didn't help.
I'll try that again.
There we go.
Oh, mustache.
Interesting.
Who uses mustache?
Can anyone explain this
line of code to me?
AUDIENCE: It's a
JavaScript template.
[INAUDIBLE] is derived from it.
COLT MCANLIS: So this is
causing a memory leak.
Can anyone fix this?
Not now?
OK.
That's cool.
Take your time.
That's all right.
We'll get back to it.
But basically, we're
seeing again this looks
like an anonymous function
calling some factory objects,
testing some object definitions.
This in and of itself
doesn't look bad.
Although it is calling another
anonymous function down here.
Sometimes the
pretty print spacing
doesn't get it all right.
This might actually be
a closure in a closure.
It looks like we've got one
closed there and one open here.
Something is going on.
Any of you who are using
third-party libraries,
it's actually really easy
to fall into these traps,
where they're allocating
memory and doing stuff
on your behalf that may
be negatively impacting
your performance.
And we sometimes
ignore these faults
and don't track
these faults down,
because of the fact that we get
event propagation or something
else, like oh, I get a call
back when something occurs.
That code you can actually
write in about 100 lines
of your own making and actually
keep it memory performant.
But instead, we pull in
these large libraries.
So it's important that
you know these trade-offs
when something like
this is occurring.
Let's do another website.
Pete, we've got what?
10 minutes left?
Yeah?
About 10 minutes?
Let's see.
What haven't we done here?
So I have to load
this, because I really
don't get this website.
And I really want to talk
about the website more
than the performance
characteristics.
So this is called
Game of Phones.
Is this your site?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
COLT MCANLIS: OK.
Cool.
I really don't get this website.
But it's here.
So we can take a look at it
from a performance perspective.
Basically, what happens
is someone will record.
And from what I
can tell, they're
very politically
charged, angry arguments.
And you sign up.
And someone will call you and
play this recorded message
that's like, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
rally, fight the power.
And then you have to call
someone else on the list
and try to regurgitate
what you heard.
And so it's like the
game of telephone
that you play as kids.
And you're trying to
get all the way through.
I have no idea why people
are even doing this.
I hate getting calls
from my wife, much less
random strangers
on the internet.
I'm on the internet because
I don't want you to call me.
Send me a text or something.
Anyhow.
Personal thing.
I'm sure it works
for your brother.
I don't get the internet.
I'm too old.
That's my problem.
AUDIENCE: I've had people tell
me it's the only phone calls
that they will answer.
COLT MCANLIS: Oh, dude.
Game of Phones.
Awesome.
You know what you need to do?
You actually need to get the
voices from "Game of Thrones"
to actually do the call.
And then it would just go
through the roof, dude.
HBO might sue me now.
Sorry about that.
Anyhow, let's look at this
from a performance perspective.
There's really
nothing on this page.
It's kind of text.
But we're going to
run through it anyway,
just so you guys can see the
differences in these things.
So I'm not here.
By the way, did you see
actually what showed up?
Was this on the screen?
Sorry.
So this is Game of Phones.
Again, it's just text and
people calling each other.
But this is it.
12 requests.
The interesting
thing here is 107K.
That's a little odd.
We were seeing some other
pages come in below that.
Mainly, this is coming from &mdash;
Bootstrap is being included.
I'm not really sure why
this needs Bootstrap.
I guess the cool
kids are doing it.
And here's the funny thing.
We got Bootstrap.min and then
CSS that replaces Bootstrap.
So that's a thing.
And then jQuery.
OK.
And then here's another
Bootstrap again and then
telephone gram and
then another jQuery.
Are you using two jQueries?
AUDIENCE: I should
mention that I've never
made a web page before.
COLT MCANLIS: You're
using two jQueries.
Do you know you're
using two jQueries?
AUDIENCE: Now I do.
COLT MCANLIS: Now you do.
OK.
And then I like the GIF.
It's spritesheeted, I guess.
Here's the cool thing.
So a 300 by 120 animated
GIF is only 4.4K.
Yet we were seeing full JPEGs
that were 9K that were static.
So I'm not really sure
what else to do with this.
Let me hit timeline and see
what this is doing here.
It's a little awkward.
So your jQueries
are using memory.
So this is kind of tell-tale.
Do you have a timer?
It looks like you have a timer.
AUDIENCE: Maybe the
audio player is using it.
COLT MCANLIS: Maybe
the audio player.
Yeah.
Yeah, it does.
So it looks like
there's a timer here.
I don't know if you
guys can see this.
It looks like
there's a timer here.
And you can see this red square
up here, just the Play button.
That Play button
has a timer that
needs jQuery and Bootstrap &mdash;
two jQueries and Bootstrap &mdash;
and is allocating a meg of
memory over seven seconds.
So that's a thing.
Lots of rasterizes occurring
in here, lots of recalculates.
So not only is it
repainting, it's
actually updating
the DOM to repaint.
Let's look at this again.
That's updating the DOM.
Don't know why.
Maybe there's a cool
jitter effect there.
Maybe I got this wrong.
Maybe I'm actually
looking at the matrix.
Am I looking at the matrix?
That would be kind of cool.
I'm like analyzing.
No, sorry.
I'm having fun.
It's late.
And I have to keep you all
awake for another five minutes.
So anyhow, I don't
like this trend.
You're actually allocating
more memory faster
than the other
websites we looked at.
It's probably because
you have two jQueries.
But anyhow, let's dig in.
So let's go to Profiles.
Again, follow the memory,
find the performance problems.
So we follow the asset
memory to figure out
where load problems are.
We follow the dynamic
memory to figure out
where compute problems
and render problems are.
Can I click this button please?
Clicky.
You've allocated too much
memory for your site.
And I can't click.
Oh, there we go.
OK.
So let's do record
heap applications.
Hit start.
So that's kind of interesting.
Do you guys see this pattern?
So this is, actually,
really very, very regular
allocations that are occurring,
two different sets of it.
But they're almost
deleted immediately,
except for the
stuff that happened
in the beginning of the trace.
So see, we're seeing
the gray lines.
So the gray lines mean
that what was allocated
has actually been freed now.
This is kind of odd.
I want to see where
this is coming from.
I like to dig in and
figure out why I'm so bald.
So we have the whole thing.
Yada, yada, yada.
Let's actually just
highlight this guy here.
So array.
Transition array.
So something is going
on inside of V8.
All these are being deleted.
Compiled code.
Is it DOP?
No, relocation.
So it looks like there's
just some sort of cases
where jQuery is executing.
Again, I see this a
lot with closures.
Closures, for some reason,
tend to bring up this pattern.
jQuery is kicking
off a closure that's
causing a reflow of your
entire page for a five pixel
by five pixel icon.
So you still loaded faster
than the other sites.
Bravo.
Round of applause for that.
[APPLAUSE]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
don't need images.
COLT MCANLIS: There you go.
I'm a fan of the text web.
That requires drinking to get
more information out of that.
Anyhow, let's load
up another one.
Pete, how are we doing on time?
PETE: About five minutes.
COLT MCANLIS: Five more minutes.
OK.
Let's clear up quickly,
because I'm actually
really interested to try this
Robitussin and whiskey thing.
I think we may have
something on there.
ADAM GROSSMAN: I
highly recommend it.
COLT MCANLIS: OK.
Let's try this CBN week.
And we're done.
I think at this time
I don't actually
need to tell you guys
what I'm about to do.
No, I don't want to translate.
I used to be able
to speak Chinese.
It was a beautiful language.
So you know what
I'm about to do.
I'm going to load up networking.
I'm going to see what images
are too large, what JavaScript
is too large, what you're using
that you shouldn't be using.
We're going to try to
call assets and get rid
of extra network loads.
I thought the points
about spritesheets
was perfect earlier.
By the way, they shouldn't
be called spritesheets.
They should be called atlases.
You should actually see my
Udacity course rant on this.
Everywhere else in the world
and video games and film
and everything, we
call them atlases.
You know what?
Never mind.
Anyhow, let's see
some scrolling.
Not that bad.
Let's head over to DevTools.
Let's take a look at this
under the microscope.
Let's go back to Network.
My computer said I'm dumb.
This will be the last site.
And then we'll actually
get to all the questions.
And I think we're going to
do a group question, right?
Fantastic.
So that's interesting.
So there's already 89
requests, 92 requests, 93, 95.
1.5 megs transferred so far.
1.9, 2 megs, 2.195.
So here's something
interesting up here.
So notice this gray
bar right here.
So in Chrome DevTools, when
you look at this Network tab,
basically, you see two values.
You see this semi-transparent
and this opaque portion
of these items.
That semi-transparent
value is actually
how long the browser spent
waiting to receive the asset.
This is one of the reasons
that spritesheets are actually
so important for you, because
each browser has a set
number of limits
of open connections
that it will allow
to a single server.
For Chrome, I believe
it's around six,
which means if you have
six requests in flight,
it'll block the rest of the
requests until a slot opens up.
Think of it like a
caching FIFO or whatnot.
And so Chrome actually shows
you this here on the timeline.
You can see some of
these actually waited
a very, very long time.
In this case, it actually
spent 471 milliseconds waiting.
It wanted to request
this asset, but it
couldn't because there were
other things in the pipe.
And you can see that this
is a function of the fact
that there's about 100 requests
and 3.6 megs transferred.
For those of you who don't
know, the average website
size right now, according
to HTTP archive,
is about 1.1 megs.
And that's for desktop.
They haven't really got into
a lot of the mobile testing
just yet.
But obviously, mobile
shouldn't be 1.1 meg, right?
So obviously, there's
too big a content here.
So let's see if there's
any big offenders.
Let's see if images
are a problem.
Who thinks images are a problem?
Here's a 300K image,
200K, 197K, 161K, 152K.
What is in that image?
I think that's bigger than raw.
Yeah.
Obviously, these
images are too big.
They're not being optimized.
They should be fixed.
Let's take a look at timeline.
Let's see if anything is
going on with memory here.
Anything crazy?
Slow, again timer.
We see this same pattern.
So we see almost
all of these pages
are falling into
the same pattern.
Also, almost all of these
pages and some of them,
in rare cases, are all using
jQuery or jQuery twice.
Closures are being passed
off to timers for things
like ads or analytics
or marquees.
And this seems to
be a common pattern.
But this is obviously is
causing a lot of memory
and a lot of churn and some
other weird things going on.
I can look at the
frames times here.
And so let me actually do this.
I don't know if I showed
you guys this tool.
Nope.
Cancel.
So as I'm scrolling here &mdash;
and it's not picking that up.
Never mind.
I won't show you that tool.
Anyhow, let's be done
with this for the evening
because I think Pete has
some other stuff he wants
to talk to you
guys about tonight.
So thank you for
your time tonight.
Perfmatters.
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
I'll let you start
the clap in a second.
So here's how you
get a hold of me.
If anything today was
controversial or something
worth tweeting or
something you just
want to ask more questions
about, go ahead and find me.
Make sure you join the Google+
web performance community.
There's a lot of
great stuff there.
Please, for the love of
God, use perfmatters.
Follow perfmatters.
It's a brand.
You should wear this at work.
Everything you do, you should
be challenging your employees,
your managers, the
owners of your company,
perfmatters,
perfmatters, perfmatters.
It's going to be the thing that
separates the billion dollar
companies from everybody
else on the mobile web
within the next year.
In fact, it already is.
It's already [INAUDIBLE].
Challenge everyone.
Hold them to the
standards of perfmatters.
Now, you can start the clap.
Yes.
Thank you for your time.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: Thanks, Colt.
That was awesome.
OK.
So we know it's late.
We're going to have a
quick Q&A with speakers.
If you're ready, we
have some chairs.
You can come sit down.
We'll make it
quick, quick, quick.
And maybe share a mic.
Runner?
OK.
Questions, anyone?
AUDIENCE: This is directed
to the weather application.
ADAM GROSSMAN: By
the way, I'm really,
really glad you didn't look at
Forecast and try to benchmark
it.
Really glad.
AUDIENCE: I just would like
to know what is actually
keeping you from
putting it to the web?
And why not?
And &mdash;
ADAM GROSSMAN: What do you mean?
AUDIENCE: Shouldn't
you try harder?
You say you can't
put it to the web.
It has to be an application.
ADAM GROSSMAN: Well,
it doesn't have to be.
But I don't know
anyone who would
be willing to check the
weather by going to a website.
It just takes way too long.
And there are so many
good apps out there.
It's just not
something people are
going to do, at least
not in large numbers.
People may try at first.
But I just don't
see that happening.
And that's definitely
not true for most things.
I think it's a weird thing
for weather, in particular.
If it's so awesome that it's
the best website in the world,
people would go to it.
But that's the one thing that
native apps have over the web
is the ease of accessibility.
And they load super fast.
That doesn't really
answer your question.
AUDIENCE: I could go on.
But next question.
PETE: You had a question
yourself, right?
ADAM GROSSMAN: I
did have a question.
Sorry.
Is Colt short for something?
Or is your name
just that awesome?
COLT MCANLIS: Thank
you first off.
Colt is short for Colton.
I was actually named
after the 1970s show,
"The Fall Guy," Colt Seavers.
It turns out my parents were
geeks before I was a geek.
By the way, go Colts.
PETE: We have another
question from the crowd.
AUDIENCE: It's a question
for Colt about the PSNR.
Is that right?
COLT MCANLIS: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Do you know
of any command line
or open source tools that can do
a little bit of that iteration
and, as a trade-off of
time versus precision,
give you a good compression?
COLT MCANLIS: Yeah, absolutely.
So pretty much every single
JPEG compressor will do that.
So the question for
the people at home,
in case they didn't
hear it is, do you
know if there's a command
line compressor for JPEG that
will actually give you
this evaluation of PSNR
and how much it takes to
get that value and whatnot?
Pretty much all of them do.
If you actually
go out and Google,
"image compressor comparison,"
the first 29 pages you'll see
are just going to
be charts of PSNR
against file size
against time to compress.
So things like
libjpeg, jpeg-turbo.
These are the top tier.
And like I said, one
of them is actually
used inside of Chrome
because of its speed.
And I think there was
actually a news article
a couple of weeks
ago of Apple actually
acquiring a Scottish
company or an Irish company
that all they did was make a
faster JPEG decoder for the iOS
platform.
And so they are now all living
in mansions with waterfalls
inside of their mansions
because they just
made a JPEG decoder
that was faster.
But yeah, definitely
check those out.
AUDIENCE: So I do
have a question
about the special font
files for Colt, the WOFF,
I guess or whatever,
whoever knows better.
And a font or some
which some people
use for icons and whatnot,
what's the suggestion?
What do you do?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: In terms of
what you would do for icons?
AUDIENCE: You don't use them at
all or how to avoid using them
if the client wants a
specific pretty font?
What do you do?
JAKE ARCHIBALD:
So I would always
avoid using web
fonts for body copy.
You can almost get away with
it for things like headlines,
because the chances are the
user has some idea of what
the headline is going to be.
They've either clicked
it from the previous page
or they've clicked it from
search results or something
like that.
The problem is when it's
there for body copy,
because that's when not
only is the user going
to have to wait for the
CSS to see anything,
because there are very
few resources that
are going to block
your first render.
It's JavaScript.
If it's done wrong,
it's CSS all the time.
And it's web fonts.
And the problem with web
fonts is their loading
is triggered by the CSS.
It's going to
happen after layout.
So your CSS downloads.
There's a layout done.
And then it goes, oh, I
need to download a font.
The font downloads.
And then it can
render that text.
I would say avoid for body copy.
You can use a
WebFont loader, which
is something developed
by Google and Typekit.
And what you can
do there is it will
use JavaScript to
load the web fonts.
And it will give you special
class names on the HTML or body
element, I forget
which, that indicate
the loading states of that font.
And you can then decide
to use a different font
while it's loading.
You can force, kind of what
Internet Explorer does.
But it means you can tweak
the size of the fallback font
to more closely match,
change the line height,
change the size to
more closely match
the font that will load in.
So you can do that
with headlines
because they tend
to be one line.
You'll struggle
with the body copy,
because the user will
be reading a bit.
And then the chances are
things are going to jump.
And the word is going to
move along the line or worse.
It's going to wrap differently.
PETE: Next question?
AUDIENCE: This is
for any and all.
We saw a lot of examples that
was pretty easy to detect
performance issues with file
sizes and number of network
requests.
Increasingly, we're seeing sites
that the perception of page
load is just as bad as
the actual throughput.
So can you talk a
little bit about how
you would analyze and
test for, basically,
all the crap that's being
done when DOM is ready
and people are just loading
stuff after the initial load
and there's all kinds of junk
happening with JavaScript?
How would you test and
analyze that kind of thing?
JAKE ARCHIBALD:
Well, first, I want
to pick up on
something that Colt
said, because I think
it's worth saying again.
If your site has a
loading bar, 99% of cases,
that's a missed opportunity.
You're doing it wrong.
And I include Gmail
in this as well.
The fact that I have to
watch a loading bar go
to see a set of email subjects,
which is just a list &mdash; it's
essentially an HTML list of
a sentence &mdash; is ridiculous.
And if you compare something
like TweetDeck to Twitter,
Twitter will do this.
They serve HTML and CSS.
You get the content
as it's loading.
Whereas in something
like TweetDeck,
you get this loading bar.
So yeah, it pulls
script out of you.
Avoid depending on script
for a first render, I think,
would be the first case.
But I don't know.
Do you have anything
in terms of how
you would test that or
any continuous integration
for that?
COLT MCANLIS: Telemetry.
Yeah.
So we didn't really
get a chance to talk
a lot about continuous
integration tonight.
I think Jake and I both agree
that probably the next big step
in web performance is getting
a good tool out there to allow
you to do performance,
continuous integration.
So you should be able to have
some distributed team checking
in code changes to some
GitHub or something like that.
And then some automated system
will actually kick off a build.
And then once that
build is done,
it's run across continuous
integration environment
across different web servers
and different mobile devices
and actually give you
performance information back,
not just from the
network side of things,
but also from the rendering
side of things, the JavaScript
side of things, post load Ajax
style information as well,
and be able to give
you that in a report.
So you can actually go back
and be like, hey, Jake, you
broke the perf build, dude.
I think this is
actually the next step
in tooling for the web.
And I think we're pretty far
away from it, unfortunately.
So I hope that there's
a lot of people
thinking about this problem.
PETE: Next question?
AUDIENCE: So the set
timeout, instead of that,
you should be using [INAUDIBLE]
for polling, for daemons.
COLT MCANLIS: So set timeout,
in itself, is not a problem.
I'll say that again.
Set timeout, in itself,
is not a problem.
The problem is passing a
closure to set timeout.
So obviously, if
you're using a closure,
there's a chance
that you don't know
why you're using a closure.
Or you're using a
closure, because you
think it's a better
coding pattern.
It seems to be a pretty
standard coding practice when
you go copy paste
off of the web.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
COLT MCANLIS: Again, the set
interval, not the problem.
Feel free to use set interval.
Yay, set interval.
Woo!
The problem is set interval
plus incorrect memory
management or closure is
being passed to set interval.
That's the problem.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: What I would say
is if you're doing animations,
you've got this,
assuming 60 Hz screen,
you've got this
16.67 milliseconds
window in order to produce what
you want to produce and then
get that on the screen
in the next refresh.
If something else in the
page is running set interval,
I'm assuming you're using
RequestAnimationFrame
for your animations, which you
should be, or CSS animations.
But if you then have set
interval or something running
or some other things
using set interval,
even if that's only going
to take three milliseconds,
if it happens in the
three milliseconds
when there's going to be a
new refresh on the screen,
it's going to block that frame
from happening on the screen.
And it will drop a frame.
So if you're doing
a set interval,
if you're going to do
some work inside that,
you do your set intervals
for whatever you want,
like every 300
milliseconds or whatever.
If you've got some
substantial work
to do in there or
really any work,
use RequestAnimationFrame
in there
as well, because it'll
queue that stuff up
for right at the
start of the refresh
and along with,
maybe, other timers
that just happen to coincide
roughly at the same time.
COLT MCANLIS: Really
quick on that.
So there's actually
a design pattern
that I don't talk about a lot,
because people throw chairs
at me.
So a lot of people are
actually handling input
when the user actually
gives them that event.
So you click.
I get the on-click event.
And you go, cool,
this is an event.
Let me run some code right now.
That's actually a
bad idea as well.
Because, again, you
have to remember
that the web page
and the browser
is going to come along
at every 16 milliseconds
or whatever the refresh
rate of the monitor is.
And it's going to try to
repaint and refresh the screen.
But if that JavaScript is in
the middle of executing input
or set intervals
or anything, it's
going to block that
from occurring.
And so there's a
different design pattern
that we've seen very
successful, and we see it
with game developers especially,
is that you don't actually
do any logic in
callback handlers.
Instead, you actually just
cache that value away.
And the next time that
your RequestAnimationFrame
comes around, you
actually respond to that.
And so if you want to get rid
of this set interval system,
just put all that logic in
a RequestAnimationFrame.
The difference is in
whatever your interval
you think your interval needs
to be in the 16 milliseconds
that RequestAnimationFrame
comes around, come on.
We're talking about polling
data or other things.
So it's a different
mental model.
PETE: OK.
So virtually, we're out
of time for questions.
That's our show for tonight.
Yes.
OK.
So our next event is
going to our Hack Day.
It's going to be November 16.
It's going to be right here.
@timesopen and @nytdevs to
follow what we're up to.
@nytdevs is the
main one on Twitter.
You can also visit our site,
developers@NYTimes.com.
I wanted to thank our speakers.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: I want to thank the
team that planned the event.
They're all wearing
purple shirts.
They can all wave their hands.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE: And Pete
LePage from Google,
who is standing there carefully
looking at his camera.
A lot of work went into this.
And we want to thank
you for coming.
It's been a great night.
Go make your websites faster.
We're good?
Oh, yes.
One other thing &mdash;