>> Dan Heberden: Hello. As you have been looking
it at for 15 minutes, I'm Dan Heberden. So
enough about that. I will get my slides up
here.
So this is bower, at least the very basic
beginnings of what you would start to use
where you just run bower install jQuery and
you see that it went and got jQuery, installed
it for us in the current folder. What we didn't
have to do is specify a version. We didn't
have to find out what the latest version is
or whatever one we wanted.
And what does getting jQuery look like for
you? Or I mean really any library, but jQuery
is a good example.
Oops, sorry about that.
Does that mean going to jquery.com and downloading
that? Does that mean going to the github repo
and looking for maybe a built copy? Do you
have to clone the repo and then build it with
their build tools? Do you memorize URL and
use wget or curl and pull it down?
Bower helps because it makes installing tools
much easier. And it uses a manifest file to
declare what it is that you actually want
to download or to use in your project. And
those downloads are centralized into a commonplace,
which are very helpful, and it by itself resolves
dependencies.
So before I get into all the pieces of what
bower is, I would like to show you what it
looks like with a canon of other tools, a
full suite. And so Yeoman and Grunt are required,
yes, are great tools. If you haven't gotten
a chance to look at them or learn about them,
I really recommend diving into them.
But we are just going to run a quick example
to just show off some stuff that bower can
do.
So first we would do is get Yeoman. Yeoman
is just a scaffolding tool that lets you define
&mdash; there's a couple generators out there.
There are, like, 16 that it comes with and
then a bunch more that help you scaffold typical
applications.
And the typical application we want to scaffold
is a requirejs app. So we can just get generator-requirejs.
You can do this yourself but it is kind of
nice to get everything already to go without
having to do a lot of work.
I will show you what that looks like. Just
make a quick &mdash;
so assuming I have gotten those two things,
I can just run Yeoman with required requirejs
and it will do a couple of things. It will
ask me some questions, what I want the app
to be called.
We are just going to make a quick weather
app. So we will say my-weather-app and a default
description. Now, I'm not going to hit enter
now just because that's going to go through
and download everything from NPM and everything
from bower and everything that we need. And
I don't really trust the WiFi.
So I'm going to just change to the baked cake
in the oven. And we can see actually &mdash; I
will just do this &mdash; that it already gave
us a lot of stuff just out the gate. It gave
us an app directory with requirejs config
file that calls the main file here. And we
can &mdash; it just says jQuery in there, but we
can put anything in there.
But it also did some other stuff. It set us
up with Grunt. So we have concatenation and
minification, js hinting and that kind stuff
already set up.
It made a packaged JSON; and it did put our
name in there for us, which is really convenient.
So some nice convenience measures.
So let's go ahead and actually write some
stuff. Now, for making a weather app, probably
someone has done the work of getting weather.
I'm sure actually thousands of people have
probably done that all by theirselves without
even looking to see if anyone has done that.
So let's just use bower, and we'll search
for weather.
I will make that a little bit bigger.
So it looks like Dan Heberden, I don't know
who that guy is, but he made a weather thing.
And I'm going to trust it for the sake of
this presentation.
So, I can just install bower &mdash; or use bower
to install weather. And I will save that to
my configuration file. If you have used NPM,
that's the same kind of thing. We will talk
more about what these pieces mean.
You can see here it went in and got the weather
component. It also got the stuff that the
component needs, which is jQuery.
And so now if I go back to my application
here, I not only have the things that were
part of the original application, requirejs
and jQuery and Qnit, but I also have my weather
module. So let's go ahead and use that. Since
this is an AMD module, I will just jump over
into my main file here; and I can just reference
it directly.
Hop back to my slides. That is not the right
slide.
There we go. Okay.
So in our app, we would put in some HTML for
our actual weather information, just temperature
and status, that kind of stuff. And then inside
of that, we can use that weather component
that we installed. So we'll just use require
to get that and typical AMD stuff here, so
nothing too crazy, and make a function that
actually uses the position object that the
weather API returns with temperature and condition
and that kind of stuff.
And then actually get our current position.
So we'll use geolocation, get our current
position, and pump that latitude and longitude
into our weather module.
I have the finished product here. Hopefully,
this will work with the connection. So I have
a connect server actually part of this whole
suite here, which is nice via Grunt, so I
can start a Web server on local host.
You see here that that worked pretty well
out of the box and was able to make a server
connection, do all that stuff, but we didn't
have to worry about finding this module and
putting it in. We were just able to take advantage
of it.
Let's look at what happened here, and this
is the bower.json that was generated from
what we did. And we have a requirejs and JS
dependencies that came out of the box. But
when we installed weather, it also added that
version here. The tilde means it is going
to keep the minor version. So if that goes
to 0.2.4, it will go ahead and install that.
So we looked at kind of a quick demo of what
that would look like using that with other
tools.
I do want to show you one really neat thing
since I have this up. And that is using all
of these tools together. And this is mostly
just a plug for Grunt and how well it does
all of this stuff.
I just ran every task that is set up with
this, so I'm hinting. I'm running my test
suite. I'm getting all of the dependencies
via requirejs and putting them all together.
And now I'm concatenating and minifying all
of that together. So my original uncompressed
file of 326K is now 23K. That's pretty cool.
So if you aren't doing this or haven't looked
in these kind of tools, I highly suggest doing
that. One HTTP request to get all of the site
running. That's pretty neat.
So why a clientside package manager? When
using clientside tools should be easy. I mean,
sure going to hotscripts.com and finding some
script was really fun ten years ago.
There's a problem with open and public code
being committed into repositories. And I don't
know about you, but I don't really like waiting
for github to download gargantuan repositories
all the time. What happens is older and buggy
versions of libraries or frameworks or plug-ins
get stuck in projects, and it is harder to
work around getting a new one in there. And
then there is a hesitancy to use an existing
solution because it is kind of a pain to go
out and find what's available.
When you do find out there is a great plug-in
or piece, you have to go find out what it
needs to run and that can be a hassle.
Bower, of course, makes it awesome, hence
this talk. Let's look into bower. Let's look
into what pieces it has that will help you.
We saw installation before. We can just install
a component and it will go and grab all of
that stuff. It will grab all the pieces, put
that into our folder. We can also do that
via manifest files. So we can declare what
we want, run bower install, and it will just
go through that manifest file just like NPM
and get the pieces that are required along
with anything that those pieces require and
anything those pieces require until it has
everything that you need.
And, of course, if you edit the manifest file,
we want to change this &mdash; say, there was a
bug and we want to force version 0.2.0, we
can do that and run bower install and it will
go get the right files and make sure everything
is okay as far as dependencies go.
Now, if you want to do this from the command
line, you can do that pretty easily just by
putting in the module name that you want and
then a hash mark and then a version. And that
will do the same thing if you need to do that
from the command line. In this case, we want
jQuery 1.8.0. And so we can force that.
And you can manually edit it, that's fine.
But we have this same as NPM--save and --savedev
and those let you just express what you want
to install but also put that into your manifest
file because chances are you will want that
any time you recreate this project or someone
else clones this project and gets it.
But at this point, bower is mostly just a
glorified URL shortener. Like, this is nice
but this isn't really what's really going
to help you.
So upgrading is where bower also shines in
making your life a lot easier in dealing with
clientside libraries and frameworks and plug-ins.
Since required packages don't have to be committed
into your repository, it makes discoverability
and it makes working with these libraries
much easier.
Check out bower ls. It gives you a quick look
at what your current project looks like. And
so in this case, we just installed jQuery
1.8.0, it is going to let us know that 2.0.0
is out and that we can look into upgrading
to that. We didn't have to go to the jQuery
site or make sure we follow the blog. And
this is for any particular plug-in or piece
that you follow. But it also hunts down the
dependencies just to make sure that everything
is fine as far as what it requires as well.
So we have a nice map of what our project
looks like.
Bower update will take the current version
and install it to the highest minor version
possible. So in this case, it will go to 1.8.3.
And that's nice if you want to just make sure
that while there shouldn't be any problems,
run the test suite, give it a run-through,
and then make sure you can deploy your site
using these latest versions.
Let's talk about the power of bower.json,
having something that expresses your clientside
needs in your application. And the easiest
way to do that is this: Just obliterate the
components directory.
And, of course, this would cripple your app
all together. And it is just as easy as running
bower install to get all of that stuff back.
Now, bower is just a package manager. Bower
doesn't give you minified code. Bower doesn't
concatenate things. It doesn't load modules
for you and it won't. You say what you want,
and bower gets it. Because there is plenty
of great tools out there. There is tons of
build tools. There's tons of things to help
you do certain tasks. Bower doesn't need to
do that for you. But what it does need to
do is play well with others.
And so since it is written in JavaScript and
since it is a node library, you can just require
it and do the same things that you can do
from the command line, search, install, look
at what packages are available, and control
it from maybe a custom build tool that you
have, or Grunt.
Another thing that is really nice and available
for you is the plug-in that Ben Schwarz made
for Sublime Text. I am not a Sublime Text
user so I might bumble around this a little
bit. But I wanted to show you what this could
look like.
Actually, let me do this from here.
All right. So here's a typical Sublime project.
And the typical way that you run the built-in
tools, command-shift-P. When you install this
tool, it adds a bower &mdash; can't really change
the font, unfortunately, of that particular
part of Sublime. I don't think so. Nope.
But what it lists there, if you can't see
it, is bower: Install, bower: Configure project
and bower: Discover packages.
And so from here, I can run bower install
and that gives me kind of an interactive search
so I can look for Angular and find that package
and install it right from Sublime. So I don't
even have to hop into the command line, if
I don't want to. Of course, if you have Little
Snitch running, it will ask you every time
but that's okay.
Just from Sublime, I was able to add something
into my bower.json file and it downloaded
it into my components directory where I have
Angular now.
So that's pretty nice. But there is another
tool that this exposes, or links to, rather,
which is Discover Packages. So sindre made
this, sindresorhus on github and Twitter.
This is a search Web site for bower where
you can take a look. And you can do the same
thing, Angular, and get some available metrics
about what matched that search, when it was
last updated, how many forks and stars, a
little bit more information to help you make
a good decision about what piece you want
to add in and discover things.
Currently there is 2,048, so exactly 2K components,
which is fantastic.
Let's look at the Angular stuff just really
quickly. I have a quick demo about what that
could look like, if you aren't a requirejs
fan or if you just like Angular.
So we're making a typical Angular app. Have
our namespace in the HTML, my app. And show
you the basic template of HTML. And we will
go ahead and install that Angular component
that's available.
So add our Angular script into our project.
And then add some basic module codes, so we'll
depend on my app and create a controller.
And this is going to make an itemized list.
So we see the UL up at the top. It is going
to make just a repeatable list element &mdash; or
list item based off of this item list.
But let's say that we want to make this actually
work with markdown instead. And I'm sure that
there's some kind of markdown Angular thing
that's existing out there. So we can search
for Angular and just parse out anything that
mentioned markdown. And we can also use this
Web site here or use Sublime text.
Angular markdown brings up the same thing.
Whatever way you choose to get there, you
can. And so at the end of the day, we install
that Angular markdown directive. And we see
that it installed Showdown. That's what it
requires for the markdown parsing. And then
we have Angular, of course, which is the directive
piece &mdash; or what it depends on to actually
run. We already installed that, so it doesn't
matter.
So now we have our three components that we
need to add which is Angular itself, the markdown
parser, and then the Angular markdown directive.
So we can add that module now as a dependency.
It has already been included as a script tag,
so it is now available. So we can include
it just like we would in a regular app.
Make sure that we specify that this item will
be parsed using that with the btf markdown
down here, the latter part of that li.
And then just add some markdown. So in this
case, on the last item we're just making that
some pretty basic markdown. And what that
looks like &mdash;
this is the full HTML. That got really big.
This was the full HTML that we have now that
was generated. These are our components all
installed. Angular, angular markdown, directive
and showdown. Bower is updated with the two
pieces that we need. And there's it running
those three items through the generator and
it is parsing markdown. So that didn't take
a lot of work to go hunt down these pieces.
Imagine that part where you find out, yes,
there is an Angular director for parsing markdown
and now I need to get showdown. Now we need
to look where they put their built file. You
are well aware that could be on their web
site. That could be in some DIS file in their
GitHub repo or in their source file but you
are not quite sure which one it is. And that
gets complicated and that takes time and that
is a particular barrier of entry to use that
particular plug-in. But that is also time
you don't need to spend. There's also a really
nice component or ability of being able to
work with a directory that's managed by a
tool and that is, if we go back to our step
three here, so I have my Bower.json file.
If I want to see what my app looks like with
a particular piece, I can just install any
version I want. If I want to test, say requirejs3
comes out and I want to test that with my
application, I can just install that using
Bower. And if my whole app just completely
explodes or I find a bug and report it to
requirejs on I install JQuery 2.0.1 and I
find a bug, I can report that bug. I can help
the community. I can help those projects that
I depend on. But then I can just switch back
to the version that I need and it wasn't a
big deal. I didn't have to, like, rename jquery.old.js
and put in the new one. If you have ever done
that &mdash; I know you have &mdash; you don't have
to anymore. So we never had to hunt down Angular.
We were able is to find everything really
easy and most of all the scripts are in a
consistent place. Now, we looked at the JS
demo earlier. I was using components as the
full path. Components weather then weather.js.
You can use &mdash; there's a Grunt contribution
plug-in for that that actually adds those
to your path automatically. So I could have
just had JQuery and weather and it would have
just worked. There's tools out there. Bower
has a lot of pieces to integrate with Rails,
with different node build tools. There's a
lot of community around making it integrate
with whatever word process that you have.
So what's coming up? There's a lot of great
stuff that we looked at but obviously there's
room for improvement. We're not perfect. This
is still a new project. And so some of the
things that we want to do are hosted packages.
We want you to be able to authenticate with
the registration server. We have started working
on this. You could rename a package if you
added one or delete it. You would be able
to push a copy of a built file if you don't
want that maybe in your repository. You can
push that up to us directly. And, of course,
we can give a cached copy. If you don't have
git or you want that even faster, we can just
push the file that you want down, which is
really helpful. Andre, who is the lead developer
for Bower, Marco and him have been working
on a rewrite of Bower to make it faster, to
make it easier for us to work on and add better
features. So this is the quick video he made.
Let's go full screen here. I'll probably pause
it. It's a really short video. So this is
his dependencies list. These are pretty big
pieces. These are a lot of pieces. This is
pretty indicative of a typical real-world
app as far as how many components are there.
So what he has here is on the left is going
to be with the rewrite and then on the right
is the current version. And so those run.
Bower just goes to town getting everything.
So you see on the left it is already much
faster. He was able to get all of that content
in just 8.8 seconds, whereas the current one
is 13. And then if you have cache, which Bower
has, once you've actually done this once and
you've gotten &mdash; most of these repos are using
across different projects, it's now down to
2.3 seconds versus 5.7 on the current version.
And then, you know, that time you are on a
plane and you need to recreate the project
and you know you have all that cached, one
second. So this isn't a big commitment as
far as having a process around getting these
packages. Running, even on the current version,
it's still pretty fast and it's only going
to get faster and it's only going to get better.
And so working this tool into your work flow
not only should make your life easier but
it should do a faster job of hunting down
all these things for you than you possibly
could. As developers, that's the whole point.
Of course, working on the regular stuff, more
docs, less bugs. Unless you want more bugs.
I guess we could put them in. And more packages
and more integration. That's really the biggest
piece of this, is we want to make Bower something
that works with &mdash; that is extendible to work
with any tools and we can just write whatever
middleware, whatever plug-ins to make it work
so you can take advantage of it in the way
that you see fit. We can focus on just getting
packages, getting stuff for you in a sane
way. But we need help with that. We need help
on Bower. We need help with these pieces and
so github.com/bower, all the pieces that we're
working on are there. Bower IRC channel and
freenode, definitely come in. Chat with us
and let us know if you are running into any
problems. We have a Bower Google group and,
that's it. So I think we have &mdash; the timer
was going pretty crazy, so I'm not sure exactly
what it all means for time. But I think I
have time for questions. Anyway.
[ Applause ]
I should note, too, that if you want to, we
have a bunch of Bower stickers and if you
liked the logo, which is pretty new by Dave
Dessandro, a pretty neat logo. If you want
to support that on your laptop or child's
forehead, definitely come up and get a Bower
sticker.
>>> So this is awesome, really awesome. I
haven't used it yet but I definitely would
love to start using this on my projects. So
this kind of is all the client side components
and so on and usually all our projects are
&mdash; have, you know, server side and client
side together. Is there &mdash; I don't know how
to &mdash; is there any sort of integration between
different kinds of service side packaging
systems as well or packages?
>>Dan Heberden: The integration, that's where
we want to make sure that as a developer you
are the one calling the shots. And so a good
demo of this is actually my &mdash; this presentation.
So I hooked up &mdash; which ended up not working
that great because there's a lot of network
connections in here. But I wanted to hook
up my phone so that I could have the next
slide show up on my phone. So I wanted to
use socket.io, and so looking at that, I was,
like, I better use Bower because I'm writing
a talk about Bower. And so if I have my node
modules, I have socket.io, so in this case
I know I need socket.io on the server, so
I just add that to my package.json. And then
Bower search socket, give you a few different
ones available. You can see there's a client
available to get. So it's still going to be
two separate pieces because they will be two
separate libs, but having the ability to hop
between the two really ease easily and have
NPM installed and Bower installed as part
of your process. When you showed Yeoman earlier,
that actually runs both for you as well. Even
if you are building something that scaffolds
an app that you maybe build in often, you
can have that as part of your work flow of
just, okay, here's my server side components,
here's all my client side components. Go.
>>> I guess we can always script if you want
just a single install, get everything from
scratch, whatever script these components
as well.
>>Dan Heberden: Yes, that's why I look at
Yeoman generators or something similar to
do that.
>>> Thanks.
>>> Hi, I had a question. We use Bower at
our company and one thing I noticed is that
when you Bower install something like Bootstrap,
you get, like, 15 LS files and 15 JS files
and it's not built. Is there any way to integrate
with Bower to have it, you know, automatically
build that as soon as I download it? Some
packages actually do have the build files,
you know, in the source. But just looking
for a way to kind of improve that work flow,
I guess.
>>Dan Heberden: Yeah. There's a &mdash; so Bower
won't be the tool that builds that because
you can imagine that might be a make file.
In the case of Bootstrap, it is a make file.
That can be node, whatever. So there needs
to be a way to make that built version available.
Now, the way that Bootstrap does it, they
actually hide it in the docs folder. So, like,
you go into docs, that's where the built JS
and CSS files are. What we have been working
on is, there's a main property inside of Bowers,
a manifest file. So we are working on the
spec to bring that to more light so that the
actual file that you want is not only highlighted
to you, here it is, but even, like, possibly
moved to root or something that makes that
easier. Also, the hosted part will mean, if
you have a complicated build process, you
can publish your built copy if you don't want
in your repo. Like, I like it in the repo,
I think that's a cool thing. Obviously, not
everyone agrees with me. We are working on
that for sure.
>>> Great, thanks.
>>> Can I use my own modules that are not
in the directory, for example, in the Bower
file?
>>Dan Heberden: Yeah, if you want to &mdash; so
if it's something in the corporate environment
you don't have. You don't want to publish
certain things or you have private code, you
can reference any git repository and just
specify the git URL and a tag. So actually
when I was working on &mdash; oops &mdash; on this.
So code mirror is, like, man, I don't want
to have to commit this into project. Of course,
click, I'm writing a talk about Bower, I can
use that. I was just able to point it to the
get repo for code mirror. It just pulled it
for me. So even without someone going through
the work of making their project Bower compatible,
I was still able to just throw it in there
and use that so you can use that and specify
a tag if you wanted to for a specific version
of that.
>>> Thank you.
>>> On the server side, you have the luxury
of, if two modules require the same thing
but have different version requirements, you
can just load them as dependencies of the
dependencies and each one gets called in for
the correct spot. On the client you can't
run JQuery 1.4.2 for one module and 2.0 for
another module. So what's the solution on
the client side for mismatched dependency?
>>Dan Heberden: That will show up on the Bower
LS. But it's going to ultimately be your decision
to mitigate that. Because, like you said,
there's no easy way out. And so that's where
you making the decision of what to do and
which library is going to be the correct one
or will work. We're working on finding out
the best way to do that. Like should our process
stop altogether and say there's a conflict
and you have to resolve this first? Or should
we just carry on and hope that you can figure
it out yourself. We're working on some better
feedback on that. It's still, like, it will
still show you that we have two different
versions and you are going to have to figure
out which one to put in. But that's where,
again, the developer needs to be the decision
maker and Bower doesn't want to be &mdash; doesn't
need to be a tool that forces you into a box
in particular situations because you might
be very well aware, oh, this person just didn't
update their dependency list. I guess that's
it for questions. Thank you very much for
your attention. Come get a sticker, if you
want.
[ Applause ]