>>Ellie Powers: All right. Hi, everybody.
Good morning.
Good morning!
Good morning. Wow, it's amazing to see so
many people out in the morning, and hello
to you back there who waved to me. Thank you.
So I'm Ellie Powers. I'm the product manager
for Google Play developer, so many of you
guys here.
>>Miles Barr: Hi. I'm Miles Barr. I'm the
engineering manager for apps in Google Play.
>>Riccardo Govoni: Hello, I'm Riccardo, tech
lead for the Google Play Developer Console.
>>Ellie Powers: All right. And some of you
saw us earlier this week at I/O, and so what
we're going to be doing today is to give you
even more of what we showed you. So you will
get to see more details on the features that
we announced as well as a couple more new
things.
So let's go back in the past for a second.
Last year, Android Market  &mdash; do you remember
that? It was a recent memory. And Google Play
was brand-new. And all of you who publish
apps on Google Play were using something that
looked like this. This is the old Developer
Console. I hope you've completely forgotten
about it but if you haven't it looked a little
bit like a Web form from 1999.
So Miles and I came on the stage at I/O last
year and said, guys, we've totally heard you.
Your businesses are really taking off and
you need something that's really going to
scale; right? You need some professional tools
to support all the great things that you're
doing now.
And we said, "Don't worry. We've got your
back. We've been working on something great."
It's the new Developer Console.
So back in London where we're all based, we
were excited to see your response. You started
sending us thousands of pieces of feedback.
It just all started pouring in. And many of
you may be wondering, I sent in that feedback
and then what happened? Did anyone read it?
Did it just go into a hole?
So I can tell you, rest assured, your feedback
was read, and I know that because I actually
read every single piece of feedback that you
sent in via the feedback ling at the top of
the new Developer Console.
So I can tell you that, actually, we were
delighted to see that the number one piece
of feedback that came in was, hey, guys, this
new Developer Console, it's a lot better than
the old one.
And so we were relieved that at least we were
going in the right direction.
[ Applause ]
>>Ellie Powers: All right. Thank you! Thank
you so much.
We were absolutely delighted to see that positive
response. But also what started coming in
was a bunch of feature requests. "Hey, this
is great, but." "Could you also do." "How
about this?" "I also need that." "You really
should be doing more."
And we said absolutely. We totally agree with
that. And so that's why we've been rolling
out a ton of new features.
So what we're going to do today for you here
with some great demos is to show you how Google
Play is evolving rapidly. We're rapidly moving
to bring you tons of new features that are
going to grow with your business and help
you support Google Play's enormous audience
around the world.
So let's walk through what we're going to
do today.
So again, we're going to be going into more
detail on what you've already seen and also
seeing new stuff.
We're going to be going through three different
areas. We have publishing your app your way
on Google Play, how you can take control of
publishing in our store, connecting directly
with customers.
Secondly, we're going to be talking about
optimizing your app, how we're giving you
more data so you can deeper into how people
are using your app and improve it. And then,
finally, how you can expand your app globally
to take advantage of Google Play's global
footprint and reach more audiences in new
markets, expanding your business.
So without further ado, we're going to look
at cool new stuff, and Miles Barr is going
to take us through that.
>>Miles Barr: Thanks, Ellie. I want to start
today by talking about how Google Play keeps
you in control of publishing your app. Our
philosophy has always been to put no barriers
between you and your users. When you have
a new version of your app ready, you can push
it out to everyone at the same time.
This can be very daunting, though, as anyone
who has pushed a new app with a serious bug
knows, so we figured we can do better.
So I was happy to announce on Wednesday that
we launched the beta testing and staged rollout
feature in Google Play. This means you can
start testing a new version of your app with
a small group of alpha testers, and when it's
ready, move on to a larger group of beta testers,
and once you're comfortable that your app
is ready for prime time, you can roll out
in stages to the rest of your user base.
This means you can keep your startup's new
apps under wraps. You can try out a major
new UI with just your power users, or you
can even give a preview to the press.
And why is this important? Because we want
to ensure that your users are always happy
with your app.
So let's take a look at how this works.
Here we are in the Developer Console. As you
can see, there are two new tabs, alpha testing
and beta testing. These are essentially the
same thing. They're two targeted groups that
allows you to send a version of your app to
specific set of users. If your user is in
both tests, they will receive the alpha one.
At Google, our philosophy is to test our software
early and often, so whenever a build is ready,
we send it to our team so they can try it
out. So let's switch to the alpha. So we'll
do the same here.
So first we've got our new APK, and what we're
going to do is we're going to target our team,
and we're going to do this with a mailing
list. So Riccardo is entering our team mailing
list here.
Now, when you target a user for a beta test
or an alpha test, they are not automatically
opted in. For them to receive the version,
they need to go to this link here and opt
into the test. And this is available on the
Web and on the phone, and it explains to your
users what being a tester is and they can
opt in. And if at any point they want to opt
out of the test, they can come back to the
same page, opt out and uninstall the test
version of your app.
Now, beta test and alpha test are private.
What this means is until a user opts in to
your test, they'll see no details about the
app on the Play Store.
Similarly, we don't allow reviews of prerelease
versions, so none of the details of your new
app will leak.
We recommend using mailing list or Google+
community to talk to your testers. We do collect
statistics and crash report data on your test
versions so you can track the progress of
how it's going.
So let's say the alpha test has gone great
so we're going to move it to beta. And this
time we want to have a wider set of testers
so instead of a mailing list I'm going to
use a Google+ community.
This community some of our most engaged users.
They love our app. They love testing early
versions and giving us feedback on the new
features.
So Riccardo is going to just let the group
know that we've got a new beta test ready
and they can opt in.
Now, when setting up a beta test, it's important
to get a good representation of your users,
and by this I mean make sure you have a good
mix of devices, people who speak different
languages and people on different carriers.
You want to ensure your app works for everyone
once you publish it.
Okay. So we've got a lot of feedback for our
beta test, we fix some bugs, and this latest
version we're comfortable with, so we want
to get it out to production. I'm feeling pretty
good about it because it's been through so
many rounds of testing, but sometimes a bug
does slip through, and what happens when you
launch it? That means you get a lot of unhappy
users and one-star reviews.
So we're going to be on the safe side here
and we're going to do a stage rollout. So
rather than choosing everyone, we're going
to start with about 10% of our users.
At this point users can now review your app
so you can see the feedback of how it's doing.
And if there's a problem, you can stop the
rollout, create a fix, and then we'll push
that fixed version to that same original 10%
of users.
>>Riccardo Govoni: Shall we go to everybody?
>>Miles Barr: Hmm?
>>Miles Barr: Yep, let's go to everyone.
All right. And you can also use this feature
to control traffic to your back-ends. We know
sometimes when you release a new version of
your app, the traffic patterns differ. So
by just looking at 10%, making sure your back-end
servers can handle the load, you can be sure
once you push it to everyone, your app will
work great.
Okay. Let's hear about how someone has been
using beta testing. Wattpad is a great app
that gives you access to over 10 million free
books and short stories. They have been beta
testing since the beginning and they do this
by having two different apps in the Play Store,
the beta version and live one. The beta version
they push every week and the live one about
once a month. Each feature they add to their
app goes through three to four rounds of beta
testing, so they get lots of feedback and
they decide if it makes the cut and should
go to the multi-release.
A great example of this is the new UI you
see up here. They recently changed how users'
books appear in their library. This is quite
a big change. They wanted to see how users
react to it. Unsurprisingly, they found that
some users got it, some didn't. There was
a bit of confusion. So before they launched
it, they added a tutorial section explaining
what the change was and of how to find your
books. This led to a seamless rollout to the
rest of their users.
Previously, while they have been beta testing
before we launched our feature, this meant
that they had to create two listings and also
manage their testers outside of Google Play.
With the launch of today's feature, you can
retain store listing and also use Google tools
like Google groups and Google+ communities
to manage your testers.
All right. Wattpad has a huge beta testing
community of 25,000 users but they've told
us that they've seen benefits back when they
only had ten users. This gave them access
to a wider range of devices than their testing
in-house and it also meant they got early
testing from real users. So if you only get
one star again, you know you haven't been
beta testing.
All right. Now I want to talk to you about
tablets.
There are over 900 million Android devices
activated now, and a growing part of that
is tablets.
On androiddeveloper.com, we now show you the
proportion of devices by screen size and screen
density. Tablets have large and extra large
screens, so you can get a good idea of how
many tablets are out there.
Also on developer.android.com we've launched
the tablet app called a checklist. This explains
Google's criteria of what makes a good tablet
app and gives you advice on how to optimize
your app for tablets. If you haven't seen
this already, please go to developer.android.com
and check it out.
Also, in the Developer Console, here in the
optimization tip section, we automatically
scan an app against the checklist to see how
you're doing. If there's anything which your
app doesn't meet, we explain it and tell you
how to fix it.
So it's important to follow these tips so
you create a great tablet experience for your
users.
Also, once you created a great new tablet
UI, nice multi-pane using the fragments API,
you want to show it off. So last month in
the Play Store we gave you the ability to
upload tablet screen shots so you can show
how your app will look on a seven-inch and
ten-inch tablet.
When a user goes to the Play Store on a tablet,
they'll see the tablet screen shots first,
and on the phone, they'll see the phone ones.
On Wednesday we announced that the top lists
on tablets will be able to be filtered down
so users will only see those apps designed
specifically for tablets.
[ Applause ]
>>Miles Barr: Thanks.
So make sure you follow all these guidelines
so your app doesn't get left behind.
So let's take a look at a great tablet app.
I'm sure you've heard of Evernote. If you
haven't, it's an app that lets you collect
notes, record Web pages, everything, and keeps
you  &mdash; syncs across all your devices.
Evernote has been creating a tablet app ever
since we launched Honeycomb back in 2011.
They created a beautiful multi-pane UI and
spent a lot of hard work on their tablet experience.
It's all this hard work that's kept them a
consistent editor's choice in Google Play.
And it's not just a hit with us. It's also
a hit with their users. As you can see here,
the second most popular device is a Nexus
7, a tablet.
Evernote has thought long and hard about what
makes a good tablet experience. If I'm on
the phone, their users want to take  &mdash; call
it a Quick Note, will maybe pull up a piece
of information, but on a tablet they spend
a lot more time organizing and planning and
getting real work done.
Here is what the V.P. of product had to say.
By focusing on creating a great tablet experience,
they created more engaged users, and these
users have gone on to become paid subscribers
of Evernote.
All right. Now I want to talk about a feature
that's coming later this summer. A lot of
you have sort of told us you want to give
access to the console to a lot of more people
in your company. In fact if you were in the
Fireside Chat yesterday, a lot of you asked
for finer grain controls to the Developer
Console. So late this summer we'll be releasing
several new permissions in the Play Store
allowing you to control exactly what each
of your users can do. And these permissions
can also be set on a per-application basis.
So if you ever wanted to give someone in your
company access to your stats but make sure
they don't mess around with your APKs, you'll
soon be able to do that so please stay tuned.
Last year here at I/O, we announced the pilot
to our reply to reviews feature. This allowed
you as a developer to reply directly to your
users.
I'm happy to say after lots of rounds of testing
and tweaking we've now made this available
to every single developer on Google Play.
[ Applause ]
>>Miles Barr: It gives you a direct channel
to your users, so if you haven't started using
this already please read up on our policies
and guidelines and start replying now.
Now I'm going to tell you how one developer
has been using this feature.
TextPlus is an app that lets you chat with
your friends all around the world through
free SMS's and cheaper calls. TextPlus has
gone all in on replying to reviews. Everyone
on their team takes part in this, from the
engineers, the product managers, and of course
their customer support team.
Every day, twice a day they look to see if
they have any new reviews and reply directly
to them. By doing this they've really connected
to their users and found out where their biggest
pain points are.
For each negative review they try to turn
around that user's experience by giving them
advice and pointers to more help. If they
succeed those users typically change their
review to a positive one.
But they don't stop just there. For their
positive reviews, the five-star reviews, they
find these reviews are their most engaged
users, their biggest advocates to tell other
people about the app.
They use the reply-to-review feature to speak
directly to them to get their opinions on
new features and what else they want to see
in this app.
By focusing on the user and having this attentive
customer support, the newer versions of TextPlus
have a higher average higher rating in the
store than the previous versions did.
Here's what they had to say about it.
They have used this direct line to the users
to prioritize a what features they can focus
on and now they have happier users and higher
scores within the store.
Now I'm going to hand over to Riccardo, our
tech lead, to tell you more about data.
>>Riccardo Govoni: Thanks, Miles. Hello, everybody.
So Miles showed you how you have more control
on the way you deploy your app to your users
and how you present it to them. Now I want
to shift your attention to data. I want to
show you how Developer Console helps you make
informed decisions about your app and your
business and helps you figure out what is
the next most important thing to focus on.
Over the course of the last year, we expanded
the amount of data that we make available
in Developer Console. I think you're familiar
with the standard metrics, installs and uninstalls,
per user, per device, divided across six different
dimensions, country, SDK version, application
version, language and more. But in the past
few months we rolled out a few more metrics,
and we announced a couple, even a couple of
these were given in the keynote, so let me
focus on them for a second.
One I want to talk about now is rating stats.
Rating stats show you how the users' star
rating for your application changed over time.
This is the metric you want to look at when
you want to see whether the new version of
your application that you just rolled out
is getting the same good user reviews, good
user satisfaction compared to the previous
version. We offer this in two variants. So
you have the cumulative rating. This is the
overall aggregated rating over the lifetime
of your application. This is good for the
long-term view, when you want to review what
you did historically in the past and the decision
that you made at the time.
Another one that we offer is the daily average
rating. This is the aggregated over all daily
ratings over the lifetime of your app and
this is good for the short-term view, when
you want to spot problems early on.
I want to mention a couple of cases where
this is particularly useful. One is reply
to reviews.
So you can use this metric to identify segments
of your user base where customer satisfaction
is not as good as you would expect. And from
that, you can then jump to reply to reviews,
as Miles just described, and provide dedicated
customer support exactly to those users.
On the other side it works the other way around
as well. If you're spending a lot of time
doing customer support and offering replies
to your users, then you might want to use
this metric to verify the effectiveness of
what you've done and see that you are actually
achieving the results that you are expecting.
Another feature in which this is particularly
useful is stage rollouts. Unlike offline beta
where a user cannot leave reviews or ratings,
during stage rollout users will able to rate
and review your app. And that means when you
are at 5% of a stage rollout, if you have
a brand-new application out there, you're
on the edge of your chair, you want to make
sure everything is fine, you might want to
use this metric to see whether everything
is doing as well as you expect.
In this example we rolled out a new version
of our application in mid-April, the orange
line, but it never really caught up with the
baseline, which is the green line. So this
is maybe the point where you want to pause
your stage rollout and decide what to do.
Like all the other metrics that we have, if
the breakdown by the top ten values, like
the top ten countries, or et cetera, is not
enough, obviously you can always export as
a SVC and you get the full data payload so
you can integrate it with your tools.
Another thing we want to talk about is filtering
crash reports because we now allow you to
filter crash reports by application version,
since a few weeks. Again, now that we have
Beta testing, this is extremely useful because
it means you can look at the crash reports
that are coming only from your alpha version,
maybe it was a little more crashy, and decide
what to do. During a stage rollout, we keep
collecting crash reports so you can see and
decide what to do for your stage rollout,
whether to pause it or continue it based on
the amount of crashes you are getting.
So now everything is fine. Users are happy.
You're not getting any crashes. Unicorns and
rainbows all over the place. It's time to
talk about money. I want to talk about the
new page that we launched on Wednesday which
is revenue charts.
I always found it a bit annoying that just
to figure out how much money you made yesterday
you had to go to Developer Console, download
the SVC report, put in a graphic in a spreadsheet
program, aggregate everything just to see
how much money you made yesterday and I think
that was just nonsense and so we decided to
fix it and starting Wednesday you have this
new page. How all the revenue for your app
changed over time. Aggregated daily, you can
divide it or inspect it by country and by
source of revenue, say by applications, revenue
generated from application sales, in in-app
products or subscriptions.
I think this is great to get an overview of
how your application is doing at a glance.
You can come here every day, look at how much
money you made yesterday.
And it lets you also do some sort of analysis.
You can, you know, look at whether you are
ahead of your company targets or not, whether
some countries are performing as well as you
would expect. But I also know that many of
you want to integrate this data with your
own custom financial reporting tools and data
pipelines.
So another thing that we're doing in the coming
few weeks is that all the financial reporting
from the Google Play Developer Console will
be available in Google Cloud Storage. What
that means is that by using the utilities
provided by Google Cloud Storage, like GSU2,
you will be able to have programmatic access
to your financial reporting, to your financial
data so you can integrate it with your own
data pipelines.
The other benefit of this is that thanks to
the new permission model, granular permissions
that Miles just described, you will be able
to set up a dedicated account that will only
have access to financial data, and only be
used for accessing financial data in cloud
storage. And that account will not be able
to mash up with your APK configuration or
something. So you can separate roles there.
Okay. Let's talk about referral tracking and
usage.
So another thing I would like all of you to
have is one place, one single place, where
you can see all the data that pertains and
is about your application. And I know that
many of you are using Google Analytics to
track user engagement and user interaction
with your application. But so far, the experience
was fragmented. You had to go to the developer
console to see device and install metrics.
You had to go to Google Analytics to see activity
and user engagement. And soon, so in the coming
few weeks, you will be able to link together
Google Analytics and Google Play Developer
Console. And what that means is that once
linked together in the Google Play Developer
Console  &mdash; sorry, in Google Analytics, you
will have access to additional new metrics.
In particular, you will be able to see how
many views, downloads, and installs your marketing
campaigns triggered on Google Play.
And this is really good, because it gives
you a better view of the conversion funnel.
You can see much more details about how your
users discover your app and then want to install
your app and then became daily active users.
This integration goes both ways. So you will
have access to engagement metrics directly
from the play developer console. So next to
installs and other metrics, you will also
see engagement, like, number of active users.
Okay. So a few more things about optimization
tips.
So Miles spent a few minutes talking about
how you can use the optimization tips section
to learn whether your app is well designed
for tablets, whether it meets the quality
checklist requirements, and et cetera.
But I have bigger plans for the optimization
tips section. I want that to become the place
where you go to discover personalized recommendations
and insights that are specific to your app
and your context.
So starting from a few days ago, from Wednesday,
you now have additional tips present in that
section, what we call them localization tips.
They help you how to reach a broader audience
and how to expand your app to multiple countries.
When you decide it's time to go global, you
know, you have to do a number of things. You
have to localize your APK, you have to then
localize your store listings. You may even
want to consider localizing your screen shots,
because for some markets, that's really important.
And most importantly, you have to decide which
countries to focus on first, where should
I go first.
So now in the optimization tips sections,
you will get these localization insights that
will guide you in the process. They will tell
you whether you're missing anything. Maybe
you localized your APK, but you forgot to
localize your listing. And we'll also help
you identify opportunities. They, for example,
will tell you, you may have a lot of users
from Russia. Even though you never localized
your app there, that's a great opportunity
that you should go into.
Which brings me to the next topic, which is
reaching Play global audience.
When you decide to go  &mdash; oops, too bad. When
you decide to go global, the first and most
important thing that you want to do is localize
your application contents. And many developers
are already doing that and expanding into
new markets.
And as a non-native English speaker, as some
of you may have guessed from my funny accent
&mdash; I'm Italian  &mdash; I think one of the most
important things is to make sure that your
app is available to as many users in as many
countries and as many languages as possible,
but still providing the same high-quality
experience that you would provide to users
who speak your own language.
And we announced on Wednesday that now from
the Google Play Developer Console, you have
access to professional translations in collaboration
with the Google Translation Manager team.
Let me show you how this works.
So in the APK screen, at the very bottom,
there will be the recently used section, which
is called the app translation that you can
use to start to request a professional translation.
Just click the button, starts a wizard that
will guide you through the process. You pick
a project name. That is just for your convenience.
Some of you may have multiple projects going
on at any same time. Pick the version  &mdash; sorry,
the language you're translating from. You
then upload the strings. If you're using the
Android developer tools, you can use that
directly from the Eclipse plug-in. Otherwise,
you can just upload the XML files.
Once that's done, you wait. Then you go, you
pick the languages you want to translate into.
I'm going to pick, I don't know, Japanese
and Korean. Those are just two markets that
you cannot be outside of.
You pick the service level. The service level
basically decides how many users, how many
people are actually looking at your strings
and contributing to the translation in a translation
company you pick. You get an idea of the price.
You choose the translation company you want
to use. You get an indication of how long
it's going to take and how much it's going
to cost. Obviously, the cost of the translation
depends on how many words you have in your
strings file.
And then you get a confirmation page where
you can reorder and get started with your
translation.
The moment you confirm that, the translation
company will start right away translating
your strings. And from the developer console,
you will be able to check progress. You will
be able to see how far (indiscernible) the
translation is in translating all your content.
While they're doing their work, you will be
able to communicate with them, answer any
questions that might arise, troubleshooting,
these kind of things. And then once all the
strings are done, you will be able to  &mdash; again,
from the developer console  &mdash; download them,
put them into your APK, pack everything, and
publish.
And this feature is rolling out in private
beta, just like we did for the developer console
itself last year, which means that if you
go to the APK page right now, you will see
a sign-up form where you can see  &mdash; where
you can leave your contact details. And then
we will shortly start rolling this out to
everybody.
I want to reinforce again the importance of
reaching a global audience. I want to speak
for a few seconds about Gameloft. I think
all of you know who Gameloft is. They are
a successful games company. They are based
in Europe. They realized very early the importance
of targeting multiple languages and multiple
locales. They're currently available to 12
languages: English, German, Italian, French,
Chinese, Japanese, and a few other European
and Asian languages. And they have (indiscernible)
experiences they want to share with you. One
is when they wanted to localize Ice Age Village
to Russian. So Ice Age Village has a user
base of 10 million users. And they discovered
that 14% of those users are actually Russian
users. That's the second biggest market after
English users.
Another case that they had is when they decided
to localize My Little Pony to Turkish. As
part of a global application update, they
had the Turkish localization. And they discovered
very interesting figures. So the number of
active users in Turkey jumped up by 95% compared
to 20 to 25% that did in other countries.
And that was thanks to the presence of localized
content rather than just a simple application
update.
The revenue jumped up by 600% in Turkey. And
the revenue per daily active users jumped
up by 300%.
Another tip that you might want to use that
I took advantage of, they used local holidays
and other local knowledge to make promotions
and sales, like they did, for example, for
the Chinese New Year.
So let me stress it one more time: Think global.
Always aim to target a really global audience
in multiple countries and multiple languages.
I hope that this feature that we just announced
will help you do that easily. And if you want
to learn more, there's a session at noon,
I think, which is Building Android Apps for
a Global Audience, where you can learn more
on how this translation process works and
the details behind that.
Having said that, let me go back to Ellie.
>>Ellie Powers: All right. Thanks, Riccardo.
Today, we've given you an overview of everything
we're bringing you to try to help you grow
your businesses across these three areas,
first, publishing your app, having more control
over it, connecting directly with your user
base. Secondly, gaining insight into your
users and what they're doing with your app.
And then expanding your app to grow your user
base into new markets.
So because there was a lot of stuff, we're
going to give you a quick summary of everything
that's new.
So, first of all, we have, of course, beta
testing and staged rollouts, which allows
you to get user feedback early in the process
and respond to it.
Secondly, we're giving you summaries and overviews
of user ratings and your revenues so that
you can check those stats at your fingertips
very easily.
Next, we're giving you tablet-specific screen
shots so you can show off your awesome tablet
layouts. And if your app isn't designed for
tablets yet, we give you optimization tips
to help you make it that way.
We're also helping you identify how to localize
your app and where you should go first with
new localization tips.
We also announced that everyone can now reply
to reviews.
But stay tuned, because there's a lot more
coming this summer. So we have three new areas
where you should watch for some announcements
on the Android Developers Blog in the future.
First of all, we're going to be having those
extra access controls so you can grant more
people access to the developer console without
getting worried. We're also adding new Google
Analytics integration figures. So these were
the campaign referral tracking flows, that
conversion funnel, and also seeing your Google
Analytics usage data directly in the developer
console.
And, finally, if you're interested in translating
your app with our new App Translation Service,
which is being offered in partnership with
our internationalization team, sign up today
in the developer console. It's at the bottom
of the APK page if you're looking for it.
Okay. So as I said at the beginning, everything
that we're doing is with you, Google Play
developers, in mind. And we need to keep getting
your feedback in order to plan our next 12
months and even farther in the future.
We hope you'll join us for office hours today
following this session. We hope that you also
rush right back after that, because at 12:00,
there's a very important session on monetization.
And everyone is looking for more information
about money.
So if you're watching this session online
and you missed the office hours, you want
to make sure that you're following Android
developers on Google+, because that's the
best place to go to see new announcements
about what's happening in the world of Android
development. You can watch Hangouts. We always
post our blog post there as well. And we go
and look for your feedback about what you're
looking to see on Google Play.
So that's it. And the next thing we're going
to do now is start by taking some questions.
We have about eight minutes left. So if you'd
like to come to the microphone at the front,
or I think there may be possibly one there
as well, that will be great. We'll alternate
between the two microphones.
You in the red hat at the front, what would
you like to ask?
>>> Hi, Chuck Grove from AWeber Communications.
I actually have two really quick questions.
I had a lot more, but I narrowed it down to
two. So with the new alpha/beta production
system for launching a new version, is there
still a concept of draft APKs? And if so,
how does that relate to testing in-app billing?
>>Ellie Powers: Great question.
>>Miles Barr: Can I take this one? Yes?
When you go to the advanced mode part of the
tab, you can upload draft APKs. So that's
sort of still separate from alpha and beta
testing. You can imagine the alpha and beta
tabs is exactly the same as production. And
the drafts are shared across all three sections.
Correct?
>>Riccardo Govoni: Yep.
>>Miles Barr: So they will have access to
in-app billing for testing purposes.
>>Riccardo Govoni: So specific for in-app
billing, I think we still have a few improvements
to do. But from the in-app billing sandbox
that was announced in these days, you can
both use the tester section and the developer
profile to decide testers that will have access,
for example, before in-app billing experience
without a link to actually pay. Or you can
use beta testing and then side loading that
APK, for example, to do fake purchases.
>>> Okay. Thank you.
And then my other question was about the staged
rollouts for the actual listing. If you want
to add some new screen shots, new description,
things like that, if you're doing a staged
rollout, is only the people who are getting
the update going to see the new listing or
is everyone going to see it?
>>Riccardo Govoni: No. At the moment, there's
just still one listing. So you may want to
be  &mdash; you want to pay attention to that for
the moment, for the time being. So if you
put something in your store listing, for example,
a brand-new feature, and you're still rolled
out only to 5% of the users, you know, it
may be  &mdash; you have to communicate it publicly.
Maybe you say to say that we are rolling a
new version, and that's the feature that they're
getting and they will be getting over the
next few days.
>>> So you say "for the time being." That
makes me hopeful about what's to company.
>>Riccardo Govoni: Yes.
>>Ellie Powers: Always looking for feedback.
In the back, please.
>>> Hi. My name is Manford (saying name).
I have an interest in automating the whole
process of the deployment, how we're staging
and deployment.
Is there some sort of, like, plan towards
being allowed to, like, integrate on a continuous
integration server to automatically, as part
of, say, a nightly build with QA tests that
are automated, push it out to a staged environment
automatically? I mean, at the moment, I'm
doing with Selenium, but that's a hack; right?
So is there some sort of plan to, like, have
an API maybe so it could even be integrated
in build tools?
>>Ellie Powers: Would you like  &mdash;
[ Applause ]
>>Ellie Powers: Yeah! All right. We totally
heard you. This has been a super popular developer
request; right? Everyone's got their own system,
and we're really excited with the beta testing
that more and more people want to be pushing
their APKs even more often.
So I guess, you know, we won't say too much
about the future. But we definitely will say
that we've heard that, we're thinking about
it, and, you know, as soon as we have anything
to share, we'll definitely let you know. But
we definitely hear you on that one. That's
a very common request that we get.
>>> Thank you.
>>> So in the Play Store, you guys added the
design for tablets feature because you recognize
that phones and tablets are fundamentally
different in their apps.
With more smart Glass products coming out,
is that going to be extensible to other types
of products? And if one were to manufacture
such a product, how would they engage with
you guys to make sure that that feature would
happen and set the criterias and all that
kind of stuff?
>>Ellie Powers: All right. Take this one?
>>Miles Barr: It's a good one.
So right now we're only sort of focusing on
tablets. But we're aware, you know, within
our own team  &mdash; well, our team and externally,
lots of different form factors that are coming
out. So, you know, when you think of things
like Google TV, it's something we consider.
I think we want to wait for a particular device
class to sort of take off or begin to get
a foothold before we change the store. But
definitely other form factors is something
we would consider.
>>> Okay. Thank you.
>>Ellie Powers: All right.
>>> I have a question about the device distribution
of my app in the Play Store.
So when I see, like, the top ten devices where
my app is doing good. But what are the top
ten devices on an aggregated level in the
Play Store? That I don't know. And it might
be the case that the top app  &mdash; device on
my app might be fifth in the global stack
ranking and I might be leaving a lot of money
on the table because my app really doesn't
do well on the top devices on a global ranking.
Is there any way I can get access to that
data?
>>Miles Barr: So short answer, no. But the
aim is that you shouldn't be focusing on particular
types of devices. You should be making sure
your app works across all devices, you know,
in the same great experience. So don't worry
too much about specific devices. Try, you
know, to use a beta testing feature. Try to
reach more users on different devices to make
sure it works well.
You know, if you're doing some really sort
of cutting-edge stuff, we've seen people,
you know, really push the boundaries of 3D,
and sometimes that causes problems. You know,
you can look at the crash reports section
in particular to find out if there's a problem
device and how best to fix on it.
But definitely don't try to optimize your
app for a specific set of devices. You know,
make sure it's a great experience for everyone.
>>> Thank you.
>>> John (saying name) with RadarNow! USNaviguide.
I have some APKs in my developer console that
are years old and essentially abandoned. And
now with the rollout of the beta feature,
I'm going to have all these beta versions
of our apps stuck out there. Is there going
to be a feature to archive or delete, you
know, old and abandoned APKs?
>>Ellie Powers: Yeah, this is also a very
popular request. I saw some applause over
there.
So it depends. So right now, many of you may
not know this, but if you have not published
an app, you can delete it today. Yeah.
So if you go to the developer console, on
the right-hand side, there's a little, I don't
know, gray button, and you can select "delete."
>>> Well, these are, like, apps that  &mdash;
>>Ellie Powers: I know. If you've published
them, I totally hear you on that. I see a
lot of feedback. It's definitely in the top
ten things that we're seeing coming in with
the feedback. So we hear you on that.
I guess with the alpha and beta, just to be
really clear, those are in the same store
listing, so it's not going to litter up your
app page anymore. But we definitely hear folks
who have apps that they don't work on anymore,
and they kind of want to hide that. So we're
definitely looking into that possibility.
>>> Well, I have beta versions for testing.
And now  &mdash;
>>Ellie Powers: Okay. With different package
names.
>>> Yes. Yeah.
>>Ellie Powers: Okay. I see. Yeah, we have
definitely heard that. I guess we're not announcing
any changes today that are happening there.
But we've definitely heard that as a top ten
request.
>>> Thanks very much.
>>Riccardo Govoni: Is that just something
that you would like to hide from the applications
list?
>>> Yeah. It would be okay if we could just
archive them so they're not sticking there
right in our face every time we go in. You
know, I mean, sometimes also it would be good
to order, be able to order the list so that
the ones that we're using and that are popular
at the top instead of, I don't know exactly,
you might have it alphabetically now or something.
>>Miles Barr: I think it's alphabet, yeah.
>>> But archiving, just archive, you know,
hide or something.
>>Ellie Powers: Yeah, a lot of folks have
wanted to hide the unpublished ones, like,
once they're not using it anymore, to hide
them. So we definitely have heard that one.
>>> Great. Thanks very much.
Oh, I love the comments thing, by the way.
I've had it for a year. It's great.
>>Ellie Powers: Oh, yeah? Awesome. I'm glad.
The back.
>>> Hi. My question is about staged rollouts
and how do you determine which percentage
of users is it? And is it the same percentage
of users each time or is it different? So
when you release new versions of the app,
is it always going to be that same 10% that
you're going to be  &mdash;
>>Riccardo Govoni: So  &mdash;
>>Miles Barr: So it's random per staged rollout.
So by that, so when you're rolling out a new
version, we sort of have a different random
seed to select which 10%. But we keep that
seed during that rollout process. So if you
don't want to push that out to 100%, you want
to place it in another APK. Those original
10% will get the update.
>>> So you can have, then, 2  &mdash; like, you
can have a 2.0 to everyone, a 2.1 to 10%,
and a then 2.2 to a different 10%? Is that
possible?
>>Miles Barr: No. There's only one staged
rollout at any time.
>>Riccardo Govoni: So anytime you do a staged
rollout, we pick a different part of the population.
So, you know, it's not the same guys that
get the same testing APK stack. But during
a staged rollout, if you decide that the particular
APK needs changing, then you can change it
and the same group of users will receive that.
>>> Okay. Great. Thank you.
>>Miles Barr: And also, to clarify, staged
rollouts, not for testing.
>>> Yeah. Sorry.
>>> Okay.
>>Miles Barr: Only staged rollout when you're
ready for everyone to get it.
>>Ellie Powers: All right. So it looks like
we basically have five seconds left. But don't
worry. I still see some folks wanting to ask
questions. We're just going to head back to
office hours. And don't forget that there's
a monetization section here in an hour, or
in  &mdash;
[ Applause ]