[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BETTS: Good morning,
everyone.
Welcome to Edge.
If you're not in your seat,
can you find a seat?
And we'll make a start.
My name is Andrew Betts.
I'm from "The Financial
Times," which is a
distinctively pink financial
newspaper.
And this is Edge Conf.
We have Wi-Fi.
That's the most important
thing.
So probably most of you have
discovered it already.
It's GoogleGuest, you don't
need a password.
And I have a few other
announcements that I need to
make before we make a start.
So first of all, Edge is
quite an experiment.
And things may go wrong.
In fact, about seven things
have gone wrong already.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDREW BETTS: So I'm just going
to give you a rundown of
the thinking that went behind
the design of the debate
format and how we're expecting
the even to run.
So each session's
an hour long.
We start with a 10-minute
opening talk.
We have primary questions for
the debate that we've
preselected from a Google
Moderator, or which have been
composed by the moderators
of the sessions.
And those have been seated
into the audience.
So the people in the audience
who are asking questions
should know who they are.
We have around 7-10 minutes
of debate on each of those
primary questions.
And we're looking for
interventions from everyone.
So if you have a point to make,
then jump in an make it,
and make your voice heard.
It should be on topic.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDREW BETTS: Yes.
Don't just wax lyrical
about anything.
So if you have a point to make
that's on the topic of the
primary question, then jump
into the debate and
participate.
Tips.
If you think you have seven
points to make, choose the
most important one.
Because we don't have time
to hear all of them.
And you don't need to introduce
yourself, because we
have this tool, which Wesley
Hales from Apigee has created,
and which we're assured will
be working perfectly today.
Which will enable everyone to
requests speaking time.
So at the beginning of every
session, you'll see a URL on
the screen.
Tap that into your smartphone,
and you'll see a remote on
your smartphone that allows you
to request speaking time.
So you can say, I want to
speak in the debate.
You'll come up on the screen.
The moderator will be able to
then call you to say what you
want to say.
30 seconds is good.
A minute is probably
pushing it.
So try and keep it short.
And keep it on topic.
This is the schedule
for the day.
So we're starting with
Responsive Images.
We've got Rendering Performance,
Third Party
Scripts, Real Time Data.
We're breaking for
lunch at 1:15.
And lunch will be in this
room I believe.
Offline, Legacy Clients, and
we finish up with Payments.
Then after Payments, we have
dinner, which will be upstairs
in The Canteen.
And then we go to the party.
We have a hub page,
EdgeConf.com/hub.
If you go to that on your phone,
you'll get all the
links to the session remotes.
So you can get an easy link
rather than having to see the
URL at the beginning of every
session, you can get the links
directly from that page.
There's also a link on that
page to our feedback form.
And it's really important for
us, particularly as we're
trying loads of new
things today, that
everyone gives us feedback.
So do please fill that form
in some point towards
the end of the day.
Here are the people who you need
to see thank for today.
I'm the curator of the event,
so I chose all the speakers
and invited them to be here.
Pete LePage from Google
is here in the room.
Or is he having a heart
attack somewhere?
Yes, there he is.
Tim Davenport, my colleague
at FT Labs.
He's back in London.
Has been sorting out delicate
logistics for us.
Vivian Cromwell, who should
be here somewhere.
Is she here?
Not here yet.
She's been liaising with a lot
of Google people for us.
Jen Bouchard from Facebook,
who's not here but is
frantically organizing our
afterparty this evening.
Wesley Hales from Apigee.
He has put a phenomenal amount
of work into creating the
moderation tool that you'll
be using today.
And he is really keen to hear
from anyone who has
trouble using it.
So where are you?
Put your hand up.
He's right over there.
So if you can't make it work,
then go and see him.
Also, if you can't make it
work, don't feel like you
can't just put your hand up.
Just get involved
any way you can.
And Dave Stanton from Pixelbots,
who designed the
Edge Conf website.
So the organizations
involved today.
FT Labs.
We created and curated
the event.
Google Chrome, in providing this
amazing venue and doing
all the hosting for us.
Facebook, organizing
our afterparty.
And we also would like to thank
Akamai and Adobe for
sponsoring a couple
of our sessions.
So important stuff.
We have some fabulous prizes,
mostly to encourage you all to
submit feedback.
But also for the most inspired
intervention.
So we want to hear people making
really good points
about new use cases, new
problems, new solutions that
they have which maybe
we don't know about.
And it's that kind of thing that
we really want to hear
and which we'll be giving
prizes for.
And we also gave everyone a
raffle ticket when they came
in, so there will be a
random draw as well.
And those fabulous prizes
are Chromebook Pixels.
Whoo!
[LAUGHTER]
STEVE THAIR: Let's do
that one again.
ANDREW BETTS: Woo!
STEVE THAIR: Chromebook Pixels!
Woo.
WHOLE AUDIENCE: Woo!
ANDREW BETTS: Steve, you're far
better at this than I am.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDREW BETTS: So you can
look forward to that.
And, of course part of the
reason we're all here today is
to support Girls Who Code, which
is a fabulous charity
based here in New York City
that promotes women in
technology and teaching
girls to program.
And I think that's an objective
we can all get behind.
So thank you very much for your
contributions already and
the contributions that you'll
make today to that cause.
So without further ado,
our first session
is Responsive Images.
And the moderator
for this session
will be Marcos Caceres?
Is that right?
Yes!
Marcos Caceres from Mozilla.
So Marcos, come up and make
your introductions.
[APPLAUSE]
MARCOS CACERES: I'm
already on.
And I didn't touch anything.
So come on up, folks, and
I'll introduce you here.
So take a seat.
This is Yoav Weiss.
I'll try to keep everything
very brief as we get
established.
So Yoav's been doing quite a
lot of work with responsive
images of late.
He's heavily involved
in the Responsive
Images Community Group.
And we have Peter Miller.
So Peter Miller's
our developer.
Works on a lot of concert-heavy
websites,
image-heavy websites.
So great experience.
Ann Robson writes.
Also works for &mdash;
ANN ROBSON: Yammer.
MARCOS CACERES: Yammer &mdash;
sorry, I forgot.
Ann has fantastic stuff
about web performance.
Has some great ideas about how
we can address some of the
responsive images problems
using progressive jpegs.
Estelle Weyl.
Has everyone heard of the
clown car technique?
The creator.
So we're going to hopefully talk
a little bit about that.
And John Mellor works
at Google.
And John Mellor's probably the
only person on Earth who can
tell you the difference between
a device pixel, a real
pixel, a CSS pixel, and all
sorts of other pixels.
So he can do it all
in his head.
It's pretty crazy.
So first up we have Yoav,
who's going to give a 10
minute talk, basically outlining
what the current
solutions are that we've been
basically discussing for the
last two years.
Trying to come up
with a solution
for responsive images.
Take it away.
We'll swap seats.
YOAV WEISS: So hi.
As Marcos said, I'm
Yoav Weiss.
I'm here to talk about
responsive images.
I'll try to sum up two
years of discussions
into 10 minutes talk.
So bear with me.
So first, in the mid-2000s,
all we had
was mobile-only sites.
They were kind of lame, with
very slim content, highly
optimized images.
It got a little better
with the iPhone.
But it wasn't that hot.
Then responsive web design
became a thing.
Which was very cool.
One code base to
rule them all.
You can serve all the devices
through a single site.
But the problem is, it
was kind of slow.
It became a synonym to
slow mobile website.
Which is a problem.
So the reason is that most
sites just serve the same
resources to both mobile
and desktop.
And most of that
data is images.
So there are a lot of
savings to be made.
I wrote a utility, which
Tim Kadlec runs.
Tim Kadlec is a developer.
Sorry for name-dropping.
But basically, we saw that up
to 72% of the image data can
be saved for some
of the viewports
in some of the cases.
So there's a lot of savings
to be made.
And the retina only makes things
worse, because the gap
between the smallest viewport,
smallest images you want to
send and the highest resolution
images you want to
send is getting bigger.
With most devs owning retina
devices, most devs are sending
high-resolution images
to all devices.
So this is the responsive images
problem which we like
to divide into two
major use cases.
The first one is resolution
switching.
Serving different dimension
images to different devices.
The images are the same images,
same proportions.
They're not cropped.
But basically, the quality
is different.
This is one example of that.
And it can be further divided
into DPR switching, serving
retina images only to retina
devices, and viewport
switching, which is adapting
the image dimensions to the
actual display, to the size in
which they will be displayed.
Then the other major use
case is art direction.
Basically, it's content
optimization without wasting
too many bytes.
It's matching the images
to the layout in a
way that makes sense.
So either a crop or different
proportions or something that
works according to the actual
responsive break points.
From a survey we ran, a lot of
developers are already doing
that using hacks.
So this is a major use case.
So we've talked about
the problem.
Let's talk about
the solutions.
There are several proposed
standard solutions.
There's a Source Set attribute,
Picture element,
Client Hints header.
And I put a question mark in
because it's not really a
standard solution.
This is just a proposal
at the moment.
But the responsive
image container.
I'll talk about each
one in detail.
So Source Set.
Basically, it's the same old
image tag, now with a new
attribute that can include
multiple resources according
to the DPR and the viewport.
It's a slightly controversial
statement, but it addresses,
mainly, the resolution switching
case and much less
the art direction case.
Some people disagree.
The current implementation.
Source Set is currently
implemented in
WebKit and in Blink.
It's behind a flag in Blink.
And it's not yet shipped
in WebKit, but it's
there in the code base.
Firefox will soon follow.
Basically, it looks something
like this you specified the 1x
or 2x or 1 and 1/2 x or 3x
qualifiers for each image
resource you add to the page.
The entire spec also includes
viewport switching, which
looks something like this.
For each resource, you specify
the max viewport for which it
can be applied to, and the x
factor that's adapted to it.
The problem with that,
it gives you a lot
of expressive power.
But you also have to, in some
cases, like you can see in the
example I put up, define a
single URL several times.
Because it fits several DPR
and viewport combinations.
Then we have Picture,
which is mainly
targeted at art direction.
It's an element with multiple
source children.
Each one of them is specifying
an image resource based on
media queries and
possibly type.
The first matching resource is
downloaded and displayed.
It looks something like this.
And as you can see, it
can mix source set
into the source elements.
So you can define an
art-directed image with
multiple DPR versions of it.
And the media attributes you use
here are most probably the
same media values that you use
for your layout break points,
unlike viewport resolution
switching, which can be
independent of the
layout viewport.
Then we have, as a third
contender or third proposal,
we have Client Hints.
That is unlike the two others.
It's not a market-based
solution, it's
an HTTP-based solution.
And basically, the client sends
out its capabilities.
It sends out hints through
the server,
saying, this is my DPR.
This is my viewport
width or height.
The actual values are
still debated.
But this is the general
spirit.
And everything is done
on the server side.
It's server logic that serves
one resource or the other.
One recent change to
that proposal is
that it's opt-in only.
The hints are not sent on
the first HTML request.
On the other hand, it saved us
from adding data to request
where the server is not going
to do anything about it.
So that's a recent compromise
that may be able to push the
spec forward.
Then you have something I'm
proposing as more of a
long-term solution.
This is not something that's on
anyone's immediate radar.
But it's a long-term solution
I'm proposing that's a file
format-based approach, where
each target resolution that we
want to serve is represented
in a layer in
some sort of a container.
And these layers are building up
one on top of the other so
that the browser can download
a certain number of layers,
and then add more layers
on that, enhancing the
quality of the image.
It can address both resolution
switching and art direction.
And I'll just show you
a bunch of examples.
So basically, for resolution
switching, we have this photo
that, if we look into
the layers that
compose it, it's a thumbnail.
Then an enhancement layer,
which is basically the
thumbnail upscaled, with a dif
from the original image
downscaled.
So an enhancement layer, and
another one that's basically
used to recreate the original
image without adding many
bytes to the process.
Overhead is very small.
And for art direction, the
same can be applied.
So this bigger image that's
used everywhere for art
direction can be split
into a crop.
Then an enhancement layer
and another one.
The advantages are that
markup is not touched.
You have a single file
per image, so
it's easy to maintain.
And the best one for me is
that the browser can just
download difs.
If they had downloaded one image
and then something in
the browser's environment
has changed, you can
download the dif.
The disadvantages are that it's
complicated to implement.
And basically, the coding
performance and network
performance without HTTP2
is currently a mystery.
We need to further investigate
that in order to know if it's
feasible or not without HTTP2
and in terms of the coding
performance.
And last-minute slides added
by John Mellor here.
Maybe you want to
talk about that?
JOHN MELLOR: Sure I guess.
So a possible way of making this
responsive image format
container load more
efficiently.
When you're making several range
requests or something
and you don't want to leave gaps
in between and wait for a
round trip each time.
It will load all the images
on the page in parallel,
progressively.
So I've taken [INAUDIBLE]
website.
I've stolen this, sorry.
On the left you see the images
being loaded one by one,
sequentially.
On the right, you see
the images being
loaded all in parallel.
It's the same progressive
jpegs on both sides.
On the left, I'm truncating the
stream of images, so that
you get the first image, and
then I truncate at some point.
On the right, I truncate all
the images at the same
percentage.
So this is 5% of the
image bytes.
And you can see that on
both sides, the page
doesn't look great.
But by the time you've got to
10% of the image bytes,
already on the right you can
kind of see what the page
looks like.
All the images are really
blurry and so on.
But that at least filled
their space well.
Whereas on the left, you can see
the start of the top left
image, but all the other images
haven't even started
loading yet.
As you gradually load more,
say you're on &mdash;
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE]
JOHN MELLOR: OK.
Say you get to 25%,
for example.
Now that page on the right,
we're only loaded a quarter of
the image bytes, but it already
starts to look OK.
The images aren't crisp,
but they're
still perfectly usable.
Whereas on the left, we have the
super crisp, lovely image
in the top left, but the
other images haven't
even started loading.
By the time you get to 50%,
the page on the right now
looks perfect.
You can almost not tell
that it hasn't
finished loading and images.
Whereas on the left,
again, we've only
got half the images.
And then, as you load more
bytes, the page on the right
gradually becomes
a super-crisp,
retina beautiful page.
But it's a very subtle
difference between that and
the 1x image.
Whereas on the left, only now,
at 100%, do we actually all
the images at all visible.
ANN ROBSON: This is great.
I love that you're giving
something to the users like
well, they're waiting.
That's brilliant.
That's what I love about
progressive jpegs, is that
it'll download the first scan
as soon as possible.
MARCOS CACERES: So I think
that's a good lead-in to the
first question that we have,
which is from Jake Archibald.
Hope I pronounced that right.
Jake, do you have your
question with you?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yeah, do
I get a microphone?
MARCOS CACERES: Yes.
Mic runner, please.
There goes Pete.
[LAUGHS]
He's going to be really slim
by the end of the day.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Hey.
So I currently send a 2 times or
2.5 times images, and just
compress the hell out of it.
And the file size is roughly
the same as a 1x image.
And that seems to do the job.
Why do we need all these
extra markup examples?
And if in the future, John's
solution could come in and
stop the download at
some point, surely
that's all we need.
MARCOS CACERES: So go ahead
and start then.
JOHN MELLOR: So should we
start with the existing
fixed-width and flexible-width
images?
So this ties into what Yoav
was saying earlier about
resolution switching.
There's two kinds.
There's DPR switching, where
your images are a fixed size,
like a logo or an icon.
It's going to be the
same width, say 32
pixels, on all devices.
And all you need to do is switch
it out based on the
device's pic screen density.
So you might need a 2x image on
a retina screen, a 3x image
on Samsung Galaxy S4,
that kind of thing.
But all you're doing is changing
it based on the
device-pixel ratio.
With a flexible-width image,
say you've got width 100%.
Then suddenly, the width
for the viewport
of the device matters.
And so your phones, your
tablets, your laptops, they
all have different
widths, they all
need different images.
And here, a simple technique,
which gets you up to double
the resolution image by
compressing it more heavily,
isn't going to scale to an
8 times bigger image.
MARCOS CACERES: So what
do you think?
YOAV WEISS: One more thing.
Regarding the compressive
images hack &mdash;
MARCOS CACERES: Explain what
the compressive images &mdash;
YOAV WEISS: What to Jake
was talking about.
Basically, taking the high-res
images and extremely
compressing them so that they
will be, when downsized to 1x
display dimensions, they
will still a good.
And also, for retina, they look
quite fine, because the
actual display dimensions
are &mdash;
MARCOS CACERES: Hang on, sir.
I'm seeing a few people
looking at you going &mdash;
Let's see if we can explain
that a little better.
Does anyone want
to have a go at
explaining it a little better?
ANN ROBSON: I can try.
Hello.
Somebody discovered that if
they keep the resolution
really high in an image, but
they put the compression down
to, I think 0 &mdash;
is that correct?
YOAV WEISS: That's correct.
ANN ROBSON: So they'll actually
get a smaller file
size that is higher resolution
and it looks good on retina
images, and you have a smaller
file size for speed.
So it's actually best
of both worlds.
And it's an amazing discovery.
MARCOS CACERES: I'm sure if we
go back to 1996, we might find
the same thing.
But who knows?
Because we were doing it from
modems and stuff anyway.
So I guess what I'm wondering
is, what might be some of the
side effects?
Because we're sending
four times the data.
Basically sending an image
that's two times
or even more bigger.
The size might be three times.
So can the browser really
handle that?
Do we know if there's side
effects within the browser?
Maybe John's in a good
position because
he's closer to Chrome.
JOHN MELLOR: We don't really
have the research yet.
It's going to take four
times the memory.
On an image-heavy page, that
might blow your memory budget.
And suddenly things like
painting and scrolling might
get slower.
It's hard to know.
We need more research,
basically.
ANN ROBSON: Right We need
to experiment with that.
But it's a super interesting
idea.
YOAV WEISS: Yeah.
Basically it's on the agenda to
get some real hard data on
the implications of that.
MARCOS CACERES: On the
agenda of who?
YOAV WEISS: On the Responsive
Images Community Group's
agenda to get some hard
data on that for the
DPR switching case.
But exactly as John said, it
doesn't cover all the cases.
And it can cause decoding
performance and memory issues.
So if you're using that, you
need to test it well to make
sure there are no problems
because we don't have general
data on that.
MARCOS CACERES: So I'm going to
bounce a question to Peter
Miller, because he's working
on a lot of &mdash;
You work on some fashion
websites, and you've done &mdash;
Anyway, from whichever ones,
obviously it'd have access to
the very high-resolution
pictures that are coming
straight from photographers.
What would this mean
for maybe you guys?
Would it mean anything?
PETER MILLER: Well, first of
all, I've looked at the
solution and I've got
a retina Macbook.
And I think it's still a matter
of subjective opinion,
maybe, about whether this does
look as good as real retina
images or 2x images.
But I think, possibly thinking
about it even today, is the
bigger problem that, OK, we
can send these pseudo 2x
images down to be shrunk
down at 50%.
But what happens when we maybe
want to expand those images or
have them been more of
a percentage width?
And then suddenly, we're
actually showing those highly
compressed 2x images at their
physical 1x size And then
maybe they look even worse.
ESTELLE WEYL: I think whenever
we have this debate, we also
still have to remember people
who have metered bandwidth.
Because yeah, on your Macbook
Pro, on your Wi-Fi, it's going
to be great.
But someone doesn't want to
download that when they're
paying $19 for &mdash;
MARCOS CACERES: Yeah,
absolutely.
But let's hold on that one,
because that one takes us off
to the following question.
So I want to not go into
those exact concerns.
Because what Ann originally
said was, you can make a
larger image that's actually
smaller in kilobytes.
And so in a sense, it doesn't
really apply.
But it does.
But we're getting exactly
to the point &mdash;
ESTELLE WEYL: We also have to
think about Android 2.4 and
older Androids, which are
still being sold today.
Because they don't have
the memory capacity.
MARCOS CACERES: Right.
Even Firefox OS is 250 megabytes
of RAM on that.
And it struggles.
So absolutely.
So I think we should probably
move on to the next topic.
So the second question.
Is there a George Crawford?
GEORGE CRAWFORD: Hi.
This is one of the anonymous
questions from Google Moderator.
Is DPI negotiation
only a stopgap?
Bandwidth keeps growing
exponentially, LCD prices are
dropping, GPUs benefit
from Moore's Law.
In several years, would it
make sense to just send
high-resolution images
to all users?
MARCOS CACERES: The
implications &mdash;
and this goes back if
we look at all of
computing history, right?
Will 64 K be enough?
Computers just get faster.
And yet, we seem to find
ourselves in the same
situation over and over again.
Back in 1996, like I was saying
before, we had modems
and we have to compress the
crap out of images then as
well to cater to users that were
just getting cable, and
who didn't have cable and still
were on 54 K. 54 broad
rate modems.
So thoughts?
Should we really worry
that much?
Should we stop caring?
I know everybody's
probably excited.
ANN ROBSON: You were all like &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
MARCOS CACERES: Let's
do a round and
bounce back if we can.
But let's keep it short.
ANN ROBSON: I think it would be
nice if we could just send
super large images.
But I don't think we can
do that quite yet.
And I think that the responsive
images, it's such a
topic because we're getting
smaller and slower, and we're
getting bigger and faster
at the same time.
So this is spreading out.
I have, obviously,
my opinions.
But I think that we need a
response images container.
Could be, possibly, a
progressive jpeg that has
really small scans and
really large scans.
And possibly the browser only
downloads what it needs.
MARCOS CACERES: We have a
delegate in the queue.
I'll just get Mike [INAUDIBLE]
ready.
If you can jump to
a mic, Mike.
Do you want to quickly
jump in on this?
PETER MILLER: I think, staying
in a hotel room in New York
City, it actually feels like
we're quite a few years away
from being very fastly connected
across everywhere.
But also, you've got to think
data plans, roaming.
You want to give the users,
maybe, an option to have a
low-resolution mode.
But if we're just always sending
that high resolution.
But also allowing for the
art direction case.
I don't think that this
caters for that.
YOAV WEISS: I think that, as
Ann started to say, Moore's
Law is not giving us
expanded bandwidth.
We get a larger range
of devices.
We have capable smaller
devices.
And the bandwidth coverage
is not ubiquitous.
So basically, it's a question
that asks us whether we can
look into the future.
And unfortunately, we can't.
In 20 years, it may
be relevant.
MARCOS CACERES: We can't look
into the future, but we can
see what the trends are.
We know that we have now Google
Glass and Samsung's
watch and things like that.
YOAV WEISS: Exactly.
MARCOS CACERES: In a sense,
we know a little bit where
machines are going.
And again, we're going to
see the same cycle.
ANN ROBSON: So basically, the
problem is getting worse.
MARCOS CACERES: So
we found Mike?
MALE SPEAKER: Yes.
MIKE: Can you hear me?
MARCOS CACERES: Yup.
Do you want to jump in?
MIKE: Yeah.
Just a quick question.
One of you mentioned, what if
you have a small image?
Using high compression at a
large size that was initially
seen small, but then expanded.
It seems to be a consequence
of the jpeg format.
What about new formats,
such as WebP, and
using things like that?
MARCOS CACERES: So maybe
I'll get John to
respond to that one.
JOHN MELLOR: So I'm not
an expert on WebP,
but it tends to give &mdash;
it seems to have two things
that are nice.
It gives slightly better
performance, and compression
performance, ranging
from 25 to 60.
Well, it depends what you're
doing with it.
But it's also, when very highly
compressed, you get
less of the blocking artifact
you get with jpeg.
So you can actually afford a
greater compression ratio than
you would use with jpeg.
So that can help.
But there's issues with
[INAUDIBLE] support
and so on of course.
ANN ROBSON: Also, with WebP,
perceived performance is
slower than progressive
jpeg, right?
Because you're actually
getting a scan
earlier than a WebP.
Even if a WebP is a smaller file
size, progressive jpeg is
going to beat it every time.
MARCOS CACERES: Someone can
correct me here, but it
doesn't support progressive
loading.
Or does it?
ANN ROBSON: That's
a good question.
JOHN MELLOR: There's no counter
[INAUDIBLE] for
progressive loading.
MARCOS CACERES: So I think
that's, at least from service
perspective, following the bug
about WebP, that's a real
showstopper for us.
ESTELLE WEYL: Correct.
YOAV WEISS: So I'm not sure a
future progressive WebP can
answer that, or a progressive
jpeg.
But basically, I think
that it's not a
question of image format.
Because we have progressive
image formats, or we can
easily come up with
the responsive
image container stuff.
We can easily.
It's a prototype, but it's not
complicated to get this done.
The problem is that currently,
there are no fetching
mechanisms in place that can
download only the start of the
image for low-resolution
devices, and download the
entire image for high-resolution
devices that
have the bandwidth and have the
capability to decode it.
And I think that getting the
fetching mechanism in place
would be an enabler for such
optimization, for such formats
to be useful
MARCOS CACERES: I
want to quickly
get Estelle's thoughts.
ESTELLE WEYL: So I was going
back to the original question.
I think we're never going
to be able to just
have one image solution.
Because you don't have the same
image if your device is
this big versus if your
image is this big.
For those listening to audio,
you don't want to have the
same image if you have
a 20 inch image
versus a half inch image.
ANN ROBSON: But we actually
could do that, right?
Because with a progressive jpeg,
you can have a variable
number of scans, and the scans
are of increasing quality.
So you could have, say, 40.
Let's expand our minds
about this.
Is that correct?
We could.
YOAV WEISS: If you're getting
into 40 times bigger zone, you
will get color distortion.
ESTELLE WEYL: I'm talking
about the art direction.
If you're going to &mdash;
ANN ROBSON: Putting the art
direction topic aside for a
second, you actually can have a
progressive jpeg that has a
very small scan and then
very high resolution.
So you can have a tiny image
that downloads very quickly,
and you can have a super
large HD image for &mdash;
ESTELLE WEYL: Yeah, but I think
we can't put the art
direction aside, because
we are serving so
many different devices.
So I think the answer to the
question is I don't think
serving one image will be the
solution in the end, because
we are reaching such a
plethora of devices.
MARCOS CACERES: We're
going to continue
to be the next question.
It's very much related
to this.
So before I do that, that I'm
going to queue up Kyle.
Kyle, do you have
a mic already?
Where's Kyle?
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE]
MARCOS CACERES: Sorry,
Kyle seems to &mdash;
ESTELLE WEYL: He's over there.
MARCOS CACERES: So I'm
going to cue up Kyle.
He's right there.
So Kyle, just a quick
question or comment.
KYLE: So a lot of these
solutions seem to be art
direction-centric.
I want the best possible images
that can be there.
But responsive seems to respond
to maybe the screen
size, maybe to the bandwidth,
but it doesn't seem to react
to the environment.
Say if I start out loading a
Flickr page that the battery
power is at 50%, I've got plenty
of processing power.
But if I'm now at 2%, maybe
the device should start
choosing not to render
these higher things.
So can't we have solutions that
allow apps to respond to
more complex situations than
just the screen size?
MARCOS CACERES: We're going
to cover that as well.
But if somebody wants to
make a quick comment?
YOAV WEISS: Just a
quick comment.
That's something that certainly
should be possible
when we're talking about
resolution switching, when
we're talking about things that
won't break the layout
but just would give the user a
lower-quality image when it
can't download the high-res
quality image.
And this is something that
should be heuristically
possible with Source Set.
So the browser in Source Set,
basically the spec contains an
asterisk saying, eventually the
browser can do whatever
the hell it wants.
So the browser can decide,
based on user preference,
based on environment, based on
battery to not download the
high-res images, but
the lower-res ones.
MARCOS CACERES: So it's
kind of a good
thing and a bad thing.
But it does mean it's
a declarative model.
You're handing over control.
You're saying to the browser,
this is what I
got, deal with that.
Do it best for the user.
YOAV WEISS: Yeah.
I don't think this should be
something decided by the web
developer, because I don't think
they have this kind of
information.
We cannot have this kind of
information available to the
web developer.
This is something that should be
done by the browser with a
user preference.
MARCOS CACERES: I'm going to
be moderator here and jump
over to the next question,
because
they're all related anyway.
So we'll [INAUDIBLE]
the points.
Calvin Spealman.
Your question.
So runner.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Yeah.
I was basically wondering about
if we are fighting a
losing battle by continually
generating all these different
sizes and different resolutions
up front when
there's constantly devices,
constantly different sizes.
We're always going to be
constantly trying to catch up
and generating more and more
images, as opposed to having
some server-side solution that
does it dynamically and
optimizes the set of
images we have.
MARCOS CACERES: So I think this
ties in briefly to the
stuff that John was presenting
before, and also to the
progressive jpeg, to having
those multiple scans.
So John, with the kind of work
that you've been doing, what
are you seeing?
What are the numbers
telling you there?
JOHN MELLOR: I guess there's two
aspects of this question.
On the server side, sure, you
don't want the artist to be
manually saving out
20 different
versions of every image.
It's not scalable.
So I guess on the server side,
you have to be, at the moment,
dynamically creating these
images by automatically
resizing them.
But then, I guess I can
[INAUDIBLE] as well, it would
be nice if there was only one
image you have to save.
You just tell your Photoshop
or whatever, save out one
ultra high-resolution image.
And the [INAUDIBLE] downloads
just the beginning of it,
however much it needs.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Yeah.
That's perfect.
I think that's the most
elegant solution.
I think that's the second most
elegant solution is like with
Clients Hints, and having the
server serve up different
resolutions, different versions
of the image.
But it has to be automatic.
We should not be creating x
number of images to serve to
different devices.
And we are fighting a losing
battle in that case.
PETER MILLER: I think the &mdash;
MARCO CACERES: Quick audience.
Did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: But if you have that
situation, aren't you going to
end up in the thing that
all the developers were
complaining about when the
operators started to compress
your images on mobile
networks.
And they said, just
get out of my way.
I don't want you to
touch my stuff.
If you've got some automated
system that sits between the
thing you're creating, the same
problem that three years
ago you were all
whinging about.
ESTELLE WEYL: My thought was
that this would be &mdash;
I think it should
be server side.
So that the developer is
actually deciding what you're
sending over.
The browser should not be
altering images is my thought.
JOHN MELLOR: But the developer
doesn't know the bandwidth of
the client.
ESTELLE WEYL: No.
When we're all said and done,
when we have Client Hints and
everything else, it should be
the server that's making the
20 images and serving the
correct image based on the
Client Hints or the Source Set,
not the browser that's
taking an image and deciding
that the upper left hand
corner should be shown instead
of the middle of it.
JOHN MELLOR: It seems a lot
easier for the browser to take
user's preference into
account though.
If the user decides, they're
roaming or something, and they
only want the very low
resolution image.
Then do you want
an extra Client
Hint saying, I'm roaming.
An extra Client Hint saying
these kinds of things?
ESTELLE WEYL: No.
The browser can say &mdash;
When you have Client Hints &mdash;
Should we ask the question about
Client Hints that we're
going to ask later?
MARCO CACERES: No.
We are talking about &mdash;
I don't think we need to move
to that question yet.
Because we are dealing with or
discussing a very serious
problem, which is A, how can
computers really decide this?
How do we set the
break points?
Or not even the break points,
but this looks good here, so
sent this, and so on.
So having that level of control,
as Steve was saying
before, that was pissing
people off, developers,
because it didn't look good.
And to some degree, well,
that's what we really
need to look at.
Can we computationally
do that?
And John's research seems
to suggest that it can.
Because at least the user gets
the initial layout with the
nice images or beginnings
of a nice image.
And then from there, you start
progressively improving it.
So how much do you
need to push it?
And what does it mean
on the server?
It's kind of hard to know.
YOAV WEISS: My opinion on this
is that basically you need all
solutions to be automizable.
So you can do either dynamic or
a build step or something
on the server side that does all
the grunt work for you as
a developer.
At least we must have
some solutions that
don't require it.
MARCO CACERES: So I've got two
questions from the floor.
I've got one from &mdash;
your name?
Sorry.
OK.
I thought you were going
to ask a question.
No problem.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: So if we start
generating 20, 30 different
versions of files on the server
side and start doing
very Client Hint headers or
whatever, are we going to have
problems where the edge caches
just can't keep all of these?
We're going to be pulling out 20
different times the number
of files on all the
edge caches.
Are CDNs going to be useful
anymore at that point?
How's it going to scale?
YOAV WEISS: Since the Client
Hints is one hints per header,
so very woodwork.
But I think the edge caches will
have to adapt to the new
reality of much more
images than before.
But since I don't think
this will be &mdash;
it may be exponential.
But there will be time
to adapt, as far as
the edge caches go.
So that's my opinion.
AUDIENCE: --1.1 yet.
MARCO CACERES: Hang on.
Don't speak without the mic.
So I was going to jump to &mdash;
I'll go to Matt.
I think you had a question?
No?
You're good?
MATT: We covered it.
MARCO CACERES: OK cool.
So Peter, you're looking like
you want to say something.
PETER MILLER: When the original
question was first
asked, the case that comes to
my mind is still the art
direction case.
Because it is very
important for
publications that I work on.
And the crop has to be right.
And that's why we do do
upfront generation.
We have picture editors.
And they are in charge of
saying, when this image is
displayed at this size, then
here's a crop I want.
But I've worked with content
management systems in the past
that will define that
given coordinates.
Yes, we can automatically resize
images dynamically.
But maybe we could allow picture
editors to dynamically
come in and draw some
coordinates for different use
cases in different contexts.
And the question about whether
it's the browser that decides
it or it's the developer
that decides it.
Absolutely.
I think it has to be the
browser decides it.
It's not just the resolution
of the screen.
It's not just the size
Is not just the battery power.
It's actually everything else
to do with what's rendering
that image element.
And it's not just the HTML.
It's the style sheet as well.
MARCO CACERES: This leads me,
really, to the next question,
which is by Jeffrey
[INAUDIBLE].
Is he here?
JEFFREY: Yeah.
MARCO CACERES: There he is.
JEFFREY: Thank you.
So this is an annoying
theoretical purity question,
supplied by the moderator.
And I have a complicated
relationship to it, because
since 1998, I've been beating
the drum for separation of
presentation and structure.
But I'm also a big supporter of
Matt, Marcos, and picture.
Hey, buddy.
"Is it problematic that we
describe the presentation of
images in markup against our
typical mantra to separate
presentation from content?
And, if so, does the
specification of a myriad of
sizes make this worse?"
MARCO CACERES: So we saw this.
Hopefully you had the same kind
of gut reaction when you
saw both source set and
picture and went &mdash;
When you saw the code up on the
screen, and you kind of
went, ugh, really?
We have to type all those
times 1 and times 2?
And you saw the picture bloats
all over the place.
And it has media queries
in it as well.
So this goes straight too &mdash;
I know Jeffrey didn't ask that
question specifically.
But like he said, it's bad,
because we are putting media
queries into our markup.
What can we do there?
Is there possible solutions?
ESTELLE WEYL: So the reason
that there's a difference
between images and background
images is because the image
tag, img, is a foreground
image.
It's content.
Versus all the design that
we have on the web page.
So yes, we do have
to keep it &mdash;
the image is actually content.
MARCO CACERES: Right.
But what about the media
query component?
ESTELLE WEYL: The media
query should be &mdash;
that's why we're trying to
come up with all these
different solutions, and why
the picture element and the
source set look so ugly.
And actually why I like the
clown car technique, because
it actually separates
out the content.
MARCO CACERES: Just for people
who don't know the clown car
technique, just super,
super Twitter-sized.
ESTELLE WEYL: OK.
Three tweets.
It's basically instead of
pulling in an image,
it pulls in an SVG.
And inside the SVG, that's
where all the
media queries are.
So it pulls in the correct image
based on the container
of the SVG.
And it works fairly well.
It's basically a stopgap
solution while we're trying to
figure out the correct
solution.
But the reason that I liked
the clown car technique is
because it actually separated
out content from presentation
from behavior from images.
PETER MILLER: I think it
absolutely is a problem that
we're defining the media
queries in the HTML.
I don't think it's a
problem of bloat.
That's fine.
I think we can give the HTML all
the sources of the images,
as I was saying before.
But I think the problem is
illustrated in the case where,
let's say, on a 500 pixel-wide
screen, virtual pixels, you
have an image at 100% width.
On a 700-pixel screen, you might
actually have that image
at 50% width, because you've got
a second column come in.
And OK, fine, when I'm writing
HTML, maybe I'll
take that into mind.
But what if it's not an HTML
generation problem?
What if it's a render problem,
where when a user's logged in,
then you have a sidebar?
But when they're
not, you don't.
And in CSS, I can have the
column at 50% or 100% if it's
got a sibling with a
logged-in sidebar.
But I'm going to want a
different image source to
apply to that element.
And that's why a technique that
takes into account the
actual width of the image
element rather than the width
of the screen I think is
absolutely essential.
And that's why I do still
have a problem
with the page element.
MARCO CACERES: I think Yoav
will come in and &mdash;
YOAV WEISS: Yeah.
[LAUGHTER]
MARCO CACERES: So this is
alluding to, some people might
have heard about,
element queries.
Which is like CSS applied to a
particular container element.
And it's pretty cool.
PETER MILLER: Has
its problems.
MARCO CACERES: It has
JONATHAN KLEIN: So actually,
they are
several questions here.
First, for the separation of
content and presentation, I
think it's a problem.
I think that this is something
that can be resolved by drying
out the media queries out of
HTML and into some sort of a
media query variable.
MARCO CACERES: Drying
out being?
YOAV WEISS: Don't
repeat yourself.
MARCO CACERES: Thank you.
YOAV WEISS: Just basically
creating variables that say
mobile, whatever that means.
Basically create named media
queries and use them instead
of the actual media queries
wherever you have media
queries in your markup.
Be it picture or external
style sheets, or
in the CSS as well.
There is work in the CSS Working
group regarding that.
I have no idea when it will
go in, but people
are working on it.
And so regarding that, I think
that will resolve most of the
issues that from this
separation of
concerns point of view.
MARCO CACERES: Hang on.
So a question I have is &mdash;
OK, so a picture is probably
the main offender here.
Should we even bother
to continue to work
on it in that sense?
YOAV WEISS: I don't think
picture is the
most visible offender.
But again, there are
style sheets.
If I'll have my way, media
attributes will be everywhere.
Which I probably won't
have my way.
But I think that there are a lot
of resources that can be
downloaded based on media.
And I think we need to have
some shortcut for media
queries that we don't have to
repeat them everywhere,
including in CSS.
Because in CSS, we repeat
them as well.
And regarding the element
queries stuff.
First of all, I'd like to say
that the main advantage of the
clown car technique versus
basically anything else is
that it basically emulates
element queries.
The media queries there referred
to the viewport of
the SVG, not the viewport
of the document.
So while it creates some
delay in download,
it's sometimes necessary.
There are cases where it's
useful, extremely useful.
But the problem with element
queries is that you cannot
start downloading the resource
before you have layout, which
means you add a significant
delay to the entire page load.
MARCO CACERES: So Ann, do you
have any comments about &mdash;
ANN ROBSON: Yeah.
I'm still a fan of progressive
jpegs.
And I think that &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
ANN ROBSON: No, I think that
there's definitely &mdash;
The art direction
case, it doesn't
really handle, obviously.
But I don't think that we should
forget about it as a
file format that we
might explore.
And we often do forget about
progressive jpegs.
I think we forgot about
progressive
jpegs for 10 years.
MARCO CACERES: What is the
reason we forgot about them?
What browser doesn't really
support them?
ANN ROBSON: Oh.
I think that in general,
there's pretty
good browser support.
I think that the reason browsers
don't support them is
because we stopped using them.
And I think we stopped using
them because things changed.
We had a faster connections.
But then things kind of reverted
with mobile, and we
went back to where we were,
where speed turned out to be
an issue again.
MARCO CACERES: Cool.
ANN ROBSON: That's it.
MARCO CACERES: So there's one
question from the audience.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: Sounded like the best
solution for a pictured
element is basically to
move the rules to CSS.
You can go back to regular IMG
and have something that says,
in CSS, for all images which
have a path that looks like
this, then apply these rules
to add .2x to the path.
This allows you to move the more
presentational parts of
it to the CSS while still
keeping the content, namely
the fallback image,
in the HTML.
And you can use something like
a regex to not have to write
this 2x, that 2x, something
else 2x for 2x version of
every single image you have.
You can sort of do this right
now using attribute selectors
and IMG tag.
MARCO CACERES: Using
what selectors?
AUDIENCE: You can sort
of do this now
using attribute selectors.
MARCO CACERES: Attribute
selectors.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
But one per SOC, which
would be annoying.
MARCO CACERES: Right.
Yeah.
So it's kind of like
a mix of things.
So I'm sure one of these other
guys will be able to talk
about their concerns there.
I can give a little.
Some of the main problem that
we're trying to solve with
responsive images as a whole is
integrating nicely into how
browsers load images and
performance wise.
So to block and wait for a style
sheet to download that
will give you the instructions
to then be able to fetch the
files that you need will
probably cause issues.
Part of the stuff that Yoav
was talking about before,
about these CSS-based variables
they can put in is
that you would need to insert
them at the top of the
document in line so then they
would actually parse before
anything else.
So there's big performance
issues with all this.
It's a cool solution,
and I'm not saying
that it wouldn't work.
But it's working out how all the
dynamics work there within
the browser.
It's pretty crazy.
Does anyone want to add?
You're all probably
ones that had a &mdash;
YOAV WEISS: I just want to add
that it's basically violating
the separation of concerns
from the
other side of the spectrum.
Basically, your content
is now part of your
presentation in a way.
Because the content URLs
rely on the CSS.
For CSS caching, content images
tend to change often.
Everything that's in
CSS usually changes
less often than that.
So it can be cached for a
while, for a long while.
It violates the layers as far
as I'm concerned, in a way.
MARCO CACERES: So let's
take that one up.
So I've got another question
from the audience.
And another one from &mdash;
So I've got a couple here.
I'm going to go there first,
and then we'll bounce to &mdash;
Sorry, you already have
the mic, so go ahead.
And then I'll bounce to you.
Sorry.
AUDIENCE: Just to counteract
that, how you say if you need
to download the CSS first in
order to display the image.
But that the CSS modifies the
size of the image, which could
modify the art direction
and the actual one
that you want to use.
Isn't that important?
MARCO CACERES: It is.
But like I said, it's all
trades and balances.
Because we are trying to keep
the performance high.
So there is going to be a
penalty for everything.
So where you defer.
Like Yoav was saying, the
separations of concern, it's
going to have issues
with how the images
are loaded and when.
So if the things have to be
deferred, then you might defer
layout, and that's going to
impact the user's perception
of whatever application
you're trying to run.
So again, we need to test
a lot of this stuff.
We don't know.
Even though we've been talking
about it, now it's really time
to start testing.
AUDIENCE: I guess I just
had more of a direct
question for Peter.
Sorry to put you on the spot.
But given the art direction
perspective, I was wondering
if you could talk a little bit
about, from your standpoint,
what is best practice
right now?
Given that it's not all just
programmers trying to do stuff
in an automated fashion.
Because every time I've tried
to do that, I fail.
And the art director looks to me
and is like, no, we need to
cop it this way instead.
MARCO CACERES: I want you to
answer that, but I think this
is a great question.
Because it's really
about what should
developers be doing today?
And I think John
has some ideas.
Ann's already talked about
let's try out these
progressive jpegs.
And Yoav and I have been working
on the standards,
trying to look forward.
Estelle's been experimenting
with the client kind of
techniques.
So we have five minutes.
One minute each, what can
developers do today?
Starting with Peter.
PETER MILLER: OK.
Well here's what we're doing.
We're sending lots of the jpeg
sources into the HTML as a
JSON string on a
data attribute.
We've got JavaScript running
that, after the CSS has
evaluated layout, will pick the
right source, and apply
it, and on resize, change it.
Yeah, the performance isn't
great for that.
But to answer a little of
what Yoav was saying.
I think that having a default
source there, low-res your
best guess is, I think, an OK
way to go for we have now.
MARCO CACERES: Ann, what do you
recommend for developers?
ANN ROBSON: I think that
what we have now
is a bunch of hacks.
So that's what we have.
I think we should
try and focus &mdash;
I love that we're doing this.
And actually, I think what we're
talking about are big
wins and solutions for
responsive images.
And I think we should really
be forward-thinking in not
forget all of the different
options and all of our
different paths and
explore them all.
MARCO CACERES: That's great.
YOAV WEISS: I think that all
current hacks have performance
trade offs.
All current hacks, basically,
you're deferring the loading
of the image to a later time
in order to download the
appropriate one.
I think that things
will look up soon.
Things will get better soon.
There is currently work in the
Responsive Images Community
Group on an x-picture
polyfill &mdash;
MARCO CACERES: --web
components.
YOAV WEISS: --that uses web
components in order to emulate
the picture.
It won't work with
the preloader.
But if you don't have any
blocking scripts at the page's
top, it should have similar
performance
characteristics as image.
So current hacks all
have problems.
Future hacks will get better.
And then there is
a Source Set.
Hopefully it will ship &mdash;
MARCO CACERES: Soon enough.
YOAV WEISS: --in a release
build soon enough.
MARCO CACERES: OK.
ESTELLE WEYL: So I guess the
question is what developers
should be doing now.
And what developers should be
do now is being concerned
about what they're sending over
the wires and making sure
that they're not sending
huge assets to
limited bandwidth devices.
And in terms of what we should
be doing is, the spec author
should be doing, is
we should also &mdash;
I think what I haven't heard,
and I just thought of while I
was on stage &mdash; so I don't know,
maybe it has been &mdash;
there's the image element
you can clip and
pick certain areas.
So maybe figuring out a way to
do that on the back end or
through Client Hint so that
you're actually just
downloading based on that
instead of downloading the
whole image.
MARCO CACERES: Right.
So just expanding on that one.
It's basically just taking &mdash;
you have your normal image, and
then you select the area
that you want to crop out.
And basically you just
crop it out with CSS.
It's a good way of doing
art direction.
And it fits quite well with
compressive images as well.
JOHN MELLOR: So I'll give
several answers.
For CSS, you can just use media
queries to switch out
the right image.
It's in a better state
these days.
For HTML, there's a few
different things.
For fixed-size images, if you're
just switching based on
device-pixel ratio, compressive
images, like
serving a double-size but highly
compressed image, is
reasonable.
Source Set will be nice, but
only once browsers support it.
For viewport-based switching,
where you need to take into
account flexible images, I think
the best solution these
days is to load a very
low-quality placeholder which
is directly referenced
from your HTML.
And then, later on, using
Javascript, you swap it out
with an appropriate-resolution
image, based on the actual
image size or whatever.
MARCO CACERES: And would
you use the classic &mdash;
I don't know even know
if this works here.
But there was a low source,
low SRC attribute on HTML.
JOHN MELLOR: I just use SRC.
So put the locals you want in
SRC and use JavaScript to
replace that with a better
quality one once you've loaded
that in the background.
So you get kind of this
progressive thing.
Where the page loads in low
quality quickly, and gradually
becomes higher quality.
So I actually released the
library for this yesterday.
It's on GitHub.com/JohnM
ellor/RespSwap.js.
Very early stages.
Finally, for art direction,
where you actually need a
different image, rather than
just a different resolution,
the same image.
You can't load a low-quality
placeholder because you don't
know what image it's
going to be.
And so for that, you
can something like
Picturefill or whatever.
But don't use Picturefill
for report switching.
MARCO CACERES: So Picturefill,
for people who don't
know what that is.
Picturefill, you
can Google it.
You'll find it pretty quick.
And it's basically similar
syntax to the picture element,
but done with, I think divs
and spans or something.
But it basically works.
JOHN MELLOR: But a downside is
that the images don't load
until the page is fully finished
loading and you've
reached DOMContentLoaded.
And so your images will start
loading much later than if
you've got a placeholder
or something.
YOAV WEISS: Just to emphasize on
that, Picturefill should be
used for art direction and not
for resolution switching.
ESTELLE WEYL: I'd like
to add one comment.
With the Picturefill, the reason
that it's an issue is
because it's on
DOMContentLoaded.
We should make on
DOMContentLoaded much faster.
It shouldn't be taking 10
seconds to download your page.
And that's one thing we should
definitely work on is &mdash;
MARCO CACERES: That one, I think
we'll hopefully cover it
in one of the other sessions.
Because that's part of
the performancing.
So there is work around that
that we would basically say.
I'm just wrapping up here
for the session.
But it basically would just
say, my page is ready now.
So as an author, you say, forget
DOMContentLoaded, but
page is done!
And you send a fake
DOMContentLoaded that
indicates to the browser, now
I'm ready to do other stuff.
So please join me in thanking
the panel here.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDREW BETTS: [INAUDIBLE]
MARCO CACERES: Sorry?
ANDREW BETTS: You didn't
give the caveat.
[INAUDIBLE]
Thanks guys.
So sorry about the technical
problems in the first session.
We have a web server
that we evidently
need to reboot somewhere.
So while we do that,
let's crack on
with the second session.
So we have Andre Behrens from
"The New York Times," who will
be leading our Rendering
Performance session.
We'll start off just
as we are.
So if you have a question,
just raise your hand.
And as soon as we can get the
moderation tool working, we'll
be switching to that.
Thanks for your patience, and
help me welcome Andre Behrens.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDRE BEHRENS: If everyone
could just come up.
Hey, Paul.
Hey.
How you doing?
OK.
So we're going about rendering
performance.
Or as I like to think of it, the
war on purple and green.
I'm sure you've engaged
in that yourselves
from time to time.
On our panel today we have Josh
Peek from GitHub, Ariya
Hidayat from Sencha.
We have our opening speaker,
Jonathan Klein from Etsy.
We have Paul Lewis
from Google.
And we have Eli Fidler
from BlackBerry.
So let's just go in with
the presentation.
You ready to go?
JONATHAN KLEIN: I'm going to
put this up on the screen.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Can we get
the presentation on?
JONATHAN KLEIN: Cool.
OK.
When we talk about rendering
performance, we're really
talking about this
number here.
Most monitors and devices we
have today are rendered &mdash;
ANDRE BEHRENS: Mic.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Hey.
That's a lot better.
Thanks.
Most monitors and devices we
have today are rendering at
about 60 frames per second.
So we talk about rendering
performance, we're really
talking about trying to get your
application to render at
60 frames per second with
all animations, with
scrolling, et cetera.
If you do the math on this,
it means that we have 16.6
milliseconds, approximately,
to get a paint event done.
So any time you have a paint
event that's taking longer
than that to render on your
page, you're going to get jank
on the page.
And it's going to be slow.
Luckily, we have tools today
that make this pretty easy to
see what's going on.
This is an example of
Chrome DevTools.
All you do is turn
on the continuous
page repainting mode.
And in the upper right section
of the page, you'll get a nice
meter that tells you
exactly how long
the paints are taking.
This is on the Edge
Conf website.
You can see here,
2.7 milliseconds
for this paint event.
And then there's a meter on the
right there that says it's
ranging between 2.6 and 4.6.
This is a very, very
fast paints.
If our budget is 16.6
milliseconds, then 2.7 is well
within that budget.
And as you scroll the page,
this meter will adjust
depending on how long the
paints are taking.
So any time you see this meter
spike above 16.6 milliseconds,
you're going to get that jank
that I talked about.
And jank is something that
I'm sure we've all seen.
It's basically when you're
scrolling a page and it hangs,
or animation is happening
and you can't scroll.
Anytime where the page
performance drops below 60
frames per second.
And again, this happens pretty
widely on the web today.
And it's a pretty big problem.
And that's the term that's
been generated for it.
What causes jank?
Now that we know what it is.
Well, this slide I pulled
directly from the Jank Busters
Google I/O talk earlier
this year.
And I think it gives a good
overview of the main things
that are important
to think about.
These things really fall
into two categories.
So first is unnecessary
paints.
So this is if you have, maybe
your paints are fast, but you
have too many of them.
So you try to jam hundreds
of paints into a
single scroll event.
And that's just not going to
perform well, no matter what
you're doing.
And the other category
is long paints.
So these are examples where you
might have a single paint
event, but it takes more
than your budget of 60
milliseconds to render.
And there are some examples
here of different event
handlers that can cause that
problem, CSS issues, and just
visually complex pages.
Why do we care about jank?
Why do we care about rendering
performance in general?
People have talked a lot
historically about page
performance itself, but this
idea of rendering performance
is fairly new.
During Edge London earlier
this year, we heard Shane
O'Sullivan say that Facebook
artificially lowered the frame
rate on their iOS and Android
apps from 60 frames per second
down to 30 frames per second,
and engagement collapsed,
according to him.
On a native app, it's
pretty easy to get
60 frames per second.
If you get down to 30,
that's pretty bad.
So they artificially did this
to, he said, a small
[INAUDIBLE] of the users,
maybe a few
dozen million users.
[LAUGHS]
And it caused major problems.
At Etsy, we did a similar test,
in the sense that we
started prefetching JavaScript
on our search results page.
When the JavaScript came down
the pipe and was actually
executed by the browser,
we got janky behavior.
So essentially, you'd see in
the Chrome console that the
JavaScript came in,
and then the page
performance would degrade.
You couldn't scroll the page
and it was really nasty.
We were monitoring all the
business metrics on this page
when we were testing
this change out.
And as soon as we rolled it out,
the business metrics got
a lot worse across the board.
So we rolled it back.
And we were unable to make that
change with the current
implementation.
This is all to say that right
now, in many cases, rendering
performance is more important
than full-page performance.
If your page is fully loaded,
you might think, OK, I'm done.
It happened quickly,
that's fine.
But if the user can't scroll and
interact with the page, or
your animations are slow, it's
going to really torpedo
engagement.
How do we fix it?
Well, that previous slide I put
up has some good advice.
Basically, we just use the tools
that exist today to hunt
down these painful repaints
or unnecessary repaints
and then fix them.
Again, these things come from
visually complex elements.
But luckily, the designers
are telling us today
that flat is cool.
So it's very easy to have a
nice site and a fast site.
All you do is just have a
flat, no gradients, no
background images, no nothing.
Just flat colors.
And then you're good
to go on all front.
But seriously, what are some
real techniques that we can
talk about today that make
an impact on rendering
performance?
The first is using
requestAnimationFrame instead
of setTimeout.
Historically, if you want to
execute something on an often
basis, but not as quickly as
possible, you use setTimeout
in JavaScript to delay that
event a given number of
milliseconds.
And people would do things like
take 1,000 milliseconds,
divide by et cetera
to try to get 16.6
millisecond execution times.
But we'd rather have people
use, going forward,
requestAnimationFrame.
This is a native browser API
that can optimize these
rendering events.
It can do things like turn
off the animation
so the tab is hidden.
It can optimize battery usage
on mobile devices.
And since it's a native browser
API, it's just going
to be more efficient at
doing animations.
Support across browsers is
pretty good, certainly in
modern browsers.
You can shim it for older
versions of IE.
But it's well-supported
across all
modern versions of browsers.
Another thing to point out is
that consistent frame rate is
better than a high, variable
frame rate.
So if you can get your page to
render consistently at 40
frames per second the entire
time, that's better than
having it render at 60
sometimes, but as soon as the
user scrolls or an animation
fires, it drops down to 30 and
bounces back and forth.
That's a terrible experience
for end users.
So you want to make sure that
the page is rendering in a
consistent fashion.
Another technique is
to paint less.
So we talked about how
having too many
paints can be an issue.
A lot of time, this comes down
to just bashing your paints
together and trying to do these
large updates to the
screen fewer times.
So just one slightly larger
paint that's still within your
budget of 60 milliseconds, but
not having tons of paints that
execute on every scroll
event, or every
hover event, et cetera.
You can consider the
translateZ hack.
We have some experts on the
panel here today that can talk
more about that.
But essentially, when you add
translateZ(0) to an element in
CSS, it doesn't actually
animate that element.
Bu it does move it to a
different compositing layer,
which can be very useful for
something that's being painted
very often.
So it'll get put under
the GPU, and the GPU
can optimize that.
Speaking of the GPU, you want to
make sure you're optimizing
how often you're uploading
textures to the GPU.
The GPU is extremely good at
manipulating textures that
have been shipped to it.
But if you saturate that bus
between the CPU and the GPU by
trying to push textures back
and forth, you're going to
have problems.
So this really comes down to
understanding when your
forcing stuff to go to the GPU,
and trying to make sure
you're not doing
that too much.
But doing it enough
to leverage it
when it make sense.
And then finally, this comes
from a post that was written
by Paul Lewis, one of our
panelists, over here.
"Don't guess it, test it." It's
really hard to give you
hard and fast rules for
rendering performance on the
web today, because they're
so specific to the site
characteristics.
It can be a single animation
that's causing your problems.
It can be a single CSS
rule in some cases.
So it really comes down to using
the tools to find out
where your page is slow.
If you want more resources,
there's a great site put
together some folks at
Google, JankFree.org.
It aggregates slides, videos,
and articles about this topic.
And there's a lot of excellent
information on there.
And with that, I'm going to
turn it over to the panel.
ANDRE BEHRENS: You
want to switch?
Here, you hold onto that.
JONATHAN KLEIN: OK.
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDRE BEHRENS: OK.
We're going to try and get up
the contribution screen here.
MALE SPEAKER: There you go.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Beautiful.
OK.
So let's go to our first
question, Pete Miller.
Someone get a microphone
to Pete.
PETER MILLER: [INAUDIBLE]
question.
So anonymous question here.
If there were a YSlow for
rendering performance, what
would its tests be?
What changes would be easiest
to implement.
And which would have
the biggest impact?
All right.
Someone form the panel
want to go?
Paul, do you have an
idea for that one?
PAUL LEWIS: I think we covered
this in the introduction talk.
A YSlow for rendering
performance is &mdash;
I won't go so far as to say
useless, but it's going to be
very difficult.
Because what are we're
looking for?
We're looking for
layout problems.
What triggers the
layout problem?
Is it that you clicked
this button up
here in the top corner?
Is that you were scrolling and
we did something Parallaxy and
that caused a layout problem?
You start to get into very,
very specific to your
application where your problems
are going to show up.
So having an automated
testing framework
is going to be tricky.
That's not to say we
shouldn't try it.
But it's not always going to
be the easiest thing to do.
So it's something that you'd run
into YSlow, where it goes,
hey, you did this,
and you did this.
We should look at it.
But I'm not at this point
sure how broadly
effective it would be.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
I think it's really hard
to automate that.
But because YSlow is partly
used as an on-demand tool,
that's what the dev tools
provide for you today.
If you're using YSlow in a sense
that you just pull up a
page and run it manually through
the Chrome extension,
that's what you can do today
with the existing tooling, and
see the rendering performance
for your given site.
So we have something similar.
It's just very, very difficult
to automate as policy.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: So one thing that
you can do is to apply
specific restrictions
in your project.
For example, Jonathan mentioned
about not using
requestAnimationFrame.
So you can put some check in
your CI system to prevent
somebody from accidentally
putting that use of
setTimeout.
So if there's a new additional
setTimeout code, code appears
on some of the JavaScript
files.
That should trigger warning.
Because the project used
requestAnimationFrame by
default, for example.
JOSHUA PEEK: Yeah.
I guess the YSlow stuff normally
runs on page load,
but obviously all these
rendering performance problems
are something that's happening
as your app is running.
So there's not really a way
to profile that initially.
So it's basically what we
already have now, which is the
timeline view of showing
all these problems.
And Chrome does a
pretty good job.
I like the new little Warning
icon you get when you trigger
a layout in the timeline.
And so that's a pretty good
situation right now.
PAUL LEWIS: Yeah.
And there are other things.
There are things like telemetry,
which Adobe had
been using brilliantly
for top coat.
So when check in code, telemetry
is a Python-based
framework that the Chrome
engineers use.
And it runs a bunch of tests
against pages for things like
smoothness of scrolling.
And that's definitely something
I'm interested in
looking at a little bit more.
Because there may be things that
we should be looking at
that give us a least an insight
into how the change we
made in our code affected
rendering performance.
And it may be that there's a
certain amount of scripting
that's required from the
developers to set this up in a
meaningful way for that
particular project.
But that might be something
that we want
to take a look at.
And if you are interested, give
me a shout after this,
because I'm actually really
interested to find people who
want to try it.
To bust out telemetry
and give it a go.
ELI FIDLER: I think also the
question is really, what are
the magic bullets?
I do this on my site
and it gets fast.
And there's enough things
going on in rendering
performance in most cases that
there isn't a hard and fast
rule there.
Things are very different
on different platforms.
So in addition to being specific
to your site, it's
specific to the device that
you're running on.
It's specific to the version
of the browser that you're
running on that device.
And so testing is really
the best way.
And testing on as many devices
as possible is the best way.
Which is not, I'm sure, what
everybody who builds content
wants to hear.
But of course, there are some
things that are good and that,
I think, people have started
to do a lot more.
Being declarative is usually
better than being imperative.
So if you're going to do an
animation, use CSS animations
or CSS transitions.
Browsers are getting much better
at optimizing things
that are left up
to the browser.
And historically, you haven't
been able to do that, because
performance hasn't been good.
But now it's a lot better.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Well, thinking
about YSlow is not just the
specific implementation
detail.
When I think about other people
that I work with and
multiple levels, are there
any big, obvious things?
Part of YSlow's powers
is just the marketing
message that it delivered.
We have these things.
OK, we should definitely all
be gzipping everything.
And it sort of consolidated
things that had been known.
ELI FIDLER: I think CSS
transitions, as opposed to
JavaScript animations, is an
obvious one that most people
are getting now.
My personal one that I've
noticed a lot is people really
like one-pixel offset,
one-pixel blur
drop shadows on text.
That's a really expensive
operation.
Don't do that.
ANDRE BEHRENS: All right.
I think we'll move on to
our next question.
OK.
Jake Archibald.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: All right.
So tricks like translateZ,
putting that on an element is
quite often a silver bullet
in terms of performance.
But could that be an
anti-pattern tomorrow?
Like when we used to tell people
to concatenate strings
using array.join and we now know
that's faster than just
doing string plus string.
Is translateZ going to
be the same thing?
PAUL LEWIS: Possibly.
There are three steps,
I think, to
most performance problems.
Which is first of all, there's
the don't-do-it stage, where
we just blindly, do
not do this thing.
It will be bad.
Then there's the next step where
we go, ah, now we can
make it less bad if you
were to do this thing.
Which is where I categorize
the translateZ hack.
It's something we'd rather
you didn't have to do.
But sometimes you've got to
step in and do it, just to
hint things up a little bit.
Then there's the final step,
which this, this is not a
problem anymore.
Now, there's the other thing
where you go, oh, actually, of
a sudden it's an anti-pattern.
So the array concat versus
array.join versus string
concat thing is the one that's
often mentioned.
And I think the only thing you
can do there is profile.
Again, we've said it before.
But if you're profiling and
it's part of your build
process, then when something
changes in the implementation,
you're going to see it.
You're going to go,
whoa, something
went really slow here.
I wasn't expecting that.
What was it?
And you can figure out what it
is that's actually triggering
your problem.
So yes, it may be a problem
in the future.
There's no crystal ball gazing,
as far as I can tell.
But profile is the
answer for me.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
And I would say that any time
you're doing something that's
known to be a hack &mdash;
that's definitely
a hack, right?
That's probably not going to be
something that we want to
be doing forever.
So any time that you feel like
you're adding some code that's
just not standards compliant.
Or translateZ(0) doesn't make
a lot of sense from a future
proofing point of view.
I think it makes sense to
abstract that stuff away.
Because chances are, it's going
to change going forward.
Because it's not
part of a spec.
It's just a workaround.
PAUL LEWIS: One thing I really
don't like, just being me for
a second, is the fact that we
don't give you a way to say
that you want something
on its own layer.
I don't have a problem with
the developer saying that.
There's a balancing act of
should the developer have to
worry about layers versus should
the browser just take
care of everything.
And in a perfect world, yeah,
the browser would maybe get
everything right for you.
It'd be able to guess your
intent perfectly.
But if it can't, then surely the
best next step is not to
provide a hack, but to provide
a decent API that says, yeah,
you know what, if you need
to call this, call this.
This is what it'll do.
And if you want to abuse it,
OK, that's your call.
You're the developer
and we trust you.
And you're not an idiot.
That's just generally how I feel
about this kind of stuff.
JOSHUA PEEK: Yeah.
It's definitely a leaky
extraction for us.
So I think if the layer
compositing system is
something that you really need
to be concerned about as a
developer, it should be
an explicit opt-in.
Not going into this magic voodoo
property that you read
about on Stack Overflow and you
don't really understand
how it works.
But having explicit API for
declaring layers is, I think,
a good idea, if that's something
we need to be
concerned about.
ELI FIDLER: So translateZ(0) is,
obviously, a hack to force
compositing.
And I think it's actually a
really good declarative API
if, right after you put that on,
or at some point later in
your page, you're about to
animate the value of
translateZ.
Or you're about to animate
the value of translate3d.
Then you are exactly saying,
this is something I'm setting
now because I'm going
to animate it later.
And that's why it does
what it does.
So that you have your content
promoted into a layer, so that
when you animate it, the
next frame is ready.
And a number of properties
are like that.
Those are the properties right
now that force compositing.
And they're there specifically
so that, if you are going to
animate then, you're primed
and ready to go.
And maybe there are
more things that
should be like that.
But I'm very hesitant about
saying that we should
introduce a new property that
says, promote to layer.
Because promote to layer isn't
something that web developers
should care about.
PAUL LEWIS: If you don't have
that, then you have this thing
where developers can't get
good performing code.
They don't have anything
other than a hack.
And so either the browser has to
infer perfectly the intent
of the developer and get it
right, or we have the
alternative, which is give them
a way of saying, no, this
is what I really mean.
And they're doing that through
this back door at the moment.
Which kind of makes me
feel uncomfortable.
Because it does give rise to,
hey, implementation's changed.
Now your expectation
needs to change.
Which is, I think, a slightly
unfair position to put a
developer in.
But maybe that's just me.
ANDRE BEHRENS: It's kind of
interesting to ask what the
distinction is between
translateZ and promote to
layer in terms of actual
developer life experience.
AUDIENCE: Can I jump
in for a sec?
I feel like I've seen developers
animating top or
left, setting something
position-fixed a lot, and then
not realizing that that's
going to have different
performance implications than
animating something with
translate or even margin.
So I feel like if we wanted to
let someone animate top but
give it the performance of
something in it's own
compositing layer, than using
some sort of layer-promoting
API would make sense in that
case, potentially.
ELI FIDLER: Your specific
example right now also does
force a layer on
most platforms.
If you set something to fixed
positioning and then animate
top, it will &mdash;
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ARIYA HIDAYAT: Just adding one
more twist to the topic.
We also have to remember that
translateZ, or even
compositing layer, is just
half of the equation.
For example, if you do that but
you try to animate, say,
blur radius or border radius,
it doesn't really help.
Because there are only a couple
of properties that you
can apply to the GPU texture
that can be executed by the
GPU efficiently.
So again, explicit or implicit,
or half-explicit,
half-implicit, web developer
person still needs to know
that only certain properties
you can run
on the layer itself.
PAUL LEWIS: And generally, the
way I always pitch it is
you're going to promote to
isolate a layer that's
probably going to get painted.
Because you're going to move
it, scale it, fade it, or
rotate it, I think.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: And filter.
PAUL LEWIS: Or filter.
And Paul Irish actually
helped me figure &mdash;
he came up with those four,
which is really helpful.
So if you're going to do one of
those things, or if you're
going to paint something and
it's going to affect other
elements, then it's a good
time to isolate it.
Other than that, like you said,
it's probably not going
offer you anything.
And you're potentially creating
more of a problem,
because you're going to have to
upload a texture for that
layer to the GPU.
And if you're on a constrained
device, like mobile one, well,
you're going to pay that
tax every time
you change that layer.
JONATHAN KLEIN: One of the
interesting things, I think,
about the web that's happening
right now is
that we have two &mdash;
or not even two, but whatever.
A gradient of use cases.
Because the browser now becomes
this platform where
you can do complex animations,
you can do full gaming
experiences, et cetera.
But you can also build a
pretty static website.
So when we talk about developers
shouldn't have to
worry about this, well, if
you're building a high
performance game in the browser,
you probably should
have to worry about
that, right?
But if you're building your
blog, you shouldn't.
So I think there needs to be a
facility for both camps of
people to be able to use these
tools effectively without
having to worry too much if
you're on the low end, but you
should be able to access those
APIs if you're working on
something really complex.
ANDRE BEHRENS: I think we'll
move on to our next question.
Ben Holland.
Grab the mic.
BEN HOLLAND: So we have
reasonably good tools and
insight into rendering
performance in a dev
environment .
But not data from the field.
What events or metrics would we
ideally like to be able to
measure and report on
for real users?
JOSHUA PEEK: The only thing we
can do live in production is
measure like the Window
Performance APIs.
Those are pretty great.
But those only affect
initial load.
You don't get anything
after the fact.
So being able to hap into the
timeline from JavaScript and
get the actual values
would be great.
We do some stuff where we
profile method times and then
report these back over Ajax
in our production app.
But you can't get access to any
timeline data live from
JavaScript.
So having those would
be great.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
I'd love to have real user data
in production as well,
but I'd also love to have even
better synthetic tooling
around it for remote use.
So what I mean by that is to
say, right now there's no
JavaScript API into the frame
rate, for example, that the
Chrome DevTools gives you for
that rendering meter.
So it'd great if you could
just hook into that with
JavaScript, because then you
could write tools that would
basically change different
events, hide nodes while
scrolling the page, and then
read off those frame numbers
and the paint numbers.
And then you could very quickly
narrow it down in an
automated fashion on the area
that's causing a problem.
So I think that's the next step,
is how can we get code
around that paint meter, so we
can easily find out where the
problem areas are.
PAUL LEWIS: I think that's
interesting.
But is that in a lab
environment or
is that in the live?
The reason I ask is because if
you're talking about live, say
frames per second, it's very
difficult to separate signal
from noise.
Because you don't know if it's
contention at the OS level, if
it's a badly-configured monitor,
terrible GPU drivers,
contention at the Chrome
level, or browser-level
contention actually within the
page and a bottleneck there.
So just a simple frames per
second probably wouldn't give
you that much.
But in a lab environment, where
you can be pretty sure
that there's nothing else
running and so on, then that
seems to me to be a reasonable
first step.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
I was thinking a lab.
Because right now, if you want
to take a page and figure out
why its rendering performance
is bad, it
takes a lot of work.
So if you could build better
tooling around that in a lab
environment, it can be very fast
to narrow down on where
the problem is.
But you're right.
It's not going to work very well
in the real world today.
ANDRE BEHRENS: I think we have
a question from the room.
James Ide.
JAMES: Hi So for some context,
I feel like a lot of the
performance characteristics of
how browsers work, like a lot
of the things in Jonathan's
slides, are understood by a
lot of web developers.
And the DevTools have
gone great.
Even 11's really great now.
You should check it out.
But understanding how the
browser works is great if
you're a one-man show
and you're building
your own web page.
And as soon as you start to have
a large team working on
your product, it's very easy
for someone to introduce a
regression.
So I'm wondering &mdash;
For example, at Facebook, we
have a library called React,
which helps avoid layouts
thrash when we
render our web pages.
And I'm wondering if there
are, let's say
organizationally scalable APIs
that the browser vendors can
provide to us.
So concretely speaking,
maybe asynchronous
APIs to decode images.
Or asynchronous APIs
to compute the
dimensions a DOM element.
Things that are asynchronous
and slow down
the page right now.
Are there these types of things
that the DOM could
provide to us that you think
would be Helpful
ELI FIDLER: I think that's
actually one of the most
interesting areas of active
development in at least most
of the popular web engines
right now.
Definitely WebKit and Blink
are both working on &mdash;
they call it different things.
But some sort of incremental
layout, where certain
properties, when you request
them from JavaScript, don't
trigger a full re-layout
of the page.
And I can't give you a list
of what works right now or
anything, because
a lot of this is
research code right now.
But this is a very good example
of where the browser
can make things fast without
you changing anything.
So right now, there's a couple
of properties that you ask
for, like Offset Width, that
will trigger a full re-layout
of the entire page.
And it doesn't technically
have to.
But right now, the way that
the engines work,
that's what they do.
So stay tuned.
But there's a lot of things
there that are getting faster
without web developers having
to change things.
In terms of adding new DOM
APIs, we have standards
bodies, and they accept
public comments.
Definitely we've seen a lot
of people providing
that sort of feedback.
ANDRE BEHRENS: We have another
question from Mike Petrovich.
Mic?
MIKE PETROVICH: So to John's
point about synthetic testing,
I know Etsy does synthetic
testing for initial page speed
performance.
But if we did something like
that with using Selenium test.
In that it's a [INAUDIBLE]
environment that would
actually, in a
context-sensitive area
for your app, how
it's meant to work.
Clicking around.
200 milliseconds later, clicking
this other element.
And that's all affected by
different rendering speeds and
also JavaScript evaluations.
So it's more of a real-world
example than just straight up,
how long did it take
to render this?
And it doesn't work at a
generalized level, like
there's usually a consensus.
But on a very contextual
basis.
What about using automated
behavioral tools such as that?
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yes.
We sort of that today
with web page tests.
So Pat's here, he built an
awesome tool that allows you
to do multi-page flows and see
screenshots for every step of
the way, and look at waterfall
that show JavaScript
execution, and even see how long
those things are taking,
and even monitor CPU during
that process.
So that's, I think, the best
proxy we have for it today.
But again, one of the
challenging things is that we
can't currently get data on
frame rate or paint events out
of the browser through an API.
So that's where you run
into that wall.
So you can get part of the way
there, but you still can't
calculate how long a paint
takes, as far as I'm aware.
Unless you patch
Chrome, maybe.
I don't know.
PAUL LEWIS: Telemetry actually
runs Chrome with a very
specific flag-enabled GPU
benchmarking, which enables a
GPU benchmarking API.
And that will give
you some stuff.
And in fact, that's the
reason telemetry can
get the data out.
The other thing you can do is
connect to DevTools over the
WebSocket, and get it to run
through the thing, pull off
the timeline data, and
then check for paint
records and so forth.
So there are things there.
They are not, I would say, that
easily grunt task-able,
and just easily inserted into
your workflow today.
And I think that's something
I'm very interested in, is
whether we can actually make
that a thing that's easy for
developers to just include
in their build steps.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: A good example
of the use of telemetry is
Adobe's topcoat project.
I think they have a fantastic
dashboard that shows how long
does it take to render a
button for every single
revision of the code,
of the CSS.
So if you accidentally change
the CSS and it slows down the
rendering of the button, then
you'll know it immediately.
I think this is all using
Chrome telemetry.
ANDRE BEHRENS: All right.
Next question.
[INAUDIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: Yup.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Microphone.
AUDIENCE: So the question
is, how can we track the
performance detriment that
third-party scripts, such as
ads, social buttons, or anything
you want to add, have
on rendering performance?
And steps to mediate that
without being too hacky.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Come
back in two hours.
[LAUGHTER]
PAUL LEWIS: I think profile.
You should know how your
app is running.
And then you should know what
happens when you add that
thing in, and see what
the change is.
If it's hideous, then you
need to make a decision.
I think operating blindly
with your code is a
very dangerous approach.
For me it is fairly simple.
Get used to the tools
that are available.
They are great tools.
And just go make sure you
understand how it runs before
and after the third-party
script, to know whether it was
worth adding it in.
Because anything you add
is going to have a tax.
it's just whether you're
happy to pay the tax.
That's really the question.
ELI FIDLER: When we've talked a
lot about painting, we find
that a lot of the issues about
badly-written third-party code
is not so much about painting,
but about adding extra event
handlers, or doing busy
work when other
things could be happening.
And the remote Web Inspector
from DevTools, or whatever's
available on all the browsers
today, are really good at
showing, you had a scroll event,
and somebody had an
on-scroll handler, and it ran
for five seconds, and it came
from Facebook.
Facebook doesn't actually have
a scroll handler that takes
five seconds.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDRE BEHRENS: So let's
go onto the next one.
Edd Sowden.
EDD SOWDEN: This was an
anonymous question.
"What is the easiest thing
browser vendors could do to
make it easy for developers to
optimize the performance of
their sites?
[LAUGHTER]
JONATHAN KLEIN: No one?
JOSHUA PEEK: It's just the
YSlow question again.
What are these magic
things you can do?
JONATHAN KLEIN: I think more
to that point &mdash; we talked
about this in the last
session, actually.
Because browsers are now being
put on watches and glasses in
really low-end phones, it's
hard to say what can the
browsers do to just make
our jobs easier.
Because devices keep getting
lower-powered.
So I think we're going to keep
seeing new environments for
browsers to operate in.
And it's hard to say,
the browser's
will just fix it all.
PAUL LEWIS: More tools.
That's the only thing
I think of.
More tools.
But that's got to be balanced.
Because you want &mdash;
If you've ever used tracing.
Tracing is brilliant.
But it's overwhelming at first
when you hit that thing.
You're like, what have you
just done to my eyes.
So here has to be balance.
For example, you can't actually
drill down in Chrome
DevTools today inside
paint records.
The know that you spent some
time painting, but you don't
know what was painted.
We recently added details on
image decode and resize so
that you know which image was
decoded and resized, which is
invaluable.
So we can continue to iterate
and improve the tools so that
you're in no doubt as to where
your bottlenecks came from.
But to make your life
easier, you're the
ones writing the code.
ELI FIDLER: I make browsers, so
I need you to answer that
question for me.
But one thing that I always ask
when I go to conferences
like this is I talk to web
developers and I say, what are
the tools that you need that
would tell you things that you
can actually act on?
So when I ask, what
do you need?
And people tell me, I want to
know what's going on in the
paint record.
And then you say, oh, but that
will be different tomorrow, or
that will be different on
different device by an order
of magnitude, which it often is,
that becomes information
that's very difficult
for them to act on.
So there are some developers who
deliberately target every
single device out there with
individualized code.
But those developers are very
rare, when you have the kind
of money and time to
spend on that.
So tell us what you
need to know.
And we will try to
make that happen.
Also, we try to just make
everything fast.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: So I have this
gut feeling that in the near
future, the rendering
performance tool, especially
with painting, will fall
into two categories.
One is how to improve from 10
frames per second to 30, and
the other one is how to go
from 40 to 60 or 58 to 60
frames per second.
Because what you're looking
for is that quick fix.
So that instead of 10, you run
up to 30 frames per second.
ANDRE BEHRENS: And you
had a question?
AUDIENCE: Just to say, one thing
that you can do is tell
us there is a problem.
So I think, granted, we don't
have best practices exactly at
how to solve it.
I get the point about doing
synthetic testing.
But most people on the panel
agreed that the profile of how
many frames per second you
get varies per device.
And of course, you can't
simulate all these different
situations.
If we had some sort of real
user monitoring at least
telling us, hey, there is a
problem on whatever Android
device X on this page frequently
enough, then that
would motivate me to go buy that
device and run some more
test just to balance the
different effects.
Even ahead of having the best
practices for exactly how
would I fix my codes
to make it go away.
JONATHAN KLEIN: I think
that's a great point.
And something that that brings
to mind is with the YSlow tool
release and the web performance
movement that's
been going on for the past 10
years, we've had a lot of
studies that come out, saying,
look at the top 1,000 Alexa
sites, and how bad they are,
and these best practices.
That hasn't happened yet,
I think, with rendering
performance.
So I think it'd be useful just
to have somebody go out and
look at popular sites, and be
like, look, there are problems
here on these devices,
on these browsers.
And just expose it on a wider
basis so that people are aware
of the problem.
Because I think in this
community, it's
obviously well known.
But I think in the wider
community people don't think
as much about rendering
performance.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: Does anyone know
if Google reduces page
rank for sites that are slow?
[LAUGHTER]
ARIYA HIDAYAT: I'm not saying.
No idea.
I'm just asking.
I have no idea.
ANDRE BEHRENS: All right.
Our next question comes
from Dunston Castin.
DUNSTON: Hey.
So my experience with paint
performance usually drops
frames with garbage collection
events and memory management.
What responsibility should web
developers take on for those
two things, memory management
and garbage collection?
PAUL LEWIS: OK.
So the immediate thing is that
GC causes jank because GC's
almost guaranteed to push you
over that frame budget of 16
milliseconds.
Your only option is to
try and avoid GC.
This, I think, depends on how
big a problem this is for you.
How much memory churn you
actually have, how much time
garbage collection is actually
taking, and how often it runs.
Which is going to be very
specific to your own
application.
There are things.
On HTML5 Rocks, we have an
article about using static
memory pools to recycle
objects and so forth.
You're avoiding object creation,
which tends to be
good for GC.
But personally speaking,
I don't believe it's &mdash;
People have requested, can we
have a garbage collection API?
And I would be concerned about
a browser including that,
because that one could get
really hairy very quickly.
ANDRE BEHRENS: What would
be the problems?
PAUL LEWIS: The browser is
uniquely positioned to &mdash;
Your page is not the
only thing that's
running in the browser.
So it's in a unique position
to know when
garbage should be collected.
And if you were to force the
issue, you may, basically,
make the wrong call.
This is one of these times
where, as I say, the browser
is the one that has all the
information and knows when
it's the right time to
pick up garbage.
Ideally, you want it to do it
at the best point for every
application that's running.
But that's the nature
of [INAUDIBLE].
ARIYA HIDAYAT: What if the GC
API is just a strong hint for
the browser to do garbage
[INAUDIBLE]
when it's possible?
PAUL LEWIS: So if you do that,
then what happens if it
ignores you?
Or you get different browsers
ignoring you
at different times?
Is it any better than
the browser just
making the call itself?
ARIYA HIDAYAT: But that's the
same situation like the
translateZ layer hacks, right?
PAUL LEWIS: Yeah.
No, exactly.
And so some of this stuff is
just real-world, yeah, we're
just going to do
this right now.
We wish we didn't, because
we just want to get
stuff that runs well.
ELI FIDLER: We've gotten
complaints, mostly from sites
that do permanent animation
all the time,
that GCs are a problem.
And that's things like games.
And if you're writing something
that is truly
interrupted by GCs on a regular
basis, then you just
have to create less garbage.
But building a game that's going
to run at 60 FPS while
doing complicated things is a
hard problem no matter what
environment it's running in and
no matter what language
you're running it in.
So you can't expect that the
browser's just going
to do it for you.
And I don't think that you could
make an easy decision,
even if you had a guaranteed
API that said, GC now?
You couldn't make an easy
decision about when
to call that API.
ANDRE BEHRENS: I'm curious.
We hear again and again when
we talk about rendering
performance, we have to test,
we have to look, we have to
look at specific things.
What is the brightest sign of
hope for the next thing that's
going to be easier to handle?
I'm curious, if anyone
has a perspective.
PAUL LEWIS: When you say
easier to handle &mdash;
ANDRE BEHRENS: In the sense of
the timeline view, made at
least getting a handle on
it easier than it was.
You could actually see it.
I know the inability to
see pictures in the &mdash;
[INAUDIBLE]
seen picture decode and say, oh,
that was a picture decode.
That's what that thing was.
Having that show up in
the tools is a easier
thing to deal with.
Is there anything that either
is going to go away or is
going to be much easier
to test for?
PAUL LEWIS: In terms of going
away, from Chrome perspective,
image decodes and resizes
are, at the
moment, extremely expensive.
And as we all probably
know, 60% of the
average page is images.
So if you can fix image decoding
and resizing as a
bottleneck, that helps
enormously with that problem.
So our engineers are definitely
looking at ways to
make that a thing.
The other that you often
see is the main thread.
The contention on the main
thread being so high such that
work can't continue, and the
app becomes unresponsive.
And we're looking at ways of
reducing the workload.
That doesn't always necessarily
mean firing off
more threads, which I think is
the sometimes mooted idea.
Which is, in Chrome's case,
we have a fairly
thread-heavy app.
So just creating more threads
wouldn't necessarily solve it.
So what you actually want
to do is do the work
in a smarter way.
So, for example, putting more
work that is suitable for the
GPU to go to the GPU,
that kind of stuff.
From a developer's point of
view, none of that actually
requires action other than try
and reduce the work that
you're doing, which has
always been the case.
If you're layout-bound try
and reduce layout.
Even if layout gets faster in
the browser, you still want to
do less of it.
Performance is the
art of doing the
least amount of work.
ANDRE BEHRENS: I think we have
a question from the crowd.
Suraj.
Yes.
Microphone.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I have a very simple question.
So a few weeks ago, I was
developing this web
application.
I don't have any complicated
CSS going on, no timeouts,
very simple layout.
But it just uses a
lot of images.
So it [INAUDIBLE] images from
Picasa and it shows it to you.
And it's just slow.
Especially the first time, the
rendering performance is just
really bad.
So what, as a developer, I
can do to increase that
performance?
PAUL LEWIS: That is a tough one
right now, if I'm honest.
From my point of view,
we don't have &mdash;
so when the page is rasterizing,
it does the image
decodes and resizes in line
as a sort of dependency.
It gets this draw bitmap where
it goes, OK, now I need to
draw an image.
And I need to decode
that image and
resize it if necessary.
And then I can actually
rasterize it into the page.
That all happens in line.
If it was decoupled from the
rasterization and there was a
gap where it was, then it
appeared later, that
might be one thing.
But as a developer, there's
not a lot you can do.
Apart from perhaps batch in your
images, is something you
could potentially look at.
Because if it's all
done on demand &mdash;
So again, this is from a
Chrome prospective &mdash;
it looks at what it needs
to rasterize.
If that's 30 images, 30 images
are going to get queued up for
decoding and resizing
in one go.
It depends on the app, but it
might be better to hold off
and go, can I do these
one by one?
Or just over a few frames
so that I'm not hitting
everything at once.
That sometimes may be a thing.
But I offer advice without
knowing the
application in detail.
So use it wisely.
[LAUGHTER]
ARIYA HIDAYAT: Does it need
to show all of those
30 images at once?
AUDIENCE: Not really.
And that was one of the
things I tried to do.
To just show that images,
whatever is
visible in one page size.
But even then, first time, you
are getting, let's say,
images, it's visibly slow.
And I've seen similar pattern
in other websites, too,
well-known websites.
So I wasn't sure if there's
anything that can
be done about it.
PAUL LEWIS: We are trying to
get reduced the tax that is
levied for decodes
and resizes.
ELI FIDLER: We just do a whole
panel talking about images.
Images are expensive.
Having to touch every pixel in
an image and doing decodes and
things like that is an
expensive operation.
There's fundamentally no way
around the fact that we have
to do a lot of work when
we show images.
But the techniques that were
talked about in the last
panel &mdash; especially if you
control your images.
In your case, you may not.
But putting low-quality images
in as placeholders, and then
asynchronously bringing in
higher-quality versions.
Or carefully choosing what types
of images that you're
using, what compression formats,
that sort of thing,
for whatever's fast for your
specific operation is
something that you can do to
optimize image-heavy sites.
But fundamentally, images
are expensive.
There's no way around that.
PAUL LEWIS: It's interesting, as
a side note, that when the
last panel was talking,
there was a lot of
discussion about bandwidth.
And that's only part of the
picture when you're talking
about images.
Which is, the other side of this
is, how long, then, does
it take me to decode
it and resize it?
So you actually need a
full understanding.
You could save time on the
transfer of an image, yay.
And then have something that is
actually really horrible to
decode, or is horrible to resize
on the other side.
So your overall picture is
actually either worse or the
same or better.
But you need to understand the
whole lifecycle of an image to
actually know whether or not
you're doing the right thing.
And also, the low-quality
placeholder switched out with
a high-res one could
be really good.
But then you're also trading off
the fact that you probably
have a second request to get
your higher-res image.
So it's not just straightforward
often anyway.
And it's very specific to your
app what it is that's
worthwhile doing.
ARIYA HIDAYAT: It'll be
interesting to see if, in the
near future, instead of a single
CPU alone responsible
for images, we could
GPAC co-processors.
Ooh.
ANDRE BEHRENS: I
think we have a
question from Jake Archibald.
ELI FIDLER: While he's getting
the mic, image decoding is
actually hardware-accelerated
in many cases.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So on the
scrolling-to-load-images
thing, like when they're out of
you, use a scroll event to
bring the images in, I just
wanted to point out that
that's a massive anti-pattern
on mobile.
Because if the radio falls
asleep, any device with a
cellular connection, waking
that radio up comes with a
huge latency and will
ruin the battery.
On the resource priority spec,
we've got a new attribute
called Postpone, which
hands that
power back to the browser.
And lets the browser
render without &mdash;
it can defer the image loading,
downloading, if it's
out of view.
PAUL LEWIS: As well as
deferring the image
downloading, I'd actually love
the ability to defer it
decoding as well.
I don't see why you'd have
one not the other.
Don't load this.
OK, do load it.
Fine.
But don't decode it.
OK, do decode it, it's fine.
That seems to go hand-in-hand
to me.
Unless I'm crazy.
It's possible.
ELI FIDLER: That's exactly the
magic of Web Audio for Audio.
Because decoding the audio is
expensive, so you want to do
it first so it's ready.
Maybe we can do Web
Audio for images.
Somebody write a spec.
PAUL LEWIS: That's
a great idea.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Next question.
Matt Todd.
MATT TODD: This is an
enormous question.
What have been the biggest wins
and wastes of time at
real websites?
And I think balancing that
between front-end developers
and web developers, but also
from browser implementation
development, what have been
really rewarding endeavors and
what have been huge wastes of
time to have taken more time
to actually produce any
kind of benefit?
ELI FIDLER: We still see a lot
of sites that, in busy loops,
add one node to the DOM and then
ask for a property that
requires you to do a layout,
and then add a note to the
DOM, and then ask for a property
that requires a
layout, in a really
tight loop.
And this is a huge
anti-pattern.
We've been telling people
this forever.
Most people are pretty good
about batching nodes dumped
into the DOM and that
sort of thing.
But still, a ton of people
do this all the time.
JOSHUA PEEK: I feel like that
doesn't happen so much where
you see the tight loop.
But it's more so that you
have all these other
components on the page.
Where one will add something
to the DOM, and something
unrelated can trigger
to compute stop.
And it just happens as
you render this page.
So a lot of it's
uncoordinated.
It's not these little tight &mdash;
The tight loop things,
I think, for
painting and rendering.
But a lot of people just have
all these components.
And then some affect the DOM
and some require reading.
So I think you see that among
just having a ton of
stuff on your page.
PAUL LEWIS: From my point of
view, the biggest waste of
time I think I've seen would
be CSS selector matching,
which is remarkably fast.
And if you're optimizing your
selectors for matching, it's
probably not something you're
going to see every turn on.
The thing that I've seen the
most use come from would be
promoting for isolation, putting
elements onto their
own layer when they're
frequently painted.
That's the one I've seen
work the most.
JOSHUA PEEK: I agree mostly on
the selector matching stuff.
But if you look at some really
huge DOMs, that have maybe
like 30,000 nodes, and
you have just a
buildup of all the CSS.
And typically people have so
many descendant selectors that
just target an anchor element.
And if you add a ton of anchor
elements in this DOM, that's
going to add up.
So it's not that every rule
matters, but there's ones that
you can call out.
PAUL LEWIS: Right.
For sure.
But I would argue that was a
fairly extreme case, unless
I'm misunderstanding
your description.
I think for most people and most
applications where the
DOM is not 30,000 nodes &mdash;
Wow.
JOSHUA PEEK: It's a GitHub
commit difs.
PAUL LEWIS: Boom.
ELI FIDLER: We see a lot
of sites that are
over 100,000 nodes.
PAUL LEWIS: Really?
Wow.
I'm just going to let that
sink in for a bit.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Jonathan,
I was wondering what
your experience was.
JOSHUA PEEK: At Etsy,
unfortunately, the big winds
have been removing content or
removing design elements.
So removing drop shadows off of
every element on the page.
Things like getting rid
of animated carousels.
Sometimes those things are hard
to pass through, because
the designers or the UX people
really want that.
But at the end of the day,
you have to test it.
And if people want a jank-free
experience more than they want
drop shadows, then that's what
you should give them.
ANDRE BEHRENS: We have a
question from John Mung.
JOHN: Hi.
We've talk about images,
decoding and resizing being
very expensive.
Do we know of any example
libraries or example
implementations that use web
workers and transferable
objects to have a significant
impact on this?
PAUL LEWIS: Oh dear.
Yes.
I did do, actually, an
experiment with this one where
I actually created canvas
elements for all the images
and used workers to decode
and resize the images.
So you can do it, is
the first answer.
Whether you should do it becomes
the next question.
And no would be &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
PAUL LEWIS: Because
you have to manage
all the images yourself.
Is it in view?
Is it decoded already?
Have I decoded this
thing before?
All these things that the
browser does fantastically
well for you, you are
now having to
take care of yourself.
And you could shoot yourself
in the foot so hard and so
fast that I feel duty-bound to
say, you can do it, but don't.
But you can do it.
And it's cool.
ELI FIDLER: Especially on
mobile, I think it will
definitely, definitely
not be a win.
So even if you can get the
image decoded a couple of
milliseconds faster, the amount
of time that you're
going to be moving pixels
around, saturating your memory
bus and the battery impact of
running these web workers at
the same time is going to be
way, way worse than just
decoding the images normally.
PAUL LEWIS: Because you're going
to spawn a new worker.
So you haven't got enough cause
on mobile, probably, to
support that decision.
And it's going to be slower
because it's JavaScript.
But you are in control.
You are in total control.
So that's the trade
off you're making.
Control for all that.
ANDRE BEHRENS: OK.
We have another question
from Sergei.
SERGEI: We've had a lot of
challenges explaining network
performance, basically the
other side of performance
through designers and
businesspeople.
And a lot of rendering
performance, actually, is much
closer to the product they might
actually understand.
Do you have any suggestions on
how we organize the process
for making them understand all
these sides of the issues.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Jonathan?
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
I think similar to network
performance, you have to show
it to them.
And in a lot of cases, it's a
lot easier to see rendering
improvements being
problematic.
Especially if you have low-end
devices that you can show
people with.
So I think it's a question of
getting it in front of them.
And like you said, it's
closer to the product.
It's closer to the design
side of things.
So I think it should be easier
for those people to have a bit
more intuitive.
But I think demonstration
is the best option.
ANDRE BEHRENS: Yeah.
ELI FIDLER: I think also demoing
on cellular instead of
Wi-Fi helps a lot.
If I'm just demoing on a
constrained device, pick one.
Look.
Slow.
Fast.
Which would you rather ship?
the 10-speed's pretty
easy then, I think.
Or easier.
JONATHAN KLEIN: And then one
thing that was really
successful for WPU was just
business metrics.
And we have some of
that data now.
It's starting to come out
from Facebook and SE.
So I think showing that
information is really
important, to say, this
doesn't really impact
engagement.
We have a question
from Paul lrish.
PAUL IRISH: I think I was going
to mostly ask about the
same sort of thing, but I'm
interested in ways to
communicate what the impact.
Because network performance,
page load time, is a really
easy metric.
We can track that across
browsers, across different
connectivity.
Rendering perf.
There's not much in the way
of numbers that we can
demonstrate, say, this is the
impact that I had, or this is
where our problem's
at right now.
We need to bring it down here.
So do you have any ideas on
making things a bit more
quantitative so that management
and clients can
really see the impact that we
have, and then understand that
there is a problem that
we need to solve
before we get into it.
JONATHAN KLEIN: Yeah.
That's a great question.
Because everyone quotes
these stats.
Like 100 milliseconds on
Amazon was 1% revenue.
But you can't say like 3 frames
per second was half a
present revenue or something
like that.
So I think we just have to have
real studies that have
been done by real companies.
And ideally, companies that
are in your market.
So again, it's a
tough problem.
But I think we just need to
have more people doing
experiments.
And be willing to slow down
half their traffic to 30
frames per second and
see what happens.
PAUL LEWIS: We are now at the
point where the browser is
capable of 60 frames a second,
which hasn't always been true.
But now that it is, we're
playing catch-up with the page
load time part of the
performance, and now we need
to ask that question.
Say, as an industry, as a body
of developers, we are
interested, I hope, in seeing
how the actual runtime
experience affects our
users, and how much
it affects our users.
Because we don't know today, is
at the same, is it less, is
it more than the
page load time?
Because they load once,
hopefully, and run
it for a long time.
So 100 milliseconds different on
rendering for page load is
a very different deal to
repeatedly hitting them with
100 miliseconds.
But we don't know
how big that is.
So we don't have a good answer,
I don't think, on how
much it affects the
bottom line.
But I think we need to find
out, and pretty quickly.
ANDRE BEHRENS: All right.
I think that about wraps
it up for us.
Are we ready for lunch?
[LAUGHTER]
ANDRE BEHRENS: Oh, someone has
a microphone ready to go?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
ANDRE BEHRENS: That's fine.
AUDIENCE: One question.
My biggest problem with
rendering performance is that
I cannot describe my intent
to the browser.
I cannot describe my intent that
I want this element to
have higher priority when
branded over another.
And I think that's the biggest
problem for me which we're
talking rendering performance.
That the browser is making false
assumptions of what my
intent is in my layout out.
And I think this goes together
with images.
This image should be rendered
before that.
This box should be rendered
before this box.
And what are we doing to look
into that so I, as a
developer, can declare my intend
to the browser so the
browser can make or the
rendering agent can make a
more intelligent guess of how
things should be composed when
layoutting.
Because now we're talking
about translateZ.
That is, to me, a hack.
First of all, it is
not hardware &mdash;
[INAUDIBLE] hardware
restoration in IE.
And as a web developer, I
shouldn't know about layers.
That's an implementation
detail in
the rendering engine.
I just want to declare my intent
that this layer is
either higher or lower priority,
and then you guys
should figure out the rest.
Are we looking into
these things?
Is there any proposals
coming up?
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE].
No?
Nobody [INAUDIBLE]?
PAUL LEWIS: First of all, the
browser should do everything
for me is one thing I would
want to pick up on.
I don't know how much
I agree with that.
I don't think I agree
with that.
The way I would normally phrase
this is if you write
spec compliant code, you should
expect spec compliant
responses from the browser.
But there is no promise
of performance.
Now, the promise comes
through the fact that
everybody wants fast code.
Browser vendors want to give
you fast implementations.
And so that's something you
should seek and you should ask
for and you should push
for, definitely.
But I think it's very difficult
to, hand-on-heart,
say any programmer should be
completely divorced from the
system they're programming on.
I can't quite bring myself
to say that.
I think it would be a nice
thing, but I don't think
that's realistic.
Is that something that we
are looking to improve?
Yeah, always.
I think there's always
a definite
balancing act of APIs.
If they're overly prescriptive
and you don't get enough
control, then you end up with
what I think is the App Cache
situation, where you can't
bridge that gap.
At least if it's too difficult
or it's a horrible API &mdash;
and I would argue that things
like WebGL are very, very
horrible from a developer's
point of view.
But at least you can
polyfill that.
You can at least add on
something like 3JS.
so I'd rather it's
that way around.
But it comes through developer
feedback, saying we don't
think this works.
We don't like this.
ANDRE BEHRENS: OK.
And I think that is really it.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDREW BETTS: Thanks
very much.
So we have a 15 minute
break now.
So go ahead and have some
snacks, go to the loo.
Back in 15 minutes.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ANDREW BETTS: Steve.
Right.
You're next.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
ANDREW BETTS: Then bring up &mdash;
[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BETTS: Hi everyone.
We're going to get started again
in a few minutes' time.
So make your way back
to your seats.
Thanks very much.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BETTS: OK everyone.
Can you take a seat, because
we're going to get started
with the next session now.
So please come back and
take your seats.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ANDREW BETTS: So are you
doing his slides?
STEVE THAIR: Yeah.
ANDREW BETTS: That works.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ANDREW BETTS: OK.
We'll make a start now.
Our next session is one that
I've been really looking
forward to.
Hey everyone.
STEVE THAIR: Grab a set!
ANDREW BETTS: Thank you Steve.
[STEVE WHISTLES]
ANDREW BETTS: This next session
is one I've been
really looking forward to.
Because most large content
publishers, including the FT,
have a lot of third-party
scripts that they
put on their websites.
And managing those scripts and
managing the performance, the
implications of having a lot of
third-party scripts can be
a really trying experience for
a lot of web developers.
And it's certainly a
challenge that we
struggle with every day.
So to moderate this panel, we
have my friend Steve Thair
who, I'm sure, will
introduce himself
and his panel admirably.
So I'll give it to Steve.
STEVE THAIR: Thanks, Andrew.
Thank you.
Thank you, Barb.
Hi.
My name's Steve Thair.
I run the London Web Performance
user group and I
run WebPerfDays in London.
So performance of third-party
scripts is a really big area
for us, and we debate
it endlessly.
I'll quickly introduce you
to the people on a panel.
On my right, I've got the &mdash;
Well, if we're going to do a
drug dealer analogy, these are
the guys who are actually
producing the stuff.
We've got Ben Vinegar
from Disqus.
Discussions and comments
you'll have
seen on many websites.
We've got Stoyan Stefanov from
Facebook, who is Like buttons
and those Facebook widgets
that you like
to put on your page.
And over here, we've got Guy
Podjarny from Akamai, who's
like the middle man, the
distribution network for the
stuff that they're dealing.
And then we've got &mdash;
well, I was going to say
addict, but that's
probably not right.
We've got Barbara Bermes from
the Canadian Broadcasting
Corporation.
She's the end user, this poor
person that's having all of
these scripts.
She has to deal with her
customers, the people on the
marketing team who never
met a third-party
script they didn't like.
And they just want to
stick a [INAUDIBLE]
on the page, and she's got to
deal with all of those issues.
So we're going to kick off
with a presentation from
Stoyan just to set
the scene on what
third-party stuff means.
Just remember, obviously we've
got the on slide stuff.
So try and use that as
much as you can.
Come in, give positive and
negative feedback.
And obviously, put your
hand up on slide
if you want to talk.
Thank you.
[INAUDIBLE].
STOYAN STEFANOV: Thank
you Steven.
All right.
So welcome to the third-party
party, where we party like
it's 1995, because in many ways,
it is 1995 when it comes
to third-party widgets.
So I'm hoping we can have a
nice discussion on how to
bring this party to today
and tomorrow.
Slide, please.
So Steven now did the same thing
that I was planning to.
So he stole my thunder, of
presenting the widget makers
versus the consumers.
I can only add that Steven
is also on the upside.
He's social on Barbara's side.
Protecting.
STEVE THAIR: Impartial
moderator.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Protecting the
publishers from all the
extravagance we put out there.
All right.
So just a quick overview.
Third-party content comes mostly
in the form of script
that you include on the page.
It may not do anything
visible.
It may be something like
Google Analytics.
Or you put an iFrame on
the page coming from a
third-party.
Or the state of the art used
to be that you do both.
You include a script that writes
an iFrame for you.
So that we focus, we want to
talk more about how we deal
with scripts than iFrames.
You're including JavaScript
on the page coming from
somewhere, you don't know, you
have no control over, coming
over the network.
So what could possibly
go wrong with that?
Well, obviously, there's
a security issue.
And Ben wanted to bring up a
recent attack on Outbrain,
which is a producer
of third-party
recommendation engine.
So it was attacked by Syrian
Army folks who were able to
mess with our JavaScript.
And in this way, affect
all the pages
that use their service.
So let's say, for example, they
could redirect all the
visitors to "Washington Post"
to some other page.
So I think if you're an
attacker, if you're a
malicious person, why would
you try to break into all
these websites, where you can do
your one-stop shopping and
break into a third-party widget
provider and have
control over so many websites.
So security is obviously
a big one.
And then you have the SPOF, or
single point of failure, where
if a page includes a script
synchronously, they add a
single point of failure.
And despite the fact that we
have now good tools from Pat
Meenan's SPOF-O-matic extension
for Chrome.
And also, you are able to find
SPOF using web page test.
But it seems like that still
tends to be an issue.
Which is pretty silly, because
if the third-party provider is
blocked in a country or an
enterprise, that means your
site is effectively blocked
as well, or black-holed.
And then there's all the
performance issues that
anything you add on the page
will add to the rendering time
and loading time and all that.
All right.
So what does the
state-of-the-art
of the script include?
So despite all the evangelism
for using asynchronous
scripts, people are still
using scripts tags.
And sometimes the widget
providers on the marketing
side will prefer that,
because it's easier.
You just have one script
tag instead of a
little bit of code.
So that's pretty bad.
There is currently some things
on the crazier side, like
using frame-in-frame, loading
JavaScript inside of a iFrame.
Or when you write an
iFrame, write it
inside of another iFrame.
So the first iFrame container
is blank, so it's not in the
way of the window
onload event.
So this is for people who still
care about the window
[INAUDIBLE] onload and
whenever it happens.
Not as easy or friendly to
copy-paste, but it exists.
Something else.
So the thing about third-party
JavaScript is they are
notoriously being very
short-lived.
10, 15 minutes, half an hour.
And the reason is so that the
third-party provider can push
fixes and security updates
very quickly.
But that's bad for performance,
because we cannot
use future expires header.
So there's this technique of,
again, using an iFrame and
reloading that iFrame
that causes
this group to be refreshed.
So we can have a third-party
JavaScript with a far future
expires header.
I don't know if anyone's
doing it currently.
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE].
STOYAN STEFANOV: [INAUDIBLE].
All right.
And then there's stuff that's
coming out from the WebPerf
W3C group, which I was hoping
someone can enlighten us
what's going on there
with the progress.
Right.
Next.
Oh yeah.
There's this idea about
what I call C3PO, or
Common 3rd Party Object.
So this is something that I put
up some time ago, and then
Ben said that he's been thinking
about the same thing,
but we never really
got to talk.
So I think that's as
good a time as any.
So the views of those scripts
that are included from third
parties usually do
the same thing.
They hunt the page for
any hints where the
iFrame should go.
So they look at the DOM and then
write an iFrame, and then
resize the iFrame because
the content doesn't fit.
Let's say you have a Like button
in German, which is a
longer word.
So you have to resize the iFrame
not to take more space
than needed.
And a lot of widget providers
are doing the same thing.
So what if we can have one
script that is open source
that handles this for
most of the widgets?
So this means that the publisher
can include the
script and package it however
they want with their scripts,
and handle all the widgets.
Or we download five, six scrips
with 100, 200K instead
of having just 0 requests.
So that is the idea.
Meanwhile, what we have in the
near future coming up.
So we have now Web Components.
I don't know if anyone's
using Web Components.
If not, why not?
It seems like the widgets are
the best use case for Web
Components.
Then I'm thinking, is it any
easier on the publisher's side
to include a Web Component
instead of the current state,
where you include a dif class
something, end the script.
There's the iFrame Sandbox.
It's really cool.
Should we encourage people
to use it or not?
What would this allow in
a third-party widget?
So there was the idea
of seamless iFrame.
Seems like it's not
going away.
The same with the
iFrame scrdoc.
I don't know what's
the state of that.
Is it dying as well?
So we can talk about it.
STEVE THAIR: We just got
a negative vote.
[LAUGHTER]
MALE SPEAKER: [INAUDIBLE]
STOYAN STEFANOV: Content
security policy.
It exists.
It's out there.
What should we do about it?
Should we encourage people to
use it, providers as well as
publishers?
I'm curious to hear
your thoughts.
But meanwhile, what
happens now &mdash;
and Barbara can talk about
this from the publisher's
perspective.
So she said that sites are
now bombarded by scripts.
There's too much
stuff going on.
And she is also, like Steven
said, challenging anyone to
stand between the marketing
people and their widgets.
So how do you monitor
third-party widgets?
Do people set a budgets
and say, OK, you have
this amount of time.
How do we keep the third-parties
in track?
Also, how do we deal with some &mdash;
because not all the
third party code is
very well-written.
So how do people deal with the
scripts that have to do
document.write and so on.
Guy brought a good question
about according to the HTTP
archive, the number of
the main [INAUDIBLE]
website he's using isn't going
up, is increasing.
And it can be largely attributed
to third parties.
So what can we do to fix this?
And he has some ideas.
Some borderline crazy, like
coping cookies from one domain
to the other.
Some maybe more manageable,
like, what if we use the same
domain name for all the static
resources and script and
styles and sprites, and shared
between all the third parties.
So instead of loading something
from Facebook,
Akamai.net, whatever, why don't
we use something else,
like common domain name.
C3PO comes to mind.
STEVE THAIR: I think it would
be C3PO.Akamai.com.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Oh, mobile.
Right.
It's finally here.
Yay.
What does it mean for widgets?
Is it only just making
performance
issues even more visible?
Should we do something
about it?
Are people using that many
widgets on mobile websites?
Curious to know.
I think that's all I had.
Let's talk about
all this stuff.
[APPLAUSE]
STEVE THAIR: Thanks
very much, Stoyan.
I'm just going to do a quick
poll of the panel.
Guy, any quick comments from
Stoyan's opening talk?
GUY PODJARNY: Sure, maybe
I'll add a couple.
One is, in general,
third-party's a little bit
broader than that.
I think there's some bias
to think about &mdash;
every person has a bias.
But there's also tracking
beacons, which for some
websites are plentiful and often
come in, often, in the
form of an image.
And there are also, actually,
third-party components that
are more inline in your pages.
Also some shopping cart
virtualization components and
such that start to
tread the line.
Because while they're
third-party, they're not
extraneous to the core flow or
requirement of the product.
But there's still a concern in
all sorts of things, like
number of domains and
reliability concerns.
Security concern is still very
much valid for them.
So that's one point.
And then the second one is just
to highlight the aspect
of the number of domains.
There's basically the problems
with third parties that have
to do with best practices around
how to use them, how to
write them.
If you're an author of them, to
try and get them out of the
way as much as possible
while still keeping
them reasonably fast.
And there's also things that
are just trends, like the
number of domains or like the
existence of unoptimized
third-party scripts that use
document.write whether you
like it or not.
And those are just paths that,
to me, are more interesting
because as far as I know,
there's no good set to advance
us in the right direction.
[INAUDIBLE]
fix those.
STEVE THAIR: Barbara?
BARBARA BERMES: For me,
I'm basically in
the middle of both.
So I want to make sure that the
developers understand what
third-party scripts really do
to your page, and also the
business side, to tell them what
to look for when asking
third-party providers to
provide their code.
STEVE THAIR: So you're saying
it's not really possible to
tell the marketing department
they can't have that piece of
code because it has a
document.write in it, because
they just won't understand.
BARBARA BERMES: Exactly.
You've got to explain to them
what the impact actually is,
and they don't always
understand that.
STEVE THAIR: Good.
Cool.
So Ben, as a provider, what
would you say about Stoyan's
opening remarks?
BEN VINEGAR: They're really
good comments.
It's been set up that this whole
panel is sort of like,
if you're a website publisher
then third-party scripts are
mean and we're villians.
Also Stoyan.
But I want to flip
this around.
Maybe people aren't thinking
that as a third-party
developer that has a pretty
complex application that I'm
serving to publish your pages,
there are publishers that are
doing really bad things to me
and I would love to talk about
some of those.
And what can &mdash;
[LAUGHTER]
BEN VINEGAR: Yes!
And I don't even mean that &mdash;
partially as a joke.
But it can be subjects, like
people immediately attribute
performance issues to a
third-party script.
That's the first place
that they go.
Where I'm debugging publishers'
websites, and then
I attribute, basically,
the performance
problems back to them.
So I'm sort of in a
hard spot as well.
And I think that's possibly
worth discussing.
STEVE THAIR: Cool.
I think we've actually got a
couple questions about how we
can find and identify those
performance bottlenecks.
But first question we've got on
the floor is actually from
Yoav Weiss.
Yoav &mdash;
Oh, you're down there.
YOAV WEISS: Hi.
"What are the mechanisms for
enabling script loading based
on media queries, and is
there a valid proposal?
And how can we get
this pushed?"
STEVE THAIR: So this is the idea
of if I've got a script
that is just not relevant to
the device that I'm running
on, why am I downloading
it in the first place?
YOAV WEISS: Exactly.
It relates to the
mobile thing.
If I don't show a Like button
on mobile, why am I
downloading the script?
STEVE THAIR: Do you want to
start taking that one?
STOYAN STEFANOV: I don't know.
I'm not aware of any
development.
Are you?
Is there a proposal going on?
YOAV WEISS: I started playing
around with the idea.
It's kind of hard to define what
happens when the media
query changes.
That's where things
get complicated.
Do I want to run the
script or not?
But in general, do you guys
think it's a good idea?
Or is it something that
should be pursued?
STOYAN STEFANOV: It definitely
sounds interesting.
GUY PODJARNY: I'm kind
of fond of it.
So I think the notion of
conditional loading,
especially in responsive design
website, is a really issue.
And in responsive design,
we focus on images,
like we spoke earlier.
But maybe the next looming
problem, if not already here,
is the notion of scripts.
And I regularly see responsive
websites download, execute
scripts and then hide them
because the layout doesn't
quite make sense for them.
So institutionalizing or
standardizing conditional
loading makes perfect
sense to me.
And using media queries seems
like one way to do it.
Not sure if there's any active
conversation about it.
So I guess we're probably going
to need to figure out
all the different
options of it.
But I do think that's a good
path that we need to go down.
BARBARA BERMES: I think also the
idea is interesting, but
I'm also wondering what
are the use cases?
So you would not load, for
example, a Facebook button for
mobile versus desktop
or whatever?
YOAV WEISS: The use cases I
can think of are Facebook
button, or social buttons
in general.
Maps that may or may not be
displayed because you want to
go to the native map.
JQuery Mobile.
UI frameworks.
Where you want to load
jQuery Mobile here
and jQuery UI there.
These are the use cases
I have in mind.
GUY PODJARNY: Twitter streams,
I think, are a common one in
responsive design.
BARBARA BERMES: Or even we are
doing different ad serving for
desktop versus mobile
for example, yeah.
STEVE THAIR: We've
got a couple of
comments from the floor.
Kyle Simpson from Getify.
Did you have something
to say on this topic?
KYLE SIMPSON: I didn't actually
intend to click that.
But I'll just say something
as I do have a question.
[LAUGHTER]
KYLE SIMPSON: Since they
gave me the mic.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
BARBARA BERMES: It's
your time.
KYLE SIMPSON: But on
that topic though.
So there is definitely a
strong push to create
declarative solutions, like
markup-only stuff.
I need to be able to
express all of my
intent through markup.
But I do just want to point out
that there's a vast array
of complex situations that you
make these decisions on.
For instance, I've got a simple
version of a calendar
widget and a complex version
of a calendar widget, and I
make decisions based upon
bandwidth and screen size and
all those other things.
So I think it's troublesome
to say, this is a
one-size-fits-all solution to
try to encode into my markup
when a script should
be loaded.
I'm a little biased, but I feel
that's the job of script
loaders rather than markup.
GUY PODJARNY: I think that's
a valid statement.
But there's also the statement
to say that, especially in
responsive design world, there
are a lot of decisions that
are made based on things that
could have been determined
through screen properties.
So maybe it's not 100%.
And you don't take away the
capability or the value of
loading things through
a more elaborate
script-based loading condition.
But if it's a common enough use
case and you can make it
faster and easier, then I still
think it's a worthy
proposition.
STEVE THAIR: We've got David
Stickman from Akamai wants to
make a comment.
Feel free to disagree with
Guy from Akamai.
[LAUGHTER]
GUY PODJARNY: At
least briefly.
DAVID STICKMAN: Hi.
One of the most common use cases
we see is actually tons
of new domain.
And people tend to do domain
shedding thinking that it's
going to improve the performance
of the website.
But obviously, we're
third-party.
We have 40, 50 different
domains that are
called by the browser.
Is there any way we can give
a hint of what kind of DNS
resolution should be done for
third-party content before
actually loading the
third-party itself?
Because there is a lot of
bottleneck with just DNS
resolution itself.
STEVE THAIR: Anyone?
GUY PODJARNY: I can take
that because I know &mdash;
STEVE THAIR: Yeah.
GUY PODJARNY: So I think the
number of domains, as pointed
out before &mdash;
this has not been coordinated,
just to make sure &mdash;
is a real problem.
It comes into play in DNS.
It comes into play with the fact
that SPDY and HTTP2 and
all sorts of pending solutions
don't touch on it.
They don't try to optimize
across domains.
So I think it's a real
problem today.
There is no deprioritization,
as far as I know, of
third-party content.
You can mark things beyond the
async or the processing
aspects in the browser.
You can mark something
as slower or faster.
So I think they contend
for resources today.
A part of it is about
how do we optimize
the number of domains?
And today, the only tools you
have for deprioritizing them
is things like async and such.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
We're going to come on
to a later question.
We're going to talk more
about dependencies
and execution time.
But just to stick with the
original intent of this
question was, in the earlier
session, we talked a lot about
how you were going to do media
queries to decide what image
you want to download?
Do we need a similar mechanism
for scripts or not?
If you were to put it to the
audience on a vote, you'd say,
yes, we need this mechanism, or
we don't need a mechanism
for this and we can
just move on.
Is this problem, you think?
I'm sending way too
many third-party
JavaScripts to my &mdash;
So we've got two votes, three
votes, four votes, five votes.
So people do think this
is a problem.
And that's not just Yoav hitting
the button five times.
[LAUGHTER]
YOAV WEISS: I have
several accounts.
[LAUGHTER]
BARBARA BERMES: And friends.
BEN VINEGAR: I would just say
that we experience that people
are conditionally loading our
application, usually doing
templates or JavaScript
or whatever, already.
So if there can just be really
nice, declarative way of doing
that as opposed to setting up
JavaScript code, I don't see
the problem with that.
People are doing it already,
is what I'm trying to say.
BARBARA BERMES: Whenever the
developer wants to do, if it's
easier for them.
And if media queries enhance
the performance as well in
loading things.
If you make it easy for them
to use stuff as a publisher
again, then it's cool.
GUY PODJARNY: I will say, it's
not just third-party, though.
So conditional loading of
JavaScript on a responsive
website is broader.
Third parties are a specific
case of it.
STEVE THAIR: OK/ So let's go
onto the second question.
We've got Tom Bushak.
Bushak?
OK.
TOM: So this one came in
anonymously as well.
The WhatWG has proposed a
solution for managing script
dependencies and
execution time.
Will this solve the
performance and
blocking use cases?
And Kyle, I believe, actually
is part of that proposal.
So maybe hell have some
helpful input as well.
STEVE THAIR: This is, as I
understand, it's related.
There are a lot of hacky ways
people download scripts as
comments and then add them
dynamically to the page when
they need them.
There's a lot of hacks out there
that people are doing to
get around the async blocking
nature of the scripts.
So what's happening with
the working groups?
And what's the best
solution for this?
BEN VINEGAR: I am not familiar
with this topic.
[LAUGHTER]
GUY PODJARNY: Well, I &mdash;
STEVE THAIR: Go ahead.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Anyone
from the audience who
wants to take it?
Kyle or &mdash;
GUY PODJARNY: I can even
starting, and then maybe we'll
switch to Kyle.
So I think there's a
few things there.
There's one in cold resource
priorities that has to do with
enabling the Lazy
Load and Defer
attributes on more objects.
Those are actually probably
further along on scripts than
they are on some other
components.
But there is some
promise there.
I think there's still
a lot of debates.
And I heard some comments in a
previous conversation today on
possible paths.
But I think there's still a hole
around how do you manage
groups of dependencies?
So that you want to say,
this script need to
run after the other.
But both of them combined
should be asynchronous.
There's things around
association of onload,
triggering with the
onload event.
And an async script.
It has an asynch script to deal
with still delay download.
So I think on the loading
process, there
are some good actions.
On the grouping and
such, I would
find them very promising.
But I don't know if they're
very far along.
KYLE SIMPSON: So since my
name was brought up,
I will speak up.
Two or three years ago, there
was some proposals.
Nicholas Zakas and I joined
together and made some
proposals on WhatWG about what
we call script preloading.
So the idea of loading
a script, but it not
automatically executing the
way normal scripts do.
And then being able to
programmatically control when
that script might load.
And that has gone through a
whole bunch of starts and
stops and restarts over
the last three years.
Most recently, about a month
ago, it started back up.
It turns out there's several
different things.
And maybe Jake Archibald
can also chime in.
So there's some stuff with
navigation controller, and
then there's discussions about
other use cases that that
might not handle.
I don't think I would classify
us as far along in terms of
implementation, but there has
been an enormous amount of
discussion about it.
And developers do you want, I
think, more control over it.
There's a one side, which is I
want control in the markup.
Again, back to this
declarative versus
programmatic control.
And I think that's really
one of the big
sticking points so far.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
Jake, did you want to
say anything, since
you got called out?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yeah.
I think the worst thing we've
got with script loading at the
moment is if you want to load
a series of scripts without
blocking, rendering, or blocking
any other computing,
but maintain the order of
execution, we don't have that
unless you use JavaScript.
And we don't want to use
JavaScript for script loading,
because then you lose
the preloader.
And the preloader, you could
boost, getting to DOM content
loaded by 20%.
So we want something in the
markup that can dictate which
order that the scripts
will be executed.
And then load them
asynchronously.
GUY PODJARNY: Just specifically
related to
third-party, I do think there
is another barrier, which is
document.write.
So when you're a publisher and
you're using a third party,
you need to be absolutely
confident 100% that that
script would never, ever use
document.write if you're
including them as an
asynchronous components.
Otherwise, that can lock
up your entire page.
And as far as I know, there is
no work going on right now,
but there definitely
should be, on doing
something like that.
Even something like just
ignoring the document.write,
in many cases, would be better
than blanking out the page and
writing only that piece, instead
of the entire page.
But ideally, there's something
a little bit more elaborate
that can, after the fact, write
content in those sections.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
Let's see.
Wilson Page from FT labs has got
his hand up to comment on
this topic, hopefully.
WILSON PAGE: Hello.
And a web app developer,
I like to have
control of my resources.
So would it be possible that
third parties, like discussed,
might let me bundle those
resources, their third-party
scripts, into my JS bundle
or other assets like CSS.
I can see why you wouldn't
want that,
because you want control.
[LAUGHTER]
WILSON PAGE: You want the
control to be able to update
when you want to update it.
But I also don't want 100 HTTP
requests going off on my page.
BEN VINEGAR: Yeah.
Oh, man. a lot of
eyes on me here.
On some level, I'm a
web developer too.
I hope so.
And I would like to do that.
So it would makes sense.
But you basically just hit be
the other end of it, which is
we're just changing things at
such a rapid pace that for
somebody to bundle it and
serve it from their own
servers or whatever,
we can't do it.
And this actually touches, a
little bit, on some of the
C3PO stuff.
The idea is that if we had a
common library that ran on
your host page.
And then you could bundlke
that part.
And then the stuff inside of
the frames could then do
whatever they wanted.
You at least got that
much out of it.
Even on that point, inevitably,
I might want to do
something different.
And now I have to go around to
thousands of websites and say,
please update this library in
order for you to have the next
version of Disqus.
And that is just such
a ridiculous pain
point, to go to &mdash;
the way that that scales is
that there's one of me and
there's thousands &mdash;
or think there's basically
millions of
websites with Disqus.
And to go and get all them to
upgrade all of their bundles
or whatever would be brutal.
So that's just &mdash;
STEVE THAIR: So no.
BEN VINEGAR: --why
we don't explore.
So, no.
BARBARA BERMES: As a publisher,
what we do, we have
all libraries like JQuery and
all that stuff, we know will
not change that often.
So we compile them or bundle
them up in one request.
But then of course, which
is the change that
could change it?
Any minute you've got to find
a solution for that.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
GUY PODJARNY: We do some
proxying of third-party
content sometimes, and there's
a different flavor of it.
So on the good side, if you
proxy third party content
through your servers, your CDN,
then you regain control
over some availability
test, over the
performance delivery of it.
They may not be delivering it as
high-quality, or we're not
willing to spend as much on
the delivering controls
as you might be.
Where that really runs
into an obstacle is
with things like tracking.
So on Facebook, you could
probably pull that off with a
Facebook SDK, which is
generic and cachable.
But you wouldn't be able to
do it with the iFrame that
figures out which of your
friends recommended this.
Because that requires some
special cookies.
And once you move it off to
a different domain, those
cookies no longer get sent.
So to me, if we are to do
something like a C3PO or some
equivalent of it, we
should tackle that.
Because our assessment &mdash; we've
done some mass testing on it &mdash;
was that that really
qualifies a lot.
In order to move something to
a different domain, you need
to be absolutely sure that
there would be no cookies
associated with that request.
Or, even if you're doing cookies
syncing, there would
be no cookies other
than a session ID
cookie on that domain.
And that's just a very
tough restriction.
So we need to standardize how
that is being handled, if we
wanted to go down
to that path.
STEVE THAIR: I think we'll
come back to that 3PO and
shared cookie things in
a later question.
But I think there's an
interesting question there for
the browser vendors.
Have we actually made this
problem for ourselves because
we can't share cookies and
domains for security reasons?
We've actually created
this problem.
And there needs to be some
way to address it.
Because effectively, there's
an ecosystem of people that
want to share this data.
There is no effective mechanism,
that I'm aware of
anyway, that can do that.
Next question we've
got is from Wes.
Oh, Calvin?
Calvin?
Sorry, Calvin.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: The problem
with document write was
mentioned earlier.
And the need to make sure your
async loaded scripts don't
have document.write tags.
I work with an environment
where I have hundreds of
unknown vendors, including
third-party
scripts, at any time.
And I have no way to ever vet
them all, because they come
from 150 different properties.
And we currently use a tool
called write capture to
override what document.write
does and force asynchronous
loading of everything.
And it's awful.
And when it breaks, it
gives me headaches
for months at a time.
We can never get rid of that.
My question is, can we
get rid of that?
Is there anything we can do so
that we can stop having to vet
these and know that they're
not going to do
document.write?
Because the surprise is awful
if it ever happens.
STEVE THAIR: So you want a
flag on the browser or
something to say, this is page
doesn't support document.write
or something.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: We add
APIs all the time.
Can we do the opposite
just once?
[LAUGHTER]
STEVE THAIR: So like that
Kill IE6 campaign.
You're just going to start a
website, Kill Document.write.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I would be
very happy with that.
STEVE THAIR: Who here would
vote for that one?
BEN VINEGAR: Wait, what
am I voting on?
STEVE THAIR: Kill
document.write.
Just get rid of it.
BEN VINEGAR: Sure.
We could start a trade
association too, in which we
vet scripts.
I don't know.
I'm not being serious.
This is a terrible joke.
[LAUGHTER]
GUY PODJARNY: So we do the
same thing, of the write
capture as part of the
optimizations we do in Akamai.
And I share your pain.
And I'd like to believe that
browser vendors should be able
to tackle that.
I don't know if any browser
vendor in the crowd
wants to chime in.
By doing some 90% accurate
version of the document.write,
just write that out in spot
where that scrips would have
been after the fact.
Because oftentimes, just killing
document.write or
trying to mark it
up in JavaScript
is the best we have.
So we use that where needed.
But it's extremely
far from ideal.
STEVE THAIR: We've got to move
on to the next question.
So the next question is
actually from Wes.
WESLEY HALES: So Facebook has
recently taken steps to
optimize the scripts for its
embeddable Like button, which
I think you guys can speak to.
But how do we measure
the impact of
embedding these scripts?
And then a second part to this
question is, is the Web
Intents specification our only
hope to conquer app linking
and embedding these scripts?
Is Web Intents our hope for
not having these types of
Share buttons and scripts that
are included with those?
STEVE THAIR: Well, I might
throw this question to
Barbara, actually,
as a consumer.
Do you do performance testing?
Somebody comes to you and says,
I want to add this new
third-party script.
What you do to measure
the impact of that?
BARBARA BERMES: I'm big
on performance.
And obviously, I have issues
when 50% of our CBC desktop
site is serving third-party
scripts and the rest we are
serving to the customers
is just all content.
So I do try to do that.
It is very difficult for us to
make sure that all the content
areas at CBC know about it
and how to include it.
So in terms of performance,
I do performance tests.
Especially the AB, what happens
before putting the
script in versus after.
And we've seen some really bad
incidents where ads or scripts
like that slow down our site.
So to track those kind of
things and give them to
business and say, see, this
is what could happen.
STEVE THAIR: What about from
your side, Stoyan?
What do you do to make sure
yours is not so slow?
STOYAN STEFANOV: When optimizing
the Like button,
then the only thing you can do
is write block post and say,
oh, see how the waterfall
is so nice now.
BARBARA BERMES: But it was.
It is.
That was good.
STOYAN STEFANOV: I don't think
we're doing anything to prove,
OK, I know how much it reduces
the average website and so on.
Just trying to do the best
thing and then let other
people measure and see how it
affects their websites.
STEVE THAIR: That's good.
Ben, you said earlier that you
do a lot of debugging of the
customers' websites because they
always blame you for the
performance issues.
So are there tools?
Are there Techniques
Are there tips?
Is there a methodology that you
follow to prove that it's
the sucky customer website and
not your awesome script?
BEN VINEGAR: That is exactly
how I phrase it.
[LAUGHTER]
BEN VINEGAR: Goes over
really well.
There's a ton of techniques that
are pretty well-published
out there that I'm
probably using.
I don't even know I was
saying "we" there.
In my mind, a lot of these seem
like very tried and true
performance things.
Like not binding
to, debouncing,
throttling, scroll handlers.
Or something we do is we
render in chunks now.
So we'll render five comments,
release to the browser.
Render five comments, release
to the browser.
We're very cognizant of just
never tying up the UI thread.
I don't think that's something
that I can &mdash;
An individual widget developer
or third-party application
developer, they all
have to do that.
And I think the big issue is
that they don't, or it's just
all over the place as
to whether they do.
I might be rambline here.
You can bring me back.
STEVE THAIR: The question &mdash;
If we take an example of where
you said that you've proved
that it wasn't your script that
was blocking the site.
Was it something that the
customer was doing that was
impacting your script
in a negative way?
And how did you prove that?
BEN VINEGAR: Actually, the last
time I was debugging a
site, I think I brought this on
myself, in the sense that I
was observing that Disqus
was slow when scrolling
through it on a blog.
And actually, I think today
that's actually a lot of CSS
performance.
Which is another topic
that I will address.
But so I was debugging our
scroll handlers, and figuring
out that in this case, the
parent website was not
throttling a scroll handler.
And they were activating it
as you went over Disqus.
So you would scroll down, and
it would actually chug a
little bit.
I don't remember the
purpose of it.
That's just a random anecdote
of something.
BARBARA BERMES: Might be nice to
automate that somewhere on
your end, that you can say, OK,
Publisher A is not using
it properly.
Or don't blame us if
the site is slow.
We've got Matt May from Adobe.
Do you have a comment on how
you measure the impact of
these scripts?
MATT MAY: Actually, my
question's a different thing.
STEVE THAIR: Oh, well we'll
hold that question, then.
We'll try and stick
with the topic.
GUY PODJARNY: I've got one
comment maybe to throw in,
which is that resource timing is
hopefully going to help us
identify in real users where
to lay the blame.
There are some security aspects
to resource timing.
But from my perspective, when
somebody comes Akamai and
says, you're not making my site
faster, sometimes the
purpose is to show that it's
actually the third party
that's on your page
that's the cause.
At least we put a lot of hope
in that front to give us
clarity about who's truly to
blame for the problem, and
therefore where should
the solution lie?
STEVE THAIR: Sergei?
Did you want to make
a comment?
SERGEI: I've actually been
working for a while with
vendors that work with us on
enforcing the contract between
the groups.
And one of the lines was, never
use document.write.
And the question is, can we
create or promote this
contract between widget
providers, of different kinds
surely, and publishers.
And kind of help emerging
providers, which have to deal
with a lot, to follow that.
At the same time, probably
protect widget providers'
needs as well.
BARBARA BERMES: I
would love that.
We talked about that.
Some sort of a policy.
And I would love to create a
policy that we could give to
the widget creators and say,
you follow those steps, we
would consider you using.
And I think it is important
to make that point.
GUY PODJARNY: We may be able to
copy some of the security
policies we're doing.
We're talking about sandboxing
from that prospective.
Saying, well, I'm only giving
you a constrained access to
certain APIs.
You're not allowed to
use document.write.
It's just going to break.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Well, there's
this organization called &mdash;
I forgot what the name was.
Interactive Advertising Bureau,
something like this.
STEVE THAIR: The IAB.
STOYAN STEFANOV: IAB.
They've released a document
saying, related to ads, saying
these are the best practices
for ads.
That kind of stuff.
So do we need something
similar for widgets?
GUY PODJARNY: Or just
enforcement
of it in the browser.
STOYAN STEFANOV: But I don't
think there is any, OK this is
the checklist that you have to
follow, otherwise you're not
given an A.
STEVE THAIR: OK.
So we'll switch on to
the next topic.
Markus?
Marquis?
Stand up.
AUDIENCE: So this is an
anonymous question.
"The growing use of third-party
services means web
pages today consume content
from over 16 domains on
average, creating performance
and reliability problems.
SPDY and HTTP2 work per
domain and don't help.
Can we share connections or
delivery across third
parties?"
STEVE THAIR: So I guess
this is the point to
discuss, the 3PO idea.
And particularly when
the [INAUDIBLE]
a lot with this is like
affiliate tracking, and you're
trying to attribute
the affiliate
referral fee to somebody.
And so all of these affiliates
are coming from different
domains and different affiliate
tracking networks.
And I've got to have that
script on my page.
It's part of the business
model of the customer.
But if all of these things were
put into one centralized
domain, or there was an
effective mechanism for
sharing synchronizing the
cookies across the domains,
that would help me a lot.
Is that something
that we can do?
Or do you think that's never
going to happen?
STOYAN STEFANOV: I really
like the idea.
There's many things that
we can optimize.
First is the script that writes
whatever the widget is
doing, the iFrame, and so on.
So having this as packaged
together with the publisher's
script sounds great.
We have to make sure that it's
absolutely future-proof.
Because people might not upgrade
it once they get it
off of GitHub.
And then the other thing about a
common domain is right after
you have already written the
iFrame or the static resources
on that iFrame, could they be
sharing the same domain?
That'd be cool.
So you still have to make a
request to the third-party
provider to get the HTML,
any loggings, and
that kind of stuff.
But when it comes to static
resources, why not?
BEN VINEGAR: So with idea, maybe
we have a 3PJS CDN.com,
and we have
3PJS/Facebook/Disqus.
And that's where we put our
static stuff, and then we
benefit from having
a single domain?
Is that basically the idea?
Try and help me understand
here.
GUY PODJARNY: I think there's
two aspects of it.
There's the standardizing of how
something gets included on
the page, which would help
alleviate some of the concern
with [INAUDIBLE]
third parties, or third parties
that don't put as much
effort into it.
And then there's the delivery
aspect, which was around.
Yeah, having some shared &mdash;
The ideal would be maybe
a single domain.
There are all sorts of security
aspects to putting
content from multiple providers
on the same domain.
So that might not
be an option.
So maybe at the very least,
that there's shared
connections for those components
to deliver them,
where possible, through
the same entity.
STEVE THAIR: So much this has
to be done client-side,
because it inherently wants to
read a cookie to find what
other website that you went to
so I can do my affiliate
tracking and things like that.
If we had some kind of shared
mechanism, could we move a lot
of this service-side?
Are there any effective
service-side solutions?
So I can just take all the
scripts off my page.
Is that feasible?
What would we need to be able
to move some of this stuff
service-side?
GUY PODJARNY: Well, for the
server to be able to pull in
content from multiple domains,
for starters, for many of
these third-party services,
you would need some cookie
syncing capability.
Because they track
different IDs.
The cookie syncing is a
solved problem in ads,
so that can be done.
But then the second problem
is non-ID cookies.
And that's not at all
a solved problem.
So we would need, basically,
a commitment from anybody
participating in this, from the
Facebooks and Disqus of
the world, to say, I will keep
everything server-side.
Maybe even provide
some supporting
mechanisms for that.
And work fully on
a session ID.
And then, of course, then the
politics kick in about who
owns that ID.
But we'll leave that
part for later.
And on top of all of those, you
would need the browser to
share connections if you didn't
literally land on the
same domain.
So you'd need to somehow
have the browsers play
ball on that front.
BARBARA BERMES: And of course
for the publisher, it would be
great to just include something,
or run a script
somewhere, and include all
the things that you need.
So that would help, for sure.
GUY PODJARNY: I would say there
is a lower bar around
sharing, at least.
Delivering them from a standard
component for providers.
So if providers had an easy way
to know which resources of
their third parties are things
that they could pull in to
their content, then
I think that would
be a big step forward.
We had to do conversations with
Facebook, with Google,
with various others to learn
that, I believe the Google
Analytics JavaScript library,
the Facebook SDK, those
components are static.
But you basically don't know
those without a very explicit
statement from the third-party
vendors.
STEVE THAIR: No questions?
No comments?
OK, we'll move straight
onto the next one.
Andre Behrens?
ANDRE BEHRENS: Hi.
And this is an anonymous
question.
"If a blocking script is loaded
from a domain that goes
down, this will cause my
page to fail to load.
How can we test and/or
address the single
point of failure issue?
I guess I'll go to Barbara.
Single points of failure?
BARBARA BERMES: Yeah.
STEVE THAIR: Is this
a real problem that
affects your website?
BARBARA BERMES: Yeah.
I would say so.
And I see, sometimes, even
script being not properly
included on the CBC domain.
Literally, ad hoc, you could
use Pat's SPOF-O-matic to
check how your site is behaving
with third-party scripts.
I also like SPOFCheck.
I think the eBay team did that,
so you can pull it into
your continuous integration.
So when somebody develops
something, we could right away
figure out that they're
including scripts not properly.
And then avoid that
potential failure.
And we've had happening
as well.
Even, I think, last
week with ads.
Where something was not properly
included, and we got
some bad hits for that.
STOYAN STEFANOV: So you were
able to check during the build
process that somebody somewhere
included a block &mdash;
BARBARA BERMES: Yeah, exactly.
So it literally checks
for script.
And if you just put
it wherever it is,
it's really cool tool.
There's even, I think, a
Grunt plugin as well
that you can use.
I would love to have those
kinds of things more
integrated in our deployment.
So that basically, as
a developer, you
can almost be dumb.
You just don't have
to think about it.
And we catch that, and we're
not able to deploy stuff.
GUY PODJARNY: It's important
to clarify that the SPOF is
the extreme scenario, this
website is down.
And maybe a slightly
more rare one.
But a mini-version of
it happens every
time the page is loaded.
Any one of these blockers is
also some sort of delay, some
sort of resource contention
for each
one of those resources.
So sometimes, the conversation
comes into, nah, Facebook's
not going to go down.
Which is a different
conversation.
But there is always a little bit
of a penalty, even for the
most cutting-edge
third parties.
So getting them out of
the line of fire is
always a good idea.
STOYAN STEFANOV: What I was
saying is, it may not be down,
but it may be blocked
in the company.
You don't want people on
Facebook during working
hours and so on.
So you effectively destroy the
website, because Facebook is
blocked for some reason.
STEVE THAIR: Kyle Kinneman,
you had a &mdash;
KYLE: It's been answered.
STEVE THAIR: It's
been answered?
OK.
Cool.
BEN VINEGAR: I was just going
to add really quickly that,
other than the case where
somebody just puts in a
blocking script tag.
There's that problem.
I do think that third-party
applications and third-party
scripts, we absolutely have
to be good citizens.
And we have to work in
situations where stuff is down
or wherever.
I know that a big push that
we're making in our company is
that if Disqus goes down, we
at least want you to see
static comments that
are not dynamic.
The server's not to listen to,
because maybe it's blowing up.
But at least you can
read comments.
And for all intents and
purposes, that's just static.
It's from a CDN, and
things look OK.
But this is just stuff
that we have to do.
And I don't know if there's just
a hammer that everybody
can just use for that.
STOYAN STEFANOV: If everybody
did that, we would be
definitely better off.
BARBARA BERMES: Yeah.
And of course I appreciate
those things
that providers do.
One of the other challenges we
have is will editors finding
news be able to include
widgets?
And they literally take them
from a website, not thinking
how to properly include it.
Those are the challenges for
us, also, to sandbox that.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Something
that [INAUDIBLE]
from your comment, I'd really
love to ask people to write
block posts and do research
and put us to shame.
Just to keep the third-party
providers in check.
And say, oh, this is horrible.
So if you see if you see some
third-party provider that
doesn't provide asynchronous
[INAUDIBLE],
make noise about it.
STEVE THAIR: I think
it's probably an
important thing to mention.
Is that not you're
not necessarily
always criticizing them.
What you're actually doing is
giving them the opportunity to
go to their boss and say, look,
all these people are
complaining about it.
And that's a really effective
mechanism for them to get the
resources they need.
A lot of these guys
are providers.
They want to fix the problem,
but they've got competing
business priorities.
If you're out there making a
lot of noise about it, it
suddenly becomes a business
priority.
And you really help
them to address.
We've only got about
four minutes left.
I'm actually going to skip
one question, which
we'll come back to.
Because I really want
to get question
number seven answered.
Which, from Rahul Choudhary?
Cho-dari?
RAHUL CHOUDHARY: So this is
another anonymous question.
"What could the browser vendors
provide to eliminate
third-party scripts and the
problems associated with
them?" I don't really agree
with this question.
[LAUGHTER]
STEVE THAIR: We've got people
from the Chrome team.
We've got people from Mozilla.
We've got people &mdash;
I'd be very interested
to hear from those.
But if you could have one thing
from a browser vendor
guy to help address this
problem, what would it be?
GUY PODJARNY: My number one
would probably be the script
dependencies.
Document.write a close second.
The ability to group async.
STEVE THAIR: Barbara?
BARBARA BERMES: Actually, same.
Same.
The document.write issue.
STOYAN STEFANOV: I like
the browsers.
They're my favorite.
BEN VINEGAR: I could
probably go off on
this for a long time.
STEVE THAIR: Please do.
BEN VINEGAR: So starting on
setup, basically the way that
most complex widgets work today
is there's a script runs
on the host page, and it usually
opens up an iFrame
that communicate with
each other.
And in a perfect world, I would
love if Disqus was just
an iFrame, and there was
that separation.
Everyone could feel confident
about it.
And that would be
the contract.
You know it's in the iFrame.
You know it's not going
to escape the iFrame.
But the problem is that the
tools for making that happen
are just nonexistent.
There are tons of &mdash;
I won't say tons.
But there are things that are
being developed right now for
further isolating iFrames.
There is the Sandbox
attribute.
Let's really break
down this iFrame.
There's no tools that are being
developed from the other
perspective, which are, let me
get access to some of stuff
that's happening on
the parent page.
Let me know that somebody's
scrolling the page.
clicking so that I can close a
menu that I have happened
to open in my iFrame.
There is none of those
tools right now.
And because of that, or even
very simply, I cannot resize
the iFrame today.
Because there are none of those
tools, we have to have
this dual system where
have we have to put
JavaScript on your page.
And that's unfortunate.
It would be terrific if we
started looking at things from
the other side, and then maybe
things could get better, I
think a lot better, just by
providing those tools.
STOYAN STEFANOV: Would
the Web Components be
an answer to that?
BEN VINEGAR: I've only
looked a little bit.
Perhaps this morning, to
research a little bit more
about Web Components
so I didn't look
like a complete fool.
But from what I've seen, is that
they're successful by the
parent page, right?
Even if they're kind
of hidden?
Is there a Web Components
person?
You create &mdash;
STOYAN STEFANOV:
Anyone who's &mdash;
STEVE THAIR: The delegate put
their hand up thing is not.
So if anybody's an expert
on Web Components.
Anyone?
BEN VINEGAR: I have somebody
over there.
STEVE THAIR: Alex!
Alex to the rescue.
ALEX RUSSELL: Hi.
Alex Russell from Google.
So the way Web Components
work are it's a
bunch of related specs.
We designed it that way for a
reason that I won't go into.
But you can have something
called a shadow DOM, which
hides away the implementation
of your UI from the normal
iteration order through
the document.
And you're entirely correct that
that doesn't solve the
problem for you.
Because you can still reach
into the shadow DOM.
It was explicitly designed not
to be a security boundary.
Today the answer is, put an
iFrame in your shadow DOM and
use it that way.
So it doesn't get you
out of any of the
sizing issues, I'm afraid.
BEN VINEGAR: So I think a lot of
this new stuff [INAUDIBLE]
thing is still being developed
from this perspective of,
almost like if I was Google, and
I had widgets that I want
on all my other services and I
trust those services, I feel
like a lot of is being
designed from that
perspective.
Somebody can shut me
up if they want.
Because the security things
aren't addressed.
There was the seamless spec that
came out, but it still
let styles come in.
For that kind of publisher,
they may be
interested in that.
But I'm not interested
in that.
Anyways.
I've got that sheet that
says, shut up.
STEVE THAIR: Time to go.
All right.
So basically, we've got
one minute left.
We're going to wrap up.
I think immediately
after this, we're
staying here for lunch.
Is that right.
ANDREW BETTS: [INAUDIBLE]
Yup.
STEVE THAIR: Yeah.
Well, thank you very much to
the people on the party &mdash;
People on the party?
P &mdash; p &mdash;
[APPLAUSE]
STEVE THAIR: People
on the panel!
Peter Piper picked a peck
of pickled peppers!
[APPLAUSE]
STEVE THAIR: I'll hand
it back to Andrew.
ANDREW BETTS: Thanks Steve.
STEVE THAIR: Thank you.
ANDREW BETTS: So we're going
to do lunch now.
I just have a couple of
announcements before lunch.
First of all, everyone's
obviously discovered that you
can change the name on your
Google accounts to put
messages on the screen.
That's very clever.
Well done.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDREW BETTS: Also, someone
sent us a pull request.
So thanks very much for that.
And if you do have trouble
connecting, it seems to be
working really well now.
But Wesley, who's sitting
right here, is really
interested to get your feedback
and but reports if
you've got a device that
it doesn't work on.
So go and chat him over lunch.
We've got some smokers who
were interested in going
outside to smoke.
Unfortunately, it is kind
of inconvenient.
We have to escort you through
the building.
But there will be people
around to do that.
So just grab hold of some of the
helpers who will take you
to where you can do that.
Remember to use the feedback
form to give us feedback
before the end of the day.
And lunch is right there.
So go help yourselves.
[MUSIC PLAYING]