LOUIS GRAY: Welcome to Google
Developers Weekly for
September 4, 2013, our highlight
reel of what's
happening in the world
of Google Developers
on the set and off.
Before the Labor Day holiday
here in the United States, we
had a big week in our studios.
So let's shake those cobwebs off
of our three-day weekend,
get back to work, and go
to those highlights.
It's one thing to know how to
code, but it's quite another
to take that leap and start your
own company based on one
of your many brilliant ideas.
Our good friends Martin Omander
and Don Dodge helped
us out with a pair of shows from
root access, covering how
startups can incorporate
and get funded.
So you can go from having a
great idea to affording to eat
in between all those
all-nighters.
Once you've started that company
and are building that
incredible app, you want to make
sure it looks good and
feels just right.
That's why we brought in our
Dev UX team, led by Nazmul,
and they spoke to us on how to
be thinking about great design
when creating new
applications.
This week, they also showed us
how to invite the world to
your application through adding
social integration
through many social networks.
Also, as I said last week,
the best shows
are made into trilogies.
I was lucky to have Chicago's
own Brian Fitzpatrick in
Mountain View for three
high-quality events to help
you take control of your career
and of your data.
We started with everybody's
favorite, organizational
manipulation.
We joined the data liberation
front, and we wrapped with a
deep dive into Google's
transparency report.
Fitz Week might be over, but
the memories live on in
YouTube, and on the Google
Developers Live website.
Here at GDL, when we're not
watching YouTube, you might
find us catching up on the
day's news with CNN.
Resident Glass guy Timothy
Jordan hosted Jeff Eddings of
CNN to talk about the
network's Glass app.
Timothy also taught the rest
of us about some cool new
options for commanding Glass
with your voice, including
integrations with social network
path and Evernote.
OK, Glass.
Send my information to path.
Well beyond our Mountain View
campus, from Tel Aviv, Ido
Green taught us how to debug
Node.js applications using
Chrome dev tools.
Alberto Rossi in Milan showed
us how to build Android apps
with HTML5 and JavaScript.
And from Buenos Aires,
[INAUDIBLE]
presented on Google+ Sign In.
Live from New York, it was the
App Script team, taking your
questions in another edition
of Google Apps Unscripted,
while Ibraham Ulukaya partnered
up with Roman Nurik
to tackle best practices from
the YouTube APIs on Android
and Android design.
Our users and developers span
the globe, so our studios and
engineers do, too.
Away from our Google Developers
Live studios, the
GDGx team of talented engineers
has produced a new
Google Developer Groups app
for Android devices.
This app provides direct access
to your favorite GDL
shows, along with news and
information about your local
GDG, and even achievements
that you can unlock.
That's not just GDGx,
that's GDG extreme.
Promises have come to Chrome.
In the HTML document object
model, a promise provides
asynchronous access to the
result of an operation,
whether it already took
place or not.
Francois Beaufort posted about
how promises come true in
Chrome 30 beta.
We've come a long way.
And Android developers, Android
Studio marches on.
The team has released version
0.2.6 with various bug fixes
to smooth your work.
Be sure to update your Android
studio to take advantage of
the latest.
And to make sure you take
advantage of the latest and
never miss a thing from the
world of Google Developers,
subscribe to Google Developers
on YouTube and check out the
GDL schedule at
developers.google.com/live.
I'm Louis Gray, and I'll
see you in the studio.