LOUIS GRAY: Welcome to Google
Developers Weekly for December
18, 2013, our 17th and final
weekly wrap up for the year.
I'm Louis Gray, and this
is our highlight reel
of what's happening in the world
of Google Developers on the set
and off.
Last week we hosted four
special edition segments
in celebration of Computer
Science Education Week
and the Hour Of Code campaign.
Here's how it all went down.
To kick things off, Van
Riper hosted three students
from GDG Fresno High, as
well as the group's sponsors,
Joshua and Courtney Woodward.
Mamie Rheingold chatted
with the founder
of code.org, Hadi
Partovi, who shared
why getting 10
million kids to code
is crucial for the
success of every industry.
In our third segment,
Deena Shakir and Girls
Who Code Founder Reshma
Saujani shared how developers
can make an impact in
teaching girls to code.
And on Friday, Natalie
Villalobos hosted
noted entrepreneur
Limor Fried, who
explained why
engineering isn't boring,
whether it's LED shoes
or DIY home automation.
You can find all these
segments on our YouTube channel
and on our Google
Developers Google+ page.
We then welcomed John Faig,
Darrel Sumi from Talkray,
and Brad Green from
Google's Angular team
into the studio for a talk
on building Chrome packaged
apps using AngularJS.
John and Darrel
discussed critical points
in transitioning
from regular web apps
to Chrome packaged apps,
as well as why AngularJS
makes for a great fit
with packaged apps.
Some of the most
helpful technical tips
come from friendly people
you've never even met,
like the active communities on
Stack Overflow in our YouTube
API community members.
This week we invited YouTube
API Google Developer experts,
who we call GDEs, Matias
Molinas, Tim Wintle and Jarom
McDonald to the studio
to learn from them
face to face and see what they
find fascinating about taking
on top code challenges.
Of course, you can always learn
more about the GDE program
by visiting
developers.google.com/experts.
Staying in YouTube land, Ibrahim
Ulukaya hosted split media labs
explaining how the X Split
broadcaster integrates
with the YouTube
live streaming API
to create an easy and powerful
game streaming experience.
Back in my day, when I
fired up my Nintendo,
the only person who would
watch me was my brother.
Now you can see all my complete
lack of skills and failure
to get to the next
level live on the web.
And finally, from the lawn, in
the latest volley from the GDL
Italia series,
Michele [? Orlessi ?]
presents on how you can deploy
a PHP application on Google App
Engine.
Beyond our studios, the
latest Chrome experiment
takes you to Middle
Earth in the world
of a new movie, The Hobbit
- The Desolation Of Smaug.
Check out the case
study on html5rocks.com,
that's html5rocks.com, to
learn how the team accomplished
the amazing interactivity
of this experiment.
But watch out for dragons.
Last week [? Miley Olya
?] and the webmaster team
put together a great checklist
for improving mobile websites.
You can read Miley's post on
the Google Developers blog
and get handy tips for making
users happier with your sites.
Also last week, Google+ Sign
In for your apps got smarter.
Google+ Sign In now supports
Google Apps accounts,
incremental auth, and migration
from other auth methods.
Take a look at the
Google Developers
blog for all of the details.
And finally, more news from the
folks working to make the web
faster.
The resource timing
API is now available.
This API enables you to
track timing information
about every resource
on the page,
so you can measure
and then optimize.
And to make sure that you never
miss a thing from the world
of Google Developers, subscribe
to Google Developers on YouTube
and check out the GDL schedule
at developers.google.com/live.
I'm Louis Gray, and I'll
see you in the studio.