[MUSIC PLAYING]
Two minutes, everyone--
take your seats, please.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BETTS: Can we get
the Real Time Data
panel on the stage?
Great.
SCOTT JENSON: John?
John Fallows, right?
Scott Jenson, nice
to meet you.
HENRIK JORETEG: Any preference
to where I should sit?
ANDREW BETTS: Sit wherever
you like.
HENRIK JORETEG: OK.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
SCOTT JENSON: What's this
less talk thing?
ANDREW BETTS: Oh, you
can just turn it on.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
OK.
Welcome back.
So our next session
is Real Time Data.
This session is going to be
chaired by Mr. Scott Jenson.
So please welcome the panel
for Real Time Data.
SCOTT JENSON: Thank
you very much.
Can we bring up the QR
code for the session?
Or is that something we have
to do next, after the talk?
After the talk, so then
I will save my little
talk for that later.
We have a very good panel here
of people who are extremely
experienced in, basically,
Real Time Data.
strongly recommend that you
just read the panel
introduction from all of them.
We've got Henrik Joreteg, right
here, John Fallows,
Wesley, who actually did this
lovely OnSlyde demonstration
as well, which by the
way, is right there.
And then to my left, we
have Martyn, and Rob.
Sorry, welcome.
Now that we have the OnSlyde
up, I really strongly
recommend that you guys
take a look at
that and get it started.
As a perfect introduction to
this talk, if you are on and
iPhone and you bring
up that web page,
and it goes to sleep.
You must refresh the page
because the website get close
down automatically--
perfect introduction as
to why we're here.
I also would like to try using
it during this talk, so as
many of you as possible can
bring it up, we'll ask some
questions along the way.
We'll see how it goes.
But I think, right now, we need
a general introduction.
That's what Henrik's here
for, so please.
HENRIK JORETEG: All right.
See if I can get my slides back
on the screen here maybe
Here we go.
OK.
Hi, guys.
My name is Henrik Joreteg.
I work at a company
called &yet.
And I've been building Real Time
web apps now for about
four years.
We started out using XMPP and
strophe.js and BOSH and all
that stuff, back in the
day, long polling.
Then WebSockets came out.
We started messing with that,
socket.io and the like.
Recently, I've gotten
really into WebRTC.
I think it's useful, before we
get too into the technical
stuff, to kind of step back a
minute and realize what this
really does in terms
of the web.
The web is really about
human communication.
And so these are my kids.
Aw.
And they love their
grandparents.
Problem is, their grandparents
live in Sweden.
For those of with a typical
American geographic
understanding, it's far away.
Sorry, that's low.
I'm sorry.
This is not this
crowd, I know.
So we built an app called--
Every Sunday, my kids get to
talk to my parents over an app
we built called Talky.io,
that uses WebRTC.
Talky.io is the first app I've
ever built that actually
passed the mom test, meaning
my parents can use it.
What it is, anytime you're on
the same URL, you're in the
same conversation.
That's all there is to it.
So no login, no off, no
friending, nothing.
And it's using WebRTC.
There's nothing to install.
It just works.
So to me, it just serves as a
very kind of practical example
for how, ultimately, these Real
Time technologies are
actually bringing people
together and helping make the
web better.
So let's talk a little
bit about WebRTC.
We're going to cover
other stuff too.
But I want to focus on this a
bit because it's been kind of
a recent focus of mine.
WebRTC really is a lot more
than video in a browser.
It's actually a low latency,
peer-to-peer networking.
And that's really exciting.
Some of the other cool examples
of what you can do
with this technology is
the called PeerCDN.
PeerCDN was actually built
by the same guy
who did Google Instant.
But it's this really cool
concept of where it actually
uses data channels
to send files to
other current visitors.
So say, for instance, I'm
hosting like a simple little
video site.
I'm actually hosting
my own videos.
All of a sudden, I'm on Reddit,
and I'm getting slammed.
So normally, that would be
expensive for bandwidth.
But in this case, the kind of
swarm of people that are
gathering on your site to
watch this footage can
actually download it
from each other.
So you kind of create this is
an ad hoc like BitTorrent
network, which is really
fascinating.
It's just kind of an example of
what you do with the stuff.
Also, given recent stuff with
the NSA and with encryption,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera,
I actually think
WebRTC is really important
for the web.
It's decentralized.
It's encrypted.
Yes, maybe there are back
doors, who knows.
But ultimately, this is stuff
that we should be doing.
And it's a big win
for the web.
So how we doing so far?
Well, let's start
with a story.
A year ago, at &yet,
we built att.js.
Att.js was kind of a
demonstration used at CES by
AT&T, to demonstrate making
and receiving actual phone
calls in browsers, using
WebRTC, which is cool.
We got it to work, but with
way too many caveats.
It actually required running a
certain modified version of
Chromium that the Ericsson
team was
maintaining, not ideal.
It's gotten better.
So if you look at this, here,
what we actually have is a
Nexus 4 running Firefox
Nightly.
We've got a Nexus 7 running
Chrome for Android and then a
desktop running Firefox Stable
and Chrome Stable, all in the
same conversation at
the same time.
So it's gotten better.
It's available now on
some mobile devices.
And interoperability is
improving for voice and video.
Sweet, so we're good.
We can all go home.
We should just use
this, right?
No.
WebRTC is still quite finicky.
And if you've tried to do
anything with it, you've
probably discovered this.
So just to give an example,
here's what you have to do to
set up a video call, right
now, between two users.
So first of all, getting
user media, it
sounds really simple.
You request access
to the camera and
the microphone, right.
You would think.
The methods are still prefixed,
which is fine.
I mean, that's to be expected.
They throw very different
error types.
So in Firefox, the error handler
that you give it will
give you a string back.
In Chrome, it will
give you an error
object, as it's supposed.
But neither quite follows a
spec, as far as telling you
what went wrong.
So in addition, specifying find
constraints for like,
hey, I want a smaller video
is available, kind of with
limited support in Chrome
and not at all in
Firefox at the moment.
Screen sharing, which is
actually really important for
replacing something like Skype
or do Google Hangouts, is
available in Chrome.
But it's behind a flag, very
hard to detect air types,
requires HTTPS.
So even if you're running local
host and if you don't
have your own self-signed cert
or something, it will just
fail silently.
And you won't know why.
So as a result, what do we do?
We create abstractions.
So we wrote a getUserMedia model
to handle that part.
Attaching media stream--
so once you request media, you
have this stream object.
And it's your job to then attach
that to, say, a video
element or an audio element.
This has gotten better.
The APIs are more similar now.
But you have to convert
it to a blob URL,
attach it as a source.
In Chrome, you set
autoplay to true.
In Firefox, you attach
it and call play.
Point is, there are
differences.
And often, you want to mute the
user's own video, so they
don't want echo back to
themselves, et cetera.
So again, now, that's another
thing that should be simple
now has become another module
that we are maintaining.
So beyond that, the thing that
a lot of people don't
understand about peer-to-peer
is, ultimately, you have to
have some mechanism for
the two peers to
discover each other.
It's not like we just magically
know each other's
external IPs, and we can just
send stuff directly.
And this is not in
the spec at all.
It's purposely left out.
So it's totally green field.
I actually think that's good.
But that means, as a developer,
you have to do a
lot more work.
You have to help users
discover each other.
You have to help them figure out
how to pass data messages
directly to another user, which
is not something that's
necessarily in the tool
belt of the average
of JavaScript developer.
So now you need some kind of
server technologies as well,
to be able to handle this.
With socket.io it's not hard.
But it's still something
that's new
for a lot of people.
In addition, you have to do
some level of capabilities
detection for certain things.
So for example, if you do screen
sharing from Chrome, it
won't appear for
a Firefox user.
But there's no way that
you would know that,
programmatically, without
specifying through the
signaling channel.
But hey, you've got users
in this chat, who
are actually in Firefox.
So there are just a few
oddities like that.
So then, we write a
signaling server.
So peer connection-- so this
is kind of the mother.
This is like the thing that
does it all, right.
This has some quirks as well.
So first of all, they're
prefixed, which is, again, to
be expected.
I don't think that's
a bad thing.
CreateDataChannel--
so this is the data stuff that
we're going to talk about.
This is extremely finicky
at the moment.
So you have to pass a very
specific set of options to
create a reliable channel versus
an unreliable channel.
It's supposed to be reliable
true or false, but that
doesn't actually work
in either browser.
As I was just talking to Kyle
about, there is an upload
limitation in the default
settings for Chrome.
So in order to actually
get this to work--
if you want to pass a file
around, it actually modified
the FTP that you send.
Tricky stuff.
So anyway, we wrote a
wrapper for that.
Other challenges--
data channels are currently not
all interoperable between
Chrome and Firefox.
You can only do one video
stream per connection.
And all of this is just--
there are other browsers
that will do this.
So it's not going to
get any better.
WebRTC is also unique, in that,
this is actually the
first time I know of where
browsers have to speak
directly to each other.
There's no intermediary.
So once you set up a signaling
channel, they better be
interoperable.
And that's a whole new level
of spec compliance that's
required, in order to
make that work.
And I can only imagine how
interesting it will be if
Microsoft and Internet
Explorer decide
to do this as well.
So I wrote a library
SimpleWebRTC.
Just basically, you provide
a container for local.
You provide a container
for remote videos.
And when it's ready, you join
the room, and it works.
It makes a bunch of assumption,
but this is the
kind of stuff you need, in order
to actually make this
approachable.
There's alternatives,
obviously.
There's PeerJS, focused on
data channels, OpenTok.
And then there's another guy
who's done a bunch of
interesting experiments.
I'm kind of running
out of time here.
Anyway, the big thing I think
that's really important is,
tinkerability is actually what
drives adoption of new
technologies.
So we like to play with new
stuff, and not everybody does.
So in the same way that jQuery
made the DOM accessible to
lots of people, socket.io
made WebSockets
accessible to a lot of people.
Abstraction library, such
as simpleWebRTC--
I don't care if it's that or
something else-- but hopefully
makes it accessible to
more people as well.
And we really just need more
Open Web hackers to really get
into this stuff and build
things with it.
If not, it's going to be
relegated into one of these
like, hey, this would
have a nice.
And it never actually works.
I really think that if you
haven't been playing with
WebRTC, get in there, built
stuff with it, make it happen.
It's phenomenal technology.
It just needs people
to make it work.
So file, feedback, improve
APIs, push for
interoperability.
We made a little site with
the compatibility chart.
We're also piping kind of
feedback data from actual
humans about the quality
of the connections.
But I encourage you
to get involved.
Let's make the Open Web even
more awesome with WebRTC.
Thanks, guys.
SCOTT JENSON: Excellent.
[APPLAUSE]
OK.
First is a test.
Can we bring up the moderator
screen again?
OK.
I want to see.
We have quite a bit of people
connected right now.
Let's just do a quick test.
How many of you would
be lying if you said
you liked the talk?
This is a test.
I just want to see.
It was just a logic
question, guys.
Work with me here.
Excellent.
Good, I just wanted to see if
we've got lots of numbers.
That's all I wanted to see.
So OK, now that's working, I
would like to follow what
Steve said, which is to have
each person take about 60
seconds to say any comments,
things you'd like to add onto
Henrik's introductory talk.
So if we start with Martyn--
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Is
this working?
SCOTT JENSON: Yeah.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: So Henrik
has dome some
great work on WebRTC.
And it's very interesting,
especially the data channel
stuff, in my opinion.
But I think we shouldn't
forget about other
technologies, WebSockets
is only two years old.
It's only just now
becoming really
available in a lot of browsers.
And there's a huge amount of
stuff we can do the TCP
connection to the browser.
SCOTT JENSON: OK, Rob.
ROB HAWKES: Yes, there's not a
huge amount to add to that.
But from my point of view, I
think what's most interesting,
particularly with WebRTC,
is the use
beyond audio and video.
So I'm keen to discuss a bit
more into those kind of use
cases, perhaps games, the CDN
stuff and just hearing a bit
more about what's next.
I mean, we have the
implementation today.
And yes, there are isssues
with that.
But what could we do next
to make things better?
SCOTT JENSON: Excellent.
John--
JOHN FALLOWS: Yes, so I agree
with the point made earlier
about other technologies being
highly relevant here.
I think they're each set out to
solve different problems.
And the point about signaling
channels, I think, going
through a server intermediary,
technologies like WebSockets
are ideally suited to that.
And WebRTC, of course, is
ideally targeted at the
peer-to-peer direct
connectivity.
So I see it as a very powerful
blend of technologies as the
web evolves, going forward.
WESLEY HALES And Wesley--
WESLEY HALES Yes, I see the
centralized part is little--
we've got to get past that.
But for instance, for this tool,
all the remotes you're
holding in your hand, it would
be cool if we could pull up
WebRTC to use the mic.
And that way, you wouldn't have
people running around
handing mics out.
So there are so many use cases,
so many possibilities.
SCOTT JENSON: Excellent.
OK, I think we'd like to move
to our first question.
I think that's Andrew Betts,
if you'd like to--
Do we have a microphone
for Andrew?
ANDREW BETTS: I've actually
got the lapel mic.
So I should be fine.
I've got 100 notes here.
So just bear with me
a second, right.
So WebSockets and other Real
Time protocols are commonly
blocked by corporate
proxies and
content inspection firewalls.
And that's a particular problem
for the sort of
customers that we
have at the FT.
How much is this a stifling
adoption?
And what can we do about it?
SCOTT JENSON: Would anyone
like to take that?
OK, John.
JOHN FALLOWS: So I think, just
taking a little step back into
history, when WebSocket was
first added to the HTML5
specification, it wasn't
even called WebSocket.
It was called TCP connection.
And when we saw that show up, we
decided to hop on that and
try to improve the protocol,
to make it web-centric and
bring HTTP to bear.
So it's actually a
web-compatible handshake.
And the reason that we did that
was to avoid tripping
over some of the problems we've
seen before on plug-in
technologies getting defeated
by corporate firewalls.
So we felt that was a huge step
in the right direction.
Now, even given that, we still
find situations where, even
though all the traffic might be
over port 80 and 443, even
with recrypting firewalls and
things like that, that they
can still intercept.
But it's definitely a much
better situation
than it used to be.
And in our particular case, at
Kaazing, we've implemented
some heavy lifting on the
emulation side, to even be
resilient in those situations.
Initially, we wrote the
emulation stuff to kind of
precede the adoption of the
standard, so we could get
started with WebSocket
architectures,
over five years ago.
But moving forward, it tends
to become something that's
still there to support older
clients but also to address
any introduce intermediaries
that might be
getting in the way.
SCOTT JENSON: Are you saying
it's not a problem?
Or it's easy to work around?
JOHN FALLOWS: On the vanilla RFC
support for the protocol,
encryption is a big help.
But even in those situations,
there can be intermediaries
that will decrypt and recrypt
on the critical path and can
still intercept.
And then, there's also a many
web sockets that don't want to
be encrypted for other
reasons, in terms of
performance and things
like that.
From our perspective, we've
seen it be an issue in the
wild, for non-compliant
browsers
trying to do emulation.
We've found ways in our
emulation technique to address
those shortcomings.
SCOTT JENSON: Any
other comments?
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I'll just
make one little comment.
I would say, for this
kind of audience,
there's very little barrier.
You can jump on with
WebSockets.
But if you really want to
address all use cases, as John
says, SSL does help.
But you need to think about
other fallback strategies.
One of the things that would
really help and we maybe could
think about is, we
do [INAUDIBLE]
a lot of work to try and reuse
successful transports again.
But we don't really have enough
information about the
browser's network connection,
to be always able to make
connections.
So maybe that's something we can
talk about later, how we
can discover--
like in the Responsive Images
discussion this morning, we
were saying, the browser has
more information than the web
application.
This is a case where the web
application could do with some
more information really.
SCOTT JENSON: The audience
clearly likes that
comment, by the way.
[AUDIENCE LAUGHING]
That was awesome.
WESLEY HALES OK, keep that up.
SCOTT JENSON: One of the
comments on the Google Monitor
said that TLS actually is an
effective way around this.
Just any comments on
TLS a useful thing?
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Yes,
John just said that.
I mean, yes, we find that.
But unfortunately, there
are examples.
For us, we've had schools,
for example.
And they often block SSL.
And they've got a kind of
a pretty bad situation.
SCOTT JENSON: OK.
Any other comments-- can we move
on to the next question?
HENRIK JORETEG: Well, this
problem is very relevant to
WebRTC as well.
The whole concept of punching
through a firewall to get
something that you can push
directly to an end user is
actually really difficult.
And this is something that the
likes of Apple and Skype have
spent lots and lots of money
trying to solve.
And I would really love to see
some of these technologies be
more broadly available.
There's a few open
source projects.
There's a server called STUN
D. But a lot of these are
really difficult problems.
And I wish that they were more
openly well-documented
solutions to dealing with this,
rather than having to,
as a blog post that came out
yesterday did, actually try to
decrypt what's going on with
FaceTime and what they're
doing to multiplex ports
and all kinds of stuff.
This is not my area
of expertise.
But I know there are people here
who are really good at
this stuff.
And please, please
share your work.
This stuff is needed, in order
to make WebRTC good.
SCOTT JENSON: OK.
The next question is
up by someone.
Is it Gus Gussins?
If we can get him
a mic, please--
AUDIENCE: Hi.
There seems to be some
functional overlap between web
circuits and WebRTC.
When should you use
one or the other?
JOHN FALLOWS: I can take that.
So the fundamental difference
of WebRTC is, it is designed
to be peer-to-peer.
So WebSockets, if you're
going server to client.
That a better use for that.
I think, really, where the
comparison comes from is the
fact that, once you've
established a data channel,
it's largely the same API.
Beyond that, they're different
technologies--
so if you're going peer-to-peer,
WebRTC, if
you're going through a server,
then WebSockets.
SCOTT JENSON: Yes,
go ahead, please.
ROB HAWKES: I was going to say,
one of the other major
differences as well, is again,
looking at beyond
just video and audio.
So for example, multiplayer
games--
WebSockets and WebRTC are
incredibly different because
one is UDP and one is TCP.
So you have unreliable data
connections and reliable data
connections, which just allow
for a very different way of
doing multiplayer
communication.
You just cannot do a
twitch-based multiplayer game
using WebSockets, because you
have to wait for things to
come through.
But WebRTC is allowing us to
use technologies that we've
been using in native
environments.
SCOTT JENSON: You want
to jump in on that?
HENRIK JORETEG: I was just going
to say, the support is a
little flaky for reliable and
unreliable data channels.
But it's part of the spec to
include both, so hopefully,
that becomes easier
to use soon.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And one of the
things I think that we're
likely to see, as the unreliable
data channels
become reliable is that,
actually, people will want to
implement this on
the server side.
And so to be able to communicate
with a game server
via UDP from a browser is
a pretty big thing.
JOHN FALLOWS: Yeah, I think
that's a very point.
And also, I think we touched on
it earlier as well, about
using WebSocket server-centric
strategies for signaling and
set up around WebRTC, is another
interesting variant.
One other thing I would
mention as well, in
deployments in certain
industries, obviously, the
security boundaries of these
things often crop up.
So it's a very interesting
challenge to address some of
those boundaries of where the
trust boundaries reside,
amongst the users and amongst
the server, in a consistent
manner, across both
technologies.
SCOTT JENSON: Isn't there a
perception that this is like a
classic web thing, where we've
got one standard that doesn't
quite work?
So we come up with another
standard that overlaps a bit.
And it's just kind of confusing,
because they kind
of are somewhat related.
Or can we really say that
there's a pure vision of each
one of these things?
And they can both be parallel,
and it's OK.
JOHN FALLOWS: As I said earlier,
I think these are
complimentary technologies
that create a powerful
combination as we
move forward.
And I think they have
well-suited
purposes in each way.
I also think that, there are
certain issues, like the
ability to successfully
navigate through these
firewalls and proxies
on the WebRTC side.
In some of the fallback cases
for WebRTC for reachability,
WebSocket can potentially
lend a hand there too.
SCOTT JENSON: Cool, excellent.
We have another question then,
from the Matthias--
is it Coutsman?
AUDIENCE: My question is, will
WebSockets protocol replace
Server-Sent Events
in the future?
Why must we have both specs, if
WebSockets can accomplish
the same tasks that
SSE does and more?
HENRIK JORETEG: I believe
there's another example of
possible overlap.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I can take
this, if you like.
HENRIK JORETEG: Please.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I would say,
the Server-Sent Events is a
very simple protocol.
And so I think that drives a
lot of adoption early on.
But I think what we'll see,
especially as the WebSockets
spec gets more widely adopted
and a lot of some of the
missing features become
available, for example,
encryption is currently possible
with Server-Sent
Events but not WebSockets.
HENRIK JORETEG: Bi-directional.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Yes, of course,
they're an extra
functionality.
But I think the question is,
for just the use cases that
one would currently use
Server-Sent Events, what's
likely to happen.
For example, multiplexing is
another thing that might allow
people to use a single
connection to address many use
cases on the page.
JOHN FALLOWS: Just to add to
that, thinking back to you
when we were working on the spec
on this stuff, Comet was
the flavor of the day.
Server-Sent Events was being
standardized as a way to
effectively standardize Comet
behavior, several years ago.
And around that time, WebSocket
was starting up too.
So this exact question
came up during
standardization process.
And apart from the points that
have been made already, one of
the overarching arguments that
was left was that, by having a
simplified interaction with
Server-Sent Events, it created
a surface area where the browser
had more control over
the actual behavior.
And the idea was that, on mobile
platforms, this might
actually allow the same
abstraction to be retargeted
at mobile-specific solutions
that didn't necessarily
involve making a traditional
HTTP request over a
traditional TCP connection
and getting a stream of
information coming
back down it.
So there are different
implementations strategies for
the abstraction.
If the abstraction is left
high, the versatility of
WebSocket, obviously means that
you can cover that use
case and many more.
SCOTT JENSON: And Wesley, you
actually had a comment
earlier, when we were talking
about possibly SPDY push.
It just adds to this layering.
WESLEY HALES: Yes.
So the way we send data to the
client, there's bidirectional.
There's with WebSockets.
There's SSE.
And now we've got HTTP
2.0 coming out.
And we've got, right now, what
we can implement is speedy.
And that's available.
And I know Node and Jetty
and other servers.
So we've got these three
options, to choose how to push
data to the client.
And so with HTTP 2.0, is
there going to be--
is it going to be WebSockets
layered over SPDY?
Is that going to be
the approach?
Or is it going to be
pure WebSockets?
Or is Speedy going to have a
mechanism to do bidirectional,
like push and then also receive
messages on one channel?
That was kind of my question,
which I don't
know the answer to.
HENRIK JORETEG: Are there any
HTTP 2.0 experts in the crowd?
SCOTT JENSON: Yeah.
HENRIK JORETEG: That would
be really interesting.
SCOTT JENSON: Don't be shy.
What do you think?
JOHN FALLOWS: Based on what I've
seen so far with SPDY,
I'd expect it to play out where
HTTP and WebSocket go
and parallel it with the same
enveloped SPDY connection, as
at least an option.
Because the to keep WebSockets
out of that would be to create
additional resource hog on that
and the client end server
connection for the
TCP endpoint.
So this seems like a very
natural consequence of having
selected an HTTP handshake to
get started on WebSocket, to
let them all play
nicely together.
SCOTT JENSON: Cool.
Any other comments people
want to make about this?
OK.
Christopher Froelick, you've
got a question
number four coming up.
Christopher--
AUDIENCE: So the WebRTC spec
has driven centralized
solutions, PubNub, et cetera
to a decentralized problem.
What we do to bring a secure,
fully-decentralized solution to bear?
HENRIK JORETEG: That's tricky,
because ultimately, you have
to have some discovery
mechanism.
Right?
There are some attempts--
I forget the name of
the developer now.
There's a project where,
basically, you end up copying
and pasting STP blobs back and
forth over whatever mechanism
you choose.
It could be email.
It could be whatever.
And it still uses STUN, ICE, and
TURN to actually connect.
And with firewalls, I
see that going away.
I mean, I don't know how
to solve that problem.
I would love to see
a solution.
SCOTT JENSON: I want to make
sure we also encourage people
to ask questions.
We're running through our
questions just fine.
But feel free to just jump in
and get on the delegate list,
if you'd like.
Do anybody want to add anything
to that question
about centralized servers?
[INAUDIBLE].
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: I suppose one
of the questions is when do
you need a decentralized
solution, and when do you not
need a decentralized solution?
I mean, I'm not quite clear
on what exactly you mean.
What are the benefits that
you'd want to see from a
decentralized solution?
AUDIENCE: So the first example
that comes to mind is video
collaboration.
So my family and I, we've all
got smartphones, high
resolution cameras
in our pockets.
And we'd like to be able to
share and collaborate on video
together in real time.
And the overhead in trying to
figure out where we are, out
and back down to each other,
seems like a lot, when you
just want a simple way to
connect people that want to.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: OK.
That's a perfect example
for WebRTC.
When you need that mean super
low latency in the UDP, you
kind of start a communication.
It makes perfect sense.
HENRIK JORETEG: Well, in theory,
STUN and ICE should
help you locate and figure out
that those they are in fact on
the same network and then be
able to connect the two.
That's not a complete
solution.
But it's something.
AUDIENCE: Sure.
So just to antagonize that
point a bit, if we're all
intimately connected, say, via
mobile data, so we're not on
the same network.
And we're using just a plain
vanilla web app.
There's no clear path to a
central server, necessarily,
in a quick and easy-to-use
way.
HENRIK JORETEG: Right.
Now you're talking about
connecting devices that really
are not on the same
network at all.
And that's a whole different
type of problem, I think.
I think that would be
awesome, but I don't
know quite how that--
I don't know how to
fix that one.
SCOTT JENSON: Kyle actually, I
believe, has got a question.
Let's make sure that
he get the mic.
Is he sitting over there?
This is a delegate, so we can
make sure we get him up there.
AUDIENCE: So it seems like
there's two major reasons why
centralization still happens.
The first one is
discoverability, obviously.
If we don't have any way for
two different people to get
hooked up on a blind date,
then they don't know what
restaurant to show up at.
So somebody has to introduce
the two.
But that seems like that should
be solvable through
other bands.
Like, there's been other
peer-to-peer networks, music
sharing and BitTorrent and
other things like that.
It seems like there should
be ways to sort
of solve that problem.
But there's another problem
that, one of the reasons why
people centralize stuff
is because they
want to bill for it.
So when companies are creating
products around this stuff, if
we truly completely
decentralized and everything
was peer-to-peer, nobody would
know that was happening.
And nobody could make
a buck off of that.
So how do you see that sort of
tension happening, where we do
want to get rid of
centralization, but we don't
want to not be able to charge
for it, for instance?
HENRIK JORETEG: I can
comment on that.
So in my opinion, the telecoms
of the future are Google,
Facebook, and the like.
The old, traditional telecom
system is likely
not to stick around.
Somebody didn't like that.
But really, I mean, if you think
about it, the reason
phones are so successful and
they're so prevalent is
because I can call anybody.
I have an AT&T phone.
I can call somebody
on Verizon.
Why can't I call somebody
from Google+ on
from my Facebook account?
The whole concept of federation
does not currently
really exist, in a broadly
accepted way, in the web.
And I think the reason
is, no one is pissed.
I think, that's something that,
if it was retroactively
imposed on--
now people are pissed.
Here we go.
ANDREW BETTS: So getting
[INAUDIBLE] web standards is a
bunch of really angry people
getting together.
HENRIK JORETEG: I guess.
I don't know.
So I don't know.
I mean, I think that's why
there's kind of this whole
silo effect going on.
SCOTT JENSON: But is WebRTC
architectured
to solve that problem?
Is that part of the issue?
HENRIK JORETEG: Yes.
SCOTT JENSON: Is it solvable?
HENRIK JORETEG: Yeah, certainly,
it's providing just
a very base level of technology,
as far as the
communication piece.
But in order to actually connect
the two, you need
other technologies on top.
You need the discoverability
piece.
You need the addressability.
You need a strong identity,
so you can say,
I am a Google user.
You can reach me at my Google
account, that sort of thing.
So WebRTC is one
of the pieces.
It's not all of it.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: The great about
WebRTC see is that, it's
enabling all the web developers
in the world.
It's removing a huge number of
barriers, from being able to
actually innovate
in that space.
For too long, we've had
dressed-up applications that
have not been able to.
ROB HAWKES: I think the
discoverability side of things
as well is a big problem.
Because right now, it's just
sort of, like you said, up to
developers and stuff
like that.
And there are so many
ways to do it.
I mean, you could manually paste
these blobs and stuff,
which is stupid.
But you can do it.
But I mean, there are ways that
we need to look at how to
better solve those kinds of
problems as well, like
preparing devices or
things like that.
So it's not always two people
that are trying to connect.
It might be one person trying
to connect two devices.
So for example, I might be
trying to connect a mobile
device to a TV, to remote
control it.
The discovery mechanisms for
that are going to be
incredibly different than
connecting two people who have
full control over processing and
can just doing a chat room
or something.
So those are the kind of
problems I want to
see solve a lot more.
And people are kind of
approaching that.
And there's a few solutions
with trying to replicate
things like Apple Bonjour and
stuff, in the browser and
requesting that from the
browser vendors.
But there has not
been significant
traction on that yet.
SCOTT JENSON: Well, It sounds
to me like there is going to
be a whole topology of
applications, like an awful
lot of websites could just put
in video chat to our tech
support line.
That will be a trivial thing for
them to do, because it's
entirely through their
own stack.
Then it's about getting
bigger.
And are you trying say that we
need more standards for the
bigger to happen?
HENRIK JORETEG: These
things have existed
for quite some time.
XMPP is extremely stable and
extremely well used.
And it's not something that
web developers like.
But they've gotten really good
at solving these problems.
And there are some efforts under
way, two specifically.
One is stanza.io, which is
basically the attempt to give
a clean JavaScript
API to XMPP.
And another one is XMPP
FTW for the web.
And thinking of things like
browser ID as a potential
alternative to identify, to be
able to provide that strong
identity piece.
Because once you have that
addressability, it actually
becomes fairly simple, in
terms of, once you know
how to reach you.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: But these
solutions are all very
heavyweight solutions, all the
XMPP, even if it has a nice
JavaScript API one day.
I think what Rob is talking
about is just saying, well,
you've got two devices
next to each other.
Can they just make it a little
kind of chirp or some video
communication or something
like that, to
discover each other.
ROB HAWKES: I think we're kind
of seeing people approach
those problems, and very, very
slightly at the moment, like
the whole idea of using audio
to connect two devices.
SCOTT JENSON: Boris [INAUDIBLE]
did that
ultrasonic demo.
Right, exactly.
ROB HAWKES: So there are people
already exploring and,
potentially, not exactly
in this area.
But there are solutions
around right now.
We've got solutions for pairing
Bluetooth devices and
stuff like that.
Like, there are methods
and means.
I think we've not seen people
use them just yet.
And we will, as people
start using WebRTC,
beyond audio and video.
And that will just
come in time.
SCOTT JENSON: We've got a
question waiting, from David,
actually, from the audience.
David Stickler--
and then, we'll go on to
Natasha's question.
AUDIENCE: We see a rise of
security issues, where people
are actually trying to open too
many TCP connections to a
web server.
And they're actually killing the
web server, by opening too
many TCP connections.
So people tend to actually
remove keepalive, to avoid
these kind of issues.
What do you think about web
circuit and security for this
kind of problem?
And how can we solve this?
JOHN FALLOWS: Well, one of the
things that was put into this,
back towards the end of its
finalization of the standard,
was a clarification on, what's
the maximum upper bound on the
number of web sockets that can
hit a server at a time.
And it was unspecified, so we
wanted to get that cleared.
And at the time, a decision was
made to not limit it but
also to add a caveat to that,
that only one handshake could
be outstanding to
the same target
server at the same time.
So from a browser invocation
standpoint, spinning up lots
and lots of WebSockets in rapid
succession would give
the server an opportunity to
intercept and potentially
detect repeated attempts, and
therefore, mitigate that.
In general, I think things like
SPDYs and Nvelope, as we
touched on earlier, underneath
these things, tends to
mitigate some of that, at
the physical TCP layer.
And also, having higher-level
abstractions on top of the
WebSocket going forward,
that's more of like a
publishing subscriber and
event-driven more
architectural approach
to things.
It allows you to partition
up the universe of
addressability.
So you don't just think of as
connecting directly to the
thing you want to speak to, just
because that's the end of
the WebSocket.
Once you're attached to the
architecture, then you can
reach a whole myriad
of services,
through that same channel.
SCOTT JENSON: Cool.
I think the next question is
actually quite high level,
about [INAUDIBLE].
Natasha, if we can give
you that one--
AUDIENCE: Thanks.
So this question if from
an anonymous sender.
Bandwidth throttling, especially
for multiple HD
video streams, is extremely
hard to do properly.
Is there any risk that WebRTC
will vary greatly by
implementation?
SCOTT JENSON: I think, most
likely, I'm assuming this is
about one to one is one thing.
If you're doing one to four, one
to five, I think it gets
to be much harder.
And are we going to see,
possibly, it just fall over
because Firefox doesn't do it
as well as say, Chrome?
HENRIK JORETEG: This
is actually--
in my opinion, it's
two problems.
One is, for example, Skype what
they will do, from what I
understand, they will elect
the strongest connection.
And it's not just connection.
It's about the ability
to encode and decode
video really quickly.
So you need a strong device and
strong connection, to kind
of be able to serve as
a rebroadcaster.
And currently, that's kind
of part of the spec.
But it's not really there yet.
Like, if you take a media
stream from one user and
attach it to another, it
just doesn't work.
And that's absolutely crucial
for the stuff to be able to be
usable for handling these other
interesting network
topologies.
Mesh is only good for so many,
because you're uploading your
video to each person that you're
connected to and so is
everybody else.
So your upload bandwidth becomes
a huge bottleneck.
SCOTT JENSON: And didn't you
say that WebRTC doesn't
throttle down?
HENRIK JORETEG: So yeah, there
needs to be control mechanisms
for adjusting bandwidth.
And they just are not in place,
as far as I can tell.
Nothing I've tried has worked.
SCOTT JENSON: Well, I actually
was working at a video
conferencing company.
And that was probably the
biggest aspect of our secret
sauce, to throttle bandwidth
properly.
So WebRTC isn't thinking about
it, it seems like it's kind of
heading for a bit of
a train wreck.
HENRIK JORETEG: I don't think
it's not thinking about it.
I think it's just, the
implementations
aren't quite there yet.
That's my impression.
I've kind of raised it to some
of the Google folks who are
working on this stuff.
And that's kind of the
answer I get back.
It's like, yeah, we know
this is a thing
we've got to deal with.
I mean, Google Hangouts,
they're well aware.
There's a low bandwidth
mode for that.
And we need to be able to do
the same kinds of things,
without re-requesting a
smaller video size.
We need to be able to just kind
of adjust them, based on
quality and lost packets.
SCOTT JENSON: Over here.
ROB HAWKES: This kind of problem
as well, particularly
the one to many kind of
bandwidth problem is
applicable in games as well.
So that's where the background
is, from my point of view.
But if you're building
multiplayer games, you're
quickly going to come
over that problem.
And it's not something you can
necessarily avoid in that
circumstance, because you have
to be communicating out to
these multiple players
in the game.
But people have solved these
problems before.
And there are ways to sort
of reduce the amount of
information you're sending.
So for example, in a game, you
don't send updates to people
that aren't necessary
in your vicinity or
something like that.
So it's not always a
technology problem.
It's just a creative way of
thinking about how the data is
being sent to all the
different people.
And are you sending it
to the right people?
There may be 100 people
in the game.
But there might only be two that
are actually applicable
and need the updates that
you're sending.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: Another
separate point to that is, I
think we might need to-- it's
only the very early days, in
terms of peer-to-peer
connections on the web.
So if you look at, historically,
you'd have
clients like Skype that are open
for many hours, unstable
broadband connections.
What happens, for example, on
battery life on a mobile
device, when suddenly, you've
got four different
connections.
And it's sending the data four
times, sending the video to
four different clients.
And you said earlier about
strong peers--
is that actually realistic
on the web?
I mean, are tabs open
long enough
for that to be realistic?
I don't know the answer
to these questions.
WESLEY HALES: Yeah, it's
a big push too.
I mean, you have around 50
people connected here, all day
long, using a WebSocket
connection.
And I mean, let's see.
My battery life, I've
got about 25% left.
So this is the same thing.
People are connected.
They're using this protocol
all day long at this
conference.
And it's draining the battery.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And that's
one to one, to a server.
What happens if it's a one to
many, with a WebRTC data
connection?
WESLEY HALES: Right.
HENRIK JORETEG: It also takes
a lot of power to encode and
decode video that fast and to do
it with multiple people at
the same time.
So that's a huge drain
on power right there.
I know my laptop fans start
going crazy, when I'm testing
with like five people.
So it's a big problem.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And this seems
to be back to the kind
of discussion this morning
about images.
I mean, for Real Time Data, do
we need to change the way to
the data is delivered for
someone who's batter is
constrained versus a PC?
HENRIK JORETEG: Yeah, I could
see the same thing, for
responsive video, essentially.
ROB HAWKES: Again, this
comes back to games.
These kind of problems are being
solved in games, in the
way you sort throttle the
communication, depending on
the bandwidth capabilities
of each person
and stuff like that.
So there's a lot of lessons
we can take
from things like games.
And this is why I'm so adamant
on not focusing so much on
audio and video.
Although, yes, that is the
use case right now.
Some of the problems that we're
approaching are being
solved or being looked
at in other areas.
And I think it's just
interlinking the two and
trying to sort of combine them
and come up with a solution.
SCOTT JENSON: I am surprised
that, maybe as a web
community, we always kind of
wring our hands a little bit
about saying, everybody and
inclusiveness and so forth.
And Sugar Crush doesn't give
a damn about battery life.
they're just like, you want to
play it, then just plug the
damn thing in, right.
And now, I'm not saying
that's correct.
But to a certain extent, the
native community kind of
washes their hands of
this a little bit.
Are we trying too hard,
just saying?
HENRIK JORETEG: I think enabling
mobile is really,
really, really important.
Because I think certain things
don't matter, obviously.
If your playing some hardcore
game, you not going to be
sitting there forever maybe.
But to not take it into
consideration when these are
the actual physical hardware
limitations that we're dealing
with, I think is selling
ourselves short.
JOHN FALLOWS: And I also think
it's important that you've got
things in place to avoid
accidentally doing it.
So we want to make sure that
developers aren't accidentally
draining their battery.
If it's a deliberate decision,
that's one thing.
But if they just happen to be
on the end of a bandwidth
connection that's a little less
capable, we want to be
able to react to that.
ROB HAWKES: I think that we
have. we're getting the APIs
to play with this kind
of stuff as well now.
And actually, I'm not seeing
people implementing this yet,
but for example, using the
battery API, and actually, if
the battery level is at a
certain point, changing the
way you're communicating
and stuff like that.
SCOTT JENSON: Yeah.
I've My point, by the way,
wasn't to seriously say, we
don't care but to say, it is
interesting that some apps
don't care.
And we just do seem to be a
little holier than thou
sometimes, which is actually
good to have that aspiration.
JOHN FALLOWS: I think that
may very well just be the
difference between thinking of
it in a platform perspective
versus thinking of it as an
application perspective.
SCOTT JENSON: Yeah, OK.
Actually, question number
six, I think
we've already answered.
I believe Steve Thayer
has a question.
Right here, he needs
a microphone.
AUDIENCE: Actually, I think
Rob has actually
just touched on this.
WebRTC seems to have
focused more on the
audio and video streams.
And data channels are
a special case.
Shouldn't all peer-to-peer
communication just be data
streams where the different data
types can be interpreted
as appropriate?
ROB HAWKES: Not all
peer-to-peer is--
how do you mean, like should
they will be the same, just
data channels?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I think the question was
sort of saying--
I'm just trying to find
a way to rephrase it.
Most of the panel has just
purely been talking about
audio and video.
But audio and video are
just a type of data.
OK, it has specific
characteristics.
Why is the focus purely focusing
on m rather than just
coming up with a more generic
data channel?
HENRIK JORETEG: I was just
going to-- a quick little
one-liner, I think it makes a
better demo, which is why it
landed first.
That's my opinion.
It's also kind of special case,
in certain ways, that
you're trying to negotiate
encoding types, et cetera.
But yeah, fundamentally,
I agree with you.
I think peer connections,
you're still
doing the same thing.
You establish a single
peer connection.
You add and remove
data channels.
You add and remove video
and audio channels.
It's still one peer
connection.
At least, that's the way it's
written in the spec.
So hopefully.
It's actually--
I don't know.
Go ahead.
ROB HAWKES: I mean,
generally, yes.
They are types of data.
But the media streaming is
incredibly different and much
more complicated than
just sending sort
of basic data across.
So there is a reason why
they are separated.
But I truly do think that the
data channel side of things,
like sending generic, non-audio,
non-video kind of
data is where WebRTC has an
incredible amount of strength
and where we're not really
focusing on yet.
So right now, we're not
exploring that too much.
But I'm very interested to
see how that is exposed.
Because audio and video is
the interesting thing.
And that's kind why WebRTC
was created.
And that's the exciting thing.
I mean, imagining be able to
call Skype from a browser.
That's incredible use case.
But it's now where do we
take that technology.
And what's next?
And I think the data
channels is where
that's sort of hiding.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: And of
course, as far as I
understand, there's some thought
of bringing in other
media streams, not just
audio and video.
What about temperature
information or sensor
information?
I don't know if anything
is happening there.
I don't really know.
But I've heard it mooted
as a possibility.
SCOTT JENSON: Well actually,
there's one comment I wanted
to make, which is that, so
often, we expect these specs
to be perfect.
And if they're not perfect, we
get really upset at them.
Look how bad the web
is and so forth.
But shouldn't we just maybe cut
WebRTC and maybe others a
little bit of slack and say,
maybe to your point, what can
we do as a community, to kind
of exercise things and then
give some feedback.
What can we do just
to do that?
HENRIK JORETEG: I mean,
definitely.
I would suggest to everybody in
here, if you haven't, start
playing with the stuff.
It's very, very--
I hate the word disruptive.
But it's a ridiculously
disruptive technology.
I mean, I seriously built my
own telecom to call my mom
with in Sweden.
I mean, come on.
I'm not supposed to be
able to do that.
So this is the kind of power
that it provides you.
And I would love to see
everybody here really get in
and hacking on this stuff.
SCOTT JENSON: Stephen--
STEPHEN THAYER: Well, I guess,
just on that last point, just
what you said there, if we could
quickly poll the panel.
You say, this is awesome.
Like, what other use cases would
the panel have, if you
could each nominate a use case
for WebRTC of something cool
that you'd like to see
that you think
this technology enables?
SCOTT JENSON: Excellent
question.
Can we just go through?
WESLEY HALES: Video
conferencing--
no.
Yeah.
So it would be cool if the
remotes that you guys are
using, like I said earlier,
you could just
pull Get User Media.
And we wouldn't have
to hand you a mic.
You could just speak
to your phone
microphone and be broadcast.
So that would require hooking
up to the AV here.
It will require writing
the code to
handle the binary data.
And then, there's a lot of
in-room geolocation.
Like, there's been a lot of
investments made in companies
doing this lately, where you
actually can find devices in
the room with much greater
granularity, using a
geolocation API.
So with WebRTC, you
could say, OK.
I guess you'd have to have some
centralized mechanism.
But you could find out
all the people who
like the color blue.
And then, you would be able to
pull up a video chat with them
in this room, using that
newer technology.
So there are complementary
technologies, I guess, that
would be required for
that use case.
But that's an idea.
SCOTT JENSON: OK, John.
JOHN FALLOWS: Yeah, I think just
enabling the internet of
things, machine of things
kind of stuff.
Because a lot of times, with a
centralized model, we assume
that, even though these devices
may be talking to one
another, that they're actually
able to potentially mediate or
coordinate against a connected
server system.
So just not having to rely on
that always being around, but
still that blending these two
worlds together seamlessly, I
think that's a tough challenge
to do well.
But just raising the abstraction
a little bit, so
it makes these things easy.
And get it out of the developers
hands, who are
trying to solve all these
complex problems.
At Kaazing, we call these things
the web of things,
instead of the internet
of things.
Because we think that a lot of
the challenges that we see, in
trying to connect together
those IP or lower-level
protocols with WebRTC, that we
don't actually see so much in
the WebSocket because
it's web centric.
It's achieved by raising the
bar a little bit and
connecting everything together
at the web level, instead of
thinking at the internet
level.
So we say, web of things.
SCOTT JENSON: Cool, Henrik.
HENRIK JORETEG: I would love
to see peer distributed
rebroadcasting.
Why couldn't I pull up my phone
and be able to stream
something just off my phone
to the entire internet?
If you have a proper
rebroadcasting ability, where
a peer could relay that feed,
you could basically turn every
person on the planet with
a smartphone into a news
reporter, capable of live
broadcast, which is
phenomenal.
And again, that's
video and audio.
But I think that particular
one is really interesting.
Of course, you could do the
exact same thing with any of
other type of data.
Examples, I can't think
of anything off
the top of my head.
I've been too focused
on the video stuff.
SCOTT JENSON: Cool.
ROB HAWKES: I've got to say,
I mean, the simplest one is
games and how that's going to
completely change, now we've
got UDP and unreliable data.
But the second one is the web
of things, like these
interconnected devices and
actually having the non-human
interaction and devices talking
to each That's where
it gets really interesting.
We have phones powered
by JavaScript.
The entire operating system
is written in JavaScript.
That's incredible.
We now have Arduino devices
powered by JavaScript and
stuff like that.
And how are things
going to change?
And how could we use
WebRTC to see to
interlink those devices?
And what does that now
allow us to do that
we couldn't do before?
Using web technologies that
already are interoperable with
all of the other things that we
have available to us, like
the hardware APIs and just all
the other web APIs, that's
where things are very,
very interesting.
WESLEY HALES: Yeah, I
think I would just
reiterate that point.
It's enabling--
it's disrupting the control.
And when you need an ultra-low
latency connection between two
objects, it's now possible
for web developers
to build those things.
So you have a control
surface for a
quadrocopter or something.
You can now build that
in a web browser.
It's amazing.
SCOTT JENSON: But isn't it going
to be an issue that not
too many adruinos will be
running Chrome right now?
So how do we get WebRTC into
these lower-level devices?
ROB HAWKES: Someone
needs to built it.
SCOTT JENSON: OK.
I mean, I was making sure I was
following what you said.
Because what you said is
great, but there's no
immediate way for us do that.
Correct?
JOHN FALLOWS: This is a room
of developers, right?
Somebody can do it.
ROB HAWKES: This is partly why
we're asking about WebRTC on
the server and things
like that.
Once you can get it
into things like
node.js, then this is--
SCOTT JENSON: It will be huge.
I think we have a few
minutes left.
And Christopher has
been patient.
We'll do him and then,
I think, you.
OK?
Christopher-- no, that
Christopher.
AUDIENCE: So I apologize if I
sound like a broken record.
But as soon as just said,
enabling technology, I'm
brought back again
to the idea of
decentralizing the solutions.
You think of dissident
suppression,
say, in Arab Spring.
And the raw potential that
exists in the phone to
directly connect people.
Without a central network
connection, that isn't possible.
Or emergency response as
earthquakes, hurricanes take
out centralized communications,
it seems like
the technology exists to solve
to help solve these
communication problems.
It's really just a comment.
ROB HAWKES: That's a really
interesting problem.
And that's something I've not
developed for, but I've been
thinking about a little bit.
And the whole idea of creating
mesh networks out of nowhere,
using these technologies,
is incredibly powerful.
The ability to then spread
communication amongst an ad
hoc local network is crazy.
You have to get over the actual
connecting the two
devices together problem.
But if we can solve that, then
what you can actually do with
that is incredibly powerful.
MARTYN LOUGHRAN: It's kind of
like the only way you could do
that now is to carry around some
extra little antenna with
you , with an extra
power supply and
create your own network.
That would have to be standard
issue for emergencies.
Yeah, I mean, that's today.
But your phone cannot power that
kind of transmission and
that and that findability.
SCOTT JENSON: And you've been
patient, one more question.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say, it
doesn't seem that you need
a web browser, in order
to have WebRTC.
You could always do it through
Node or through a JavaScript
on chip device.
SCOTT JENSON: Right, it's a
simple matter of programming.
ROB HAWKES: It just doesn't
exist at the moment.
HENRIK JORETEG: There have
been some efforts.
There's actually a [INAUDIBLE]
library that attempted
to bind to libjingle.
And I don't quite know
the status of that.
It hasn't had much activity.
SCOTT JENSON: I think we've
got the wrap up.
So thank you very much.
If you liked the session,
please give us a vote.
And if you don't, just
give us a vote.
WESLEY HALES: Whoever is writing
the script to do like
50 votes, just go ahead
up that to 100.
SCOTT JENSON: Awesome.
Thanks very much.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN FALLOWS: Good job, whoever
wrote that for loop.
ANDREW BETTS: Does anyone
want to admit to
hacking the voting system?
No?
OK.
WESLEY HALES: His name
is [INAUDIBLE].
ANDREW BETTS: His name
is [INAUDIBLE]
apparently.
OK.
So our next panel is
the Offline panel.
This is actually a panel we're
reprising from Edge 1.
Because we didn't fix it then,
so we're going to try again.
Also, a lot has change
in offline.
We have the solution that was
called Navigation Trawler,
which was then called Event
Worker, which was then called
Service Worker.
And what is it called now?
AUDIENCE: Service Worker.
ANDREW BETTS: Service
Worker, excellent.
So I think everyone needs a bit
of a refresher on where we
are with offline.
And so we have a great panel
of people to discuss that.
The chair for the session is
Jake Archibald from Google.
And I will hand it over to Jake,
as soon as he's ready.
Are you ready?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yeah.
And Alex, you can get set up
while I'm doing the intro.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the Offline panel.
Most of us, as web developers,
I think it's fair to say that
we declare, game over, when
there's no network connection
available or when it's faulty.
But if we want to compete with
the creme of native apps, then
having the networks
as a dependency is
simply not good enough.
But the five brave souls in
front of you today, they laugh
in the face of zero bars
of connectivity.
And they do not want your wallet
to be drained, when you
are roaming.
And they do not want to give up
on you, when your ISP has.
We have Matt Andrews from the
"Financial Times." We've got
Craig Cavalier from
LiquidFrameworks.
We've got Calvin Spielman
from Cactus Consulting.
These guys have been building
stuff with the current crop of
inadequate APIs that
we have on the web.
But they've suffered
through that.
So give them a hug afterwards,
because they've
been damaged by that.
But we also have Anne Van
Kesteren from Mozilla and Alex
Russell from Google.
And these guys been working on
the future APIs that are going
to solve of all of our
worldly problems.
Is that fair to say?
Yeah.
OK, that's good
So we're hoping that, in the
future, making a site work
offline is not going to be an
act of self-flagellation.
And on that note, Alex, I
believe you're going to
introduce the topic.
Are you good to go?
ALEX RUSSELL: Sure.
As Jake says, I'm Alex.
Do we have slides?
Did I fail at this
miserably, again?
So good at this--
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So yeah, we've
changed the name of the new
stuff a couple of
times recently.
It offers navigation control.
But it's been expanded.
It spent a little bit time
as Event Worker.
Now it's Service Worker.
But it has been pointed out by
Lady Ada King, on Twitter,
that Service Worker does sound
somewhat like the oldest
profession in the world.
So I don't know.
We kind of thought maybe
Service Controller.
but does that sound
like a pimp?
I don't know.
But then App Pimp, that's
pretty cool.
We all want to use
an App Pimp.
So maybe we'll go with
that, pimp our apps.
That could be cool.
So yeah, we're going to have
to find a name for it that
doesn't evoke that kind
of a negative thing.
But how are you doing, Alex?
Because I'm running
out of filler.
Is it because it doesn't
work offline?
Is that your problem?
That might actually be it.
ALEX RUSSELL: Yes, so as
Jake says, I am Alex.
And I am rescaling the
slides as we speak.
So I spend a lot of
time offline.
I most recently lived in London
before I returned to
San Francisco.
And they did something in the
tube for the Olympics, where
they said they were going to put
Wi-Fi in all the stations,
which technically speaking
is accurate.
They did happen to put Wi-Fi
transmitters and receivers in
all of the stations.
But one of my most frequent tube
journeys was to and from
airports because I spend a
lot of time on airplanes.
And it always seemed
really punitive.
Because you would get to a
station, and for about 20
seconds, while people were
loading and unloading, you
wireless, Wi-Fi radio would
be attempting to connect,
frantically to the thing.
And you'd be trying to log in
a little bit, so you could
just download the next--
no!
Fuck, we're moving.
So I got really good at figuring
out how to turn off
the Wi-Fi on my device, because
the network just
wasn't reliable.
Even when I absolutely wanted
it, I wanted to see the news.
I wanted to get the latest
"Times" or "Guardian" or
whatever it is.
OK, I've outed myself
as a lefty, fine.
And the end of this journey, of
course, ends you up in an
airport, where you are at the
whim of whoever happens to
have the crappy Wi-Fi in
whatever bit of hell you've
ended yourself up in,
with the captive
portal and all the rest.
So these are hostile network
environments.
And they mediate our lives.
I think the work environment and
the home environment are
special cases of how we
interact with the
stuff around us.
And it's in those environments--
the airport,
the tube, the ones that are
really stressful, where you're
trying to get some place.
You've got a thing.
Where the heck was I going?
What's this thing I'm trying
to do right now?
I don't remember.
I look at my phone and---
It's that environment that we,
as a technology stack, fail at
miserably, largely because we
have built ourselves the
assumption that what
is remote is cheap.
Because everything
is remote, right.
The web is designed around the
idea of the URL, the thing
that is over there, that's
cheap to do.
And that little, tiny anchor
tag makes it look like
everything is connected
to you, all the time.
a href is the most innocent
thing you
can possibly imagine.
And at the same time,
the implications
of a href are massive.
It says nothing about
whether or not you
can get to the network.
And the tube gives us a good
window into what it means to
know whether or not
you're online.
So we keep getting requests for
you a bandwidth property
in the browser.
Tell me what my bandwidth is.
Tell me what my available
bandwidth is.
There's no way to
actually know.
So if I show up at a conference
and there's a
captive portal to go
get me my thing.
My bandwidth to a thing
which does nothing I
want might be infinite.
Whereas, my bandwidth to all the
services I actually care
about might be negative.
So we find ourselves in
this situation a lot.
And it's very difficult from the
browser's perspective to
say anything meaningful
about your connection.
Saying something other than,
I can't do anything because
there's no radio turned on,
and it's not connected
anything, is a very difficult
call to make.
So we've put ourselves in a
situation on the web where
we've architected an entire
stack of stuff around the idea
that, the thing that's over
there is really cheap or at
least as cheap as everything
else is.
And the thing that's local
is unreliable.
Caches are things that
get evicted.
They're things that
you can't trust.
They're things you
can't rely on.
And this isn't how we build
anything, anywhere else.
I would never build a
browser on top of
this technology stack.
And I don't mean that in the
sense that, there are things
that you can't do.
I mean, you'd never put up with
the idea that the Close
Tab icon might be evicted.
That's not a thing that you
would ever put up with.
So let's think through
how we got here.
So imagine a little website
that's a little, tiny two-man
agency, two-person agency,
two-alien agency, two beings.
And they're trying to put
together a website.
And it's the simplest thing
that could possibly work.
And if you sort of deconstruct
this layout, it tells you kind
of everything you
need to know.
This is really, really simple.
This is static content,
effectively.
And it probably will bit rot.
You know, they're probably not
going to change their team
website, if they're even
moderately successful.
Because it will strip their
ability to actually build
websites for themselves, because
they'll be doing it
for clients.
OK.
So this is going to be
effectively unmaintained.
And if you look at how it's
built, you can sort of get a
sense for what it takes to
get started on the web.
You have some resources.
You have some HTML files.
And when you really start out,
it's copy and paste.
If you're going to get advance
for $19.95, you'll eventually
configure Apache to do
server-side includes.
And you'll change these to
.SHTML, thank you very much.
And you'll have your server-side
includes for the
navigations and the footers
at the top and the bottom.
And you will have whacked
all that in.
And so now we're starting to see
that there is a repeated
bit of content around some
of the things that we're
addressing with URLs.
So I have a blog, right.
Please don't read it.
I'll save you time and
embarrassment.
But that blog is much more
sophisticated than that little
tiny way layout for a static
website, effectively, like a
brochure ware site, largely
because the location of my
domain in frequently.org has
nothing to do with an
individual but bit of content.
It's not addressing some
bit of content.
It's addressing a database
query, a reverse chronological
order query across
these tables.
And when we ship this stuff down
to the client, we don't
ship those tables.
We explode a bunch of
that stuff out.
We denormalize it entirely,
serialize it, through
templates, and then
spit it all out.
But if you go look at any
individual article, it sort of
corresponds to one item in
one of those tables.
And then, we take all the whole
machinery again, which
is the shell around that little
bit of content that
we're addressing with the URL.
And we explode it all out.
And we ship this huge bundle
of content down, which
effectively wraps the stuff.
And if you look at the HTML,
that's actually what happens.
It's just document and then tons
and tons of stuff around
it and then this thing that we
were actually putting in the
center of this template thing,
which is what the URL is kind
of actually pointing at.
When we talk about meaningful
URLs, we tend to mean
meaningful, with regards to the
thing that's the primary
thing you, as a user,
would focus on.
It's a very subjective view,
because it's about what the
user is experiencing about that
location, about that state.
So if you think about
it, what is the URL
actually talking about?
We start to get this idea that
what we've done for a couple
of decades now is to take
server-side graphs of state
and pre-explode them for
digestion by the client.
And that pre-explosion means
that, HTML is something that's
incredibly powerful and
effectively display only.
And it gets really confused, as
soon as you start talking
about doing dynamic stuff.
Because there's that big model
over on the server which is
written in--
at least in the cases of
Wordpress, it's PHP and MySQL.
These are two technologies
which, without extraordinary
acts of inhuman and inhumane
technology, are not going to
be running in my browser
anytime soon.
I'm sure there's a scum
VM that would run
something like this.
But today, we're
not doing that.
And the latency characteristics
haven't been
set up to do it.
So let's imagine the next sort
of leap, from little, tiny
blogware, or sorry, brochureware
thing to blog,
which is a moderately
complicated CMS to the biggest
thing we can think of that's
still effectively static
content, infrequently updated
static content.
I submit Wikipedia.
So the question becomes, if
you're building Wikipedia as
an app or if you're trying to
make it possible for me, while
sitting on a tube--
20 seconds at the time of
connectivity, if I'm lucky--
to go and read an article and
click on a link to go to the
next article, what is required
for us to think about making
that a meaningful thing to do.
It turns out, the thing that you
really require is the help
of the user.
Because it's not possible to
think through this whole
system and say, I'm going
to go grab all of it.
My blog is relatively small.
You could maybe fetch it all.
But you couldn't fetch
all of Wikipedia.
I've tried this.
Decompressing this takes about
20 minutes in an i7, a really
ballsy laptop.
Now, downloading it took
a couple minutes too.
So think about Gmail.
What am I indexing when I
go to one of these URLs?
Or when I go to a music site,
could I possibly download that
entire library?
My Gmail is really,
really full.
I don't want the entire
contents.
In fact, I want some
subset of that.
And I, as the user, am willing
to help you go figure
out what that is.
And as the media size, the
atomic size of the media gets
bigger and the more of it that
I've got, the more that
pressure builds up on us.
We don't really have a way
of thinking about it.
So the way I've phrased this
now is that, there's an
application that you'd like to
think about, which is what
helps the browser
render content.
And then there's content.
And in the old days,
quote-unquote "old days," we
tried to conflate the two
as much as possible.
We would smoosh the shell into
the content with server-side
includes and CGI.
And as we get more sophisticated
and more
dynamic, we have to serve the
shell and think about the
shell differently
to the content.
They're different entities.
So it turns out the offline
problem is actually about
making applications that can
bootstrap themselves.
It's not about this, how do I
transparently turn the thing
that I've got into that other
thing over there.
It's about the data model
and where it's split.
Who owns the data, and
where does it live?
Am I doing synchronization over
a thing that I've synched
part of to the client?
Or am I shipping a series
of pre-exploded pages?
That's kind of the
core problem that
we have with offline.
So a service worker is an
attempt to get us through--
oh, went too far--
a couple of these problems, by
saying that, we don't know the
answer for your application.
But what we do know is that,
you don't have enough
control right now.
We spend a lot of time
looking through it.
And basically, it's an
in-browser proxy that you can
install from the perspective
of your origin.
And when you do, at some point
later when it finishes
installing, you'll get notified
and the ability to
proxy, do whatever you like,
with the response for any
request those documents make.
You get to own the request.
Cross domain, same origin,
you name it.
And it gives you programmatic
control over a series of
caches as well.
So it's relatively simple.
You say, I would like
to register for
one of these things.
And it gives you
a promise back.
Yes, promises are coming
to the dome.
You can thank some
people later.
And you can actually compose
stuff, from third parties.
You can pull in resources to use
with these cache objects.
And then, this add event
listener for fetches actually
gives you the ability to
go and construct--
you see that e.respond with new
SameOrigin response there
toward the bottom.
That's actually creating a
response out of whole cloth.
You're just programmatically
saying, this is the content
that you should send back
to this document.
That's the idea.
You've never been able
to do this before,
except on the server.
What if we could do this
on the client?
And why can't we, by the way?
You can imagine another
couple of ideas.
I would like to, when I'm
offline, serve some fallback.
Or if I've got pictures of cats,
and I would like them to
be responsive cats.
I would like you to, through
some magical API, figure out
what we've already stored about
the client, what we
know, the device pixel width,
the aspect ratio that we
probably are displaying at,
the kinds of things that a
document could tell us, while
it's populating the service
worker and then have the service
worker respond with
the correct one, as opposed to
trying to figure it all out
preemptively upfront
and make CSS do the
heavy lifting for us.
I'm actually getting
to the end.
So there are a bunch of big
implications for this design.
What does it mean to have real
URLs in these applications,
when we think of a shell
that boots up but
then mediates content?
What does the URL mean?
It means something that's
interpreted by the shell.
Can we build transparent
caching proxies?
The answer is yes.
It's the simplest thing
to possibly do.
You actually just populate
a new thing in this cache
object, every time you
get a request.
And then, suddenly, things
mostly work offline.
Is that good?
Is that bad?
We're not sure yet.
We don't know.
And we don't really have good
synchronization technology today.
There's some work happening.
I know the media guys are
spending a lot of time on
operational transform.
And the Ember guys are
looking at it.
But synchronization technology
is not our lingua Franca.
This is not how we have
thought about
building the web.
And it's the sort of thing that
we're going to have to
get good at, if we really bite
off this idea of building
applications that are shells,
that boot up to mediate
content and not simply documents
which happen to be
fully-formed things, sprung
from the head of Zeus.
So there's a bunch of
open questions.
And I guess it's time for
us talk about it.
ANDREW BETTS: And then that's
his out of time.
Thank you very much, good-bye.
No, the underground example
is a very good one.
When I was building lanyards,
the underground was the most
convenient place to
go and test a
real-world, offline situation.
Because you know, turning things
on to airplane mode is
not quite sufficient.
But I remember I was there
with five mobile phones.
And one of the staff
came up to me.
And he just stood there
staring at me.
I looked behind me.
And I was standing in front of
a poster, which essentially
said, if you see someone with
more than one mobile phone,
they're probably a terrorist.
And you should deal with them.
So first, before we go to the
first question, do any of the
panelists have anything to say
about what Alex was talking
about there in the intro?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I had just one
comment, which is, I do
wonder how many people working
on the service navigator,
controller, whatever the
eventual name is-- how many
are the same people who built
Google Gears, which I think
had almost exactly the same
mechanism for dealing with
offline, just insert a proxy
into the browser?
Is there a connection there?
ALEX RUSSELL: So it's
a good question.
So Michael Nordman was
on the Gears team.
And he's one of the people who's
helping us implement the
Service Worker.
We've tried to at least twice
before, from the Chrome
perspective.
Before there was Chrome, it was
Gears-- and then inside of
Chrome, with application
cache--
to give you tools to make
things work offline.
And we have failed
miserably twice.
And Gears wasn't what
you thought it was.
So if you go back and you pull
the documentation out of the
internet archive, what you'll
find is that, Gears has a
thing called--
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Local
server, isn't it?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah,
local server.
And the local server wasn't a
server that you could script.
You couldn't ever give it a bit
of code and say, please go
run this, whenever I
request a resource.
That never happened in Gears.
You give it a manifest, a
declarative format, which is
exactly what we did in the
application cache too.
And in both cases, they were,
like Jake put it at Edge in
London, like playing a game
where you can see the effects
of what you're doing a couple
of turns later.
But you can't actually
control any of it.
And as a result, we don't have
a lot of data about what you
actually need.
We've never giving you the
primitives that you need to go
build the stuff you want and
evolve and iterate on that.
And I think they're just
hasn't been a lot of
exploration.
Because it takes a
lot to get going.
And there hasn't been
the ability to
explore these patterns.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think his was
essentially the precursor
to App Cache, rather than
the precursor to this
thing we have now.
I think we should go to
the first question.
And if I'm reading the right
documents, that's from some
chap called Andrew Betts,
never heard of him.
Where are you, Andrew?
Can someone get Andrew
a microphone?
There he is.
ANDREW BETTS: OK.
Currently offline data may be
evicted at any time by the
user agent.
Can we have storage persistence
guarantees or at
least provide hints to the
user agent to tell it to
prioritize app logic
over content data?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Yes, this is
a very interesting question
because the whole thing about
using an airport.
I mean, if we make a guarantee
that, yes, as a user, your
data of when you're flight is
going to be will be available
to you offline.
The spec does not currently let
us make that guarantee.
It can chuck all the data
under a bus, whenever
it feels like it.
CRAIG CAVALIER: This is really
important for us as a business.
To give a bit of background, I
work with field engineers.
And they work on
oil refineries.
And they write up their
invoices and
their equipment tracking.
We can't have their data just
disappearing on them as
they're writing up these
new invoices.
We don't want to
lose that data.
So that's a really important
problem for us
that we need to solve.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is this a
problem that you actually
encountered in the FT?
Or is this do a problem
you encountered, data
disappearing like that?
Or is it just a theoretical
problem?
CRAIG CAVALIER: It's a
theoretical problem at this
point, for us.
MATT ANDREWS: We have real
experience, in particular--
I can't say this on record.
Oh, dammit.
iOS 5, we suspect strongly that,
occasionally, it wiped
our apps in certain situations,
but not sure,
can't prove it.
But we have strong suspicions.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I'd like to
add the, I think, the most
important aspect of this is how
the user understands where
the data is and when the
browser may evict it.
We can't tell the browser that
they can evict something.
Only users should be
able to say that.
We have ways those installing an
app in an implicit way that
the user is invisible to.
And the data should
be tied to that.
So the user might say, this is
an app I want to keep around.
And therefore, they're opting
in to keep that data.
And then, it would be
safe to not evict.
So I think a bigger problem here
is not so much the APIs
we have, but the way
that the browser
presents that to the user.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So to say that
the user has to be responsible
for the removing of data, they
have to be responsible for the
adding of the data as well.
CRAIG CAVALIER: Yeah, and if the
user hasn't said, I want
this app to stay available and
its data to stay available.
Then, it's safe to evict.
And so they need to
opt in to this.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Anne, Alex, I'm
looking at the wrong one,
when I say that.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: So we've
been looking into this for
Firefox OS as well, because the
problem comes up there as
well, for apps.
And it's really hard, because
once you get through
persistence, it becomes
a UX problem.
So we have this sort of concept
of, you have temporary
storage, which you can just
grant to everyone.
We'll just grant you a slot,
so you can use it.
And the other concept would
be persistent storage.
But that is much harder, because
the user sort of has
to be aware of it.
But then, most users are not
really aware of storage and
how that is allocated for apps
and how that works across
their device.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: It's not
a problem with a
phone though, right.
Because if my phone tells me I'm
low on space, I can go to
the apps menu.
And it says, oh, this game
you don't care about
is using 200 megabytes.
And this one you really care
about is using less than that.
So I can throw one of
them out the window.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Yes.
So I think we have to sort of
evolve it into that direction.
And yeah, so it has to be-- the
thing is, do you ask the
user right up front?
And which apps do
you grant space?
Or do all apps have to ask for
persistent storage or not?
Whenever you sort of hit the
UX side of things, with
standards, it becomes a lot
harder to get things done.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is there an API
or a standard that this
kind of work fits in?
Is it the Quota API?
Is that the plan?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yes, so there
is a Quota API.
And it does have this idea
of persistent storage and
ephemeral storage.
And right, persistent storage
is only available in Chrome
for certain file system calls.
You can't, in a granular way,
opt some bit of your cookies
and your local storage and your
index TP into persistent
storage and then say,
this other stuff, I
don't really need.
And there's no clear way, in
the UX, to communicate to
users about what
they're doing.
It feels to me like
Anne was saying.
There's a very clear missing
moment of intent, where you
give users the power to
say, no, I really want
to keep this thing.
I like this a lot.
I would like to get back
to this easily.
I would like to bless it with
the ability to keep all of its
data around.
And we don't have
that moment yet.
We are missing what is
effectively a very small
manifest and then some
UI, to let users say,
yeah, I like this.
I want to keep this.
And once users have said they
like it, I don't see why we
should ever be second
guessing them.
I trust myself to be mediating
the content of my phone, in a
lot of cases.
And in many cases, that means
throwing out an application.
And I like doing that, not
getting so annoyed by an
application that
I uninstall it.
But I like the ability to do
that and reason about that, at
that level.
MATT ANDREWS: Don't we sort of
have this already, with web
apps on iOS, where you add the
web app to your home screen?
So that's kind of similar to
saying, I want to keep this
app around.
I know Firefox as well,
I think, you can--
it asks you, when you load the
web page, it's got an app
cache, whether it you want it
to stay around offline.
And you can say, no.
And the website will continue
being a website.
Isn't that equivalent?
ALEX RUSSELL: Yeah, I think
that's a great point.
And I think that's kind of the
direction that we all need to
figure out a way to get to.
And someone asked about
the Quota API.
The Quota API is probably
something that we definitely
need to integrate into the
Service Worker design.
We've talked to the folks who
are in charge of the Quota API
about this.
Because it should also be the
case that, when applications
get under pressure, you should
be able to give an application
the ability to say, hey,
I'm about to ask you
for this much storage.
You need to figure out where
it's going to come from.
And if you don't do that, maybe
we evict you entirely.
But one of the nice bits about
the Service Worker design
versus the HTTP cache today is
that it's not HTTP cache.
Once resources are there, unless
you pull them out,
they're there, for the last
time of the thing.
It'll get evicted as a bundle,
but it's up to you as an
application to make smart
decisions about what you
prioritize.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Yeah, and
it's a little bit harder.
Like you can put it on
the home screen,
but it doesn't mean--
how much storage were
you granted then?
It might need two gigabytes.
It might need four.
It might get most of
your hard drive.
And is the user comfortable
with that?
Does the user even know
what that means?
MATT ANDREWS: One of the points
we have when we were
developing the HTML5 app for the
economists was, in IE10,
you can actually configure
exactly how much space you can
give to a web app.
You can make that
one megabyte.
So for us, that's far,
far not enough.
So we have to detect how
much space we have.
So I think too much control
can also be a bad
thing, quite limiting.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So if you did
this installable app thing, is
that going to replace the number
of tool bars we get for
each permission?
What's that going to
replace it with?
Are we going to get the sort
of Android solution, where,
upfront, you get the list
of permissions.
And you just ignore
it and click Next.
Is that the kind of model that
we see working on the web?
ALEX RUSSELL: If I had my
druthers, it would be a system
where the user can
always say no.
And to the extent that they've
said, yes, they've said, yes.
But they can change
their mind later.
So the Android model of a bundle
of permissions which
can't be split apart from each
other sort of implies APIs
that aren't allowed to fail.
There's only a return true.
There's never some sort
of a failure case.
And I think the web has gotten
a long way on the basis of
APIs that can fail.
That's how we adapt.
It's the ability for the
environment to just not be
there or for feature detection
to help us understand and live
within the contours of whatever
the runtime is.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So I think it's
about time we moved on to
the next question.
And this one's from
Natasha Rooney.
So if we can get Natasha
a microphone.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
Thank you very much.
So should network information
APIs be extended to include
triggers for a user having less
than optimal connection
speeds and not just offline
or online triggers?
Could this help developers
code for content caching?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So this is
a question that came at
the last Edge Conf.
And this was voted up quite
high in the Moderator.
But I also had some people
coming up to me and saying,
this just really went on too
long and was really boring, at
the last Edge Conf, this kind of
debate whether we should be
offering the developer
information about the
connection speed.
So as a compromise, I'd like
each of the panelists to
answer the question, making
only a sound.
So in a sound, should the
developer be given details on
the current connection speed?
ALEX RUSSELL: Nah.
CRAIG CAVALIER: Doesn't
bother me.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: That's
not a sound.
You can leave now.
MATT ANDREWS: Error callback.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: That's
not a sound.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Eh.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Eh.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
That's a good percentage of the
panelists, kind of you know.
But we should have a serious
discussion about the-- we've
got these online-offline
event triggers.
And so how should we be
using them to make
something work offline?
Should we build, assuming the
network is there and then fall
back, using this method?
Or should we build the machine
offline, and it's there?
And you had an example, Alex,
with using offline detection.
ALEX RUSSELL: The online
thing is a lie.
I think that's really what
it boils down to.
It's a dirty, nasty,
terrible lie.
And the only thing that you'll
ever be able to do, that's
meaningful, is to ping
your service.
You'll be able to send a request
out to your service.
And if you get a response back
under deadline-- like, let's
say you've got a performance
guarantee
that you need to meet.
And if you get a response back
under deadline, from your
service, great.
So it's over HTTPS.
It's from your service.
Things look legit.
Any other case is failure.
It's just a giant panoply of
potential failure cases, that
would all be online.
Under some strict definition of,
I connected to the radio.
And I got a PCP stock.
It warmed up.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Craig, Calvin,
Matt, did you use the online
in anything you were doing?
Or did you want that
kind of extra
detection around the network?
CRAIG CAVALIER: We've made use
of the online and offline.
We don't have so many
requirements for the grey area
of not having a decent
amount of connection.
So for us, we tell the user
whether they can sync or not,
based on whether they have
this online or offline.
But as he said, in a lot of
cases, online is bit of a lie.
But for our users, when they
have a connection, they have a
connection.
It's often that they've come
back off of a rig.
And they're in a hotel.
And they're making use of
the connection there.
So for us, just having the
yes and no is enough.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think we'll
take a question from the
audience, from Schabse.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Just to add,
I think it will also get
easier once browsers and OSes
get more capable at detecting
captive portals.
And I know, Mozilla, we're going
to add this to Firefox,
in case the OS falls through and
figuring out if you're in
a captive portal and then tell
the web pages they're offline
and not give them a false
impression and stuff.
AUDIENCE: When caching app logic
within content, is there
a way to cache per-JITted
code.
A, so you don't need a JIT
for faster start up.
And B, as JITters get more
intelligent, so that you can
re-use what the JITter learned
about how your app behaved for
the last five hours of usage,
both for offline and for
online scenarios, for
faster start up.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Does anyone
want to take that?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: No.
That actually was an issue that
come up, I know, in the
assembly drive JS project.
There is a very bad problem
there with the time it takes
to compile, especially large
demos, even the actual
function, parsing, and compiling
is all synchronous
and blocking.
So that's the issue that came
up there, not necessarily
being offline or reused, but
just the time it takes.
And could it be asynchronous?
And I know from that, right now,
the only thing is parsing
it from the raw JavaScript and
compiling at the time.
It would be, I think, a really
important thing to look into,
if they're going to look into
an asynchronous API, to also
have a way to then reuse
that result.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So back
onto the kind of
network state stuff.
I mean, if I'm asking the
browser, am I online.
It's going to say, yes.
And what we're going to end up
with is, it could just have
one bar or a kind of intimate
bar of data, which eventually
is just going to take five
minutes to try getting
something from the network
and then ultimately fail.
Anne, you're saying, is that
something that is solvable as
it was a problem.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: That might
be harder, the case where a
captive portal gives
you a time out.
But yeah, you would have to
do like periodic checks or
something like that.
I think, it might be there
forever, until captive portals
actually start returning
different status codes.
There is some kind of RFC that
makes captive portals actually
part of the network stack,
instead of just a hack.
You would still have some logic
in your application that
detects it as well.
It's hard to get away from,
given the legacy.
MATT ANDREWS: I think a whole
analogue kind of quality of
connection over the past
X period of time
will be more useful.
But really, most of the time, as
long as you're implementing
error callbacks, you can always
try and fail gracefully
or offer something to the user
first and then fall back to
something else.
I think that's a much
better pattern.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we've got a follow up
question from Natasha.
AUDIENCE: Yes, sorry.
So just to give a proper use
case from the reason why I ask
the particular question, which
might be able to help.
And actually, subscription
models is probably the best
one to go on, which I know
is important for any
publications, like "FT" and
other such newspapers.
What a user who was on a
subscription method and that
meant that they capped out.
Say the read 10 articles.
They read that on the tube,
which I'm also a tube user.
So they will read
out on the tube.
They consume that, and then
they violate their
subscription.
They've gone, right.
So they shouldn't be able
to read any more.
So some trigger has to happen
at some point, for it to go
back to the server to
say, this user has
gone over their limit.
Don't give them anymore.
So my real idea is trying to
understand how that can
happen, because that
has massive
implications for some markets.
I'm talking videos as
well as publication.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So this is
offering the user a different
experience, if they are on
some kind of metered
connection, where it's going
to disappear after certain
points, or potentially bring
a financial situation.
Does the phone even know if the
user is in that situation?
CRAIG CAVALIER: A lot of times
I've found that it's not
necessarily the technology that
has to care about that.
There's usually a business
process around this.
So for instance, if you're not
in a banking system, you're
going to cash point.
And you withdraw some cash.
If your spouse has gone to
another cash point and
withdrawn that amount as well,
and that would take you over
your overdraft.
They've got this concept of
overdraft in banking.
So they've got to a set
way of handling that.
And usually, in these business
scenarios, there are business
processes for handling
those cases.
So for instance, in the case of
your videos, I've watched a
couple of videos offline.
Someone else has used
my account to
watch a few more offline.
Then there must be some kind of
consolidation, some kind of
process to pick up those pieces
and then trace that
back to the billing.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Are we
collectively happy with a
mobile site or app sending
us into our overdraft?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I think we're
collectively unhappy
about that even being
a possibility.
The whole bandwidth cap thing is
like bullshit and should be
gone at some point.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I've been in
situations where my phone
knows that I'm roaming, but I've
actually managed to get a
deal with the provider where
I essentially have the same
quality and amount of data
that I have at home.
I guess, if an app at this point
was to serve me lower
quality content, I'd be a
bit annoyed about that.
I'm being treated as a
second-class citizen, when I'm
not in that situation.
So do we need an option to--
is this going to be a
site-per-site option to say, can
you be easy on the data.
Or should sites just be doing
easy on data, by default?
ALEX RUSSELL: I think there was
a billing issue, not so
much about the data that Natasha
was bringing up.
But there's some non-packet
based metric for use.
So the question I always
ask is, what
is a Wikipedia article.
Is it the text?
Is it the history?
Is it all the images that
are part of it?
Is it the set of things
that it's linked to?
Is it the URL?
It's actually probably a bundle
of binary resources and
then some ephemeral metadata
around it.
And so you're talking
about consuming one
of those at a time.
So if I'm on the "FT" or the
"New York Times" or whatever,
and I'm clicking through.
How do I get to my limit?
And then how do I
enforce that?
Not to go design a solution for
enforcement for anybody,
but you can imagine a relatively
straightforward
sort of soft landing for users,
where there's a bit of
code on the client that's
watching usage and then
attempts to enforce some
soft limit, with a cap,
with one or two extra.
And then, at some point later,
if you haven't synced in n
number of days, then maybe the
content becomes inaccessible.
I mean, those are the sorts of
solutions that folks who have
to implement CRM are doing
today, for things like my
synced Spotify offline data.
You have to it you have to show
that you're willing to be
part of the ecosystem for
some period of time.
Otherwise, the device itself
decides to stop playing.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we'll take another
question from the audience.
Hendrick, whereabouts are you?
Can we get that man
a microphone?
Just throw it.
ALEX RUSSELL: It's
a good question.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: It'll be safe.
AUDIENCE: So this is kind of
back at the permission models.
It seems like, at the point,
you're going offline, you're
making a fundamentally
different type
of app than a website.
There's a distinction
between a site and a
website at that point.
It's very clearly an app.
And then you're talking
about requesting
permission for storage.
But also, that's a perfect time
to ask for permission for
other things as well.
So there's this kind of whole
installable model that you're
seeing a little bit in
Android and Chrome
installed apps as well.
But is there standards efforts
to really unify that
experience?
And for example, if I'm going to
do video conferencing, why
shouldn't I be able to ask for
that upfront, as a mandatory
requirement?
And if they say,
no, then sorry.
I can't install the app.
I mean, whatever.
That's just an example, but
unifying that, standardizing
that process, and seeing that as
the permission point, where
you ask for everything
that you need.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I feel like I
could sink the rest of the
panel into a discussion of, do
apps actually exist as a term.
Or is it just a bit of marketing
fluff, like web 2.0?
MATT ANDREWS: That's not fair.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: But we're
not going to go there.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I feel
Alex already answered
his question earlier.
Like he said, on the web, you
want to feel gracefully for
each of the things.
So you don't want to bundle and
then get the users to give
up his location data, all his
storage, and all those things.
You want to let the user be in
control, which sort of argues
in the way of doing a
per-feature grant.
AUDIENCE: But isn't that always
going to make you a
second-class citizen to
an installed app?
ALEX RUSSELL: I don't
think so.
So just to answer directly, I
don't think that makes you a
second-class citizen to the
installed applications, for a
couple of reasons.
One, it leaves it up to the
system to mediate the length
and breadth of that grant.
So you can imagine that--
iOS versus Android, running the
same application, as long
as the API is the same, they
can make different choices
about how often to prompt
someone about a thing.
Secondly, you can imagine this
being a consent in review kind
of a system, where users are
always able to see the list of
permissions that are currently
granted to a thing and maybe
choose to give it forever
or revoke it entirely.
And as long as the API allows
revocation to happen--
you say, you demand
this thing.
Well, I think it's not
reasonable to demand the thing
at install time.
I think it's reasonable to try
to explain that behavior in
context of use.
I click on a link to go do
a thing, and you say, no.
OK, great.
I did a thing, and then we had
a conversation about it.
And then you can tell me
why you need me to do
that thing for you.
It's not foolproof.
And it may train users
the wrong way.
But it's at least a start of
having a conversation about
why you want permissions.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I can maybe
see, in a way, how it's second
class from a developer's
perspective.
But I think, from a user's
perspective, it's
a way better deal.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Can we get the
microphone to Kyle Simpson for
the next question?
But first, Matt, you, with the
Financial Times, taking that
stuff offline, some of
that stuff was quite
heavy, due to imagery.
Did you deal with that in any
particular Way did you ask the
user, within your app,
before doing that?
MATT ANDREWS: Yes.
So when you first let out the
app, originally, it was
designed for iOS.
And the limitation on iOS is,
you can have five megabytes of
storage, without
any permission.
So we first give them five
megabytes of data, which what
they asked for basically.
And once they've used
the app a bit.
Or it pinches their
homescreen and
actually using it properly.
We then ask for more.
So I think you can definitely
design your applications so
that you have a certain number
of mandatory requirements and
then add things on.
I mean, it's starts
off as a website.
You can always fall back
to being a website.
All this stuff is extra.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I just caught
myself on the screen looking
like I'm advertising the
thing I'm drinking.
So I'm going to balance it out
by saying, it's actually quite
disgusting.
We've got a question
now, from Kyle.
Kyle is over there.
AUDIENCE: So usually, I am the
one who's screaming for more
APIs, more functionality
to be given to us.
But I'm going to flip the table
here and say, going with
the theme that browsers are
generally better at a lot of
these tasks, as a developer of
apps and sites, one thing I'd
really not like to deal
with is the idea
of online and offline.
So one idea that I would just
wanted to bounce and see if
you think would be possible--
we've talked a lot about
persisting the actual app, the
files that make the app run.
But what about all the
network requests?
Could the browser proxy the
request that I'm making for me
and then, when I come back
online, prompt me and say, do
you want to still send
these Tweets.
Do you want to still send
these emails, because
you requested that
a few minutes ago?
That way, I, as an app
developer, don't have to think
about those details.
I just make the app assume
online, and let the browser
take care of it.
CALVIN SPEALMAN: I think there's
actually two areas
there that need to be addressed
differently, which
is a things and things
you do--
keeping the data locally first
and allowing synchronization
to happen separate
from your app.
For example, CouchDB has a
PouchDB layer that will be
implemented inside
the browser.
And you have all your
local data.
And the transition happens
in a separate process.
Synchronizing API calls, like
Tweets and things, I don't
think it makes sense to do
separately or to queue up in
the background.
Because the user needs to know
that hasn't happened yet.
You can't just make the Tweet
and say, here's my API call.
I hope the browser did it
sometime later, maybe.
You have to tell the browser
user, this hasn't sent yet.
This hasn't completed.
They have to know
what's going on.
ALEX RUSSELL: There's a related
issue, which is, what
does it mean to get success
back from an API.
If I get a 200 response and the
return content is error.
How do I cut the browser
into the
conversation, so that it retries?
AUDIENCE: So I was under the
assumption that a browser
knows that it doesn't
have connectivity.
It tries to talk to the radio,
an d the radio doesn't give
any sort of response back.
But also, there's plenty of UIs
that we do this already.
When I'm downloading files,
there are UIs that tell me the
status of my downloads and
let me unpause it.
So I don't understand why the
same sort of API couldn't
present to me, the user,
that here's the
request that I've made.
And I want to say, yes.
These are OK to make, now
that you're back online.
No, that Tweet is not one I want
to send out or whatever.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: It sounds like
a difference between adaptive
requests and predictive
requests, in terms of what we
expect to get from
the network.
Is that something that
comes into this?
Are we going to have
APIs around that?
ALEX RUSSELL: I think there's
a fundamental difference
between the download case that
you just tried to outline and
these other cases.
It is that, in the download
case, we're talking in terms
of a single resource
that the browser
knows everything about.
The browser knows the
entire protocol for
downloading a file.
And in fact, it's the thing
giving you the UI for
downloading the file.
This is a situation in which
we're asking the browser to
coordinate with the application
that its hosting,
to talk about mediating that
conversation about content.
It's running the application and
saying, hey application,
you're doing stuff.
The user intends
to do a thing.
You're going to tell me what
that thing is and then tell me
how that relates to the
rest of the world.
And we don't have any
higher-level semantic
equivalents.
There's no way to tell the
browser, oh, this thing is
sending a tweet.
Browsers don't know
what Tweets are.
These are just different
data types.
One of them is a composite data
type, and one of them is
a primitive.
And browsers are OK at
primitives they understand.
But when it comes to composites,
we have to give
applications control.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think
we're going to move
on to the next topic.
The next question is
from Nick Molineau.
Whereabouts are you hiding?
Over there, can we get a
microphone over there?
Oh, someone was just going
to the toilet.
I thought they were
asking a question.
Never mind, I should ask them a
question anyway, serve them
right for getting up.
AUDIENCE: So users only expect
offline behavior from apps
downloaded from their
app store.
Will initiatives like iOS's
Start Up image and Touch icon
ever be expanded to include a
full metadata set, suitable
for web apps to finally be
included in app stores?
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I think this is
a very important question.
Because even if we solve all the
API issues, we still have
that user expectation that they
do not think they can go
into the browser, type in the
URL, and expect it to work,
when they know they have
no connectivity.
So the guys who have been
building stuff using the
current set of APIs, what did
you do to let the user know
that, yeah, this is
going to work?
CALVIN SPEALMAN: Well, I first
started looking at these
offline apps in Firefox 3.
So my choice then was, I'm just
not going to use this.
Because there's no solution.
And the point of that was,
it's been a long time.
We should have solved
this by now.
We do have a mechanism for users
to the access to an app
or a website and to indicate
to the browser that it's
important to them and to
remember to come back to it.
It's the bookmark.
And we have this.
And it's barely used.
And it makes a lot of sense
to connect that into the
permissions, into quotas, into
all these things we need to
remember about a website.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Craig, you
kind of specialized that for a
particular set of people.
How did you communicate to them
that, though this is a
browser, this is
going to work?
This is going to work for you.
CRAIG CAVALIER: We go about this
in different approaches,
depending on the different
requirements for the hardware.
So one of the nice things about
iOS is, you can add apps
to your home screen.
And that becomes kind
of difficult in some
of the other browsers.
I think you can do, add
to home screen in
other browsers as well.
It's a bit shaky.
So yeah, it would be nice if
there were some way of saying,
hey, I want to be able
to install this.
I know Firefox has made some
progress in that direction,
with the manifest file.
So you can specify things that
your application needs when
you install.
I think having some
standardization around this
kind of processes is going
to help companies like
us make that work.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Matt, your
site was open to all users.
You had to explain to them
that this was possible.
How do you do that?
MATT ANDREWS: Well, iOS,
like you say, is easy.
The best of them,
we just don't.
And unfortunately, this is one
of the reasons why we don't
see that many users on Chrome
for Android, even though the
app works absolutely
brilliantly on it.
And the Chrome Web Store, you
said, there were two ways of
making web apps work offline,
the Google Gaze and AppCache.
There's also, the Chrome
Web Store offers
an alternative approach.
And you can use that to get
your app icon on the dock
called Start Menu.
And I think that would be really
nice to make that more
open and accessible
to other places.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Is there
anything in the spec that's
going to make this better?
Or how can we communicate this
better to users, that the web
will work offline?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: So we've been
looking into the manifest
thing and making that better.
But I think a lot of the
standards, how they've evolved
is in small, incremental
steps.
So first, we need to
solve this offline
thing and get it right.
And then people can start
building apps.
And then we can start thinking
about how to improve bookmarks
to make that work better.
And then, long term, hopefully,
we can obsolete the
concept of app stores entirely,
because you can just
browse the web and bookmark
things to your home screen and
know that we need those.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Can we get this
right before we have the
mechanism for users to
realize it works?
Because we don't know we've got
it right, until we've got
users using it.
We see the behavior patterns,
and we see the bits of the
APIs that aren't working.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Chicken-egg,
I guess.
You have to grow into
getting there.
You can't really just design the
whole thing up front and
then present it.
And it just works.
MATT ANDREWS: When you say
getting offline working right,
you mean the terminology
formerly called navigation
controller, right?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: Yeah.
Well, I'm hoping Service
Worker is the answer.
We'll have to find out.
We have to test.
We have to incrementally
evolve.
We're at prototyping stage
now, so it's early days.
MATT ANDREWS: But from the
user's perspective, as much
AppCache is a bit loathed,
it does kind of work.
It will give you an
application that works offline.
Can we not just fill in
that little step to
get the icon in there?
And then it will be compatible
with both.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: The problem
with AppCache is that, we got
a sort of universal no
back from developers.
So people don't really want to
experiment with it and roll it
out on their sites.
And if there's no adoption, then
we can't really further
experiment with other things.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Alex, it
seems like the sentiment of
the rest of the panel is that
Chrome for Android is doing
this very badly, that the
installed home screen this is
great for iOS.
Where is it?
ALEX RUSSELL: That's
a great question.
John--
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Are you prepared
to answer this, John?
We'll get a microphone
to John anyway.
And he can at least
tell us that he's
not allowed to answer.
ALEX RUSSELL: If I had
my druthers, we would
absolutely have that.
I mean, I think that's
a reasonable
thing to want to have.
My personal view-- and I'm not
speaking for Google here-- is
that, the manifest destiny of
web apps is that, they can do
everything that apps can do.
Everything that your system
application should be able to
do, you should be able to
write as web page first.
And then you should be able to
transition to a world that's
much more powerful.
And that just depends on getting
users to a point where
they believe that's a
safe thing to do.
And if that's saying no to
some permissions to get
others, that sounds good.
Or asking users to install or
bless a thing, that seems
reasonable.
But yeah I want it.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: John, do you
have a comment or no comment?
JOHN: I'm with Alex.
I think we have a lot more
to do in this space.
And to make it, with apps, more
capable, we're putting
friends only.
We'll see what happens.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: We'll
take one more
question from the audience.
CRAIG CAVALIER: One more thing
to add on there, Binfire for
Chrome for Android, the
installable apps is
only part of that.
And we found that, actually,
Chrome for Android has the
best support for things like
IndexDB, which we don't get on
other devices, like
Safari on iOS.
So we need to have that problem
solved consistently
across browsers.
Because at the moment we have to
rely on things like shims,
to fall back to Web SQL with
iOS7 and the five meg cap that
we have for the user prompt,
that now it's really important
to get that piece of
the puzzle solved.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Thanks
for that.
We can declare one all, between
iOS and Android now.
That's pretty good.
We're going to take one question
from the audience,
before we move topic.
Eric Shepherd, whereabouts
are you?
Get a microphone over here--
AUDIENCE: This is sort of a
follow up, the flip side of
the payment question
from earlier.
For the number of issues, there
are a whole host of
other things that you may want
to know about that, if people
start using the web offline
in large numbers,
we're going to lose.
Third-party networks want to
know things, for tracking
purposes, for re-marketing
purposes.
We want to know what people
are looking at.
So that when we're giving
more and more customized
recommendations in e-commerce or
article recommendations in
publishing, those are things
we want to know about too.
Are any of the ad networks or
anyone looking into possible
APIs for how to deal with
this kind of stuff?
ALEX RUSSELL: I haven't been
talking to them and probably
should be, with regards to the
Service Worker design.
But I can only talk about
the thing I'm working
on, which is that.
And it allows you to--
a thing we've put on the screen
oh so briefly was the
Import Scripts API,
which allows--
these things are
just workers--
a worker of any kind to just go
out and import some other
script, like a require call in
AMD, something like that.
So you can compose behavior
from multiple origins.
So that if you're working with
a third party, you could
include their offline
handling code too.
And because the Service Worker
sees requests for all origins,
including those third party
ones, you can write your
handlers in such a way that
well-behaved Service Worker
scripts will only pay attention
to the requests for
their origin and do the
right thing by them.
And you can import scripts
from other origins to do
things like handling those kinds
of tracking and counting
when offline.
And they get the ability to run
when you're online too.
So they'll be able to do their
own synchronization.
It does require kind of the
global coordination thing that
we love so much about
JavaScript.
And so we get ES6 modules, but
I think that's kind of going
to be the state of the
art for a while.
It's possible it will
require care.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
We're going to move on
to the next question.
And the next question is asked
by Jake Archibald--
oh, not that guy again.
OK.
Well, this is a bit
weird, so I should
probably ask the question.
Oh, John's back.
Hello.
JOHN: This on?
Yes.
We are actually working on
adding an [INAUDIBLE] feature
to Chrome for Android.
It's a public commit, so I can
talk about it, excellent--
coming soon, hopefully.
I think we added an About
flag recently.
It's in [INAUDIBLE]
probably.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Declassified,
excellent.
JOHN: Oh, and I think
Vivian was asking--
AUDIENCE: I'm interested in
knowing if developers want to
have a similar API like iOS that
allows you to have API
access, to prompt the user to
install on the home screen.
MATT ANDREWS: Yes.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: OK.
I'll take that as a whole
panel's opinion.
So on to the question from
this Jake Archibald guy.
I'm going to try and read it in
a different accent, so it
doesn't seem super weird.
Maybe that will make it
seems even weirder.
I'll sit over here slightly.
So I'll do an American accent.
I'll try and do your accent.
[AMERICAN ACCENT]
So currently, if a post fails, I
can stick it in the Index DB
and post it later.
But if the user has to visit
the site later, to actually
send that data.
How can I do that?
Is there a better
way for that?
That's a very good
question, Jake.
Yeah, we're going to put that to
the whole panel right now.
So yeah, we don't have
anything to do
synchronization.
Is there a sync API coming?
Can we do this, when the
user is not actually
sitting on the site?
CRAIG CAVALIER: So I think
that there are background
needs for APIs added in Firefox
OS, for things like
push notifications, and that
there is a definite
possibility of integrating the
need for to happen in the
background, whenever you don't
even have the tab open, to
also be built upon to have
some kind of synchronized
process or cron jobs
for your website.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Craig,
you had this
specific problem, right?
CRAIG CAVALIER: We do.
Going back to the question of
having it running in the
background, it's
kind of tricky.
Because firstly, you've got
situations like, actually,
does the user really want
to be syncing when
they don't know it.
I mean, we could be eating up
all of their bandwidth, for
roaming, for instance.
So in some cases, it makes a lot
more sense for it to be an
explicit question for them.
But in other cases, also, and
particularly for business
data, you have this process of
making business decisions when
merge conflicts happen.
So for us, we do something
that's kind of similar to a
Git rebase, when we're
synchronizing.
So we actually can prompt the
user and say, hey, we've
detected that these two
events happened.
And they conflict
with each other.
And you need to take
some action.
So that's running in
the background.
That becomes kind of tricky.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So Alex
and Anne, you guys
are from the future.
What's in the future for us?
ALEX RUSSELL: You have to
do this in his accent.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN: I'm not
sure I can do that.
I think push notifications
will have to be opt-in.
I think background updates for
apps, like for your caches and
stuff, we can do, if the user
is connected to wireless.
I guess, in that case, we can
sort of assume there won't be
a cap, although it's not
universally true.
In Russia and stuff, they have
still quite low caps, even on
those kind of connections.
So that might have to be a
preference of sorts, like do
you want to allow apps to update
in the background.
And it could even be a
preference that the user wants
his apps always up-to-date,
even on 3G or 4G.
And the browser will just, every
now and then, wake up
the worker and give it the
event to start updating.
And then the work does
its updates and
then shuts down again.
And then, when the user next
visits the site, he'll get the
latest stuff.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So we are going
to go to the audience
for the next question.
Jeffrey Burtoft, whereabouts
are you?
Down here--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I guess this
ties in a little bit more with
the last question.
But there are always a lot of
developers in Microsoft
platform who are developing for
both our store apps, which
are HTML5-based, and then for
the web apps and trying to
bring those closer together.
One of the questions I hear a
lot about web apps is about
the safety of the data that is
stored, which I think tends to
push us more towards developing
in the native space.
What are we doing to make sure
that data can be trusted, can
be safely encrypted and meet the
needs of different types
of developers.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: So if we're
storing something like credit
card data or people's contact
information, what can we do to
make sure that other app
can't sneak in there
and get that data.
Is that something
we do already?
CRAIG CAVALIER: I think there
is a certain amount of that.
I mean, you have to be on the
same domain to be able to
access things like
local store.
So there's a certain amount
of security in place.
There's only so much you can do,
I think, with these kind
of devices.
ANNE VAN KESTEREN:
I'm not sure.
Is the question about what
the origin can access?
Or if someone has physical
access to the device, they can
access the local stored data
because it's not encrypted.
So in that case, it depends on
the security characteristics
provide by the OS.
And I think, in a lot of cases,
browsers default to
what the OS provides and don't
have additional layers on top.
Because if the OS is not
secure, then you're
compromised anyway.
ALEX RUSSELL: It depends on the
threat model, obviously.
But there is an API called Web
Crypto API, which Microsoft is
heavily involved in, working
with Netflix and eBay and
Google and a bunch
of other people.
And one of the key aspects of
Web Crypto API is that, it
allows you to have wrapped
keys, which are to say,
hardware tokens or tokens
protected by the OS, which are
not owned by user space code.
So you can't actually see the
key material, and you can do
operations with that.
So in that world, as long as you
trust the OS, you should
be able to get encrypted content
stored and allow that
to be trusted all the way
through the cert chain, back
to the server.
And I think that's a pretty
deft answer, actually.
I think it gives you most of
the control that you want,
without giving you most of the
complexity that you would like
not to have.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: And I think
that takes us out of time.
I know, the bathrooms at Google
UK are completely out
of Wi-Fi and cellular data.
So it sounds like, if we can get
all this stuff sorted, I
can be a lot more productive
than I am, currently, in my
spare time.
But if you're interested in any
of this stuff and want to
look at the spec as it is
currently, it's github.com/--
ALEX RUSSELL: slightlyoff/--
JAKE ARCHIBALD: serviceworker,
right?
ANNE VAN KESTEREN:
serviceworker, yes.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Excellent.
MATT ANDREWS: When will we
get that in a browser?
ALEX RUSSELL: So I can't speak
for Firefox, but I know that
there are prototypes happening
on the Mozilla side.
And on the Chrome side,
we've built a
prototype which does work.
And we're in the process
of implementing now.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: Excellent. thank
you very much, everyone.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDREW BETTS: Thanks, Jake.
I can't remember what
we're doing now.
Do we have a break now?
So we have a 15 minute
break now, everyone.
There are still some more
snacks at the back.
Use the restrooms.
Come back in 15 minutes.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
ANDREW BETTS: Hi, everyone.
We'll be starting again in five
minutes, so please retake
your seats.
Thanks.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
OK, everyone.
We're going to get
started now.
So please take your seats.
Yeah, I knew it was that.
Someone said to me on Twitter,
they could see me here.
OK, so our next--
what happened?
Our next and penultimate session
is Legacy Clients,
which is, I think, something
which we can all relate to as
a big challenge that we have
to deal with every day and
which makes our job much, much
more difficult than we would
like it to be.
So we have a panel of very
experienced people in this
area, to discuss the topic,
led by Mr. Paul Irish, who
probably needs no introduction
to any of you.
So I will let him take over.
Thanks very much.
PAUL IRISH: All right.
So I'm really excited
about this.
Edge Conf is kind of like the
focal point of a discussion
around using cutting edge
technologies to build amazing
user experiences.
But I think the elephant in
the room is, it's great to
learn all about all these
new technologies.
But what about older browsers,
browsers that are less
capable, that cannot
take advantage of
some of these things?
So this session is an
opportunity to kind of discuss
some of those challenges that
we've had for a long time and
what we can do about them now.
We have a really powerful
panel up here, so let me
quickly introduce everyone.
Over here, to my right,
is Shwetank Dixit.
He has been on the Operator
Developer Relations team and
Open Web team for a while now,
working a lot on compatibility
of all sorts of sites.
So whether they have willy-nilly
Reg Xs that are
blocking the Opera and such,
also a member of the Web
Education Community group and
the Mobile Web for Social
Development group
and at the W3C.
To my left, Tomomi Imura, so she
has been kind of fighting
for the mobile web for a long
time, ever since 2005, when
she was leading the
mobile yahoo.com.
TOMOMI IMURA: [INAUDIBLE].
PAUL IRISH: yahoo.com?
And yahoo.com, yes.
She also was using [INAUDIBLE]
to great success, trying to
wrangle all sorts of kind of
tricky little mobile devices
coming over there, worked at
WebOS and is now at Nokia.
TOMOMI IMURA: That's right.
PAUL IRISH: Cool.
On her left is Ed Sowden.
Ed works for the Government
Digital Service.
And the GDS finished a big,
huge redesign of gov.uk, a
kind of much-lauded, progressive
enhancement
redesign, bringing all of the
UK's government online.
And they're now continuing to
bring more departments online.
They've done a really good job
presenting the best way to do
progressive enhancement and
documenting their strategies
and methodologies and also
providing a very transparent
development process, blogging,
documenting, guidelines
everywhere--
really fantastic job.
And our opening speaker,
Tom Maslen--
Tom is the tech lead for BBC
News Visual Journalism and has
been leading the client-side
team for the mobile BBC News
team for a while, has been
kind of a standards-based
developer, knows browser
performance and JavaScript
extremely well and also, a while
ago, worked on the team
that built and open-sourced the
Glow JavaScript library.
TOM MASLEN: Small
part of that--
PAUL IRISH: Blast from the
past, all right, cool.
So Tom, if you want to take
it away, would be great.
TOM MASLEN: Hi, hello.
And can I have my slides?
Hi, hello, and welcome to the
introduction talk, Legacy
Clients, by me, Tom Maslen.
Or as I think this talk should
really be called, yay, I'm so
excited there are going to be
five versions of Internet
Explorer for me to support
next year.
I'm 34 years old.
Back in my arrogant 20s, I saw
myself as a bit of a Han Solo,
flying around the office, saving
princess's websites,
fixing bugs.
My job used to be easy.
I had four rendering
engines to support.
And yet, I also had to worry
about accessibility.
But writing my code semantically
fixed that.
And I also had to concern
myself about SEO.
But that's essentially
accessibility for search
engines, right.
So my semantic code
sorted that too.
This was a time when we could
all afford to be a little Han
Solos, quickly putting
sites together.
But then, in 2007, all that
changed, when Steve Jobs
invented the bloody iPhone.
Shit got more complicated.
Suddenly, we had mobiles with
very slow connection speeds
and phones with different sized
screens, new types of
interactions.
Smartphones started to appear,
with pathetic little
processors and tiny amounts
of RAM that ran
my code really slowly.
And PPK also pointed out that
there were like 100 different
versions of WebKits
to support.
But all of these problems were
nothing compared to what was
about to wash over us--
an avalanche of devices.
Being confident little
Han Solos
wasn't good enough anymore.
Instead, we've all had to become
intelligent, clever
Spocks, who can balance all of
these issues against getting
our job done correctly.
As developers, this is
the biggest problem
that we have today--
balancing agility, getting the
stuff done quickly versus
robustness, getting
the stuff right.
Now, in this paradigm that we
find ourselves in, it's very
easy to concentrate on this
issue so much that we forget
about boring, old issues like
supporting IE 7 and 8.
I can test in IE 8 and
7, using a virtual
machine on my Mac.
But it's really hard to do.
The experience is slow, and the
dev tools are terrible.
Trying to get IE 7 dev tools to
i1 is like asking a wookie
who's wearing boxing gloves
to wipe my bottom clean.
It's a terrible situation that
normally ends up covering you
in something.
Some bugs, I just give up on,
because it's not worth
spending the time required
to fix a problem for
such a small audience.
It raises questions about
whether we should actually
support these browsers.
I'd argue that, sometimes
it depends.
While the challenges surrounding
client support
have increased, web development
itself has become
more popular.
It's entered the mainstream.
Everyone from schoolchildren
to contestants on "The
Apprentice" are now
making web pages.
And the act of making a web page
is actually pretty easy,
build something to, look
at it in your browser.
There you go.
It's done.
It's very fast.
But as I've just shown you,
the practice of web
development is the complete
opposite.
It's actually really
hard to do right.
Anyone can pick up a book or
read an article online that
teaches you how to
make a web page.
How to write HTML5 or CSS or
JavaScript, these things are
hard to master.
But they're easy
to start doing.
What is hard to learn, though,
is how to scale your website
up from a single user, ie
yourself, to a larger audience.
These things here, they help
you to scale your audience.
But learning them is much
harder, because to understand
these, you have to change the
context of your thinking away
from what's in front of you.
As a developer, I often
find myself having to
defend these things.
But ultimately, the web
isn't about these.
They're important.
But we don't do accessibility
for the sake of accessibility.
And we don't make sites fast or
SEO-friendly or work about
JavaScript because it's nice.
What we're trying to
achieve, our actual
end goal, is ubiquity.
We want as many people as
possible to see our site.
The web should be inclusive,
not exclusive.
I mean, nobody would be build
a shop that only the dwarf
from "Game of Thrones" could
get into, right.
Shops have doors that are wide
and as tall as possible.
Websites should be the same.
An easier way to think
of ubiquity is to
call it browser support.
When people talk about web
browser support, they think,
well, how far back
should we go--
IE 6, IE 7.
In the website versus native
apps debate, the reason why
website wins is because
apps are binary.
They either work,
or they don't.
An iOS app works on
an iPhone, but it
doesn't work on an Android.
However, your site will
work on both.
And even better, if you build it
properly, it will work to a
certain degree on pretty
much anything.
It's the ubiquity of the
website that wins.
So to go back to the original
problem I defined, this job is
also harder because the problem
is continuing to
increase in complexity.
And we have to balance that
against getting stuff done
fast and robustly.
What we shouldn't do is fight
that complexity with ever more
complex solutions.
People who build responsive
websites that are really just
a collection of smaller
websites within it are
creating more problems
for themselves.
When a problem grows to a
certain size, the problem
changes into something else.
And to survive, you have to
change how you think as well.
We did that at BBC News.
We turned the problem of browser
support upside down.
Instead of thinking about how
far back we should go, we
decided to support everything.
We call this technique
cutting the mustard.
The responsive site has a very
basic core experience, that
has a simple layout, is
very fast, and is
delivered to all browsers.
The core experience is good
enough to allow everyone to
consume the news.
On top of this, we built an
enhanced experience using
JavaScript and Modern CSS.
Pardon me.
It has a complex layout and
is very functional.
This is only delivered
to modern browsers.
It's conditionally loaded by
checking for the existence of
specific features.
All browsers that cut the
mustard have great JavaScript
and CSS support.
They have fast-rendering engines
and are less buggy.
This technique is robust because
it supports a massive
amount of browsers.
It's also agile, as you're
building the enhanced
experience using modern
coding practices.
But IE 7 and 8 only get
the core experience.
Now, this might be good enough
for you, if these browsers
don't bring a significant
amount of traffic.
Or you might decide that these
browsers need more than just
the core experience.
How do you do that?
Well, with two ways--
we can edit the cuts the
mustard test to load an
alternative JavaScript, the
app specifically just
for IE 7 and 8.
We can then cherry pick what
features of the enhanced
experience we give them,
like a two-column
layout or video support.
We also need to give these
browsers better CSS.
With Mobile First CSS, IE 7 and
8 only render the smallest
view, because they don't
understand media queries.
But with the CSS pre-processor,
you can output
a version of a site style
at any defined width,
specifically for
these browsers.
The panelist Ed Sowden has
already implemented this, for
the UK government website.
And here is one example
of how you can do it.
Instead of writing media queries
directly into a SCSS,
use this mixing instead.
Then make a new SCSS file that
sets a variable with value the
width value that you want IE 7
and 8 to render the desktop
view to, import the main
SCSS file into this.
And it will render out an
alternative desktop-only
version of your CSS
into a new file.
You should add the legacy IE
style sheet into the pages in
the conditional comment.
Now, however, you have to be
careful now, as IE 7 and 8
will be exposed to
your Modern CSS.
And there's lots of selectors
and properties that you need
to watch out for.
If you're lucky, you may find
IE 7 and 8 will be rendering
your Modern CCC onto the page
in a way that reminds you of
how Donald Trump's hair renders
itself onto his head.
So to summarize, how do you
support legacy clients?
I'd say, don't think about
stretching your code across an
ever-increasing browser
support list.
The problem is only ever going
to get more complex.
And you can't keep up
by making an ever
more complex solution.
If you keep thinking like a
Han Solo, eventually, this
problem will get
on top of you.
Instead, I think the best
way to solve this
is with team work.
Use a solid base of progressive
enhancement as a
springboard for your JavaScript
and treat each
feature on your website like an
away mission, deciding when
to send these aging browsers
to the fall.
So that's enough from me.
Let's chat about it.
[APPLAUSE]
PAUL IRISH: Very nice.
I'm sorry.
TOM MASLEN: Gee, thanks.
[LAUGHING]
PAUL IRISH: All right.
Thank you very much, Tom.
That was great.
So we'll go to our
first question.
Our first question delivered
by Hakim, there.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
Anonymous question--
why should there be a stigma
attached to not supporting
older clients?
If the developer knows their
audience and they all have the
latest clients, what's
the problem?
I think that should be, why is
there a stigma attached, not
why should there be.
So I'll rephrase that.
PAUL IRISH: So Shwetank, do
you want to take this?
Why is there a stigma
attached to not
supporting older browsers?
SHWETANK DIXIT: There is.
But they shouldn't be, mainly
because when it comes to older
browsers, there's a lot of
reason to actually support
older browsers.
Because there are a lot of times
in which the user cannot
update their browser, whether
it's because the system
administrator doesn't allow it
or because, many times, the
user doesn't know what
a browser is.
So if you say, update
your browser.
How could I update my browser?
I don't know what it is.
So that's one thing.
Second things are that,
sometimes people know what a
browser is.
They're fully aware of how
did to update it, but
they don't want to.
Sometimes it's because they're
using a phone, and they have a
very crappy network.
And they might use a proxy
browser, instead of something
which is like a full-fledged
browser.
And proxy browsers are tricky,
as we'll see later on.
Sometimes, people have very
limited data plans.
I know people in Europe
who have 30 MB
data plans for a month.
And if you exceed that,
then you'll get
charged very, very highly.
So there are multiple of the
reasons and genuine reasons
why you should support older
or proxy browsers.
And they shouldn't be any stigma
attached, as such.
I mean, we all like to play with
the greatest and the most
cutting-edge stuff.
But the reality of the
world is, we need to
deal with every one.
And sometimes, there's also
regulation or some laws
regarding accessibility and
stuff like that as well, which
need to be considered as well.
PAUL IRISH: So I wonder--
so the second part is, if we do
know what your clients are,
if you're looking at analytics
and numbers, and they're
indicating that you're OK on
dropping support for IE 6 and
7 and potentially 8.
Is that fine?
TOM MASLEN: I think it depends
on the context of the content.
I think, if you're making a
government website, then there
definitely is a stigma,
because these
services are mandatory.
They have to be viewable
by anyone.
But if you're making an
application like Gmail, then
probably not, because somebody
with IE 7 won't give you that
much benefit.
PAUL IRISH: Ed, is there legal
legislation that requires the
accessibility to old browsers?
ED SOWDEN: So the only legal
legislation or legal things
that exist for older browsers
are accessibility.
You can be sued for not having
an accessible website.
But that's not for the user to
determine what accessible is.
The stigma that we have, this
industry seems to have this
horrible stigma.
You can't drop support
for old browsers.
You can't drop support for--
you've got to go back to the
question, what is supporting
an old browser.
Supporting an old browser for
most of us means that we're
going to test in it.
So that's not support at all.
That means you're testing
in these browsers.
Supporting is actually, if
anyone has a problem, you'll
go and to fix it for them.
That's support.
So if someone has a problem
using your website, yeah, you
want to help that person out.
But there shouldn't be
any stigma attached
with helping someone.
But if you want to spend time
making sure ahead of time that
those people won't have
problems, then that's how you
spend your time.
PAUL IRISH: I see.
TOMOMI IMURA: The one problem
I've see is that--
let's say, maybe with their
statistics, each company's
services stat.
And maybe they just decide
to drop IE support.
And sometimes they're doing
it the wrong way.
I mean, they try to sniff in
the user agent or something
and try to eliminate the older
IE, which seem to be old.
But many times, they're doing
it the wrong way.
So let's say, I work
for Nokia.
And I use a Lumia
phone regularly.
And my browser choice-- well,
it's not my choice actually.
It comes with the operating
system.
And it's IE 10.
And oftentimes, I
see the site.
Sorry, you have to update
your browser.
It's like, really.
It's IE 10.
It's pretty decent.
And I believe that service
or sites should work.
But I think they're just
trying to sniff it out,
mistakenly and try to suggest
to me to upgrade the browser
or just download some
other browsers.
But the thing is, like you were
saying, we don't always
have a choice.
Users don't always
have the choice.
So that's something I have
to just remind people.
I have to remind.
PAUL IRISH: So I guess, on the
topic of support, support is
kind of difficult.
It's the verb that we always
use in this discussion.
And it implies that it
is a binary decision.
You either support
it, or you don't.
And I think, for many of our
development cycles, our
development approach support is
kind of this sliding scale.
So Tom, with cutting the
mustard, when a browser falls
into unsupported, they get
a core experience.
TOM MASLEN: There is
no unsupported.
The idea is that everybody is
supplied a core experience.
Everybody gets the content.
But the content, the way it's
displayed is very simple.
So if there's additional content
on the homepage of the
BBC News site, for example,
analysis and features.
That's available, but you have
to click it, to go to it.
So the experience
is very basic.
But you still get
all the content.
But then, with the premium
version, we'll just go and
fetch all of that content
and put it straight into
the page for you.
PAUL IRISH: And is the
difference in your case the
amount of testing between
the core and the premium
experience?
I imagine you are not as
actively testing the core
experience.
TOM MASLEN: The core experience
is so simple.
It's a single column.
We don't add any functionality
into the page.
Yeah, so that's going to pretty
much render on anything.
PAUL IRISH: Right.
I think Andy Clark, a well-known
developer in the
UK, a while ago, released a
universal IE 6 style sheet.
The idea here was basically a
style sheet that had very good
looking typography but destroyed
all the layout,
killed all your floats,
just kept it
all in a single column.
And the idea was, give that to
IE, give them nothing else.
The content is there,
and it's accessible.
But you can forget about
the visualness of
the rest of the site.
And I think that's kind of a
nice way for something to go
unsupported.
It's basically to fall into it
a pit of accessible content.
ED SOWDEN: So having an IE
6 style sheet which has
virtually nothing is kind of the
approach we took for on of
the large sections of GOV UK.
Because we used the approach
that Tom was mentioning during
the intro, with using mobile
first and then sending
specific IE style sheet
for IE 6, 7, and 8.
But IE 6, they don't get any
layout, because layout is
added on desktop.
So IE 6 just gets
a mobile view.
So it's a single column.
It's basically got typography
because that's
all that you get.
TOM MASLEN: I think it's a
benefit as well, because
people with IE 6 or
IE 7 probably
don't have a good computer.
And so the fact that it's so
simple means it will render
like five or six times faster
than other experiences.
TOMOMI IMURA: [INAUDIBLE], and
that's as long as users can
get what they want.
The experience is not killed.
SHWETANK DIXIT: I think that's
a good strategy, because
there's so many sites which
either support it or just send
an error message saying
that, OK,
this site is not supported.
And that's it.
The user cannot do anything
about that.
So I think that's a very
important thing, that you
don't block anyone.
You at least serve them
the core experience.
And the first part of that
question was, if
you know your audience.
And it's really difficult to
know your audience in a very,
very accurate way.
Even if you know, using your
statistics and your analysis,
what are the browsers which are
coming through, there are
times in which you get to
know a mention on the
front page of Reddit.
Or you get slashdotted.
Or an influential news
website mentions you.
And then you'll get this whole
stream of traffic, which is
completely unpredictable.
So even that premise of that
question, that you know your
audience, is flawed.
PAUL IRISH: So I think it's a
good time to move on to the
next question.
This one is to be asked
by John Fallows.
AUDIENCE: So this is an
anonymous question.
What's the best way to make
legacy clients a visible part
of the development process?
PAUL IRISH: So I think this
is both visibility on the
developer side, to understand
what is necessary to give them
what you plan to give them and
also, potentially on the
executive side, to better
understand what from a
development cost perspective
is included here.
TOM MASLEN: So at the BBC
News, once we made the
responsive site.
But it was a small
team that did it.
And then, eventually, we fanned
it out to the rest of
the department And so we've had
to go through a training
process with everyone,
as they become
engaged with the product.
So we've got the designers
thinking about the core
experience as well.
And they're thinking about
progressive enhancement.
So they start off with the core
experience, and then they
progressively enhance it and
make the better version.
The problem that we find is
that, many people just
associated the core
basic experience
with a very thin layout.
What they find harder to do is
to probably try and understand
that, the core experience
could be any width.
And the premium experience could
be any width as well.
PAUL IRISH: I also
wonder is there--
included on this, I think, there
is a visibility of the
perceived experience
between legacy
clients and modern clients.
And one of these parts is
performance, certainly.
So just rendering a page or
any sort of interactivity,
with a more modern browser, it's
going to be quite a bit
more responsive.
Is there a good way to kind of
demonstrate the difference
between the user experience of
someone on an older client
versus a newer client?
And is that something that the
executive team wants to see
and understand?
TOMOMI IMURA: Maybe, I
would say, some UI.
Or I would say UX, using some
Ajaxy type of interaction.
And that works probably
wonderfully on the latest
greatest browsers--
Chrome on desktop for
me works nicely.
But yeah, they show the
same UI on, let's say,
older mobile browsers.
It could be Android, older
Android and stuff.
Probably, it's going to
look really janky
or maybe even fails.
ED SOWDEN: A lot of it is
managing expectation though.
People on the older browser,
people on IE 6 who are stuck
on IE 6 in their corporate
environments, they'll be used
to an internet which is not
quite like the internet the
rest of us use.
So while, for me or for you,
browsing a website in IE 6
will feel painfully janky
and painfully horrible.
They're kind of almost
expecting that.
And people aren't left on these
browsers because they
want to be there.
They're there because those are
the browsers they have.
Because corporate IT have said,
that's what they've got.
So it's all a case of managing
expectation, for those guys.
Those people, if they know
they're getting a janky
experience, they come
into that knowing.
And my colleagues, I have
colleagues who have IE 6 as
their browser on
their machines.
And they know it's
going look crap.
And they joke with me like,
is this supposed
to look that bad?
And it's like, I think
the developer picked
that color for you.
It's like no.
They know the internet
is horrible.
SHWETANK DIXIT: Yeah, the thing
is just to add or maybe
even remove from your point,
they might be used to it when
they're working.
But for sure, they're using the
internet at their home or
on their mobile in transit
or something.
So they know what the real
internet is like.
And it will be even more
frustrating for them to see
the internet as it is
in the wild on IE 6,
all the time at work.
ED SOWDEN: Go and sit next
to them at work.
Their lives are a pain,
at work anyway.
They know.
PAUL IRISH: Calvin Spealman,
something to add?
AUDIENCE: Actually, I was going
to ask something about
what you just said.
But I wanted to ask,
specifically,
is there a way to--
if people have these different
experiences at work and at
home, they know your site is
different when they're
accessing it at work.
And so they might be missing
functionality that they're
used to at home.
Is there some strategy we can
take to make them not
frustrated at us, seeming like
they're suddenly hitting a
broken version of the site
they're used to?
ED SOWDEN: I think this comes
back to the approach with
cutting the mustard.
You make sure they can
get the content they
need to get, still.
While it will look different.
It will feel at bit different.
As long as they can achieve
the goals they need to
achieve, it's the best
you can do for them.
PAUL IRISH: I think, what I'm
hearing from both of you is
that, there is kind of--
both strategies include a
degraded experience for older
browsers, in some way.
And that seems to scale
pretty well.
But that does mean that we do
have at least two experiences.
And so if we are in a situation
where you have
someone that has seen both of
the experiences, is that going
to be a problem?
TOM MASLEN: I think that's fine,
because like I said in
the talk, we can't make a
premium experience that works
across the whole spectrum
of browsers.
Because poly filling and mobile
internet connections
are so hard to marry
up together.
PAUL IRISH: So it has to be good
enough, because there's
no other way.
SHWETANK DIXIT: Yeah, it's
better than just showing them
that, your browser is
not supported by--
it's at least better
than that.
TOM MASLEN: Sorry, the one
caveat to what I just said is
that, if you do server-side
detection and
sniff for old browsers.
Because normally people, when
they talk about UA sniffing,
you think about, is this
a mobile device.
Or is this a desktop device?
Whereas, I think now, we should
probably be thinking
about, is this an old browser
or a new browser.
I think that would be
an interesting--
PAUL IRISH: In your case,
would it be--
does this browser
cut the mustard?
TOM MASLEN: Yeah, you could
do that on the server,
if you wanted to.
TOMOMI IMURA: Right, the old
browser, that doesn't support
JavaScript.
It doesn't understand JavaScript
feature detection.
Then you have to rely
on the server side.
PAUL IRISH: All right.
I'd like to move on to
the next question.
This one comes from
Dustin Castin.
Dustin is up here
in the purple.
AUDIENCE: So what, as a
community, can we do to help
the holdouts of legacy clients,
such as government
and IT departments?
PAUL IRISH: Nothing.
TOM MASLEN: That was
my answer as well.
I was going to say, nothing.
ED SOWDEN: So I did a little bit
of research kind of around
this point, before I
came, this think
Paul said to me earlier.
I've built a thing which takes
your Google Analytics and
splits out browsers with graphs,
so you can see browser
usage over time.
PAUL IRISH: So it's called
Browser Matrix, takes in your
Google Analytics account and
then just charts the trend
lines for a browser merger.
ED SOWDEN: Paul said, it would
be cool, if you could show
future trends.
So I went and had a look,
because I'm a nerd.
IE 6's and 7's trend lines on
GOV UK, they're going down.
IE 6 lost half a percent
in the last six months.
It's gone from just over
one to around half.
TOM MASLEN: Is that any
particular time of the week?
ED SOWDEN: So it can also show
you stats on a day by day,
seven day rolling basis.
And during the week,
6 is above that.
And at weekends, it's
not really there.
PAUL IRISH: But I guess the
question is, IE 8 would be a
better case.
ED SOWDEN: So those guys,
they're going down.
They're going to get there.
And from the government
perspective, like working in
government, everyone is
painfully aware in government,
that we're tied into these
horrible contracts that
require us to have IE 6.
And everyone is working try
and get out of them.
No one is trying to stay
in that world.
There's not much the development
community can do
to help that.
And on GOV UK, we have a browser
bar that pops up, if
you're on an old browser, that
says, try and upgrade.
which hilariously--
we won a design award
earlier this year.
And a whole collection of the
screen shot that were in news
articles, you could see
that browser bar.
It made our [INAUDIBLE]
smile that these people writing
reports for fairly
large magazines online still
use older browsers as well.
But in terms of government and
massive corporates, very
aware, we're trying to get
rid of it, internally.
PAUL IRISH: Question from
the audience, Daniel.
AUDIENCE: So we always want to
allow users to be happy.
And I looked at some numbers.
And we have IE.
All of IE is like 8%
of our traffic.
Maybe 4% of our traffic
is IE 8.
But is it worth spending the
effort versus things like
developer happiness
and retention?
PAUL IRISH: Sounds like it's not
worth the effort for you.
Sounds like you're doing well.
TOM MASLEN: I'd say,
it depends.
I mean, those old devices might
bring a lot of traffic
to your site.
But do they bring a
lot of revenue?
PAUL IRISH: I think that's
something that, it's more by
the performance load
time of the site.
But I think it's worth looking
into how those technical
metrics of the site and of those
users translate into
their success on site.
I guess, to get back to Dustin's
question, we're
talking about what our community
can do to help
legacy clients.
So Google Apps dropped support
for IE 8 last November.
And Google Analytics dashboards
is dropping support
for IE 8 in a few months.
Google has a policy of only
supporting the most recent and
the last version.
And so Google is being kind of
aggressive in this and saying,
you just have to upgrade,
in order to use it.
You can't use Google
Docs on IE 8.
But is there anyone else that
is in a position where they
can help move this forward?
Or were you just in a case where
we are just waiting for
those trend lines to naturally
go down over the course years,
as we did with IE 6.
ED SOWDEN: Internally,
in UK government,
I'd love to say more.
But there is work going on to
fix it there But yeah, it's
still-- there are
people trying.
SHWETANK DIXIT: One more thing
that I wanted to add was, a
lot of these things are decided
at the contract level.
I can at least talk about
the Indian government.
Sometimes, what happens
is, they don't make
the government websites.
They sometimes send it out
to a contractor who
makes it for them.
And usually, things
are decided when
the contract is signed.
And if there's a clause
saying that, OK,
IE 6 will be supported.
It has to be supported.
So one of the two
things is to--
as a web developer, if you're
vying for that contract-- to
argue at that level, before
signing, that, yes.
I will not be supporting
these things.
I might be supporting
the newer versions.
And the second thing I wanted
to mention was, this problem
is exacerbated by the fact that
many people who were in
government weren't really tech
savvy that much, for a while.
They didn't really know about
browsers and stuff like that.
But with newer devices coming
in, people are having iPhones
and iPads and stuff like that.
They still might not know what
a browser is or not care.
But they do know that, OK, this
website that I'm signing
the contract for, it has to work
on my iPad, for example.
So they're more focused on
those things, on devices,
rather than the older
browsers.
So that mind shift is happening
a little bit.
But once again, as web
developers, before signing the
contract, you have to
see it and be very
careful about that.
ED SOWDEN: Talking of contracts,
old contracts that
UK government signs now can't
have anything which even hints
at vendor lock-in or device
or browse or lock-in.
Anything that hints at a
specific version has to be
removed before contracts
can go out to tender.
There's nothing like that
sent out anymore.
PAUL IRISH: Coming from the
audience, Mary from O'Reilly--
AUDIENCE: Hey.
So just going back to--
we were talking earlier about
how frustrating it is for your
coworkers, if they have one
browser version at home and
one browser version at work and
those types of scenarios.
I think we might be referring to
a very specific portion of
the world, in that, those are
the people who are very tech
savvy, who have the latest and
greatest things, who--
yeah, bigger and newer
is better.
But what about the rest
of the world that--
updating your browser is scary,
because it means, all
of a sudden, you don't know
how to use it anymore.
So there are people who
consciously make the choice to
not update because of that.
TOMOMI IMURA: Your moms.
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry?
TOMOMI IMURA: I said,
your moms.
AUDIENCE: Well, OK.
So yeah, that's an example.
My mom does that.
But I mean, it's a
legit scenario.
And by eliminating the ability
for them to view your website,
you're basically telling
them they don't matter.
PAUL IRISH: Yes.
I think change aversion is real
for everyone, in a lot of
cases, browsers and website
features as well.
And my take here is that, lot of
it is up to browser makers
themselves, to make transitions
as smooth as possible.
TOM MASLEN: We're getting there,
because the problem was
always IE or more like
corporate IE.
So people would build corporate
intranets, and they
would rely on ActiveX.
And that's why we're in a
situation where there are so
many corporate desktops
that can't upgrade.
TOMOMI IMURA: I was going
to mention that too.
Many times, you can't just
download and install any
browser on you computers.
You have to ask the IT
guys to do that.
So obviously, probably,
that's where legacy
IE is coming from.
So if you're working for the web
services, for enterprise
and such, this is something
like a really huge issue.
And you have to really watch
your browser stats and what
your people are using.
PAUL IRISH: So I want to move
on to the next question.
But before I do, I want
to get Jeffrey
Burtoft from Microsoft.
Since we are talking about IE a
lot, it would be nice to get
his comment here.
JEFFREY BURTOFT: Yeah,
thank you.
So first, to defend
Microsoft here--
and I do that proudly.
Because one of the things I
want to make sure that we
understand is that, Windows
XP that runs IE
8 was a great product.
And that's why people
still use it.
So any time we build great
products, we're going to have
to deal with legacy browsers,
because they're
going to stick around.
So if you look at a parallel
to iOS, Apple just stopped
supporting--
was it 3GS--
with updates, which means that
iOS 6 is the last version
they'll ever see.
But those phones are going
to continue to be around.
And they'll become
a legacy platform
that we have to support.
So when we have good products
that are going to stick
around, it's something that
we need to plan for.
So these type of discussions
will always be relevant.
PAUL IRISH: I think, in this
case, our situation is that,
Windows XP is a great product.
But the problem there is that,
users of IE on Windows XP
don't have an ability to upgrade
their browser to the
next version of IE.
JEFFREY BURTOFT: Yeah, so that's
something that's clear.
If you are on that platform,
there are two different things
that are going to cause you to
stay on older versions of IE.
One is, it's your environment,
whether it's because you don't
want to upgrade.
Or you can't upgrade or the fact
that, with IE, you can't
upgrade past IE 8, if you're
on Windows XP.
So at Microsoft, we
use JavaScript.
We use our JavaScript
engine, HTML5, in
a lot of our products.
And so whether it's writing apps
for Office or in embedded
or an Xbox or in Windows 8 apps,
all of that can be done
with the JavaScript engine.
So there's definitely a coupling
there that makes us
have to draw some lines in the
sand, as to where we can
update and where we can't.
So there are reasons behind
it, I guess is
what I would say.
PAUL IRISH: Sure.
And I guess we can close this
IE discussion for now, with
the end-of-support date for
Windows XP is April, 2014.
JEFFREY BURTOFT: That's right.
PAUL IRISH: So that trend line
that we're watching for IE 8
may potentially drop down more
substantially at that point.
ED SOWDEN: So there's a whole
other dark world which no one
talks about.
Talking about old IEs and the
fact there are other things
which we have support, which
no one talks about.
And they're old screen readers,
screen-reading
technology.
PAUL IRISH: Ed, before we move
on to screen readers, I want
to get Alex Russell's
comments here.
ALEX RUSSELL: Thanks.
Alex Russell-- one of my first
projects at Google was a
product called Chrome Frame,
which was necessitated because
you didn't do what
you just said.
Microsoft didn't take
care of the legacy.
It was Microsoft's
responsibility to do that.
And instead, Microsoft chose not
to invest in making sure
that users of Windows XP could
continue to use modern
technology.
So having done the clean-up work
for you, I just need to
make the point that
you didn't.
[APPLAUSE]
PAUL IRISH: This is going
to get exciting.
So for the moment, we're
going to move
on to the next question.
This one, Matthias Coutsman.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
My question is, for how long
is it for worth polyfilling
features for legacy browsers
and taking the hit in
performance or of
productivity?
What factors should influence
the [INAUDIBLE]
tries to see support for
a legacy client?
PAUL IRISH: So in a lot of
cases, our method of dealing
with older clients that don't
support a certain capability
is polyfilling them.
We started out with the
json2.js, the JSON polyfill.
And we've managed to polyfill
many, many things.
These polyfills do have
performance cost, not only in
the bytes that we have to send
down the wire in CSS and
JavaScript, but also in
runtime performance.
So performance of polyfills
is a concern.
And what are the other aspects
that could help influence the
choice to--
see support might not
be the right words--
but change the support level?
TOM MASLEN: So maybe a good
example is with animation.
So a couple years ago, people
would JavaScript animations.
And now we try [INAUDIBLE]
animations with CSS.
And we just say, well, if you
don't have that CSS feature,
you just get a janky
animation.
I'd say, that's fine.
I don't have a problem with
people in IE getting janky
transitions.
TOMOMI IMURA: I'm not sure
about jankiness.
I mean, if you want to have some
animation but it doesn't
work in some browsers,
I think you have to
just kill the animation.
I think not moving
at all is far
better than janky animation.
TOM MASLEN: So when I say,
janky, I'll actually mean
binary-like.
It's closed, then it's open.
But then, with a more modern
browser, you can slide--
TOMOMI IMURA: On and
off toggling.
TOM MASLEN: Although, I guess
an issue with that is not so
much with polyfill.
I've seen recently where
I made a panel, a pair.
And I gave it a nice
animation.
It worked lovely in iOS.
But when I checked it on
an Amazon Kindle Fire--
it had a great browser.
It supported the feature.
But it was really janky, because
the hardware just
couldn't keep up.
TOMOMI IMURA: And not just
the hardware, actually.
On the Amazon Kindle,
and the sale
browser is a proxy browser.
Or maybe in marketing terms,
it's cloud accelerated browser
or whatever that is.
Yeah, so let us keep in mind,
it's not like all JavaScript
is forced to work in some
WebKit, works in any way you
want in a proxy.
PAUL IRISH: But I think when we
talk about legacy clients,
there's a few reasons why
we use the term legacy.
And that does happen
to usually refer
to them being old.
But I think the reason that we
don't embrace them and love
them is because they
may have bugs.
They're probably slower than
what we're used to.
And they lack features that
we want to use, that we're
interested in using.
So it's not necessarily that
they're old, but they're
aren't good as what we want.
And is it worth forming a policy
around how to change
your support level
for browsers.
What's your take on
this, Shwetank?
SHWETANK DIXIT: I think,
ultimately, there are going to
be so many variations that you
should stop with the mindset
of supporting or not supporting
those kind of
browsers or not.
You should just go with the
thing of progressive
enhancement and feature
detection.
Because what will happen is, you
say that, OK, I'm going to
support this old browser.
But ultimately, what will happen
is, you'll get more and
more devices.
And nowadays, we get devices
which are running a very good
version of Android but
are less than $100.
So even though they're running
like a very, very nice version
of WebKit, for example, the
performance is such that it
really makes them almost
like a legacy
browser, in many cases.
So how you define a legacy
browser is going to become
more and more muddled.
Because a browser with a very,
very nice phone can behave
like a legacy browser, if the
network connection sucks.
And there's a lot of smartphones
coming up, with a
good version of WebKit but
very underpowered.
TOM MASLEN: It's
a strange time.
So you've got like a Nokia C5,
that's an entry level phone.
It's got a really bad
processor and RAM.
But it'll have to have
a really good version
of WebKit on it.
So it will render the
page really well.
And then, you can compare that
to an iPhone 5 that has Opera
Mini in it.
So the capabilities would be
less, or you'd at least get a
static version of the site.
It's a very bizarre issue
to try and solve.
I don't think there is
where a magic bullet.
TOMOMI IMURA: Actually, in the
Modernizr web page, the
documentation says, because you
can use a portal doesn't
mean you should.
I think it says that.
PAUL IRISH: It's true.
TOMOMI IMURA: So that's really,
developers have to
decide what you want
to really support.
And many times, a fancy UI
will be breeding nice.
But do you really care
in some browsers,
having rounded corners?
Really?
You don't always need this.
You can always drop certain--
especially if it's just a UI
prettiness, you can drop that.
PAUL IRISH: But I guess the
other part of this is that,
there are some features.
There's a set of features that
you cannot let degrade
gracefully.
WebGL, GetUserMedia, Web Audio
API, these many can't be
polyfilled.
So what is the responsible way
in defining a browser-support
policy, when you're dealing with
features of this sort,
where you're providing an
experience that competes with
something on a native
platform, and
it's not content based?
TOM MASLEN: So you
mentioned WebGL.
I can give you an
example there.
On the BBC m we've started
doing WebGL content now.
We have the Mars Lander
3D object.
So if you had WebGL supported,
you could spin it around and
zoom in and stuff like that.
And it was really nice.
But then, there's no
polyfill in that.
So what other browsers
would get an image
gallery of the 3D model.
So we wouldn't try to polyfill
the content.
We'd offer an alternative
content.
PAUL IRISH: OK.
I'd like to move on to
the next question.
John Resig, if you could--
I would love.
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: So I took this
question because
I didn't like it.
So I didn't want
it to be asked.
The question was roughly that,
they felt that you could get
away with supporting browsers
that did not have JavaScript.
And I feel that's
not the case.
That for most content websites,
you need to support
clients that do not
have JavaScript.
But to spin into a more
legitimate question, what
about web applications where
you're not dealing with
strictly content-based?
I feel like most of you are
dealing with content, where
it's like, here's
a news article.
Here's some information
you want to read.
Obviously, in that case, there
shouldn't be a barrier between
you and reading that.
But what about a whole
application that is built and
very JavaScript-concentric?
Should do you be making
a fall-back for that?
Like, I know, if you want to
use Gmail and there's no
JavaScript, you fall back to
this form-based thing.
And I have no idea how well
that's maintained.
But that's got to be
someone's sad job.
But I assume not everyone wants
to be doing old HTML
tables and doing the forms.
And so is that a legitimate
thing?
Should people be worrying
about that, for their
applications?
PAUL IRISH: Tom--
TOM MASLEN: I'd say, it's
always best to create an
experience that doesn't just
immediately fail, when
something goes wrong with
the JavaScript.
So I think Gmail is a great
example that you point out.
So it's something that
is a service.
It is purely functionality.
But then, I think we should
just make experiences.
There's a great.
In fact, I'll let
you say this.
So I read on the GDS website
about why you should make
progress enhancement
with JavaScript.
Do you get what I'm
talking about?
ED SOWDEN: No.
TOM MASLEN: OK, so that said,
instead of build your
applications like an escalator
instead of a lift.
Do you get me now?
Was the you that said that?
ED SOWDEN: I don't think
I wrote that.
TOMOMI IMURA: Was it Jake?
I remember reading this
about an elevator.
ED SOWDEN: So somebody said,
if an escalator breaks, the
worst thing that's going to
happen is, it's going to turn
into some stairs.
So you can keep walking up it.
But then, if you're in
a lift and it breaks.
Then you're stuck in the
fucking lift, you know.
There's nothing you can do.
And it's the same with
JavaScript applications.
PAUL IRISH: Well, I guess
there's a certain class.
There's plenty of JavaScript
applications, diagramming tool
and IM Client.
Many of these rely on Real Time
Data, cannot be done with
page refreshes.
And so some of these do require
JavaScript for their
interactions.
TOM MASLEN: Jake, wrote a good
blog post on this recently.
PAUL IRISH: Jake, would you
like to comment on how--
TOM MASLEN: For those who can't
see, Jake was waving
quite madly.
JAKE ARCHIBALD: I'm kind of
perching on the stairs because
I was actually on the
way to the bathroom.
So you caught me just
at the right point.
Any website that has a loading
bar is a missed opportunity.
It's a missed opportunity to
serve the content directly,
without JavaScript and
then get JavaScript
in there to do it.
And Gmail is an example
of that.
Gmail should have URLs.
I should be able to bookmark a
page, to a particular email.
And when I hit that, I should
get that content on the page.
And then JavaScript can come
in and add the rest.
It is just a series
of tabs and forms.
It doesn't need to depend on
JavaScript for first render.
PAUL IRISH: But the Gmail web
app also has URLs that are
perma-linkable for all
messages as well.
SHWETANK DIXIT: One thing I
wanted to mention, just to
repeat, which matches this use
case is, you have JavaScript
applications heavily reliant
on JavaScript.
But you also have these phones
which are coming up, which
will have browsers which
support JavaScript.
But these are on underpowered
phones, in which it will be
actually better for them to
get a version without
JavaScript than to get a version
with JavaScript, which
runs really slowly.
So in those cases, it might be
better for them to get a
lighter version of the page.
And the other thing is, search
engines-- once again, if you
have single-page applications,
you can run Node and Phantom
JS and use a solution
with that.
But I still think that, it would
be better to just have
something which can be run
without JavaScript.
PAUL IRISH: Yes.
I suppose, in the search engine
optimization, its a
balance of what's
easy for you.
But certainly, if it's important
for you to have that
content available to search, you
need to find a way to do
that, either through progressive
enhancement or
through a complex server-side
rendering farm.
TOM MASLEN: The alternative, the
other side of the argument
is that, making an application
that purely relies on
JavaScript is probably
a lot faster.
So I'd say, if you're trying
to get something up and
running fast, if you're
prototyping, if you've got
deadline issues, then
that is an option.
You can do that.
However, I would always try to
make something a progressive
enhancement.
So in the slide where I spoke
about the things that were
that were nice-- so
accessibility, SEO, working
without JavaScript,
usability--
all those things
are idealisms.
But on their own, they're
probably not great arguments
that you can go to your manager
and say, hey, this
doesn't work with
screen readers.
Because your boss would probably
turn around and say,
I don't care about
screen readers.
But when you add them all
together, they create
something bigger.
And that's the whole
point of the web.
And all of those things, if you
develop with all of those
things in mind, then you're
kind of developing in the
current of the web.
You're swimming with the web,
as opposed to swimming and
against it, which is what I
think is why applications that
are purely the JavaScript are
swimming against a little bit.
So you can make things that
are purely JavaScript.
But I think it's better, and
you get added benefits by
building things in the
progressive enhancement.
PAUL IRISH: Matt May, I see
you have a comment.
We're going to have to
make this very quick.
But I want to get
your voice here.
AUDIENCE: Sorry.
Somebody says, accessibility,
and I go crazy.
I just wanted to say, to add on
to this-- and I think BBC
is a great example of this.
The users of assisted technology
are not legacy or
down-level users either.
If you have something like data
visualization or chat or
anything interactive, those are
still things that you need
to make successful, whether or
not you're going to serve them
to legacy clients.
Everybody is expecting that.
They have the latest assistive
technologies.
They have the latest browsers,
like everybody else.
And it's important to decouple
them from, well, we'll just
serve them the text-only site.
Because that's the same
thin girl they've
had since the '90s.
PAUL IRISH: Yes, 98.4% of
screen reader users have
JavaScript enabled from the
latest WebAIM survey.
But guys, I think we're
out of time.
Thank you very much to
our panelists for
joining us up here.
And thank you guys.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDREW BETTS: OK.
We're going to go straight into
the Payments Panel now.
So could the Payments
panelist come up?
ROB GRIMSHAW: Where
do you want me?
ANDREW BETTS: Take
a seat anywhere,
really, just not there.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
We're for our final session
of the day, everyone.
This is the Payment session.
So for those of us in the
business of selling content,
Payments is a problem that we
all have to deal with, whether
we like it or not.
And the range of solutions we
have available at moment for
payments is really quite
limiting to the kinds of
things we can do with
web developers.
So there's a lot of exciting new
technologies coming along.
And I think now is a great time
to be discussing that.
So we have a great panel of
people to talk about this.
And the chair for this session
is Natasha Rooney, Web
Technologist at GSMA.
And I'll let her introduce
the rest of the panel.
[APPLAUSE]
NATASHA ROONEY: Cool.
Thank you so much.
So yeah, we have the exciting
topic of payments left for
this afternoon.
I'm sorry.
But it's one of these
things that is--
usually, at home actually, when
we have the last panel,
I'd say, I'm sorry for standing
in the way of you
guys and the pub.
But we don't really
have the pub here.
So I'm sorry.
We're standing in front of
you guys and dinner.
But there is decent beer,
so I suppose that's OK.
And now I'm starting to sound
like an alcoholic Brit.
OK, let's move on.
So payments are very,
very important.
I've been speaking a lot with
the W3C people, a lot of
people that are involved
in standardization.
And we all want to make
the web better.
And that's fantastic.
But you know what one
of problems is?
It's the money needs to
come from somewhere.
We need the funding to
do the cool things
that we want to do.
So unfortunately, this is just
something that we have to go
and have a chat about.
And you know, if you're really
into it, then great.
Because there's a lot of money
to be made out of it.
So cool, panelists, we've got
Manu Sporny, on my left.
He sits in the W3C on the IETF,
doing a lot of work
around standardization on
payments right now and founder
of Digital Bazaar.
Ricardo from Telefonica, Ricardo
Villera, head honcho
of the BlueVia change to mobile
work and did some stuff
on [INAUDIBLE] before then.
Rob Grimshaw, managing director
of the "Financial
Times," is sitting to my right
here, known for "FT's"
pioneering payment models.
So cool, we'll have a lot
of questions for you.
Kumar McMillan, right at the
end there, from Mozilla,
working on a lot of things.
I'm sure you do a lot of stuff
with mozPay and Firefox
Marketplace, excellent.
And Cindy over here does a lot
of working in Google, with
Google Wallet and the magic
requestAutocomplete, which I'm
sure will come up today.
So Manu is speaking
for us today.
So I'm driver of the slides.
So I get all the good jobs.
So take it away.
MANU SPORNY: So this panel is
kind of titled Payments.
But I think it's far
deeper than that.
When we think payments, we think
getting a payment from
customer to the vendor.
We don't think about, for
example, 30% of the people in
the United States that currently
don't have a bank
account, that has no
way of saving.
In other nations, it's
even worse than that.
It can be up to 70% of the
population that has no way of
saving money, putting money
aside for school, for food,
things of that nature.
So while we're talking about
web payments, I think that
there's a far deeper and more
important story here.
And that is figuring out a way
to get the web to help people
that can't save money, that
don't live in countries where
putting money in a bank is a
feasible solution for them.
So OK.
So this isn't just about paying
for products, while
that's important
for all of us.
This is not just a first
world problem.
It's a problem for people
all around the world.
So as Natasha said, I am the W3C
Chair for the Web Payments
Group right now.
I also deal quite a bit with
linked data, microformats,
micro data, RDFA, JSON-LD,
things like that.
And I also deal quite a bit with
identity and security,
both at the ITF and the W3C.
And basically, what that means
is, I get to see a lot of
different technologies
come by these groups.
And what we're trying to do is,
we're trying to pick and
choose which technologies will
probably be good candidates
for integrating into the core
of the web's architecture.
Until now, we really haven't had
a core way of transferring
value around the web.
I mean, the thing that we look
at to spend money on the web
right now are to move money
back and forth with things
like credit cards and ATH.
And that's just not
cool anymore.
We have to have a
better solution.
And so I spent a lot of time
kind of championing
technologies, a lot of the
technologies that our
panelists are working
on currently.
So we've got a problem
on the web.
And that's, sending and
receiving money is typically
proprietary.
It's very slow.
It's insecure.
And it is actively hostile
to innovation.
That's the reason that we
don't have very many
innovative companies in
the payment space.
You could argue that we do.
And I hope that we do get into
that argument on this panel.
But really, when it comes to
making money on the web, many
of us, our jobs are such
that we get paid
to work on the web.
But some people don't have the
benefit of working for a large
company like Google or
Microsoft, that can cover
their expenses.
They would like to have
a more direct
relationship with their customers.
And right, now content
monetization on the web is
really hard.
It's really expensive,
especially if you're a merchant.
You pay thousands of dollars in
fees, just for the right to
process credit cards.
And the reason that is,
partially, is because a lot of
the payment tech that we use
today on the web was invented
in the '70s.
It's ACH, Automated
Clearinghouse system.
It's credit cards.
All this stuff is really, really
old legacy stuff, that
predates the web by
a large degree.
So I guess it would be good to
kind of take a look at some to
use cases that we're trying
to address, right.
Let's ground this discussion.
Payment for physical goods
today is actually--
we do a pretty decent job
at it on the web.
We've got like things like
Google Wallet and Paypal, that
you can use to pay for goods.
We get the goods.
Everyone is kind of happy.
But when you look at the
merchant side of this,
creating a merchant account to
be able to process credit
cards is very expensive.
There are a lot of fees
attached to it.
Even when you have a really
good merchant provider,
payment provider, it's still
an awful process for folks
that are kind of mom and
pop shops that try to
set up on the web.
You're usually locked into
a payment processor,
when you pick them.
There's no such thing
as data portability.
Or if there is, it's really
kind of terrible.
Doing things like in-app
payments right now, you're
usually tied to a particular app
store of some kind, either
the iTunes store or the
Google Play store
or things like that.
And doing things like crowd
funding and crowd loaning on
by yourself, instead of going
through Kickstarter, which
takes 10% of the money that you
make, you can't do that.
And these are things that, at
least some of us in the Web
Payments group, think should
be fundamental rights, not
just in the US, but
around the world.
You should be able to be in
charge of your own financial
well-being.
So I guess the core here that
we're talking about at this
panel is three different
categories of things, three
different ways that we spend
money on the web, three
different ways of
raising money.
And the first one is kind of
the old money, the popular
proprietary category.
This is most of the payment
services that
we have right now.
And this is absolutely not a
slam to any of the companies
that are on this slide.
These companies solve a very
important problem, which is,
it really sucks to do
transactions over the web,
using your credit card in ACH.
So we've got Paypal, Amazon
payments, Google Wallet.
Even the new poster children
for really cool payment
startups, like Stripe Square,
Paymode, Dwolla, and sites
like Kickstarter Indiegogo and
Crowdtilt, these are all based
on this really horrible
old, legacy system.
There are tons and tons of
problems that we'll go into,
during the discussion today.
So that's kind of the
first category.
This is what's kind of
popular right now.
The next category is
online app stores.
So these are other types of
kind of proprietary silos.
They lock you in, the Apple
iTunes store, the Apple store,
Facebook credits, which used
to exist when these slides
were made but doesn't
exist anymore.
They were just shut down
a little while ago.
The Windows Store, Google Play,
these are all kind of
examples of stores that give
really great user experiences.
But you're kind of locked into
them when you use them.
The idea of having this open
app marketplace has been
talked about.
And luckily for us, I think,
Mozilla has been doing some
really great work in this area,
making it so that you
can sell web apps from
any website.
You don't have to go through
an app store
of one kind or another.
And so then the final category,
I think, is
predominantly what I'm
really excited about.
This is what gives me hope.
And so the last bit are these
Open Web payment solutions.
Finally, people are starting
to work on things that fit
very nicely with the web.
They don't try and shim the
old 1970s credit card
architecture into the web.
They are a new way of looking at
payments on the web, where
payments are instantaneous.
There's a lot of rich metadata
that goes with it.
So Firefox OS is doing
a great job with
their Marketplace stuff.
We have Pay Swarm, which is the
first universal payment
standard for the web.
Bitcoin, I'm sure many of you
have heard of Bitcoin.
How many of you have
heard of Ripple?
Wow.
I was just at a banking
conference last week.
And like half the bankers
raised their hands.
That's surprising.
That never happens.
So anyway Ripple was built
by the Bitcoin folks.
It's kind of a better
version of Bitcoin.
But these are all really cool
technologies, that are native
to the web, that are really
going to shake things up.
I think they're really going to
finally bring payments into
the modern age.
So I guess the goal here, what
we're trying to do is, we're
trying to integrate open payment
technology into the
core architecture of the web.
We did this for communication
with email.
Emails got protocols.
The reason that it's so easy
to type in a person's email
address and send a message
halfway around the world is,
there's a whole set of
protocol around it.
No such thing exists for
payments on the web.
It's just starting.
We've got Bitcoin and
Ripple coming along.
But we really need
to work on it.
And that's what we focus
on the Web Payments
Group at the W3C.
Most of the panel members
here are a part of the
Web Payments Group.
It's completely open.
We really need developers
to join.
So if you're interested in any
of the stuff that you hear on
the panel today, please join.
Jump onto the group and join,
if you just Google Web
Payments W3C.
And if you want to talk about
this stuff, pull me aside and
introduce yourself.
I love talking about
this stuff.
So please, at the party after
this, pull me aside, if you're
interested in any of the stuff
that you hear on the panel, as
well as the rest of the
panelists here.
So quickly, in closing, there's
a whole bunch of
contact info for you to get in
touch, if you're interested in
payments or interested
in actually taking
part in this work.
There's a lot of good that
you can do here.
This is world-changing stuff.
Twitter, G+ handle, email, and
the slides are posted up
there-- payswarm.com/slides.
So without further ado, let's
get into the discussion.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
[APPLAUSE]
So thank you very much
for that, Manu.
And with that, like you said,
we'll kick off with the first
question, which comes
from Ada Edwards.
I believe you're reading
out this one.
Oh, actually, can we just
wait for a mic.
Thanks.
AUDIENCE: So I have a question
from a certain Andrew Betts.
Topping up a prepaid account
with a merchant to fund
micropayments is free money
for the merchant.
Why would they kill the golden
goose by moving to instant
micropayments?
MANU SPORNY: So I can jump in?
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah,
go for it.
MANU SPORNY: I don't know if I
quite agree with the question,
meaning that I think it's short
sighted for any merchant
to think of it as-- anybody
that's not large, so Google
can think in that way.
Google can say, I'm going
to require someone
to prefund an account.
And then across all the Google
properties, you can buy things.
Your mom and pop web store,
someone doing a niche site is
never going to be
able to do that.
Or if they're good if they're
going to do that, they're
going to lose quite
a bit of business.
Because I guess Theme Forest
is a great example of this.
They require you to put in
like $5 or $10, but their
themes cost $1.24.
And you have to kind of be--
at least I was, when I bought
one of the themes off there.
I was pretty desperate.
I was really looking
for a theme.
I was under a deadline.
I was like, fine, here's $5.
And a lot of my money is kind
of sitting there still.
So I'm a bit ticked
at them for that.
I wish I could have just gone to
the site, spent $1.24, and
gone somewhere else.
And I think that is the model
that we really should be
shooting for on the web.
You should be able to go to a
site, just click a buy button.
You don't have to sign
up for an account.
You don't have to put in your
credit card information.
You just click Buy.
The browser takes care of
the vast majority of
the payment for you.
It's ease of use.
And I think micropayments is
kind of a part of that.
You don't want to be charging
people $0.02
or $0.03 at a time.
But the idea that you should
be able to do $1.25
transaction I don't
think is crazy.
I think you should be able
to do that on the web.
NATASHA ROONEY: Does anybody
feel any differently about--
Ricardo--
RICARDO VILLERO: I was
actually going
to comment one thing.
So first, actually, if I could
do a bit of a survey, how many
people actually take payments
on the web?
How many people have a product
that actually takes payment
kind of reduce one?
And regarding the Ripple
question, how many people know
Bitcoin, for example?
Everybody, no?
OK, it's a good one.
Good.
So the thing that I was going to
mention is, that one of the
problems that we have
had with payments.
I've been working in
payments for years.
And when I got in, I worked with
mobile operators, which,
if they're good at something,
it's basically taking your
money, as you probably know.
So has anybody never
received a charge
from a mobile operator?
The bill always gets
there, right.
So I thought that, actually, we
had our stuff better sorted
out, than when I actually
go there.
And in payments, the main
problem is that, it's a
domain-specific problem.
And it's heavily regulated
domain as well.
So for example, why would
somebody want to pre-load an
account and then take your money
from there and actually
make that charge of fees
in that transaction?
Because there are different
roles in payments, so
actually, when a payment
occurs, it
hasn't really occurred.
It occurs in different phases.
So when you, for example, pay
something with a credit card,
that money is not yet on
the merchant account.
That money has got to go from
bank to bank, normally through
a series if not only one,
of clearinghouses.
And then that ends up
in the other bank.
So basically, that means that
bank hasn't actually got paid.
There's actually a risk that
money never gets paid.
And that is what, normally,
your bank calls bad debt.
So when you, for example, prepay
an account, what that
merchant, that acquirer in that
case is actually trying
to do is reduce their
bad debt problem.
They're trying to say,
I've got the funds.
So if actually this transaction
occurs, I'm going
to automatically pay myself.
Thank you very much.
So that actually occurs whenever
two parties in a
transaction don't have trust
in between them.
And this is a concept I suppose
will go back and back
again in the panel, because
payments is all about trust.
If I actually email
you and tell you,
will you lend me $20.
And you actually give me $20.
That is a transaction
that has occurred.
Maybe I don't even have my
money, but you've promised me
that you're going
to pay me $20.
Then I get my $20.
At some point, I may pay
you back or not.
You never know.
So that is actually
a transaction, and
that actually happens.
So the concept of you paying
me, the concept of you
establishing my identity via
receiving an email from me,
which by the way, is
not something you
should trust probably.
SMTP is not the most secure
thing in the world.
Those things are what actually
happens in payments.
And I think we still don't have
a full solution to model
all that complexity technically
in the web.
And that's one of the problems
we're trying to deal with.
NATASHA ROONEY: And I think I
actually owe Andrew Betts $20.
So we'll see if he does or
does not get that money.
So we actually have a question
from the floor.
So Alex Sexton, please, there
you go, over there, guys.
AUDIENCE: Hello.
Full disclosure, Stripe
employee--
NATASHA ROONEY: Actually, for
the floor, would you mind just
explaining what Stripe
is, just in case?
AUDIENCE: Stripe is a company
that currently does payments
for the web.
So I think we're in the
first slide, along
with many other companies.
So I think me and my friends
would all agree that stuff
like Ripple and Bitcoin is
really cool and totally this
cool, federated way
of doing payments.
But the bootstrapping of that
system is the blocker I think.
So how do you get my
parents to be able
to deal with Bitcoin.
You're talking about,
I don't want to
sign up for an account.
I don't want tot do
any of this stuff.
I just want to hit
this button, and
money changes hands.
And there aren't any of
these old systems.
So how do you rewire people's
brains to make this much more
complicated system to
them, something that
makes sense at all?
MANU SPORNY: I think the short
answer is, ease of use.
I mean that is the killer app
for all of these payment
technologies.
It's the ability to just go to
any site, click the Buy Now
button, be shown what
you're going to buy.
And that's it.
And it doesn't matter if you're
using Google Wallet.
It doesn't matter if
you're using Stripe
or Paypal or anything.
They're all speaking a fairly
similar payments protocol.
This is kind of what Pay Swarm,
that universal payment
standard, is designed to do.
The idea here is that, you
have a common payments
protocol that all of
the sites use.
It's open, non-proprietary,
W3C standard.
And then you can choose.
You can pick and choose who's
going to process your payments
for you, if it's going to be
your bank or if it's going to
be Google Wallet or if it's
going to be Paypal.
And then the merchant can choose
whoever they want too.
So I think the way that you
bootstrap this stuff is, one,
through ease of use.
And then, the second thing is,
you have to somehow convince
vendors that this
is worth doing.
And I think that's going to be
incredibly difficult to do, if
Google Wallet, Stripe, Paypal,
don't join onto the work, if
they do if they continue do
the proprietary stuff.
NATASHA ROONEY: We'll take one
more comment from Rob.
ROB GRIMSHAW: I do agree,
actually, with the point of
the question.
Things I Bitcoin are such
wonderful ideas.
but these things only really
thrive if they're starting
from scratch.
I mean, you do it in a market
somewhere like developing
countries, like Kenya or
whatever, then actually you
can make something happen
very quickly.
So you've got a system like
M-PESA, with 17 million users.
But most of those people never
had a bank account in their
life, so they just accept it
as, this is what it is.
For most of the developed
markets that we're dealing
with, on a day to day, as a
merchant, like the "FT," all
these people have got their
money in existing bank
accounts stuck in this
1970s system.
And it's not going to
come out quickly.
So for me, the practical
solutions are about mitigating
that existing system of making
it to something which is at
least some way practical from a
web payments point of view,
rather than thinking about how
we can start again, through
some of these ideas which are
wonderful, but to some extent,
Utopian, from the perspective
of today's business.
MANU SPORNY: Just quickly,
Ripple's whole business plan
is to get banks for
what's there.
NATASHA ROONEY: We'll
come to Ripple in
next couple of questions.
But interesting, to what Rob
said, I think one of the next
questions is going to make you
touch on those utopian
viewpoints a little bit.
So Teddy Conda, I think
has the next
question for us, here.
Thank you.
AUDIENCE: So this question kind
of strikes close to home,
because I worked in publishing
and media for a good majority
of my career.
And I don't know if we'll have
an answer to it in this forum,
because it's a topic that
has fundamental
problems of its own.
However, I'll add a bit to it,
as well as read the question.
What payment model is the one
that will finally make
quote-unquote "old media"
profitable enough online?
And how soon can
we get to that?
And furthermore, do know of any
media venues, publishing
houses, that are doing this
correctly and are actually
profitable, through a payment
model online?
RICARDO VILLERO: Well, I think,
Rob, this kind of hits
in [INAUDIBLE].
ROB GRIMSHAW: We've done it.
It's fine.
NATASHA ROONEY: So explain
it to us, Rob.
What's it all about?
ROB GRIMSHAW: Well, the sort of
key thing is actually to be
bold enough to charge
for your product.
And actually, the world
is prepared to
pay for great content.
And I think we've established
that quite successfully, over
the past five years that we've
really pursued this policy of
becoming a company that
generates the majority of its
money from content, rather
from advertising.
If you look at ft.com's
finances right now, we
generate in excess of 70% of
our revenues from content,
i.e. subscriptions, the vast
marjority of that page
digitally, through our
subscriptions.
And that is not an indication
that we've lost all our
advertising revenue.
In fact, our advertising grew
over the period of time that
we grew our subscriptions
business.
It's a sign that, actually, if
you have the right offering
and you do work hard on the
payment side, you can build a
very successful business around
quality content online.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
We've got a couple of questions
from the floor.
So Ally, if you want to
raise your hand--
right here, oh, sorry.
AUDIENCE: It's kind of off topic
now, because I wanted to
speak, actually, about
the last topic.
Is it OK to go back to that?
Or would you rather continue
moving forward?
I guess what I was thinking was,
we mentioned, with the
problem with more widespread
adoption of Bitcoin
being ease of use.
And I just had a gut reaction
to disagree with that.
Because I think that a much
bigger issue with it,
especially among an older crowd,
has to do with trust
issues and feeling that
they can trust
these different sources.
And it was just kind of what
I wanted to bring up.
And I'm wondering how you
address that and how you make
those older people feel
more comfortable with
these payment options.
CINDY: I'm not sure that they'll
ever be comfortable
with them, honestly.
I mean, look at the
supermarket.
When you're standing at the
supermarket, how many older
people use debit cards?
And how many are
writing checks?
So it might be that user
behavior is so divergent that,
they won't get there.
But that doesn't mean that we
should not continue to push
the envelope.
I do believe that Bitcoin
is going to be really
challenging.
I do believe that, from a
usability perspective, even
when I read up on it.
And there are big warnings,
keep your wallet offline.
I was like, whoa.
And I'm a tech person.
So the lay person is going to
read that one line that's
right on the Bitcoin website.
And they're going to run.
They're going to run as
fast as they can.
So this is a social issue, as
much as it's a payment issue.
And it's a trust issue.
So payments is a complex
ecosystem of a lot of
different players.
And trying to make everyone
happy is very challenging.
ROB GRIMSHAW: We do live in a
period where the price of gold
is at an all time high, mainly
because people don't trust
currencies full stop,
let alone new
ideas like by Bitcoin.
And this is a really difficult,
complex issue for
societies and economies as a
whole, which people have been
wrestling with hundreds
of year.
And just kind of introducing
something new into that is not
something that happens
in a couple of months
or a couple of years.
It can take decades, hundreds of
years, to really establish
a new currency properly.
RICARDO VILLERO: Also, I was
going to comment that,
actually, in Payments just
recently, we've been actually
talking about how this whole
payments on the web thing
should really be a bit more--
well, some of us think that
this should be more like a
two-phased approach.
Essentially, there's no open
technology to basically do
payments on the web
at the moment.
And there's also the whole bill
toward currency thing,
which at some point
may arrive.
And actually, I think there
would be even government
initiatives to do this.
Because there are lots of
benefits about issuing
currency that is not physical.
But until that moment happens,
basically, that doesn't mean
that you cannot start with the
first part of it, which is,
OK, how about we have open
technology to do those
payments on the web.
And we have that thing in W3C,
where we basically go into
inventing problems that you
cannot really solve, not even
in the existing system.
Imagine on the new system.
So we tried to first
have a system.
And then, we tried to add
things like virtual
currencies on it.
NATASHA ROONEY: So this goes
into the third question, which
came from--
actually, Manu, I believe this
is one of the questions that
you originally asked.
So I will ask it for you.
It actually goes back to the
Bitcoin and Ripple question,
which is, do they fit into the
plan for web-based payments.
And should they be included
as payment options?
Or should they remain
on the periphery?
But it seems like what Ricardo
is talking about now is,
they've already been considered
as being wrapped
into the standards.
MANU SPORNY: Yeah, and I really
asked that question
because I was more
interested in the
answer from the panelists.
And I wanted to be a bit more
pointed with the question.
Are there definite plans to
integrate alternative
currencies into product lines,
like Google Wallet.
Would Google Wallet
ever consider
adding Bitcoin or Ripple?
Would Mozilla consider putting a
Bitcoin wallet or even a USD
wallet directly into
the browser?
So that when you download a
browser, you've got preloaded
$10 that you can spend
online with it.
You go to a website.
You click Buy Now.
And the payment is made.
It's instantaneous
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah,
that's actually a
quite interesting question.
So like Manu said at the
beginning, lots of us are
involved in this payment stuff,
and Ricardo and I from
the operator space.
And Kumar, Mozilla has taken
a little bit of a different
approach to this, where they
have said, we don't care who
the payment provider is.
We're just giving you the option
to pay, which is a very
different stance,
in this space.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Yeah, the thing
with Bitcoin is, you can
already pay with Bitcoin
on the web.
There's already web-based
wallets.
And so Mozilla's mozPay API,
which I think you're referring
to, is just one of the ways you
could pay in Firefox OS.
It's not the only way.
So any app in Firefox us can
take Bitcoin payments.
There would just need the
JavaScript to do it.
They would need to online
wallet, in order to do it.
So it would just work.
But yeah, as far as mozPay, a
lot of people are interested
in incorporating Bitcoin.
it's already been asked
by a lot of people.
They want to see that as a
way to buy apps in the
marketplace, for sure.
Whether or not it will
happen, I don't know,
because it is tough.
There are a lot of challenges.
RICARDO VILLERO: And while we're
at it, actually, so that
you get some of the data that
we wanted to get, how many
people here actually own
Bitcoin of any kind?
Because we're the geekiest of
the geeks, somebody here
should have Bitcoin.
How many people have
actually done a
transaction with Bitcoin?
OK, and how many people, when
they bought Bitcoin,
actually-- when you mean you
have Bitcoin, you bought it
either in MongoX or one of,
basically, the big exchanges?
How many people are on
MongoX, actually?
OK, then you used a
smaller exchange.
Woo-hoo, OK.
This thing is working.
MANU SPORNY: How many people
have lost their wallet and
lost over $10 to $15?
[LAUGHING]
There's the problem right there,
at least with Bitcoin.
NATASHA ROONEY: Cool,
can we refer some
questions to the floor.
I think Marcus has got a
question, at the front.
And this is quite a contentious
topic, so if you
guys want to vote on OnSlyde
tool, that would be great.
Because it's a strange one,
where we'd like a little bit
more developer feedback on how
people are feeling about
particular payment methods.
So Marcus, please--
CINDY: OK.
It's on, sorry.
So Manu started the discussion,
kind of talking
about people that are not
in the old system.
So they're still using real
money, so paper money.
One thing to notice, a lot of
people don't want to move to
digital money.
Even if they now need to or if
they had to because they
wanted to buy a service,
how would they enter
this digital economy?
You haven't really
touched on that.
MANU SPORNY: Mobile devices,
M-PASA is completely
mobile-based.
Mobile devices are basically the
way that a lot of people
in emerging nations are getting
access to the web.
And they have access to the
largest communication network
that mankind has ever known.
And if we build a financial
protocol into
that, that's huge.
That's a really big thing.
CINDY: You're basically
converting telcos into banks.
RICARDO VILLERO: Hopefully, it's
going to be telcos and
the banks and companies,
like Google and Paypal.
Everyone would have a level
playing field, to effectively
be a financial institution
to these people.
So we know, for example, in
Europe, there's actually a
green paper that's being
discussed at the moment, by
the European Union, regarding
what is the role of actually
telcos, regarding the whole
payments industry.
This is to regulate, explicitly,
basically these
bill payments and one of the
things that would have full
consequences for telcos, if it
actually ended up being true.
Because the moment you've
regulated a financial product,
then basically, you don't have
a prepaid phone account.
You have a value-added account
that telcos are storing, which
means you could go to a shop.
And they could refund your money
and things like that.
So it has a lot of implications,
regarding how do
you handle money there.
But it also has a lot
of advantages.
So in this I can actually give
one anecdote, which is, at
BlueVia we do payments
for different--
basically, we're the back
end that different
stores connect to.
We do payments with Mozilla.
We do payments with Google.
And one of things happened in
Google recently is that, in
the Android store, WhatsApp,
which is this famous
application, recently decided
to charge for subscriptions.
And only WhatsApp tripled our
transactions during a period
of time in Spain, because people
who had never entered
their credit card in Google
Wallet decided to pay with
their mobile account.
Because they didn't
want to enter the
whole credit card thing.
They just said, OK, there's
an option to
actually pay with my phone.
That was the first time
they saw the option.
Pay with My Phone, probably
because it was the first time
that they actually paid.
And that thing really launched
the transactions up.
So it actually shows that
percentage of population, who
probably was the only paid
transaction they ever did,
they actually used
a mobile phone.
AUDIENCE: OK.
So the larger question is--
you mentioned some of
the implications.
There are tons of legal
implications around this.
How are you guys going to deal
with that, especially in a
small community group?
RICARDO VILLERO: Right
now, it's actually a
bit of a gray area.
Because at the moment, for
example, when you charge
something to your phone and then
it gets into your bill.
And then your bill gets settled
with your bank account.
In reality, the operator never
got hold of that money.
That money has to never
gone to the operator.
It actually only settles when
the bank pays me from your
bank account.
So in reality, your money
has always been
in your bank account.
It's more like a virtual ledger,
what we are holding.
AUDIENCE: Which wasn't what ha
said initially, about the 70%
of the people in the
world not having
access to a bank account.
So the thing I'm not
getting is that.
RICARDO VILLERO: But that's
because that's 70% of--
so you take, for example, a
country, this is a country
like Spain, where people have
got more contracts, or UK.
There are countries like Brazil
mostly Latin America,
where, actually, there are
three phone plans.
Basically, there's prepaid.
There's post-pay, the construct
the you're used to.
And there's [INAUDIBLE],
which is where I pay
during a period of time.
So say, I pay 5 Euros.
And I'm like in a contract for
a week, that kind of thing.
So when you're in
those systems.
Most people are prepay on those
markets, by the way.
And what they do is,
they actually pay
their bill on a shop.
They go to a shop.
They get a coupon.
And they load their phone.
So that's mostly
what they use.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK.
Yeah, complicated like Las Vegas
hotel-- so we will go on
to the next question,
which has come up
a little bit already.
But Matt Morgan, if
you're around, and
stick your hand up.
Oh, there we go, very easy.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
I think part of this
question comes from
our host, Andre Betts.
I'm going to personalize
it a little.
The basic question is, what
needs to happen to make
one-quick payment a reality
for everyone?
What I'd like you to do is
think of everyone really
broadly and include maybe
organizations like libraries
and their readers, for
whom complete content
confidentiality is
a requirement.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK.
So the one-click payment thing
is quite interesting. and it
was one of the things that I was
quite blown away with, at
Google I/O this year.
And Cindy, this is something
that work on, right?
CINDY: So this is a
common problem.
Users go to hundreds of
different forms and fill out
the exact same information.
So that was kind of the
hypothesis behind
requestAutocomplete, which
is the new web standard
initiative that Chrome
is implementing.
And part of that initiative, I'm
fortunate to be able to be
part of it, because they are
integrating Google Wallet as a
payment option, in addition
to Chrome Autofill data.
But it's that concept that users
are filling out the same
exact information again
and again and again.
They don't necessarily want to
hand it over to 50 different
merchant websites.
So why does not the browser,
as a container, hold that
information for them and provide
it to the different
merchant websites
on their behalf?
So now, requestAutocomplete is
obviously dedicated to that
true payments use case.
It is providing the user's
information to complete the
transaction.
So in terms of--
I cannot pronounce.
MANU SPORNY: Anonymity.
AUDIENCE: In terms of that,
you know, that gets
challenging in payments
period.
So that's an interesting thread
that I was surprised
hasn't come up sooner, because
that is one of the biggest
changes between those 1970s
technologies and kind of what
is coming out today.
Because there are tons
of regulations
around payment companies.
And once you're regulated, you
have to monitor, depending on
changes country by country.
But there's anti-money
laundering.
There are initiatives that
governments put in place
really for consumer safety that,
with this anonymous new
digital currency, you lose.
So definitely, the identity
thread is an interesting one.
MANU SPORNY: You will not be
able to be anonymous when you
do a payment online.
It is going to be highly,
highly, highly unlikely your
government will not let that
happen, unless you rise
up and change it.
But if we look at history,
that doesn't happen.
NATASHA ROONEY: So actually,
I have a quick
questions to go over.
Talking about one-click payment,
is this something
that FireFox OS or Mozilla
are looking at generally?
And then, what if a user
decides to opt
in to Do Not Track.
And then, how does that work?
Oh, sorry.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: I mean,
one-tap payments are
definitely something that
mozPay wants to support.
Firefox Marketplace wants
to support it.
That doesn't mean it'll
work for everybody.
So that's a really much harder
problem to solve.
Amazon already does one-click
payments.
I mean, it's obviously very
possible on the web.
It's very easy to do.
I think, in the short term,
requestAutocomplete is the
best way to get there.
I think that's just the reality
of the web right now.
It's that every place takes a
credit card form, and carried
billing is a little bit
more complicated.
But with credit cards, you can
have requestAutocomplete
securely store your credit
card number.
And it's two clicks maybe.
But you could just tap the
button and say that, yes, fill
in my credit card.
And you're done.
And that's going to be a big
win for both sides, for
consumers and for
the merchants.
Because on mobile especially,
it's really hard to enter in
your credit card, if you
do it once on one site.
And if you have to do it an
infinite number of time for
each other site, that's
going to really suck.
MANU SPORNY: So I disagree,
partially.
I think you're right
in that it is-- and
you were very specific.
You said, in the short term,
that's probably going to be
the best solution,
requestAutocomplete.
And I totally agree with that.
And I don't think anyone on
the panel believes this.
But I think it would be
incredibly shortsighted for us
to stop there, to say that, this
is the way it should be
for the next five or 10 years.
We really need to fix the whole
credit card numbers
given to every single
merchant you visit
our on the web issue.
I mean, how many people in here
would tell your users, I
think you should use the exact
same password for every single
financial account
that you have.
And whenever you go to a
website, whenever you want to
spend money, you give
them your password.
That's your credit
card number.
CINDY: I'm going to jump in.
And that's where the Google
Wallet integration with
requestAutocomplete, especially
on the Chrome side,
does close that hole, because we
do use the virtual tokens.
So we do protect that user's
true credit card.
MANU SPORNY: But it's
proprietary to Google, right.
AUDIENCE: It is.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK.
We probably should take--
CINDY: But we are open to
integration with other browser
manufacturers.
NATASHA ROONEY: We
need to take some
questions from the floor.
Tede, so somebody can pass
Tede a mic, please.
CINDY: So I guess my question
kind of relates to the debate
that was just on.
But we've been talking about
responsiveness, legacy clients.
And it's great when we move to
world where there is an open
web standard for payments.
But right now, it's not that.
It's very fragmented.
Everyone is trying to push a
one-click solution to payments.
You have Amazon.
You have Strip.
Everyone is putting a
button on your page,
saying, pay with me.
And so now, for developers, our
payment form is just now
cluttered with pay
with everything.
So is there kind of strategy for
developers in a way that
we're not cutting into our
margins, because we're not
given the users the payment
method they want.
How do we balance that?
NATASHA ROONEY: Is this
a web-intense thing?
ROB GRIMSHAW: I've got to
endorse that comment, because
referring back onto so many of
these solutions for one-click
payment are essentially
proprietary.
And when you look at it from a
merchant's point of view, what
it amounts to is this sort of
smorgasbord of different
payment solutions that, one by
one, you have to kind of
integrate with your
own systems.
And each one just
delivers a tiny
fraction of extra payments.
And for a merchant like
this, which is
operating across borders--
we have subscribers
in 150 countries.
This is just a nightmare,
because many of these
solutions only work in one or
two or a select number of
territories.
And it's completely
impractical.
We are so far away from a
one-click solution which will
operate seamlessly around the
globe, for any merchant
really, at the moment.
And that's what we really need
to make things work.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yeah.
I was going to talk about
something around the intense
model, to be able to say,
I just want to pay.
And then, it's just your
chosen payment
method comes through.
But this is very similar along
the lines of what Facebook
tried with credits.
And then they came up against
the foreign exchange problem,
which anyone who's worked in
the financial markets will
know is just a complete
nightmare.
So your any other thoughts
on this topic?
MANU SPORNY: So I think Cindy
and Kumar are probably never
going to talk to me again
after this panel.
CINDY: You're slopping
dangerously close.
MANU SPORNY: Yes, I know,
by the hole too.
So I think the best thing that
web developers can do is put
some pressure on Google and
Mozilla and Paypal and Stripe
and tell them that you want some
kind of unified payment
mechanism that's
non-proprietary, on the web.
I honestly think that is
the best thing for
the web right now.
And I really, in your heart of
hearts, I think you agree.
CINDY: He's a tough salesman.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: What I think
is really interesting about
that this is, Mozilla and Google
are browser vendors.
And I actually don't think
we have a lot of
leverage to do this.
I think it needs to
come from banks.
MANU SPORNY: You do.
I was in Dubai at a banking
conference with all the major
world banks.
And they are absolutely
terrified of technology
companies coming in and stealing
their customers.
You have so much power
to change this.
NATASHA ROONEY: OK.
Let's move back to the questions
from the floor.
Steve, here, if we can
get another mic--
AUDIENCE: I guess it was really
just a question about
what Manu said, that I can't
be anonymous on the web.
In the physical world, I can go
pay something with cash and
be completely anonymous.
Why would I want to give up--
why should I give up that
anonymity that I currently
have in a physical world?
MANU SPORNY: It's a very
good question.
You shouldn't if you
don't want to.
But I mean, we're
dealing with--
there's a lot of information
that's collected from
on us on the web.
If you don't want that
information collected on you,
don't get on the web.
We've got issues with PRISM, the
NSA, we know how easy it
is to tap this stuff.
It's very easy to track it,
even Bitcoin, which is
supposed to be this
pseudo-anonymous protocol,
people have been able to track
down spending habits, who's
spending money.
So for example, if someone
steals your Bitcoin wallet,
that money can't ever
be used, really.
Because if it's used and it's
tracked down to a shipping
address, then they
can find you.
You report your wallet
as stolen.
And any money coming out of that
wallet can be tracked to
the person that made of any
kind of physical purchase.
NATASHA ROONEY: Well, this
brings me back to the whole do
not track thing.
I'm still really quite
interested to know about how
this would work, with them a
mozPay system on FireFox OS,
because they're pushing
so much for that.
RICARDO VILLERO: I'll wait for
the mozPay one, if I can add
only one thing to this.
The problem, as we were saying
before, is basically, the
whole payments is based
on risk and trust.
And in this case, what
you're saying.
What you're doing in that
financial transaction in cash
with somebody is that, they
issuer, the person who's
generating the funds, AKA you
is making a transaction with
the merchant, which is,
at the same time, the
acquire, this person.
And this transaction occurs on
something that we both trust,
AKA government money, because we
both think that is actually
valuable money.
So this transaction has
occurred between us.
You actually gave away
your identity.
You gave away your identity to
this person who actually can
recognize you.
And he felt that this was enough
to establish trust.
So that's why they accepted
your money.
In the digital world, the
problem is that, this person
is a server down there.
And you are a browser,
somewhere down here.
And that trust has got to be
established between you two,
before those funds get changed
from your bank to their bank.
And that's kind of
the problem.
It's that, at that moment,
that other person, that
acquirer is going to only
trust something.
And in general, Google will
perfectly trust your Google
Wallet account.
Paypal will perfectly trust
your PayPal account.
And Mozilla will trust whichever
account you actually
have got to be configured
in mozPay.
But Google won't accept your
PayPal identity as being a
valid identity.
That is where the problem comes,
because they don't
establish trust based on
the other identity.
NATASHA ROONEY: We probably
should actually move forward.
So Tom, see if you've.
OK, good.
There we go.
AUDIENCE: Thanks.
I think, if I can distinguish
between anonymity and
confidentiality.
Somebody is coming to the
library to pay a $0.25 fine
for an overdue book.
And we don't want
anybody to know.
We know who that person is
because we know you checked
out the book.
But I don't want anybody
else to know that you
paid a fine on it.
Is there a way I can do
that online for $0.25?
KUMAR MCMILLAN: No.
ROB GRIMSHAW: No.
MANU SPORNY: Yes.
I mean, not yet.
I think there is.
If you use Bitcoin to do it
and you create a one-off
wallet, you could
do that payment.
But I mean, it's very difficult
to do that,
technically possible, not very
feasible, which I think is the
answer they were giving.
It's not a good user
experience.
NATASHA ROONEY: Oh, sorry, Rob.
You go.
ROB GRIMSHAW: Some of the
stuff is not about the
technology.
I think governments around the
globe are attacking anonymity
in the financial system, on
all fronts, for issues of
taxation, money laundering,
et cetera.
And I don't think that effort
is going to stop.
And as we move into an
electronics payments world, I
don't think they're going
to allow big channels of
anonymous payments,
whether it's
technically possible or not.
NATASHA ROONEY: All right.
We should move on now.
I'm liking what people are
managing to get on the-- here
we have money bags and
Scrooge McDuck.
CINDY: Is this the
end of the day?
Am I Scrooge McDuck?
Brilliant, that's fantastic.
I see how it is.
I kind of wish that was the
case, unfortunately not.
So Matt Andrews, if you'd stick
up your had for the next
question, please.
AUDIENCE: Here's another
anonymous question.
I think it's pretty been
done to death.
But here we go.
What are the possibilities for
decentralized peer-to-peer
payments, and what security
considerations are involved in
doing this?
NATASHA ROONEY: So decentralized
peer-to-peer
payments, and what security
considerations are involved in
doing this, going back
to a similar think.
Kumar, do you want to start
us off on this?
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Sure.
Well, I've been sort of in the
realm of Firefox OS, which is
a mobile operating system.
And it's really hard, on
mobile devices, to do
something to get to a
decentralized place like that.
We would need the Web Crypto
API to land, so that we can
make sure that things are
very secure and even
in memory are secure.
maybe And another API which is
coming is to access a secure
element, on certain Sim cards,
where you can actually do sort
of public key exchange
type of things.
All those technologies
are needed.
But at the end of the day, you
could still route a device, if
you were to steal it.
And then, you can get access
to a lot of things.
So I think we're
pretty far off.
But I think that's what
would need to happen.
It would have to be something
that's would have to be this
bulletproof device.
Because also, if it's completely
decentralized, that
means that you're paying
with a device.
And let's say, it's Bitcoin
or something.
And it's not backed up on
a server because it's
decentralized.
You might lose that device.
And then you lose
all your money.
And maybe there's some
way to distribute
that across many nodes.
I don't know, but
hard problem.
NATASHA ROONEY: Sort of against
the cloud pattern that
seems to be happening with
lots of things, I guess.
Any other points on that--
MANU SPORNY: I mean, there
are already decentralized
peer-to-peer payment
systems on the web.
Bitcoin and Ripple
are two of them.
You can use them.
They're online wallets.
So you have to be able to get
to some website to run the
transaction.
But the protocols work.
I mean, the Bitcoin has been
under attack, since
it ever came out.
And by really smart people in
crypto and security areas.
And no one has really
broken the protocol.
So I think they're here.
It's just, the idea of it being
integrated directly into
the browser is probably--
I would expect that would never
happen, at least not for
the next 10 to 15 years.
Because the risk you run when
you put it into a browsers is,
you have to end up supporting
it forever.
And I don't think any of the
browser-- and I don't think it
would be smart for any of the
browser vendors to build that
technology in right now, which
is why the Firefox Marketplace
and Telefonica are taking
the approach they
are on these APIs.
They're trying to be very
generic and not trying to be
king makers, when it comes
to payment technologies.
It's the right way to do it.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
Let's take another question.
So Adam Sontag, if you're
in the room, put up--
I think he's over there.
CINDY: So this is an anonymous
question that, at the request
of Jake Archibald, I have
mildly reformatted into
rhyming verse.
So one question that still needs
distilling is, wha't the
feasibility of operator
billing.
And given that phone prefer
Wi-Fi to cell, will I have to
forget this network
to buy and sell?
RICARDO VILLERO: Very
impressive, by the way-- so my
skill is not enough to actually
answer you in verse,
I'm afraid.
But definitely, integrative
billing is something that is
widely used now.
We are also, for people who
are not familiar, in the
middle of a change
of technology.
So we went from premium SMS,
which is essentially charging
you for an SMS message--
very clunky, had lots of
messages, really high revenue
share for the operator because
it was a really old technology
used to sell ring tones
and things like that.
So not as good as
direct-operator billing, which
is essentially, you make a call
to an API, which is more,
hello, 21st century.
And basically, you send me an
amount and a phone number.
And the phone number acts as,
basically, the user account.
That is working now.
Actually, you can pay
with that in Google.
You can pay in RIM, in Nokia.
In BlueVia, we work with at
least 20-something different
providers, including Mozilla.
And basically, that
is what modern
operator billing is about.
The problem that I see with
modern operator billing is
that, modern operator billing
was thought to be something
that you negotiate
with an operator.
So you negotiate with O2.
Then you go and negotiate
with Vodafone.
with Telefonica.
And the problem there is that,
you have to close one account
for each of these things.
So one of the things that we
actually tried to stop with
BlueVia to give, to the
Telefonica group, just one
connection for all
those billings.
So do what Visa does in the
case of banks, where you
basically take Visa payments.
You don't take Lloyd's,
NatWest, Barclays, and
whatnot, don't know
what payments.
You take payments
from a network.
So I think that is the step
that we have missing.
But actually, you can do charges
to a phone number now
with modern technology.
NATASHA ROONEY: One of the
functions is, though, this
issue of being over Wi-Fi.
It's that an operator cannot
recognize you as a user, if
you're on a Wi-Fi network,
correct?
RICARDO VILLERO: You only need
to know what's the phone
number of the user.
And that can happen in a
one-time transaction, which
is, for example, how
google does it.
It's how Mozilla does it.
Basically, operators have
multiple ways of recognizing
what phone number you're in.
For a start, you're connected
to a base station.
So we if we are giving you
service, we know your number.
So if you're connected to a
normal network, you can
identify the user through
the network.
If they're connected in Wi-Fi,
then you do a fallback to SMS,
which normally mean either
you send an SMS to the
device with a code.
Or you make the device send
you an SMS, and then you
receive it.
In both cases, you establish
what is the
number of the user.
And then you can guess use
that again and again.
We have a specific API built
for this in BlueVia.
In other operators, you have
to do it more manually.
But you can that.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: And to be clear,
you can do it again and
again because it just stores
a cookie on-device.
I mean, the cookie lasts 30 days
or something like that.
And when you're on Wi-Fi,
it reads the cookies.
So you know you're
authenticated.
NATASHA ROONEY: Fantastic.
So enough can I be
Montgomery Burns,
please, this time, yeah?
Awesome.
It's getting better.
We only have five
minutes left.
So I kind of want
to close on a--
we have a room of technologists
here.
And I'd like to focus on a
little bit of the standards, a
little bit of what we can do.
So if we just go around and have
a little bit of a chat.
If you could all give one minute
on what we could do
you, as developers, to push to
the ideal payment solution--
and Kumar, I'm afraid I'm
going to start with you.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Sure.
As developers--
NATASHA ROONEY: Or
standardizers.
KUMAR MCMILLAN: Yeah,
that's a tricky one.
I do think, as I mentioned
before, I think to a really
have a sort of federated payment
system, where anyone
can pay with any currency and
any merchant can accept money
from anywhere, I think some API
needs to be agreed upon
and implemented by
banks or maybe a
clearinghouse in front of banks.
And I don't think the browser
vendors can do that.
So I have strayed from
the topic of what
developers can do.
I still don't know what
NATASHA ROONEY: Ricardo--
RICARDO VILLERO: Well, I think
that, for a start, we have add
more realistic expectations
in all of this.
I think, judging from the work
that we did in WAC, where you
tried to do mobile billing, in
this case, for 40-something
operators across the globe.
And this includes Asia and
Africa and Latin America.
There's no way you can sync
all of those things.
It's too big a problem.
However, you can start
in smaller areas.
So you take something like
the European Union.
The European Union is about to
standardize on a series of
measures, called SEPA.
You could do, in theory, some
hub for the European Union,
with a specific protocol that
works across all the providers
in the European Union.
Obviously, it won't work
in Latin America.
It won't work in China.
But it's something.
So we start trying to
standardize there.
And we try to push for a
standard API or a standard way
that different providers can
implement that there, which is
how it normally happens.
Banks didn't go and try to
standardize on this type of
thing worldwide.
They standardize in the European
Union, more or less.
And then, let's see
how it extends.
Or you do two networks.
And then we talk among protocol,
among our networks.
That would be fine.
The thing is, that you
need those initial
solutions to be there.
So requestAutocomplete or mozPay
are initial tries of
getting to that standard API.
Just use them, feedback to them
into saying, I'm lacking
this thing.
So requestAutocomplete doesn't
support [INAUDIBLE] billing.
MozPay, we're going to do
another iteration now, which
everything that we have just
feed back to that and start
with that smaller goal, before
we get to the bigger goal.
ROB GRIMSHAW: I'm actually very
excited about some of the
things that Ricardo
is talking about.
I believe, fundamentally, that
the solutions are going to be
mobile based, ultimately.
We're almost to the point where,
there are more mobile
devices than people
on the planet.
There are far more people with
mobiles that there are with
bank accounts, for example.
And if some of the things that
Ricardo is talking about, i.e.
the development of a sort of
global standard network for
payments, across major mobile
operators can develop.
Then I can see how a merchant
like us can take payments on
mobile devices, potentially from
a marketplace of billions
of people around the globe.
And that's very,
very exciting.
And if you think about
it, what you've
got there is a chain.
All these devices, in some way,
are linked up to a source
of value, whether that's a bank
account or whether that's
a prepay or whatever.
The chain of value is already
there, if you can create the
standard across the top of it,
maybe starting in the US or
whatever, which then a merchant
like us can then hook
into, that can deliver
the solution.
And I don't think you have to
think about Utopian scenarios,
in order to get there.
It's not difficult to see how
this step can be taken.
NATASHA ROONEY: Yes, so from
my point of view, I think
that's an important issue.
Lots of users think about what
would be great for the users.
And I think, the way you're
going to get the thing that
you want as a user is to
influence from a merchant
standpoint or from the bank
standpoint or from the
standardization standpoint.
And that's my takeaway.
It's that, OK, if you
want your user
goals, you go for it.
But you put a slant on it and
sell it up to those other
people, that makes them think
they're getting something when
you're actually getting
something.
And that's the way to
get where you want--
so lifestyle tips.
Manu, go for it.
MANU SPORNY: So anybody in
here that's interested in
payments, the thing that you
could do is join the Web
Payments Group, join
the discussion.
It's completely open.
Anyone can join and
participate.
Educate yourself about it and
help us actually figure out
what standards to build, what to
build it that you can use.
The only other point I wanted
to kind of make is, playing
off of Kumar's bank-based
thing.
I did spend the last week
at the World Banking
Conference in Dubai.
No bank is working on this.
I guarantee you.
I had a high-level, low-level,
all kinds of
discussions with them.
The standard bank system is
written in COBOL or Fortran.
It was implemented in
1987 through 1992.
They're still running
that code base.
They're absolutely mortified
of doing any kind of large
change to their system.
So this solution is not going
to come from the banks.
It could come from the
mobile operators.
people like Google
Wallet, Paypal, Stripe.
But at some point, all of us
are going to have to band
together in some kind of clump
and push something forward.
It's definitely not going
to be the banks
that do that though.
NATASHA ROONEY: So throw
yourself into the
standardization.
And finally, Cindy--
CINDY: Real quick, because
I know everyone
is ready to be done.
So just really use mozPay,
use requestAutocomplete.
Even though it is technology
from the '70s, it is what
everyone is still using.
And there's plenty of room to
improve that '70s technology
experience on the web, as we try
and lay a foundation and
segue into more different
technologies.
But definitely
requestAutocomplete, mozPay--
participate, we are trying
to make it better.
NATASHA ROONEY: Excellent.
So that's our stand.
Thank you so much to
the panelists.
[APPLAUSE]
ANDREW BETTS: So I
think we're done.
I just have a few wrap up things
to do, including giving
out some prizes.
So don't go anywhere, because
you don't get a prize unless
you are in the room A couple
of other things,
sorry about the noise.
Nothing we could do about it,
I think Google is building a
new tree house or something.
So a few thank yous--
I think the biggest thanks I
want to give is to Peter Page
who's behind me, frantically
doing some presentation work.
He tirelessly did all the
logistics for Edge, including
all of the venue stuff that's
been going on today.
And Wes, who's over here, who
wrote, OnSlyde, basically from
scratch for this event.
And I think we can all agree
that even though it might be
slightly gameable, it
works pretty well.
And yes, so I'm going to just
switch to my slides, if these
are working.
Yes.
So the first thing and
most important thing
is to give out prizes.
We also, of course, are
supporting Girls Who Code.
So we'll just cover that off.
Then we have dinner.
And then we have party.
So all of these agenda items
are fairly important.
So first of all, I said,
we were doing
some prizes for feedback.
I cocked this up terribly.
I didn't tick the box that said
I wanted to know who had
left the feedback.
So I have no idea who
any of them are.
I've now ticked the box, so
please do leave feedback.
AUDIENCE: If I'm not
going to get a
Chromebook, then for feedback.
ANDREW BETTS: You're not going
to get a Chromebook, sorry.
But I still want to
know the feedback.
So we're going to do random
draw instead.
So I loaded up Eventbrite, did
some query selector all, with
some random node selection
on our attendee list.
And we came up with some
random drawings.
And I also chatted with some
of the other moderators.
And we picked out a couple
of people for their great
interventions today and also for
covering the event really
well on social media.
So without further ado, Pete,
do we have the Chromebooks?
Pete is running to get
the Chromebooks.
The most inspired interventions
of the day, I
think we all thought
came from Kyle.
So is he here?
Congratulations.
Come and get a Chromebook.
So maybe, Pete, you can give
out the Chromebooks.
The second Chromebook goes to
the person who thought covered
the event best on
social media.
And that's not just kind of
bigging us up but also just
making really insightful
comments--
it'll work, honestly--
insightful comments about the
day and really kind of drawing
on what the panelists have been
saying and producing some
nice original content.
And for that, we thought
Ashley Williams did a
brilliant job.
Is she here?
[APPLAUSE]
Congratulations.
So that leaves us just to
dig into our digital
hat of raffle tickets.
Unfortunately, due to another
slight crisis, we didn't give
raffle tickets to everyone.
So we've randomly chosen
people from Eventbrite.
And those people are
Kyle Kennerman.
Are you here?
No.
AUDIENCE: Ooh.
Poor Kyle.
ANDREW BETTS: Kyle does
not get a Chromebook.
Schabse Laks, are you here?
No, we've lost another one.
OK.
Aurelia Moser, are you here?
Aurelia, hurray.
So I had one back that was the
round random on the list.
And I didn't get two.
So we'll this one.
And we'll do another
one after.
So Ben Holland, are you here?
Ben, congratulations.
So we'll do another one.
We'll do it over dinner
or something.
So next, the financials,
we did this for Edge 1.
And was quite well received that
we told everyone exactly
how much money we made, where
we got it from, and
how we spent it.
So this is where we made our
money, how we spent our money.
And that's left us with $8,216,
which we're donating
to Girls Who Code.
So I'm really delighted to to
say that, Kristen Titus from
Girls Who Code is
actually here.
And she's going to say a
few words to everyone.
Let's get you a mic.
KRISTEN TITUS: It's OK.
Hi, guys.
Can you hear me?
No, you can't.
Hi, I'm Kristen.
I'm the executive director
of Girls Who Code.
And that number makes
me very happy.
And it'll make everyone happy.
Michelle, Danielle--
does everyone know there are two
Girls Who code, who missed
school today to be here all day
and have done nothing but
dream about this for weeks?
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks to you guys, this number
right here will make
sure that we have half of this
room as women, in five years,
in four year, hopefully,
in three years if
we're really lucky.
So thank you immensely.
It means the world to us.
And if any of you are interested
in getting involved
in Girls Who Code, we're working
to close the gender
gap in the tech space.
We need everyone here
a part of that.
This is going to make
a big difference.
Thank you, immensely.
ANDREW BETTS: Thank you.
So that is pretty much it.
We have dinner.
Dinner is upstairs.
And this is going to be slightly
complicated because
we all have to be escorted
up to the canteen.
So I'm told that Googlers are
assembling near the doors.
So go and grab a Google,
not physically.
And they will take
you to dinner.
Before you guy, just to be
aware, after dinner, we're
going to see the party
hosted by Facebook.
Facebook wants to escort
us there as well.
So Facebookers will be
arriving to do that.
[LAUGHING]
And this is how we're
going to get there.
So if you want to know roughly
where you're going.
That's where the party is.
There will be Facebook
people to take
you there after dinner.
So I'll see you upstairs.
[MUSIC PLAYING]