>>Ankit Jain: Good morning, everyone. It's
so great to see so many of you early here
on day three of Google I/O.
Last night, I wasn't sure if I was going to
make it this early.
My name is Ankit Jain, and I lead all things
search and discovery for Google Play. I'm
extremely excited to be here and share this
material with you today.
As most of you know, we've never discussed
our search or discovery engine publicly before
today. But before I get started, I wanted
to get to know you guys a little better.
With a raise of hands, how many of you are
making money on Google Play today?
Great. How many of you would like to make
even more money on Google Play?
Great. For those on YouTube, pretty much everyone
would like to make even more money.
Let's step out of our normally roles as developers
or business owners and for a second, let's
step into the shoes of our users, and think
like a user when you come to the store.
How many of you have installed an app just
while browsing, you were bored, you opened
the Play Store, saw something interesting,
clicked through, and installed it?
Okay. How many of you have installed an app
because you thought about, I need to get something
done. I need a recipe app, or I need to find
a train schedule, went looked for it, and
then installed it.
Okay. That's a smaller -- smaller portion.
And how many of you have installed an app
because a friend of yours told you, "Hey,
you really have to go check out this app."
And then you go to the store, look for it,
and install it.
Great.
So my goal today is to talk to you about how
we try to bring these online and offline thought
processes of how all of us install apps and
how we try to get that discovered on Play.
So I'm going to present you with three high-level
sets of information. The first one is our
vision for the new Google Play Store.
The second is some of the details of the search
and discovery algorithms that we have and
how you can take advantage of them to get
discovered more.
And, finally, I want to leave you with five
very concrete examples of what you can do
to get discovered more on Play.
Sounds good?
All right. Great. So let's get right into
it.
A few weeks ago, we rolled out the new version
of the Google Play Store. It's very different
from what we had in the past, a year ago,
a few of us stepped aside and said if we could
reimagine the entire store, the new Google
Play experience, what would it be like?
The goal was to come up with something that
was dynamic, very fresh. The user should be
trained and look forward to coming back into
the store, something that is personalized,
yet personal.
So some of you might be thinking, Ankit, what
are you saying? Personalized, yet personal.
What's the difference there?
Well, personalized, to me, is something that
is personally relevant, related to what you
have told us in the past, what users have
purchased, what -- personally relevant because
it's popular in the user's area. Personally
relevant because the user has shown interest
in certain categories or in certain developers.
Or personally relevant because your friends
are showing interest in those things.
Then we want to take you to the next level.
We want to make it personal by showing you
and annotating each of these recommendations
or each of the pieces of content in our store
with why you should get it.
This could be a +1 by a friend. This could
be a review by a friend. Or this could be
something based on the new Google Play Game
Services that three others are currently playing
Puzzles & Dragons. We should tell the user,
this is why you should get it. And our goal
was to help each and every one of you, each
and every one of our developers, to get people
more engaged installs. Because at the end
of the day, that's what's really going to
move the needle. Those are the users that
build sustainable and great businesses.
So our goal was threefold: First, to help
our users find what they're looking for as
effortlessly and seamlessly as possible. Second,
to help Android ship more, and more beautiful,
apps. And, finally, to help all of you build
even more thriving businesses on top of our
platform.
So let's get to the meat of today's talk.
Let's talk about our major install source.
At the ends of the day, nothing can be built
unless you have installs. Specifically, I
want to talk about how to get engaged installs.
So most of you have reached -- many of you
reached out to me in the past and said, "Hey,
I'm ranked number five or number ten or number
50 on these top lists or on these trending
lists." These are what I call our browse and
discovery features. I like to break them into
three subcomponents.
The first are these top charts, the top lists,
the editors' picks, the trending lists. The
next are the features that we launched at
Google I/O last year. These were the personalized
recommendations. Some of you saw these as
part of the Google Play home page experience
in the cluster there. Others might have seen
this on the widgets on the Nexus 7 and the
Nexus 10 on the home screens there.
And the last set of features that we have
for discovery, based on your context, are
the related and cross-sell items. These are
the users who viewed X also viewed Y on the
details page of all of your apps. Also, the
other set, which is users who installed this
app also installed these other apps, which
is also on your details pages. And we'll get
into details of each of these and how we look
at them and how the algorithms are built.
What most developers don't think about as
much is the search component. For the average
app, search actually makes up the vast majority
of installs. And when I think about search,
I like to break it down and look at our query
stream from -- in terms of two kinds of queries.
The first are the kinds of queries that many
of you raised your hand for, which are, I
had to get something done, so I looked it
up. I needed to look up a recipe. I wanted
to find a restaurant review in a city that
I'm in. I wanted to find multiplayer games
or free games, or RPG games, the kind of categorical
queries. You know the general idea of what
you want or what you want to do, and then
you use search to find the right app for -- to
fulfill that.
The second kind of query is where you know
exactly what you're looking for. This is when
a presented has told you about an app or if
you heard about it through marketing, navigational
queries.
Hey, I want to get a hotel tonight. I want
to get Beautylish, or I want to get Angry
Birds, which is not necessarily a single app,
it could be a set of apps, but you know what
direction you want to look in. That's navigational
queries.
Just to show you how important search is,
in any given day, 12% of our active users
come back to the store and search at least
once for apps. In any given week, half of
our users come to our store and search for
apps.
And even -- given the number of apps we have,
in any given month, there's over 6 million
unique phrases that are being searched for.
So really thinking about search is important
as you try to figure out how to get discovered
on Play.
So just to put what we've talked about, I've
talked about our vision for Google Play and
how our goal is to present each user with
a personalized play, made personal. How search
and browse are the two main sources of installs
in the store. And, finally, a lot of this
happens because our goal is to bring the rest
of Google to Play. That was the transition
from Android Market into Google Play. It was
to integrate all of our systems together and
make Google Play a very smart store, make
it your store.
So now that we've talked about it, let's step
back and think about how we think of our search
and discovery systems.
When we built our search engines and our discovery
engines, we have two options. Either we can
spend a lot of time trying to detect the apps
that are bad or spammy or simply annoying,
or we can spend a lot of time trying to figure
out which apps are good.
And we spend a lot more time focusing on what's
good, because if we can promote the apps that
are not just good from what we can tell, based
on your APK, based on your metadata, based
on what users are telling us about each of
the apps, then other -- other users are also
going to find these delightful experiences.
And so this part of the talk is going to be
talking about how you can complement your
app with good app metadata.
So the most important piece of your app metadata
is your title. It's important to be creative,
but it's just as important, if not more important,
to be very clear.
So this -- so this example up on screen is
about an app named Beautylish.
As you can see, most of you might not have
heard of it, some of you might have heard
of it, but right after you see the title,
you know this is about makeup and beauty tips.
So what this title helps you do is helps the
developer reinforce not just their branding,
but also what their app is about.
As you see this more and more often, either
in the store or even once you have it installed
in your list of apps on your home screen,
it's very clear that Beautylish is the app
I go to for makeup and beauty tips. So I highly
recommend thinking about the name of your
app. It also helps a lot for SEO. When someone
looks up beauty tips or makeup tips, these
guys are the top of that list just because
everyone associates the two of those terms
together.
The next important part of your details page
in your metadata is your description. You
can write as long a description as you want,
but I always say get the main message out
first.
Star Chart does a great job here. Their first
sentence says, "You can now have a virtual
planetarium in your pocket." Again, if you've
never used this app, you already know what
it's about. After that, you can go on, describe
it in more detail, list the awards you have,
and just have your sales and marketing pitches
for your users. But right up-front, make sure
your user knows what your app is about.
And on a smaller phone, that's the part that's
above the fold. So you want to make sure on
that first screen itself it's extremely clear
what your goal is, what utility you provide
or what entertainment value or whatever the
goal of your app is, what it provides.
Now, that also, again, helps a lot with getting
found. This app is extremely optimized for
star charts, star maps, virtual planetariums.
So the beginning of descriptions are extremely
important, both from a user's perspective
and also from our search engine's perspective.
The next couple of slides, I'm going to talk
about how you can use your app details page
to mimic the real user experience. It's important
that you set the expectations of your user
to be very realistic, to really be what your
app is going to be like.
The first place to do this is in your screen
shots. In our developer console, we let you
upload screen shots for tablets, for phones,
and really show the user what it's going to
be like once you install the app.
Now, if you don't do this, and your app experience
is actually very different from your screen
shots, it can have a very negative effect
on all of your systems. Why? Because, well,
the user loves what they see in your details
page. They install your app. They open the
app. And then they see something very different.
What are they going to do? Well, most users
will uninstall the app. Some of those users
will go back to the store and give you a low
rating, maybe even write you a negative review.
And that negative feedback cycle is going
to hurt you more than help you.
And so really thinking about how do you present
the user with the right -- setting the right
expectation and then delivering on it, that's
the message here. We're looking for apps that
do deliver on their promises.
Video previews are the next level of screen
shots. With a short video, you're able to
show the user really what it's like to play
with your app. And developers have told us
that uploading a video can really help gain
user adoption. And users in a lot of studies
have told us that video previews are amongst
the most convincing features of an app details
page.
Again, the whole goal here is to tell your
user what your app does. If you can convince
them and make sure that -- and communicate
what your app's promise is and then deliver
on it, you're going to delight them, and they're
going to recommend to you other users as well.
So I talked about reviews and ratings in terms
of the feedback loop. And this is a key part
of our search and discovery experience.
Now, the first piece of this comes because
people come back and review your app, whether
it's good or bad. The second piece is, we
really try to order our reviews and ratings
in an order that is relevant to the user.
So you are going to see reviews that are on
the same device as the current user, in the
same country as the current user, and as time
goes on, people that are in a user's circle
or people that the users trust are going to
come at the top of these reviews.
So investing in making sure that your users
are reviewing and rating your apps will be
key going forward, because that's a very strong
signal for us at Google Play.
So I'm going to step back and tell you a story
about a developer, a developer in India that
I was talking to a few weeks ago. And his
goal was to target the rural population. As
you can see on the graph on the right, about
75% of India's population lives in rural cities.
His goal was to target the audience that had
low- to mid-end phones and was on slow to
2G networks. He had really optimized his app
to give a delightful experience for these
users.
But then he reached out to me and said, Ankit,
when I look at my reviews, I have this polarized
view, there's a whole bunch of five stars
with people saying I could never imagine technology
would change my world this way. And also a
lot of one stars with people saying, "Complete
crap. I can't believe I downloaded this. Uninstalling
it right now."
Right? And he was perplexed. He wasn't sure
what was going on. We dug a little deeper.
One of the things we noticed was that he was
getting a lot of positive reaction from the
people in rural areas, his target audience.
And he was getting a lot of negative reviews
from the people on the 4G networks, on the
top-of-the-line devices, because his app just
was not designed for them. His goal was not
to go after that market. And so the thing
that he ended up doing was, he went to the
developer console and targeted his app to
the countries and carriers where his target
audience really was. And since then, he's
already seen an uptick in his average rating
and his reviews. And, hopefully, that continues
over time. But my message here to you is think
about who you're trying to target. For most
apps, you don't have to worry about this.
You can let your app get to everybody. But
if your app is targeted at a specific set
of target audience, make sure those are the
people helping you get even more adoption.
You don't want people not in your target audience
polluting your reviewer rating.
So we've talked about creating a very creative,
yet clear, message through your title and
description. To mimic your real world experience
through your images, your screen shots, and
your video previews. And, finally, really
about understanding your audience. This is
what's going to help you optimize your -- your
app details page.
So let's see how this manifests itself. At
the end of the day, there's the top charts
and the search engines. What are the things
we look for? Once you do all of these great
things in your app details page, how does
it feed back?
And no search or discovery system would be
complete without really taking into account
the statistics that we're constantly collecting.
So the first piece of this, as most of you
probably have already figured out, are the
installs. Of course we care about how many
installs each app has. The more you have,
the higher up in the rankings you'll go.
We also care about how many uninstalls you
have, because that's the metric for us to
know whether users are having a good or a
bad experience.
Now, some of you are game developers out there,
and you might say, hey, my game overall takes
one gig of memory or two gigs of memory on
a person's device. So after they're done playing
my game, of course they're going to uninstall
my app, because they want to play the next
game. You know, they've already won every
level there is. Why are you going to hurt
me? And that's why we have the third static,
which is long installs.
If a person plays through or uses an app for
a long period of time, we don't want to penalize
it. Our goal is really to detect the behavior
which is, hey, I installed an app, I really
did not have a good experience, so I'm uninstalling
it right away.
So the long install encapsulated that phenomenon
in it.
In the coming months, one of the things that
we want to focus on is engagement, and really
understanding for each of your apps when are
people using it, how are they using it, and
how is it different across different kinds
of apps. For example, Google Now, I just go
to it when I need to pick up my latest boarding
pass. I'm not going to spend tens of minutes
or hours on it. But there might be a game
where I spend an hour or two on it. But that
doesn't mean one is better than the other.
They're just different kinds of functions
they're providing.
This is an area where having a conversation
with all of you is great. And I really look
forward to having some of your feedback. So
a lot of this is about setting the stage for
the first conversation. We've never discussed
any of this before. So if you guys have ideas,
please let us know.
I'll talk about Google Play services -- the
game services that we launched and how we're
going to use that for engagement in the coming
months as well.
Here's a query that I get very often from
developers. "Hey, for some search query, I'm
number three even though the app ranked above
mine has fewer installs and has a lower rating
than me."
Right? I'm sure many of you have thought about
this as well.
On the previous slide, I talked about the
uninstall rate. Not only do we look at the
number of people that are uninstalling your
app compared to the number of people installing
it. We also have some amount of a recent -- recent
uninstall rate as well.
The idea here is that you might have an app
that has not been updated in a couple of years,
and now more people are uninstalling your
app than installing it. Or there's a newer
app, or your app could be on the other sides
of this where you made an update and now a
lot of people are really keeping your app.
That's going to help you move up in the rankings.
We want to make sure users are getting the
best apps as easily as possible.
So I hope this answers this very common question
that I get.
>>> (off mike) it's a shooting star phenomenon.
>>Ankit Jain: So the other piece of what we've
talked about a lot at Google I/O this year
is personalization across all of our products
at Google. And Google Play is no exception
to this. We're constantly slicing and dicing
all of the data that we're collecting in order
to personalize and improve each user's experience.
One -- I'll give you a couple of examples.
The query Yahoo! in the U.S. leads to people
installing the Yahoo! app or the Yahoo! Mail
app.
In Japan, however, people are installing the
Yahoo! Japan app. And over time, our systems
learned this and figured out, hey, in Japan,
show Yahoo! Japan as number one. In the U.S.,
show Yahoo! and Yahoo! Mail as number one
and number two.
Similarly, on tablets, people tends to install
different apps than they do on mobile devices.
Again, using the feedback loops of what people
are searching for, what they're clicking on,
and what they're enjoying and installing,
we're able to really tailor the search experience
and the search results per device type, per
locale, and across a whole bunch of different
dimensions.
About a year ago, in addition to having the
search suggestions as you type, we added the
ability to have navigational search suggestions.
These are suggestions that Google believes
are the right one for a user. So as the user
is typing in "sub," most users tend to actually
go straight to Subway Surfers. So we allow
them to do that right from the search suggest
box. If you click on that navigational suggestion,
you won't go to a search results page. You'll
go straight to the app's details page. It
even shows you the icon of the app that it's
going to take you straight to.
Now, if a user wants to find the tips or the
strategies or other apps that are around Subway
Surfers, they can still complete their query
and look at the app details page. Again, the
theme here is that we're trying to make it
easier for users to get what they want.
Let's switch gears a little bit, and I'll
let you guys look at this for a couple of
seconds. There's a lot of data up there.
So a lot of you always have asked us the question
how are your top lists generated? When are
they generated and what's the rationale behind
them?
Like any search or discovery system we're
constantly tuning our systems. And this is
a snapshot of what it looks like recently.
There's a basic quality barrier that's there.
There are some review and rating metrics that
we take into account, but at a high level
we create top lists daily per country, per
category and even per device type.
You guys saw some of the design for tablet
top lists that were launched earlier at I/O,
and our top paid free and grossing lists are
really targeting first-time users to Google
Play or people who just got a new device because
they're looking for the basic apps they need
to load up in order to get their stuff done.
What's most popular on Google Play?
The top new paid and top new lists are targeting
users who have the basic apps and saying,
Hey, what's new right now, what's new and
popular?
And for that reason we limit it to the apps
that have been published in the last 30 days.
And this is very important because many app
developers launch an app in a single country
and then over time roll it out to a bunch
of countries.
So I get a question a lot of times saying,
Hey, I just launched in Italy last week and
it's going gangbusters. We're just getting
more installs than we ever have. How come
we're not in the top new free or top paid
list?
Well, the reason is your original launch might
have been six months ago so you're not qualified
to be in the top new list of even new countries
that you launch in. It's a global publish
date that we look at.
So think about your global rollout strategy,
if being in the top new list is part of your
strategy, a 30-day window extremely important.
And the metrics across these are different.
For the grossing we look at the revenues.
For the others we look at installs over the
last several days.
The next list that I want to talk about is
our trending list, and this is one that has
had no clarity about it ever.
Internally we like to call this our movers
and shakers list. Our goal here is to present
the user with a system that can give them
what's really hot right now. Amongst all the
apps on Google Play, what are the apps that
a lot of users, more than we predict, are
being installed?
We have a predicted growth rate. This predicted
growth rate takes into consideration where
in your app life cycle you are and how many
installs you have.
And if a given app performs significantly
better, if it starts getting installs much
faster than what we predict, it makes it into
this movers and shakers or trending list.
So when the soccer World Cup was going on
a few years ago, the FIFA app was at the top
of this list.
Last year when the unfortunate tsunami hit
Japan, many radiation tracking apps were at
the top of this list.
Any app can be can be part of this list and
we're looking at a 30-day window to figure
out really what's hot right now.
I mentioned the related and cross-sell features
that we have. On every app's details page
there are the people who viewed this also
viewed these other apps and the users who
installed this app also installed these other
apps.
So let's go through a few examples. The first
one is Bank of America. The user looking to
do banking, when they're considering a banking
app they might consider other banking apps,
PayPal or Wells Fargo, but once they've decided
to get the Bank of America app they're more
likely to install a complementary app, not
a supplementary app. Here you see them installing
a trading app such as Merrill Edge or another
app by the same developer, the BOFA help app.
In the middle is an example of a user looking
to get a Bible. Users looking to get a Bible
might consider the various options, but once
they get the Bible they will get other religious
apps, not other Bible apps, so it's complementary
to what they've gotten.
The third is example is a widget that helps
users show the time on their home screen.
They might consider digit clock or dash clock,
but once they installed the dash clock, they
bought into that style, that ecosystem, so
then they're more likely to install other
widgets or other add-ons that have the same
style, have the unified experience on their
Android device.
Last year at Google I/O we launched personalized
recommendations. As I said, these were on
the home screen of the Google Play home page
and they've been performing extremely well.
With the new launch of Google Play we really
decided to double-down on this and start personalizing
many different parts of our system.
So I thought it's a good opportunity for me
to tell you what really we look for. We have
over 80 signals not just from Google Play,
but also from the rest of Google, but some
of our major signals include apps that are
complementary and supplementary to apps that
users installed in the past. We look at apps
that are popular in a user's area. We look
at apps that have been +1'd by a user's Circles,
reviewed by a user's Circles. We also look
at apps that are developed by some of you,
if the user has already shown interest in
your developer account and by other apps by
you.
So here are some recommendations for three
different users. You can see +1's by people's
friends. You can see apps that are similar
other things they have bought and also apps
that are popular in their area.
So how does this manifest itself? So this
is the home page that we envisioned. This
is going to start rolling out to users in
the coming months.
On the left is my grandma's home page. That's
what she sees. She grew up very close to military
quarters in India because my grandpa lived
in that area.
And she was very interested in getting stuff
done. We call her the colonel of the family.
So for her growing up in a military area means
you play a lot of cards. She actually plays
two to four hours of card games a day. It's
ridiculous. I don't know how she does it.
So seeing the tablet highlight apps for her
and seeing the card games right up there is
really what's relevant to her.
For me, I travel a lot and so on the tablet
highlight section not only do you see Google
Translate, which I should get so that I can
communicate with people all around the world,
but it also tells me why. It tells me that
my friend (Indiscernible) has +1'd this app.
He had a great experience so that helps me
improve trust in the system and get this app.
You can take this a step further. On all of
our category home pages -- both of these are
for me. On the left, I live in San Francisco,
so you see the San Francisco Giants app, you
see the Oakland baseball app, you see a Sacramento
Kings app.
On the right is the news home page. You see
news apps and magazine apps that are related
to what I've bought in the past. I have Pulse
and people who have Pulse tend to also enjoy
the "New York Times."
It's amazing to me the "Times of India" comes
on my personalized home page, but it wouldn't
on some of yours just because my friends tend
to come from that part of the world and they
say this is a great app, to adopt it.
How can we apply personalization to search?
I've talked about using location. So a user
in Japan will see different results for Yahoo!
than a user in the U.S. But we think categorical
queries are a place that we can really help
the user find what they're looking for.
Imagine a user searches for free games. If
we know that they like word games, showing
them free word games makes a lot of sense.
If they like RPG games, that will help them
get a much faster acquisition rate.
For train schedules, a user in New York should
get the subway train schedule, a user in San
Francisco should get the BART train schedule
or the Cal train schedule. It just makes sense.
So over the coming months we're going to roll
out more experiments, and finally to everybody,
personalization across categorical searches.
So I've thrown a lot of things at you so far.
So just to step back and summarize, we've
talked about the search statistics, the feedback
loops that we've looked at in order to improve
or search and discovery systems. We talked
about navigational search suggestions. We
talked about how our top charts are created
across each category, generated daily and
across every country. We talked about what
trending apps are, what it means to be in
there and how you can get in there. We talked
about how related and cross-sell works. And
we also talked about how we're starting to
personalize play and how that's going to roll
out over the coming months and how that really
fulfills our vision of a personalized play
made personal.
So I promised you guys I would leave you with
five things that you can do to improve your
discoverability on play. So let's get right
into it, but before we do that I want to tell
you it's just as important to build a good
app. So take the time to go through those
app developer guidelines on developer.android.com
and make sure you have a good app. You can
complement that by optimizing on the store,
but at the end of the day nothing substitutes
a very good experience for your app.
Two months ago we added a list of guidelines,
the tablet app guidelines, what it means to
be designed for tablets. And I highly recommend
that you get the design for tablet designation.
Earlier at I/O we announced design for tablets
top lists on some of our home pages. Over
time this is going to roll across the store
so a tablet user gets the best experience
possible by showing the apps and promoting
the apps that have gone through the trouble
of making that experience better.
So you're going to see this not just in the
top list, but over time in search and in all
of our other discovery features as well.
The developer console helps you with the optimization
tips that they have added and the next talk
by Ellie, Miles and Riccardo will go through
this in detail, what you can do to really
get some of these designations. So get the
design for tablet designation.
Number two -- and this is a much less known
fact about the way we do search ranking at
Google Play.
Today most articles that are published on
the Web about play apps have a link at the
end that says Google Play Store or play link.
Actually, over 99% of anchors that we get
into the Google Play Store just have those
two phrases and that doesn't help us at all.
We want to help you get discovered even more
on play.
Sure, you tell us a little bit about your
app, but if a trusted source -- on the right,
for example, Tech Crunch, is telling us what
your app is about. Even before you have any
installs, we can trust it and start boosting
you for those terms.
So next time you're talking to a blog writer
or someone writing an article about your app,
have them give you some link juice. Have them
put something interesting in those links linking
to your app.
The third one is to avoid common mistakes.
I told you there were six million and more
unique phrases that are searched for every
month. What I didn't tell you is over half
of them are misspelled. That's amazing that
half the people are mistyping queries, but
that's how the query stream is on mobile today.
So as Google, what we have to do is we have
to aggressively correct for it. We have to
make sure we help the user find what they're
looking for even if it's a typo.
So the one thing you can learn from this is
don't name your app something that is a cute
but a common misspelling of a very popular
app because chances are you will get -- a
user looking for your app will get auto corrected
into something that you're not happy with.
A second thing I already talked about using
the targeting expressions on the developer
console carefully, which countries and carriers
you're targeting depending on your target
audience.
And the third one again is one that we have
-- that is a little subtle, but I think it's
important. If you do have a developer URL
that is not a play.google.com link or a code.google.com
link, something that is your home on the Web,
if it exists do make sure you upload that
in the developer console.
Why? Well, we crawl the Web, we index the
Web for our Web search engine and we use a
lot of those signals in order to help you.
If we know that you're the kind of developer
that is about a specific subset of the world,
we will help you get discovered when people
are looking for those terms on Google Play.
So again, if you have a developer URL other
than something at Google.com, do upload that.
Number four is to make your APK smaller, right?
Users tend to install smaller apps a lot more
than they do larger apps and they tend to
uninstall larger apps at a higher rate as
well.
Let's think about why. As your phone runs
out of memory, there is a finite amount of
memory, users tend to go through the list
of apps they have in decreasing order of size
and start uninstalling the apps that they're
using least actively.
So the further down that list you are, the
less likely you are to be uninstalled. So
make your APK size smaller.
In the coming months we'll start looking deeper
into the APK from a search and discovery perspective
as well. We're going to look at the kind of
SDK's you're linking with, the libraries you're
linking with, to figure out what is your app
really about, looking at the kind of sites
that your app is connecting with by emulating
it and try to figure out what is your app
about so we can help users find apps that
will help them do what they're looking to
do.
And the last one, and this is something many
of you have asked us for, is to create a second
channel of distribution, the viral channel.
There hasn't been too much of a viral channel,
and I'm going to go to go through a through
things that we'll be pushing over the coming
months.
The first are highly rated apps. These are
apps that your friends, your circles and others
that you trust have rated highly in our store.
So here are some apps that are rated highly
for me. On the right you see the Quora app
is rated highly by my roommate David, he rated
it five stars. Then Logo Quiz, my friend Rivika
said it's an extremely fun game, so addicting
she couldn't stop.
That's the personal touch that we can add
to the Google Play Store. Some of these apps
have never been on the home page. This is
the easiest way for each of you to get on
Google Play's home page, have your users review
your apps. Their friends will start seeing
them on their Google Play home page.
I've talked a lot about +1's already. +1's
have been an integral part of our system since
we first launched personalized recommendations
last year.
The reason I bring it up again is because
there's an API which I'm not sure why many
of you are not using. This API is available
on the Google+ recommendations API page and
it enables you to allow your users to +1 an
app from within your app so you don't have
to have a message that says "Go to Google
Play and +1 my app."
You don't need to have your users leave your
experience. Keep them in your app. We want
to make it easier.
So we already have in-app billing for you
guys. There's in-app +1. And in the coming
months we're going to also have in-app rate
and review.
So again, we don't want your users to leave
your app. If we can do what they need to do
from within your app, great and we're going
to help you with that as well.
The last thing to create the viral loop is
to integrate with Google Play Game Services.
At first what you will get is when someone
opens your app they can see which of their
friends are playing, they can find opponents.
It makes your app more interactive. You have
the multiplayer, you have the leaderboards.
It makes your app social.
In the longer term, though this along with
the Google+ moments API, which allows you
to share specific pieces of information, "I'm
currently playing this game" or "I am at level
27 of this game," will allow us in the store
to annotate and make things more personal.
How great would it be if my home page said,
"Right now Shelavi is looking for an opponent
on Riptide."
That's not only the best way to get someone
to install your app, but open it right away,
get you those engaged users that you're looking
for.
So I highly recommend integrating with the
Google Play game services.
Again, the five things that you should do
to get discovered more on play, get the design
for tablets designation, start getting helpful
Web anchors, avoid some of the common mistakes
about misspelling because we have to auto
correct for them, and targeting your audience
correctly, reduce the size of your APK and
then really start closing that viral loop.
Help your users promote you in addition to
depending on just the store.
So we've talked a lot about user acquisition.
I've talked about the organic growth that
you can get from the search and discovery
aspects of the Google Play Store. We've talked
about the viral aspect of search and discovery.
And many of you already know about the paid
aspect, which is important to some of your
businesses as well.
I won't talk too much about it, but what I
will say is that investing in paid user acquisition
can have a very positive impact on organic
and viral growth as well. And so if you can,
it is something to think about in the bigger
picture of things.
Now, user acquisition is just the first step
in creating lifetime value for your users.
As a business owner I always like to think
about my key metrics and have a very good
handle on them. And the one that I've found
in the mobile space and any user-centered
space is the lifetime value of every one of
my users.
We talked about user acquisition. Let me briefly
mention the other two.
User retention I like to break into two different
ratios. The first is a short-term user retention
ratio. This is how do I initially keep my
users?
Most of the time this happens because the
users like what you're promising them. They
install your app, they open it.
The long-term user retention ratio, which
is very much like the long install metric
that I talked about, is the ongoing mechanics
of your app or what are you -- you delivering
on your promise?
So an example of Scramble With Friends, initially
they got a lot of their users because it was
very much like the word games that we grew
up with, but over time their social, their
interactive features are what kept it growing
and made it successful.
User monetization, I look at it in terms of
two different lenses. The big picture is the
revenue per install, and that makes sense.
It's a very good macro metric and it's comparable
to your user acquisition cost, your cost per
install is low so you can do that. But the
real picture is the revenue per active user.
That's what you have most control over, the
people that are in your system, in your game,
in your app, and how can you tune it to make
the most money?
So as you think about your users try to break
it down into key metrics and have a very good
handle on them.
So I hope this talk has helped you get a good
idea of how we build some of our search and
discovery systems. My goal was to really start
this conversation. I want to continue it.
And none of this would have been possible
without my team at Google Play. So this is
my shout-out to them. Thank you for doing
all the great stuff that you've done.
And for all of you, thank you for being here
so early. I would like to continue this conversation.
I'll be at office hours right after this,
so if you have any questions please come there.
Or you can reach out to me on Google+ or Twitter
and I'm happy to continue this. Thank you
very much.
[ Applause ]