>>Ilya Grigorik: Hi, everyone. My name is
Ilya Grigork. I'm a developer advocate on
the Make the Web Fast Team at Google. Today
I want to talk to you about mobile performance
from radio up, which is to say taking a lower
level look at how the radio works and what
we can learn about it to make our apps -- mobile
apps and Web pages with more performance.
These are some tricks and tips I have learned
from working with different Google properties,
helping them optimize their applications,
and some general best practices.
So, first, I think we should start with the
obvious which is -- or maybe it is not so
obvious to many of us -- which is wireless
is fundamentally different than wired. There
are different constraints. The technology,
the underlying technology, is, in fact, very
different.
And, fortunately, or unfortunately, I'm not
quite sure yet, our platform actually abstracts
that, right?
TCP and our browsers make it seem like it
is all the same, whether you are accessing
over a wireless network, whether it is WiFi
or mobile network or wired network. It feels
like all the same.
But once you actually dig a little bit deeper,
you will realize that there are different
design constraints within -- even within the
different wireless standards. And that actually
dictates how you need to design your applications
to make them feel performant.
So, first of all, why do we care? It turns
out that performance is a top criteria for
all applications, mobile especially. And there's
a number of great studies that have been done
about performance on mobile.
And the first take-away is that users expect
mobile sites to perform just as well, if not
better, on mobile than they do on desktop.
We don't kind of have more relaxed expectations
on mobile. If anything, it should be faster.
You're on the go. You are trying to check
something quickly. You don't have much time.
You want it to perform well.
Now, out of all of these users that have asked
these questions, more than half actually reported
feeling frustrated about having a problem
when accessing a site or an app over a mobile
network. And most of those, the number one
complaint has been the slow load time for
their applications.
So -- and after that, almost half of them
said, If I had a problem, I couldn't get the
page to load fast enough. It didn't react
fast enough. They wouldn't come back. So you
have lost that user and they're not returning
to your site, which is the worst possible
outcome.
And, of course, this also translates to dollars
and cents and even millions of dollars. So
this is another great case study that I would
like to share. This was done by Aberdeen Group.
They looked at a whole number, 100-plus e-commerce
sites and they realized that adding one second
of delay to their pages and to their applications
dropped their conversions significantly. So
this is your actual purchases. People viewed
fewer pages. And, of course, customer satisfaction
decreased as well. So this is just a thousand
milliseconds of latency added to your application.
So it is not just dollars and cents. For many
sites, large sites, it's literally millions
of dollars.
So our agenda today is to actually look at
radio performance 101. It is kind of a propeller-hat
talk a little bit. And, specifically, we'll
compare WiFi and mobile. And you will see
why, because it is important to understand
that even something like WiFi and mobile networks
are fundamentally different in how we schedule
how the communication is done and how we design
our applications or what we can even do to
optimize our applications.
And we'll also look at some practical tips
for what you can do in your applications to
design for this. And then I'll leave the last
part for you, which is to optimize the profit
part.
So there are tons and tons of techniques for
how to make your applications more performant.
There is application optimizations. There
is PageSpeed-specific optimizations or Speed
1-specific optimizations. We are not going
to touch on those. We are going to mention
them at the very end. We will are actually
going to go a little bit deeper.
We are going to go below the application layer,
even below the TCP layer, and kind of look
at how does the radio actually work, right?
So we will put the wired stuff aside, look
at the radio and dive into WiFi and mobile.
So 3G and 4G, what's so special about that?
How does battery life play into this? It turns
out that battery life is kind of the central
component. There is the radio, and then there
is a battery. Those are two connected components
that we need to think about. And what is the
radio resource controller? Our friend and
foe.
So let's dive right in. First of all, wireless
or WiFi came around in the early '90s. That's
when the first standards were published. Really,
it only became popular in the late '90s with
the release of the 802.11b, which is the 11-megabits-per-second
standard.
And the thing to realize about WiFi is it
was literally designed as an extension to
your local area network, your LAN. So we re-use
all of the same framing, protocols, mechanisms,
and all the rest of them, basically added
a wireless interface to it. So it is not designed
for a mobile device, which is to say a device
with limited battery. It was designed for
your desktop computer, your laptop computer,
right?
We weren't constrained by power at the time.
Think back to the phone that you had in 1999.
Right? We weren't thinking about the kinds
of applications that we were delivering at
the time.
And the thing about WiFi is we need to understand
how we actually schedule how we communicate
over WiFi, right? So when we are communicating
over a wired connection, we have a switch
or a router which routes all of the packets
between the destination -- or the client and
server, for example.
In WiFi, we share the radio channel. And the
radio channel is a shared medium between all
of us, right? All of us can't talk at the
same time. That would just generate a lot
of noise. So we need some sort of mechanism
to figure out who is going to talk when. And
WiFi takes a very hands-off approach about
this. It basically says let's use a very simple
algorithm, which is if you want to talk first,
listen if nobody else is talking. If nobody
else is talking, then start talking, right?
And if another person starts talking while
you're talking, well, then both of you stop,
wait for random interval of time and repeat
the whole process, right? So it is kind of
like this party algorithm of, We'll just trust
that all of you behave nicely and you will
all respect each other and we will just kind
of share this medium. That's WiFi.
Now, you can actually model this and prove
that the channel load or the amount of traffic
needs to be kept fairly low. In fact, the
load of the network needs to be below 10%
in order to achieve good performance. Like,
you're always going to have retransmissions.
There will always be the case when I start
talking and you start talking a little bit
later and we collide. That's okay because
we will wait and then we will retransmit data
and everything is okay. You can get pretty
good performance.
But after a while, you basically run into
the case where there are too many devices
trying to compete for the same medium and
the network basically collapses. There is
no way to recover from this state.
And I'm pretty sure all of us have experienced
this at some point, right? WiFi in a large
group of people and a room, not a good combination
oftentimes. So that's in part why.
And we can dig a little bit deeper and actually
look at how it's implemented. So in the 2.4-gigahertz
spectrum, we actually have a limited amount
of spectrum. Like, let's say 60 megahertz.
Within that 60 megahertz, we can actually
have three channels, which is to say up to
three devices can talk in parallel and they
won't interfere with each other, right? So
these are the channels. If you guys have ever
dug into your settings on your WiFi router,
that would be your, like, channel 1, channel
6 or channel 11 or something to that extent.
Now, the problem is -- this is nice and pretty.
This is a little chart that I pulled up on
my own home network. And you can see that
there is over a dozen networks, right? And
they're all overlapping. We are all trying
to talk over each other. And, basically, WiFi,
to some degree, is a victim of its own success.
It has become so ubiquitous, there are so
many WiFi routers out there, that it's just
-- it is very hard to get a slot to talk to
somebody without interfering with anybody,
right?
So your neighbor, when they start streaming
that HD Netflix movie, they are interfering
with you as well even though it is a different
access point. They are still using the same
shared spectrum.
So there is limited capacity. And most networks
have tens or even more than dozens of overlapping
networks.
So here's a fun experiment. I ran this at
my house. This is not definitive data, but
this is an example of a data point. There's
about 15 access points just in and around
my apartment. And I ran a very simple test.
I took my laptop and I had my router which
was about 15 feet away and I was staring right
at it. And I figured, hey, how long does it
take for one packet to get from my laptop
to the router? What is the latency of that
first hop?
And I gathered data for several hours. So
this is, you know, a good sample of data.
And if you look at the numbers here, the 95th
percentile is about 50 milliseconds. So to
travel 15 feet from my laptop to my router,
it was taking about 50 milliseconds, which
is crazy because 50 milliseconds is about
the amount of time that it takes to travel
from the West Coast to the East Coast, right?
So here I am trying to, like, shuttle a packet
15 feet away to my router. This is a function
of there is just a lot of other activity in
the vicinity. So we were competing for the
same spectrum.
So then I tried something different. I actually
went out and bought a different router, which
is using the new -- the new 802.11n standard
and it's running on the 5-gigahertz band.
And the 5-gigahertz band gives us more bandwidth.
And by the function that it is also new, not
many people are using it, right? So I was
like the lone person on that channel.
And I ran the same test and there you go.
My 95th percentile latency is down to 2 milliseconds.
So as far as I'm concerned that was a fantastic
investment. So if nothing else, you can go
back home, upgrade your router to 5 gigahertz,
and hope that not many of you are living in
the same neighborhood, and you are not competing
with each other.
[ Laughter ]
>>Ilya Grigorik: And then you will get much
better performance -- Web performance. We
just cut 50 milliseconds of latency. That
is huge for performance.
So some take-aways from this. First of all,
WiFi makes no guarantees about the bandwidth
or the data rate that you are going to get.
Anybody else can start transmitting at any
point in time, so it is unpredictable.
One way to adapt to this is to -- well, one
way to deal with this is to adapt to the variable
bandwidth. Not to predict it, you can't predict
it. You can only adapt to it.
We leverage this to, for example, serve video.
Like, when we serve video on YouTube, we serve
it in small chunks, like, 5 to 10-second chunks,
where we stream a chunk of video. We see if
you can download it fast enough. If you can
download it fast enough, we can upgrade you
to a higher-quality stream. Vice versa, if
your bandwidth was all of a sudden cut in
half because somebody else is streaming a
video, we will downgrade you seamlessly to
a lower resolution video. So that's adaptive
streaming. And that's something that you can
do as well if you're streaming music, streaming
video, or other things.
The other variable that you can't really control
with WiFi is, of course, latency and jitter,
right? So because we have these collisions
all the time. Your packets need to be retransmitted,
and there is not much you can do. WiFi provides
no guarantees about this. If you have ever
tried to implement a real-time chat or real-time
voice and video over WiFi, you have certainly
run into this problem.
So perhaps the only thing you can really do
is start looking into something like WebRTC
which allows you to leverage unreliable delivery
and basically UDP in the browser.
And we had a great session on WebRTC earlier
today. So if you guys have missed it, check
out the video for that.
So that's WiFi, right? So that's just a baseline.
Now let's take a look at 2G, 3G and 4G networks.
How do they work and how are they different?
So, first of all, when the mobile carriers
or the mobile standards started, you know,
they set aside some specific constraints that
they needed to optimize for. First, they needed
to guarantee some level of performance.
So they wanted to make sure that they don't
have this congestion collapse scenario which
is present in WiFi, right? And they wanted
to have some knobs to tweak to say, like,
if this is really overloading a network, we
will lower the data rates for everybody. But
you can still sort of get a lower data rate.
We want to be able to control that, and we
need some knobs for that. That's number one.
Second is, of course, we're covering a much
larger geographical area which means that,
once again, we need to handle more clients.
And that's something we need to account for.
And the second one is our battery life. So
it turns out when you're optimizing for mobile
devices, you really need to think about battery
life. I think for many of us, you know, if
we use our phone actively, or our mobile device
actively, you will find that your battery
is draining very, very quickly. So, radio
is a very important component of that.
You add these two things together and you
get the radio resource controller. And what
is the radio resource controller? So, mobile
networks, the 2G, 3G and 4G standards take
a different approach as to how they schedule
when you can communicate. Instead of doing
this freebie approach of you just start talking
when you think nobody else is talking, they're
actually employing a moderator, which is to
say the radio tower actually tells you when
you can speak.
You tell the radio tower that, Hey, I would
like to send some data and then the radio
tower consults its schedule and tells you,
okay, I've got these five people that are
queued up. You're this far away, so you start
transmitting at this point in time with this
signal power with these parameters, with this
encoding and then you have this amount of
time, right?
So it is a very different scheduling mechanism.
And as you can imagine, this adds a lot more
overhead, but it allows us to schedule resources
more efficiently within the network. And this
obviously has its pros and cons.
So the radio resource controller lives within
a different component of the network infrastructure
in 2G and 3G networks. It was actually living
in the core network. In the latest networks,
it is living right at the radio tower, which
is one of the ways of how we are improving
performance in 4G networks. By moving it closer
to you, we are reducing the latency.
But the radio resource controller has a number
of implications. So first of these is the
difference -- and the distinction between
the control and the user-plane latency. So
whenever you talk to anybody that's working
in the mobile space, they'll often throw this
out and mention the control and user-plane
latency. What is it?
Recall that we need to talk to the radio tower
to figure out when we're allowed to transmit
data. This is what happens first. You send
a message to the radio tower and say, I would
like to send data. The radio tower determines
when you can talk. And then it sends you a
message back. That is the control plane latency.
In 3G networks, this can take up to 2 1/2
seconds. 2 1/2 seconds just -- we haven't
even sent a packet of data, application data,
from your phone. We're basically trying to
get a resource assignment from the radio tower.
In 4G networks and the latest generation networks,
this time is significantly improved. It's
under 100 milliseconds. But, nonetheless,
every millisecond counts and 100 milliseconds
is a significant amount of time.
And then only after we've incurred this cost
and we have gotten a resource assignment,
can we then trance -- start transmitting data
from our phone to the radio tower?
And that is known as the user-plane latency.
And, for example, in 4G networks that can
be about 10 milliseconds, right? We're definitely
in the weeds here looking at how the mobile
radio works, but some important take-aways
there.
Let's take this from the ground up. Your phone
is idle. It has been asleep. You take it out
of your pocket. You start typing in an URL.
You hit "go." What happens?
We -- so this is a 4G network. First, we need
to talk to the tower. So we're going to incur
at least 100 milliseconds of latency. Then
our phone is active and starts transmitting
data or the radio was active and it starts
transmitting data.
After some time, it will actually downgrade
your radio into a short sleep cycle which
is to say it is not going to listen for transmissions
all the time. It will sleep for some time
and then it will wake up periodically to save
power. It turns out that the radio is the
second most expensive component in terms of
power or energy use in your phone after the
screen.
So this is why we want to turn off the radio
as quickly as possible. And in the case of
4G networks, this is usually done after 100
milliseconds of inactivity on your radio.
So we've transmitted some data. We wait for
a 100-millisecond pause and then we downgrade
your radio into this half sleep state.
And at that point, if you want to transmit
data again, we need to go through that whole
control plane cycle once more. So you're,
once again, incurring this same cost.
But then if your phone continues to be idle,
we wait for another 100 milliseconds. We go
into the second, the long sleep mode, and
only after then -- after about 10 seconds,
we will go back into the idle mode.
Right? So a kind of pretty complicated flowchart.
But effectively what this says is, first,
we have to incur the cost to upgrade the radio
and then it takes roughly 10 seconds to get
back to idle mode. And this is very important,
as you will see in a second.
So let's put this together, right? This is
pretty low level. How does this affect an
actual data transfer, something like an hspeed
edit data transfer. Let's start from the beginning.
We want to send the request which means we
need to do a DNS lookup. We may need to do
a DNS lookup. We need to do a TCP handshake
followed by the dispatching the actual hspear
request and then we actually need to fetch
the content and maybe optionally we need to
do the TLS handshake for another -- up to
two round trips there.
So let's add up all of these numbers. First
of all, we have the control plane latency,
which is the time to wake up the radio and
get into the active state.
So I'm using HSPA here, which is a 3G network.
And I'm using an average round trip time of
about 200 milliseconds, which is roughly the
time that we see at Google for 3G networks.
And then for 4G networks, these new-generation
networks, let's use 80 milliseconds, which
is actually fairly aggressive.
So 200 to 2.5 seconds -- so 200 milliseconds
to 2 1/2 seconds just to get out of the control
plane for the 3G network and then we have
these round trips to fetch the DNS, to establish
TCP and all the rest. And very quickly you
add up all the numbers, and this is without
your server response time, we already have
over half a second of just network latency.
And this is very important if you're trying
to design a responsive application that feels
responsive to the user. So the good news is,
things are definitely getting better with
4G. We are down into hundreds of milliseconds
and half a second territory. But we also can't
rely on 4G as you will see in a second. So
really you should assume that there's literally
seconds of latency -- of network latency overhead
when you design your applications.
So the first take-away here is we know that
there are some constants that good applications
need to follow. A number of different user
experience research studies have shown that
in order for an app to feel instant, it needs
to respond to the user, knowledge user input
within hundreds of milliseconds. We just saw
in that, even on the latest 4G network, you
are incurring 300 to 500 milliseconds. Which
means that you basically -- you cannot wait
for the http request or any request to complete.
You need to acknowledge the user input independently
of dispatching the request. That's the only
way you will have an application that feels
instant to the user. All communication should
be asynchronous.
Similarly, you should anticipate the RRC latency.
It is a very common complaint about mobile
networks. Oh, my God, they are so unpredictable.
The variability is so high. Turns out, once
you are aware of the control playing latency
or listening negotiation at the beginning
which is the time to wake up your radio, you
can model the stuff very well. You can build
and you can bake these things into the design
process of your application. Once you talk
to your designers and let them know, hey,
it may actually take two seconds before we
can do anything like even send an application
packet, they can design their application
in a way that provides some sort of feedback
to the user that, hey, we are working on processing
your input but it may take a while.
All right. So moving on. We talked about energy.
So this is another gotcha that I think is
top of mind for a lot of applications that
are native applications but is not top of
mind for web applications but it certainly
will be soon. So notice that in our earlier
diagram we said it takes about ten seconds
to cycle from a high-power state to a low-power
state. This actually causes what is known
as an energy tail where it doesn't matter
how much data you have transferred, the radio
will be active for a certain period of time.
Like it could have transferred one bit or
one byte of data. It doesn't matter, right?
Or you could have transferred 10 kilobytes
or 100 kilobytes for data. The radio is going
to be on effectively for ten seconds after
that. So you are not going to save much by
kind of sending data bit by bit. What you
want do is you want to send as much data as
possible as early as possible. And, in fact,
intermittent data transfers is a huge, huge
anti-pattern, performance anti-pattern on
mobile. So I have an example of this. And
average mobile device today has about five
watt hours of battery capacity. Don't worry
about the units too much. This is just to
illustrate the point. Five watt hours is about
18,000 joules. It turns out that an average
phone today, a4G connection, in order to cycle
to a low state to high state back to low state
will take about ten joules of energy. All
right. Let's do our math. Let's say we have
a one-minute pulling interval. So I built
an application like a gmail application which
every minute will wake up and just ping the
server, say, do I have any mail? Are there
any messages for me? You multiply that out.
It turns out that this application will consume
3% of battery life per hour. Right? Now you
have a couple of these applications running
on your phone. They have nonoverlapping intervals.
You have your phone in your pocket for half
a day. You take it out. Your battery is at
20%. You wonder what the heck happened there?
That's what happened there. We're doing these
intermittent pings and that's what's draining
the battery. So intermittent data transfers
are extremely expensive. There's a really
cool case study that was done as a joint case
study between AT&T and Pandora. They analyzed
the native Pandora application, which is,
of course, a music streaming application.
And they discovered something interesting.
Pandora was doing all the right things when
they were streaming the music. You start playing
the song. They would stream the entire song
down to the client. Play the whole thing,
and turn off the radio which is exactly what
you want to do. But then about every 58 seconds
or 60 seconds, Pandora would fire an analytics
beacon which was reporting, like, how far
along did you listen in a song and did you
like the song and all the rest. It seems reasonable.
They analyze it and realized that those data
transfers were accounting to .2% of the total
bytes transferred but it was 46% of the battery
life of that application. So -- which is a
huge, of course, huge performance problem.
So all they had to do was to move -- these
are not critical beacons. Right? They could
simply defer that until later until the next
song data transfer. They could accumulate
this data. They did exactly that and they
significantly improved the performance of
their application. So here are a couple of
examples. It's a little bit small but I was
looking at, for example, CNN.com here. And
I notice that they have a realtime Analytics
beacon installed in their site. So whenever
you're reading a CNN article on your mobile
phone, about every five seconds chart beat
sends a beacon saying, yep, I'm still here.
Yep, I'm still here. Yep, I'm still alive.
And guess what? As you're reading CNN, you're
draining your battery, which is not a great
experience. So in Google Analytics, we actually
caught this problem early and fixed it and
we don't do this. We will actually -- we have
a different way to provide realtime Analytics
but we have a way to do that without requiring
these beacons. So the short take-away is if
you are sending these kinds of beacons in
your application, web or native, definitely
something to reconsider because it's extremely
expensive. Now, unfortunately today I don't
think many platforms provide very good instrumentation
or visibility into how much energy does my
application consume? Whether that's web or
native, but one tool that is actually very
good is the AT&T's error tool. It is a free
and open source tool. I will show you a quick
demo of this. What it allows you to do, it
allows you to capture a trace file. It can
actually record -- you can install an application
on your Android device. You hit record. You
interact with your application. Then you export
a trace and you can analyze it with this analyzer
tool. I have already prerecorded a trace.
I will show it to you guys here. So let me
load this app here. And you can also run it
in emulator, but I prefer do it on my phone.
I loaded a web site. I have this trace. One
of the cool things it provides is it will
-- it can also record your screen. Here I'm
starting collector and I will fast forward
a little bit. So I'm loading the site Red
Robin here. It can look at the diagnostics
here. This is us downloading the images, downloading
the page. You can see the through put, different
RCC states or the states of the radio and
the energy consumption of your app. So let
me pause this. And one of the cool things
about this tool it will actually also analyze
the content that you are downloading and point
out common performance anti-patterns. Things
like, hey, you're not caching the data. Or
you have intermittent data transfers. But
then on top of all of that, it will also tell
you the energy consumed during this session
that you have recorded, right? So you can
actually model this. Now, one thing to call
out is this is not an exact measurement. This
is based on a model. So it has some assumptions
about the phone that you are using and the
network type you are on. You can actually
switch those and you say, I want to run this
model on the 3G network versus a 4G network.
So if nothing else, this is a great tool to
play with and I encourage you guys to check
it out. I hope that in the future we will
have more tools like this baked right into
our, kind of day-to-day DevTools both on native
and web platforms.
So it is all about the battery. It literally
is all about the battery. Whenever you're
wondering, why does my mobile radio behave
in a certain way? Always ask the question
of, how does it impact my battery life and
you will often find the answer there. Radio
at full power, if it is on all the time, will
literally drain your battery in a matter of
hours. If you have ever had your phone burning
your leg, you know how that feels. What's
usually happening there is you can't get a
connection and some application is just continuously
trying to reconnect and that turns on the
radio at full power. It drains your battery
like there's no tomorrow. And the actual transfer
size does not matter. It doesn't matter if
you're transferring one byte or a hundred
kilobytes. That's the other important take-away.
So the consequence of that is you want to
pre-fetch data. You don't want to fetch -- I'll
fetch the previews and thumbnails of my awesome
application and then as you scroll, I will
fetch the rest. That's an anti-pattern in
mobile. You want to pre-fetch as much data
as possible. Turn off the radio and hopefully
keep it off for as long as possible. We talked
about periodic data transfers. What can you
do that? You can defer the request until later.
You can combine them. You can log that data
into a local database like localstorage and
then fire the request later. Of course, we
provide some tools for this, both on Android
and Chrome. So Google Cloud Messaging is definitely
something that you guys should check out and
leverage. What it allows you to do is you
can push notifications to our servers, through
the Google Cloud Messaging servers, and then
those servers determine a optimal strategy
for delivering those messages to your form
by limiting the number of data transfers.
So for example, we just launched this support
on Chrome. We don't have future parity with
Android. I hope we get there quick. On Android,
you can mark a message as delay while idle,
which is to say, if the user's phone is idle,
don't push it right now. But when they wake
up their phone, push the message there. And
not only that, but if you are going to delay
the message, this is the time to live. Like
if the user doesn't wake up their phone within
the next hour, just drop the message on the
floor. It's no longer relevant, right? It's
an combination of these things that allow
you to build efficient applications with efficient
delivery of messages to the phone without
necessarily having to wake up the phone or
having your phone wake up periodically and
query our service. Which clearly does not
scale.
So that's a little bit about how the network
-- or how the radio works on the phone itself.
Now let's take a deep dive into how the mobile
network, the core network actually works and
what implication it is has on performance.
So at a very high level, the mobile network
effectively has a couple of important components.
The first one is packet gateway. The way to
think about packet gateway, is basically like
your wireless router or your router at your
us, right? It's a nat device which accepts
all of the connections. It terminates all
the connections and then it forwards the packets
to your device. In this case, a mobile device.
And there's an important pause here which
is your connection or the connection to your
phone between the server and your phone is
not an end-to-end connection. It is being
terminated by this router. So just the fact
that you are turning off your radio or you're
pressing the power button on your phone does
not terminate the TCP connection which I think
is a common misconception. And if you are
ever seeing this kind of pattern where you
have your code basically saying, look, if
I turn off the radio, I'm going to lose my
web socket connection or something else, that
is not true. Because the connection is still
maintained by the radio network and it will
wake up your radio when it's necessary. So
if you have code like this in your application,
you definitely want to turn that off. Most
carriers have actually timeouts of anywhere
between five to 30 minutes for a TCP connection.
If anything, I found that by working with
many different apps, it's usually the applications
server on your side that's terminating the
connection early on. Like you have aggressive
timeouts of 60 seconds. And then because of
that, your app needs to periodically pull
your server to keep it open. So make sure
that that plumbing is correct. It's not the
carriers in most cases.
Okay. So we've got the packet gateway. Packet
gateway has no idea about the location of
your device. What it actually does is it sends
-- it forwards the packets to the serving
gateway. The serving gateway needs to figure
out, where are you? Where is your device?
The trick is, the serving gateway actually
doesn't know that either. It basically needs
to query a database like a user database to
say which radio tower are you currently associated
with and how is your billing status? Should
I be even forwarding this packet to begin
with? That's this mobility management entity.
It's like a user database. That's all it is.
All right. So let's try this. Let's say we
want to send a data packet from your phone.
We can actually connect all the pieces together
now. First my device is going to wake up and
the first component is it is going to talk
to the radio tower. It is going to negotiate
the time when it can send data. That will
take hundreds of milliseconds or up to two
seconds on 3G networks. After that, it will
transfer data to the radio tower. The radio
tower will transfer it to the serving gateway
which will forward it to the packet gateway.
Only then will it hit the external network.
This is when the data is transferred to the
server and all the rest. The latencies for
this end-to-end transferring here without
the external network is anywhere between 50
milliseconds to hundreds of milliseconds on
different networks. I pulled out these numbers
from the AT&T technical FAQ. Right? Basically
the take-away here is 4G, 50 milliseconds
plus the transfer time to your server. On
3G, as high as 400 milliseconds and much,
much worse for 2G networks. Turns out that's
a simple case. Let's try the more complicated
case. I hope you guys stay with me here. Let's
say we actually want to push a packet to the
device. Right? So we are trying to wake up
the device. Our server pushes a packet to
the mobile carrier. It hits the packet gateway.
That goes to the serving gateway. The serving
gateway, once again, has no idea where you
are. Right? Once of the nice properties in
mobile networks, you guys are mobile. You
hop into a car accident now you are on your
way out of San Francisco. We have no idea
where you are. The serving gateway talks to
the mobility management here and it says,
okay, I need to send this packet to this user.
Tell me where to forward the packet to. The
mobility interface doesn't actually know your
current physical location. It knows geographically
where you are. Okay, last time he checked
in, he was in San Francisco. So it sends a
ping to all of the radio towers in the vicinity
and says just flood the entire network with
a beacon that says, hey you, user number blah
blah blah, there's a packet waiting for you.
Identify yourself, please. Your radio wakes
up. It gets that packet. It then talks to
the tower and says, I'm here. I'm associated
with you right now. That data gets transferred
back, goes back to the serving gateway and
now can transfer the data back to the tower
and to your device. This is pretty complicated,
right? The reason I'm pointing this out is
oftentimes there's a question of, like, why
does it take 200 milliseconds to do this?
But clearly this is a pretty complicated problem
to solve, right? So the fact that we can do
this in 40 to 50 milliseconds in 4G is actually
rather impressive to be honest.
All right, so, this is a little crazy. But
is it worth it? I think this is a valid question
to ask. We went from Wi-Fi where we had nothing.
Right? We had just talk. We hoped for the
best. Cross our fingers. We went to this 4G
network interface where we now have all these
routers. Radio towers talking to each other.
It's all crazy. Where are we going? So this
is a great case study that was done a couple
years back actually in 2011. Where they measured
performance of Wi-Fi networks, typical whole
router networks. I think this was 802.11G,
so fairly new standard. They compared it against
LTE. So just focus on these two clusters here.
What I want to point out, first of all the
through put is better. Most importantly is
this graph right here, the round trip time
for our packets. With Wi-Fi, there's no guaranties
about the latency of the delivery of your
packets. That's why you have these giant tails
here. Generally speaking, the latency is fairly
low. But then you have these outliers which
is why this line is stretched. With LTE, even
though it is seemingly more complicated -- not
seemingly, it is more complicated, we can
deliver more reliable latency and lower jitter
across the network. So this is good. Right?
This is, like, great. 4G will make things
better.
So a couple of things. Mobile radio is optimized
for burst data transfers. It is not optimized
for sending bits in small chunks, right? If
what you want to do is transfer as much data
as possible and then turn off the radio. In
fact, the latest 4G networks can transfer
on the order of tens of megabits per second,
which is really high data rates. But it will
do so in very small assignments. In fact,
the bandwidth assignments are done in millisecond
and lower chunks. All right? So you get a
chunk of space, air space, for about one millisecond.
You can transfer huge amounts of data. So
pack as much data as you can. Group your requests.
Don't delay requests. The not so good news
part of the 4G world is that 4G will take
a while to come. Despite the fact that there
is ads everywhere across all the highways
and everywhere else that 4G will save all
things, 4G will take a while to deploy. Current
carriers have deployed a lot of infrastructure
for 3G and they are continuing to improve
that in part because they can and in part
because it's very expensive. So the dominant
network type of this decade -- not just this
year or in the coming year -- of this decade
will be 3G networks. Granted, they are being
enhanced to deliver higher data rates. But
nevertheless, you can see overall growth projections
are for 3G networks. The good news is, at
least within North America, LTE and HSPA,
which are 4G networks, are actually taking
off quite well. In fact, we are way ahead
of the curve compared to all the other countries.
But nonetheless, you have to basically assume
that your users will be using a mix of 3G
and 4G networks. Right? Even if you have a
4G network data plan on your phone, your phone
is switching between 4G and 3G all the time
and depending on coverage or where you currently
are and load within the network. So because
of that, you have to design for variable network
performance and availability. It is truly
a multi-generation future. You can't assume
that you will get great performance with 4G.
You need to plan for 3G networks as well.
Bandwidth and latency are variable and, of
course, as we have all experienced, connectivity
is intermittent. So if you are building a
mobile application or an application for the
mobile web, you have to assume that there
should be an offline mode or some fallback
to say what happens when I can't actually
connect. And I mentioned this before, but
I think this is an important point to make
once again. You should have some sort of a
back-off strategy. Oftentimes the reason we
have poor battery performance is because some
application does not plan for intermittent
connectivity or the fact that there is no
connectivity and it just continues to pull
the server to say, are you there yet? Are
you there yet? Are you there yet? And that's
what's burning your leg and burning the battery
on your device. What you want to do instead
is to say, I'm going to try to connect now
and then every time I fail, I will just punt
further out into the future, have some sort
of a decay function, and then say I'm going
to stop after this interval and retry later.
Nine cases out of ten, whenever I have a performance
or battery life program, I track it down to
exactly this. It's some application that's
just sitting there in the loop while not connected,
keep trying, right? Not a good strategy.
So with that, I think we've gone through kind
of the full cycle and we're back to application
best practices. Of course, all of the radio
stuff is very important but optimizing TCP
best practices, TLS, and http is very important.
The take-away here is, of course, measure
first. Make sure that you are using a real
user measurement and measuring performance
across real networks. Do that first, then
optimize later. And I'll just call out an
couple of examples. Fastest request is a request
not made. This is an obvious one. But turns
out when we analyze a lot of mobile applications,
they are not caching data. This is like number
one problem for a lot of applications. So
make sure you do that. Bytes are literally
expensive for a lot of users. You need to
compress resources and it's funny because
we have been talking about compressing resources,
compressing images for years but we still
find that a lot of applications don't do it.
And of course, leveraging performance like
WebP as you heard in the keynote. We had a
session earlier today in WebP, I definitely
encourage you to try it both on web and native.
And then finally, a shameless self-promotion.
I have been writing a book on this stuff and
specifically on mobile radio performance and
other things and it's available online for
free. If you guys are curious to learn more
about this, and I can talk about it all day,
please check it out and please offer feedback.
You can actually comment right on it.
And with that, I think we have some time for
questions. If you can grab one of the mics,
I would be happy to answer them.
[ Applause ]
>>> My name is Mauricio. I work for Verizon
wireless. I have a question regarding APIs
or services that can be provided by Google
-- the Android framework itself to help verticals
to make application more efficient. For example,
the same way today does not allow you to put
network accessing your main thread. Is there
anything planned to do in that manner?
>>Ilya Grigorik: So I can't -- -- I'm more
-- I have more experience with the web part
of the stack so I can't necessarily comment
on the Android part. I would actually direct
you to the Android guys sitting outside for
that. But something like GCM, we continue
to enhance GCM, or the Google Cloud Messaging,
and that's what you want to use for a lot
of your communication. Just recently we announced
the ability to actually send data through
GCM as well.
>>> Thank you.
>>> So my understanding of why LT is much
better is partially because of the modulation
that it uses, since LT uses RFDM and Wi-Fi
uses something different. Do you know if there's
any, like, industry trends to move the modulation
scheme of the access points that you might
have at home to use that technology over,
you know, what we have today since it's so
jittery.
>>Ilya Grigorik: There's a couple of questions
in there. So LT has a host of different improvements.
So they are basically redesigning the network
from the ground up. They are moving the scheduling
stuff into the edges of the network. They
are using a new modulation scheme as you described.
It's not just a modulation. Right? Because
that helps you with through-put but there's
a number of other variables. Energy used,
latency of the assumption, connection, all
the rest. For moving that same technology
into, let's say, your local access points,
yes, to some degree. Wi-Fi standards and LTE
or 3GPP standards are completely separate.
But just watching both of them, they do borrow
and steal from each other. So with the latest
Wi-Fi standards, you will find that the way
they are -- the way they are achieving gigabyte
data rates is by using the same tricks to
a large degree.
>>> Do you know if that's in ADT2C or --
>>Ilya Grigorik: Yeah, that's in part how
-- yeah, exactly. >>> Thank you.
>>> I'm fairly new to Android development.
This may have been covered in the Cloud Messaging
feature. I was just wondering, is there any
currently or plans to provide support for
aggregating requests from the OS level or
framework to, you know, if you have multiple
apps running that have a stupid beacon request,
is there any support for, like, ganging these
together so multiple apps kind of work with
each other instead of against each other to
reduce radio usage?
>>Ilya Grigorik: That's something definitely
we are looking at. That is only something
the platform can provide. As an application
designer, you can't control what the other
applications are doing. This is definitely
something we are thinking about both on the
web, like, on Chrome for example, how can
Chrome leverage something like this, and also
with the Android platform. A good example
of this is turning off the radio early. Like
if we know that there's no other connections
being made, we can terminate the connections
early. That can be done by the operating system
in conjunction with the radio resource controller.
So, yes, there's definitely work in that direction.
>>> So that's nothing current but it's in
the works?
>>Ilya Grigorik: Yep.
>>> Do you have recommendations for tools
to just as a user to help figure out, like,
what's killing your battery on iOS and Android?
>>Ilya Grigorik: So I hope we make that tooling
much better. I guess a couple of tips that
I use. One is you actually have the battery
panel within Android. If you go into your
settings and kind of navigate down, it actually
gives you a really good breakdown of which
applications consume power. If you click on
the graph, it will also show you a breakdown
of when the power is being consumed. So I
find that is the most effective way to identify
specific applications. I think we need to
do more to isolate, like, at a web page level,
there's nothing really like that. And I think
we need something like that. So I hope we
will have a better answer in a year's time.
>>> Hi, could you talk a little bit about
strategies you would use for games because
they have a completely different data access
pattern and they typically [indiscernable]
instead of TCP and require lower latency in
case you are playing with someone else.
>>Ilya Grigorik: So all of the same optimization
strategies apply there. Intermittent, it doesn't
matter if it CCP, TCP. You need to wake up
the radio. So to the extent possible, you
want to aggregate data. You don't want to
be beaconing back every single achievement
unlocked by the user if that can be kept on
the device. So once again, leveraging things
like GCM and others to aggregate that data,
it's all the same. The protocol doesn't actually
matter.
>>> Hi, as a JavaScript developer, the best
practice as you said is to batch API requests
or other requests. And could you comment on
the beacon API which would help us tap into
actually when the radio is active.
>>Ilya Grigorik: The beacon API? Are you talking
about the new proposal?
>>> Yeah, and then what the status of that
is.
>>Ilya Grigorik: Yeah. So in the http performance
working group, we are working on a couple
of proposals I guess. One is the beacon API
which is to say I want you to send this request
but I don't actually care when you send it,
just send it when it's convenient for you.
Good example of that is Analytics beacons.
Right? You don't want to wake up the radio
right now. You are saying defer this. Dispatch
it at some later time. So there's no implementation
of that yet. We have early drafts of the spec.
If you guys are interested, I definitely encourage
you to check out the working group and comment
on it. But hopefully soon we will have something.
>>> Okay, thanks.
>>> Can you talk about what tools you use
to look at your Wi-Fi networks in those slides?
>>Ilya Grigorik: What is the tool that I used
in -- I don't remember off the top of my head.
If you talk to me afterwards, I can find it
on my laptop.
>>> I have a question about Analytics. What
solutions are you currently [indiscernible]
not to lose the data value and to reduce the
page rate consumption?
>>Ilya Grigorik: So for Analytics, what you
generally want to do -- so this is actually
related to the previous question about the
beacon API. Oftentimes you can report the
data later. One strategy is to literally stash
the data into your local database and then
report it when the radio is active. This requires
some modifications of your application itself.
But, for example, on the realtime Analytics,
we don't actually ping back every so often
to just say that you are there. We actually
do the realtime Analytics differently which
is to say, we track when you first visit the
page, which is when you hit that beacon. And
then we say that you are active on the page
for the next 30 seconds. Right? You have to
be -- if you navigate to another page, then
you are still active. We are not forcing this
five-second interval. I think we need to talk
to the other vendors and get them to move
in the same direction. They are literally
costing a lot in terms of performance.
>>> And about Google Analytics, an additional
question. Will it be a separate API extended
for request bulking?
>>Ilya Grigorik: Can you say that again?
>>> So for example, we start an activity and
we are reporting the user, when there is a
start of activity and when he left it. And
there is a chain of that event. And will the
API Google Analytics extend it so we can bufferize
this like to put a buffer and report later.
>>Ilya Grigorik: That's a great idea. There's
ways to tackle that. Google Analytics can
provide a new API to basically say stash this
and remember later. You can implement your
own wrap around it and basically say I am
going to fire this later when I consider that
it is active. The best approach, I think,
is a combination of two which is the beacon
API that we were just talking about which
is basically a browser mechanism to say, we
will defer this to the browser to determine
because it's actually in the best position.
So today the fastest way to get what you are
talking about is to implement the new application.
I can certainly talk to the Google Analytics
team and see if there is interest in implementing
something like this. I think that's a great
idea. Maybe in a year's time we will have
something like the beacon Analytics.
>>> We are way over. We are going to need
to wrap up.
>>Ilya Grigorik: Okay, one more.
>>> My question is related to the Nexus 4.
I have always used Verizon, I have never had
any signal reception issues until I switched
to T-Mobile. At my house on the first floor,
I only get edge. On the second floor, I get
edge but it's if-y. On the third floor, I
will get edge and HSPA+. This is the thing,
with this phone, the decibel rating, from
what I'm reading, is like around a hundred.
If I hold the phone in my hand, I lose signal.
>>Ilya Grigorik: Yep. You're holding it wrong.
[ Laughter ]
>>> But this is the thing, if I'm on a phone
call and then I hold it, it doesn't drop signal.
So my question is, is there a way that I,
as an end user, can make the phone put more
power into the radio to hold the signal? Because
I can't change T-Mobile.
>>Ilya Grigorik: So the short answer is no.
The energy use is actually dictated by the
radio tower. It actually tells you, depending
on where you are, like the distance between
you and the radio tower. The amount of other
people talking. The exact signal power that
you should be transmitting. So, in fact, radio
tower is trying to help you optimize your
battery use. Which sounds like, in this case,
it may be working against you. But there's
no explicit control of that, unfortunately.
>>> Thank you.
>>Ilya Grigorik: Thank, thanks guys.
[ Applause ]