So my name is James Hawkins. I'm the tech
lead of the Chrome team in Los Angeles, and
for the past year we've been working very
closely with the Google+ Photos team on a
new product. That's the Google+ Photos Chrome
app.
So this is a Chrome packaged app, and if you'll
remember, packaged apps were announced a little
over a year ago and this is, you know, the
key piece of Chrome's app platform.
Packaged apps give you the ability to have
extended permissions. You can do a little
bit more. You can have a more native look
and feel with your app. It's a step above
what you can do with the web platform today.
So we're going to talk about Google+ Photos
Chrome app.
Actually, instead of talking about it, let's
cut to the demo.
Okay. So this is Google+ Photos, the Chrome
app. This is my personal account. I've got
all my photos loaded up into it. We're doing
some nice scrolling. And if you note, I'm
on a Pixel right here, so we obviously have
touchscreen capabilities to do scrolling with
this.
Okay. So we're viewing some photos. Let's
say I want to go in and check out a particular
photo.
All right. I've got this photo and I've got
my nice information, my tags and details.
Very neat.
But I just went and used my camera, took a
bunch of pictures, and I've got it on an SD
card. I'd like to upload these to the cloud.
I want to share it with my friends. So let's
go ahead and do that. Close this.
So here we go.
The app was already open and it's already
started importing photos and it's going to
start uploading them. We can view the ones
that are on this SD card.
Cool. So these are the pictures that I just
took. Got a little notification that we have
some photos copied and they're being uploaded
right now.
We got a notification that we're finding the
best photos and there we go.
What you just saw is something that you heard
about in the keynote. This is autocuration.
So in the back end, Google said, "We're looking
at your photos. We want to see what are the
best photos of the ones you just took. Let's
make it very simple for you to share the best
photos that you have with your -- with your
friends, your families, et cetera."
For example, this is -- this photo has been
deemed to be underexposed. Cool. All right.
That's fine. I'm not too picky. I just want
the best photos to go up.
So we want to share these.
Cool. I shared it with my family. Cool new
photos.
And so this is -- these are the photos that
I just shared. We can change the name. No,
it's '13.
[ Laughter ]
>>James Hawkins: It is early, after all.
Cool. So this is Google+ Photos. You've got
the autocuration magic behind the scenes.
You've got a very slick interface, very fast
viewing of all your photos, just really nice
scrolling. And we're going to talk a bit today
about what it took to develop this product
as a Chrome packaged app on the platform.
>> (Speaker is off microphone.)
>>James Hawkins: This is not available yet.
It will be available soon.
So we started developing this product with
a set of goals in mind. What did we want to
accomplish?
When we started development, the only way
to view photos in Chrome OS was through the
file manager, and even then that was not the
best experience. You could do some minimal
editing. You couldn't really share very easily.
And, you know, the viewing experience was
just a stopgap. That's not to say it's not
good, but we wanted to do something better.
We wanted a better photos experience for Chrome
OS.
In addition, we wanted a place where the Google+
Photos team could experiment with new UI,
new back-end functionality like we were talking
about with autocuration. In fact, autocuration
was not available to the public in, you know,
the Google+ desktop until, you know, we just
announced it at I/O a couple days ago, and
so this was -- this product was the only place
where the autocuration team could see autocuration
live, see how it worked out, get a lot of
feedback on the feature, and so this is going
to continue to be one of the places where
that feature development happens, like sandbox,
if you will.
And coming from the Chrome team side of things,
we wanted to make sure that the platform had
everything that we needed in order to be very
successful and very easy for people to develop
apps. What's missing? Could we identify it?
What are the bugs?
A lot of -- you know, it's a very nascent
platform and a lot of the APIs that are being
developed are even right now in development,
and we wanted to test them out, have a user
for the platform instead of, you know, giving
it to you guys and you guys have to cut your
teeth on it, which is not the best experience.
We wanted to do that ourselves, to spare you
guys some pain.
And as a part of that as well, we are Chrome
developers in addition to doing some of this
front-end stuff, so when we did find areas
that were lacking in the platform, we could
go in and, you know, add those APIs that were
missing. And I'll talk about one of those
specifically later on.
So Chrome, as you know, has three core principles.
You want your UI to be extremely quick, extremely
fast. You want animations to be very snappy
and fluid. When you have jank, you have stuttering,
you have a really bad user experience. It's
jarring for the user.
Keeping your app very simple to me means getting
out of the way. Get your UI out of the way
of the user, out of the way of what they're
trying to do. And sometimes that is actually
the hardest thing to accomplish.
Security, obviously, is extremely important.
You want to keep your users secure. Not only
from your app misbehaving but from malicious
attackers that, you know, can get -- can use
your app to harm your user. You want to make
sure that that is not possible.
So we took these principles to mind when we
were developing the app, and the challenges
that we faced when developing the app, I'm
going to frame around these core principles.
Speed. You got to be fast. Everybody wants
to be fast.
One of the first problems we ran into was
with having to have a clientside photo and
needing to know if we needed to upload it
or not. You obviously don't want to waste
bandwidth if the user already has that photo
in the cloud, and so the way we did that is
to store SHA-512 hashes of these photos in
the cloud when it was already uploaded and
so when we have a new photo to upload, we
have to calculate that hash to say, "Hey,
do you have this photo or not; and if not,
we don't need to upload it."
So we have a little demo here. This is a quite
large image. It's about 12 megabytes, I think.
And this is just one example of what the user
could be uploading that we need to get the
-- the hash of.
And we found that the JavaScript implementation,
while we could optimize it as much as we possibly
could, it could never compare to a native
implementation. And we got that native implementation
through Native Client, which allows you to
run C++ binaries in your Webapp. It's a really
amazing technology that is extremely useful,
especially for this use case, where you need
to do data processing, you want to get bare
bones as close to the middle as possible.
So I'm going to do a little demo. We have
hashing done in JavaScript and we have hashing
done in Native Client and we're going to get
the timings of those and we'll see what the
difference is.
Okay. Almost 3 seconds compared to 200 milliseconds.
That is an order of magnitude difference.
That's amazing. Not to mention the fact that
Native Client doesn't block the UI, the main
thread, whereas this JavaScript implementation
does.
So if you're taking 3 seconds to hash an image,
your user is doing nothing. They're looking
at your app not doing anything. So Native
Client saved us on this one. And in fact,
you know, with more native-like apps being
produced for the Web, I think we're going
to see Native Client being used a tremendous
amount.
One of the first big apps that was done with
Native Client was actually games and it makes
perfect sense. You've got to have high -- super-high
performance, so calculating with a lot of
data.
So actually, I want to go in and let's look
at this and see how we hooked up with Native
Client.
So we're going to go into the JavaScript,
and the meat of this is the nacl hash for
the nacl implementation. We'll ignore the
JavaScript for now. We're going to do document.getelementbyID
fileio, so let's go see what that was.
That is -- and I'm going to zoom this up so
you guys can see it.
That's an embed of type xnacl. This fileio.nmf
is in nacl manifest format and it specifies,
you know, what the binary is for -- I'm not
going to open it up but it specifies what
the binary is that needs to be run.
We communicate with this -- go down here -- with
post message, so we post message the filename,
and inside the implementation of the nacl
module, we take that filename, do the hashing
on it in C++, that's compiled, and post message
-- and send a message back through the nacl
API to the app and we handle that message
here.
So this is essentially how we are doing it
in Native Client. It's actually really simple.
So this is, what, maybe 10 lines total of
code for handling this? And C++ code on the
other side.
The meat of it is getting the nacl module
built, which there are tons of tutorials out
there. It's not that hard.
Go to full screen.
Okay. Hold on.
Just one second.
>> (Speaker is off microphone.)
>>James Hawkins: Oh, yeah. Thank you very
much. I was zoomed in.
So the next issue that we were running into
is the Data Store layer. So with photos, there
are users that have, say, 40,000 photos. This
is a case that we have to handle. It's very
difficult. And the fact that this app needs
to be native, needs to act like a real app
on your platform, you have to have offline
support which means you need to store your
user's data locally to some degree. You don't
have to store everything, but at least the
metadata. So for photos you'd have maybe a
link to where the file is on the filesystem
and the dimensions of the photo and any other
metadata that you have.
This needs to be stored somewhere in your
data layer and we use index DB to do this.
The problem that we ran into with our initial
implementation is that we were not using transactions
in index DB appropriately and this was kind
of killer because it's not -- it's not immediately
obvious what you're doing wrong when your
reads are going really slowly, unless you're
very familiar with the API.
So I'll give you a demo here. We have writing
a thousand records, reading, removing them,
et cetera, and with transaction and with no
transaction. We'll see what the differences
are. Okay. It's taking a long time.
So again, this is -- and this is even worse.
This is two orders of magnitude worse without
transactions. It's very simple. Let's go in
and see what the transactions do.
So you open a transaction -- let me zoom this
up, and I -- thank you very much. I will zoom
back out when I'm done with this.
So we have a notification when the transaction
is complete. That is when we say, "I've done
all of my thousand operations," and you just
do all of your operations at once using the
transaction object. You get this -- the object
store out from the transaction. You do your
operation on the store. And once this goes
out of scope, the transaction will be complete
and it will be done.
The implementation that doesn't use transaction
has one database transaction per call, so
every time you're doing a new call, you're
creating a new transaction. Very inefficient.
So I think the biggest part of making this
app very performant is the scrolling performance,
and this was the biggest challenge for us
to solve.
There's a lot of optimizations you have to
do all across the board. You have to make
sure that you don't have any leaks. You have
to make sure that you're doing the right thing
in order to be on fast scroll path.
This needs to be very non-choppy. Otherwise,
if it is choppy, your user's jarred and they're
just very confused. It looks like not a native
app; it looks like a Webapp.
And so the solution for this is the fast scroll
path.
The fast scroll path is where the GPU does
the scrolling for you. Off-load the processing
for handling this chunk of image -- video
memory. You've got everything rendered into
it. And whenever you scroll, you just ask
the GPU to do the op set for you. This is
common in, you know, games, graphics, whatever,
and we're starting to add this to the browser
in a lot of places.
Keep in mind that this is very preliminary
and the GPU team is working very hard on this,
but it is -- there are a lot of things you
have to keep in mind.
When you do scrolling, the element that you
scroll has to be the body element. That's
the first thing. And I say that right off
the bat because it's not obvious that that
is a requirement or a constraint, and you
can set up your DOM, your HTML structure,
in such a way that it's very hard, after the
fact, to move scrolling to the body, and we
ran into that problem. It was a total pain.
For example, let's go look at the app for
a second.
We have our main content here in the middle
-- and I'm going to go into the single-photo
view to show you more -- and the toolbar on
the top and this sidebar on the right. The
toolbar and the sidebar were siblings of the
main content and this was all in one wrapper
that could be scrolled. This doesn't work
because you're not in the body and in order
to be on the body element, we had to make
the toolbar and the sidebar fixed position,
and that has its own intricacies, like, for
example, the scrollbar goes all the way up
through the toolbar. There's really not anything
we can do about that right now and if that's
the worst of our problems that gets us this
type of scrolling, this fast scrolling, then
it's definitely worth it.
You also want to make sure when you're handling
the scroll event that you're not doing too
much work. This is when the -- the browser
is saying, "I'm about to scroll, I'm about
to change your UI, the page." If you start
doing a lot of processing, maybe you start
loading a bunch of image elements, a lot of
photo elements, that's going to make -- that
inherently is going to make the scrolling
a lot worse, a lot slower. So you want to
off-load your processing to a time that is
not in your body scrolling.
Perhaps queuing up and batching operations
that could be done later.
And we'll talk about that in one of our solutions.
One thing that we had to do was to reduce
image loads, so when you set the source attribute
on an image element, the browser, no matter
whether it's in the viewport or not, the image
element has to decode the image. And we've
found that the decoding can be very expensive
and it obviously scales with the size of the
image, so you want to question expensive operations
like that.
And setting image source is one of those expensive
operations.
So we talked about batching your heavy processing
so that you're not doing everything in your
scroll. One way to do this, and the best way
right now, is to have a call back to this
method called requestAnimationFrame.
This method is a way for the browser to alert
you, "Hey, I'm about to do an animation and
you should do some heavy processing in this
time period, batch it all up, do everything
at once because we're going to swap everything
out," and this is a way for the browser to
say, "This will be less janky." And so whenever
we do scrolling, we do requestAnimationFrame
and then we obviously need to load more elements,
so in requestAnimationFrame, the callback,
we do that image loading then, because that's
when the browser says, "Do your heavy intensive
processing." And this is really great to have
high performance in your scrolling.
Another thing that I think is starting to
be more well-known but it is not that well-known,
I think, and it's not very -- necessarily
intuitive is that when you measure certain
properties on DOM elements, you can cause
reflows, which may call repaints, and painting
is the one thing you want to minimize at all
costs.
If you're doing a bunch of paints, then you
don't have the benefit of the GPU doing the
scroll for you, because you're just thrashing
what the GPU had.
Scroll top, for example. If you're reading
scroll top, not writing to it, if you read
it, you're going to do a reflow and you could
potentially repaint. Another one is get client
bounding rect on elements, and you know what?
It's kind of iffy on some of these whether
it will cause a reflow or not. There are several
good articles and I recommend looking up reflow,
HTML reflow, to get a lot of information about
this. But this is something you have to keep
in mind. This is the next stage of app development
and this type of performance is -- is what
the -- these apps are going be to doing, and
you want to your app to be this performant.
Garbage collection is nasty. JavaScript is
a fun language and obviously the way the memory
layout works is very fortunate in some ways
but garbage collection is not one of those
ways, so you want to try to minimize garbage
collection by minimizing the pressure buildup
on memory.
One of the ways that we do that in this photos
app is, you know, if you consider it, you
have your main viewport and you have image
elements for each of the photos that the user
wants to see, and we obviously have to preload
before and after the viewport, and that could
be 40,000 DOM nodes. That's too many. That's
going to cause a lot of garbage collection
and a lot of memory pressure that you don't
need.
Consider that you can compress those nodes
given like, say, a square of a 1024 by 768
higher up that is not visible in the viewport.
Get rid of all those nodes. You can either
store them around somewhere, but at least
keep them out of the tree and replace them
with one div that's sized the exact same size,
so that's like compressing what you had before.
And that will keep the structure of your document,
will not change the size of the entire body,
so the user won't even be aware that you've
taken nodes out.
Nifty little trick you can do.
It is really important. Leaks are bad. Everybody
knows that. But you got to pay attention to
it. The profiler inside of Chrome itself can
really help with this. And let's take a look
real quick.
Nope. So profiles here allows you to take
a heap snapshot. Obviously, the heap snapshot
for this is not going to be entirely interesting,
but it does show you some of the objects that
are going on.
So we have the slide deck object. And there
are two of them. So I may question, if I only
have one set of slides, why do I have two
slide decks? I don't know the answer to that.
Could be a leak.
We found in many instances of just going through
this -- and you can arrange things by, for
example, dominators which are saying, this
thing is huge. Obviously, you want to go through
the native stuff at the top that's not yours
and get down to where you're allocating stuff
and say, We are -- This is too heavy. This
slide deck is too heavy, for example.
And that will just -- that's just one way
to say, I need to go in here and start looking
for places where I may be leaking. I may not
be freeing references, removing references,
et cetera.
There are a lot of tools that can help with
this. In our experience, they're not very
great. There's not a lot of tools right now
that have a very low false-positive rate,
but it can point you in the right direction.
And it doesn't hurt to just have a -- run
it every once in a while and say, These are
the known false-positives. These are the ones
we need to fix.
Listeners can get very expensive. We had an
instance where you would start the app with
no photos and we had 40,000 listeners. What
are they listening to? I mean, that doesn't
even make sense. You need to make sure that
things are being detached appropriately. They
stop listening.
They can be dangerous not just in the memory
footprint but also in the processing footprint.
If these listeners are being fired on events
and they don't need to be listening, then
they're going to some processing that is unnecessary
and that's going to hurt your performance
as well.
And we already talked about profiling memory
usage, so we'll skip that.
So back to simplicity. I truly think that
this is one of the most difficult things that
you have to solve in an app, how to get out
of the way so that the user can just see what
they want to see, do what they want to do,
minimize your UI footprint, et cetera.
And the Chrome platform is really starting
to take over this and give you APIs that allow
you to get out of the way.
The biggest one we had, one of the big ones
we had was with sign-in. Signing into an app
really feels like a Web page that you have
to sign into, especially if you don't have
the ability to sign in once and have that
persistent across multiple lifetimes, multiple
instances of the app. It just doesn't feel
native. And we do. That's our goal, is to
feel native.
Also, if you are signing in, that's a step,
that's a roadblock to the user getting to
do what they want to do. And so we really
needed a way around this, and thankfully the
Chrome platform has a way. There is this thing
called the identity API which allows you to
retrieve the OAuth2 token of the user that's
currently signed in.
Now, this app is right now designed for Chrome
OS but the identity API works on all platforms.
So if the user is signed into the browser,
you can get their OAuth2 token for their Google
account. For example, in this app, I didn't
have to sign in. There is no sign-in button
anywhere. When you start the app, I don't
ask you to sign in, or I'm not asked to sign
in. I mean, that all comes from the identity
API and the fact that on Chrome OS specifically,
you're always signed into the browser. So
for an app on Chrome OS, you shouldn't have
to sign in if you're using Google accounts.
Now, you may not be using Google accounts.
And the identity API has a solution for that.
It is called launchWebauthflow. So with that
API, you can pass in a third-party URL end
point for OAuth2. And under the hood, all
of the workings -- all of the workings happen.
A pop-up happens -- a pop-up is shown that
allows the user to log in.
Now, obviously, that doesn't solve the issue
of getting out of the way and not having a
dialogue; but if you are not using Google
accounts, which is a fair point, you need
a way to sign in the user to your app. And
that token can be persisted across instances
of the app.
So, for example, in this, in this code sample
here, we are calling getauthtoken and we are
storing that token. So for the lifetime of
the app, we don't have to keep calling getauthtoken.
We just have the token around and we build
this request with this token to, for example,
the photos back-end at Google. We will do
a request to read all of the photos of the
user.
And so what we've done is we have the token
stored. We just keep using this same token
for all of the requests in the app. It is
really easy to use.
So, like I said, I had a camera and I had
a SD card in it, and I plugged it in and the
right thing just happened. It is a photos
app. I have installed this app. I said, I
trust this app to do what I need it to do,
including the fact that it says it has access
to your media.
Currently, in the Web today, and in most native
apps as well, you have to select the media
specifically, say, by the file open dialogue,
which I consider the worst piece of UI in
browser history. It is awful. But everybody
has to go through that.
The alternative is Flash, but even then you
still have to do file, directory browsing,
et cetera. We wanted to get rid of that.
The solution to this was the media gallery
API which is like the pinnacle API of this
app. It is what makes this app pop. It's what
makes it real. The media galleries API allows
the developer to have access to media devices,
so SD cards, platform media, like my pictures
or the photos on a Mac.
And it has seamless access. You don't have
to ask the user at the time of app running,
at the app running, only at installation and
only that one time. So in this app, we have
UI that shows up a notification that says,
You just plugged in a card. We will start
uploading. And you have the ability to stop
the uploading, but that action happens right
away. The user doesn't have to wait; and the
user doesn't have to do the file open dialogue,
which is just awful.
So here's a little code snapshot of how to
use this. The API call is getmediafilesystems.
And if you're familiar with it, it returns
a DOM filesystem which has its own file entries
inside of that. It's directory structure.
You can read through this with the filesystem
API. So this is really neat. We don't have
-- we just had this one little layer on top
of the already-existing filesystem API that
restricts what is shown to the -- to the app
to just media locations.
For example, when I plugged in the SD card,
it knew that it had DSIM -- a DSIM folder
and we said, we think this is a media. It
is a simple heuristic, but it really solves
a lot of the -- 90% of the use cases that
we are looking for.
If you plugged in an external drive and it
had a DSIM directory, we would say that this
probably has photos on it as well and we would
start loading that.
So the first time I saw the Pixel screen,
it was detached from the actual laptop. It
was not even put together yet. It was this
little piece. And he said, You have to see
this, one of the developers of the Pixel.
And he showed it to me and it was just mind
blowing the picture he showed on it. I had
never seen something like this.
And then he started swiping it and moving
things around. The touch on this one screen,
it was just amazing.
And so you have the ability when writing apps
not just for this but, say, for tablets as
well, like high DPI tablets. You obviously
have Mac books that have high-retina display.
You want to make sure that you're optimizing
for these form factors which are becoming
more and more prevalent.
And for the high-resolution display, it is
not hard. You just provide 2X assets, high-resolution
assets. The API to do this is in CSS itself.
It is called Webkit Media Set, and you can
specify the multiplicative factors, so 1X
or 2X and you just pass in the right resource
through that.
One thing to keep in mind is that you want
to make sure to set the background size of
your asset to the low res. So we have this
closed icon, and it is 32 pixels in the low-res
asset. When we load the high-res asset, we
still want it to be 32 pixels on the -- 32
pixels on the screen so that doesn't blow
up unproportionally. We just have it more
dense inside of those 32 pixels.
You want to make sure you do this, especially
if your user is going to be on a high-resolution
display, because on most browsers, and definitely
in Chrome, the scaling algorithm for images
to scale up to high resolution is optimized
for speed, not quality. You'll get very blurry
images. And, you know, your user is going
to get a headache after a while. It looks
really bad.
We had a regression one time where the high-resolution
assets were not being loaded properly and
everybody was like, Oh, my gosh. This is -- this
is awful. Something is clearly wrong with
this app. Imagine if your user saw that and
they not expecting it, they just know something
is wrong.
And to touch support, this is a really fun
thing to touch. And they always say, you know,
why would you touch this -- this laptop screen?
People don't want to reach over their keyboard
to do it. But the more you use this, the more
you start touching everything around you.
Like, you reach over everything. I touch my
work 32-inch monitor expecting it to do something
and it doesn't. It is extremely frustrating.
More and more displays are going to be touch,
whether it's a hybrid, whether it can be converted,
et cetera.
Your app should really handle, if not touch
gestures specifically, like, dragging and
touchstart, touchend, to consider what your
user actions should be.
For example, consider the photos view. So
we have this photo here. I admit, I was in
the wrong when we were having this discussion.
I felt that we should have double clicked
to activate these objects. So if I wanted
to go into the single photo view for this
photo, I should have double click. And that
was me coming from wanting to have a more
native experience. And in native apps and
in the filesystem, browsing around things,
you double click to activate, for the most
part. And I thought that would be a more native
experience.
But then we had the issue of, well, what do
you do when you're tapping? Do you double
tap the screen? No. That doesn't work.
We could have it where you -- with the mouse
or a track pad that you double click. And
then with touch, you single click. But then
you have a very confusing UX. Your user doesn't
know what to do. And then they are going to
start doing the wrong thing the entire time.
They will start double touching the screen.
So the key take-away for this one is just
to consider that tap support is very important.
Users are going to start using tap and touchscreens.
And you don't necessarily have to have full
touch support. Just think about what your
UX is going to be.
I know a lot of you are engineers. Maybe some
of you are designers in UX. But it is all
of our responsibility to create the best-looking
app.
So on to security, that last principle. This
section, you know, it can come off a little
dry. It's kind of difficult to deal with.
But security's extremely important for the
user. And there are a lot of things in the
platform that at first feel like you have
to deal with; but at the end, assuming you
start designing the app the right way from
the beginning, you are much better off. Your
user is much safer.
So content security policy is this essentially
whitelist, blacklist that says your app has
access to these resources, these remote URLs,
these domains, et cetera. And by default,
you really don't have access to hardly anything
at all. As you are adding a whitelist for
resources your app shouldn't have access to,
you know, you consider, like, your back-end
server. You obviously need access to that
and nothing else.
So if an attacker gets ahold of your app,
something gets injected and starts making
requests to some malicious server, those requests
are going to be denied because they are blocked
by content security policy.
The key thing here is to start designing your
app from the very beginning with content security
policy in mind. You can't load remote scripts.
You can't use eval. And for this, this was
kind of a problem because we -- we're getting
JSON objects back from the server. And so
we had to translate those into objects using
eval, and we couldn't do that.
So what we ended up doing was having a Sandboxed
iframe that had the use of eval inside of
it and we passed the JSON objects into this
iframe. It would do the eval, get the object
back, and then post a message back to the
app, this object. So if something malicious
goes on, the eval is going wonky, that Sandbox
iframe has no permissions whatsoever. All
it can do is communicate back and forth. So
you are pretty safe as far as that goes.
Making requests. So you can't say image source
equal remote. You actually have to pull down
the bits for that image. All of these photos
we have to pull them down from the server.
XMLHttpRequest is the way we do this. You
just create your URL for the request, send
it off. You get your response. You should
save it in your data layer obviously. And
then once you get that, the UI -- the data
gets bubbled up through your UI.
Another tip as far as thinking what you should
do from the beginning, designing from the
beginning, resource compilation comes in very
handy with packaged apps. We particularly
use closure, but there are a lot of tools
that you can use to do the same thing.
You're going to say essentially in your main
HTML of the packaged app script equals some
local file. So you could say a bunch of local
files, but it is a lot easier to just have
your code compiled, have if minified, et cetera,
and say script equals this local file.
So to wrap it up, we look back at what our
goals were, and I think we really achieved
those goals. We identified holes in the platform,
APIs that were missing. We added media gallery
APIs.
We tested a lot of features from Google+ Photos.
We got autocuration working really well. And
we just pushed the platform to its limits.
How far can you go with this? How hard is
it for developers to use this? I think the
answer is not very hard.
The biggest thing you have to do is to understand
your constraints from the very beginning,
understand that you don't have access to remote
URLs. Understand that if you want fast scrolling,
you need to scroll your body.
Obviously, the platform is constantly changing.
Things are being fixed. I know I've reached
out to the GPU team a lot to say, "This is
not easy enough. We have to fix this." And
just imagine the evolution that's happening
right now. You can see it at I/O.
This platform is just moving forward at this
speed of light, the things that you're going
to be able to do. It's getting a lot easier,
and it is getting a lot better.
So packaged apps, yeah, we definitely want
that. And I think the way to think about it
in terms of how does it relate to Web apps
is that you could have the core of your app
have functionality that is available cross-platform,
is not necessarily specific to Chrome, doesn't
have these extended APIs and permissions that
are requested. And in doing that, you are
going to have a lot safer API.
For example, you got to use XMLHttpRequest.
You are going to have content security policy
support, all of that from the get-go. And
that's just your core bundle.
Layered on top of this is all the goodies
that you get from the platform. You get the
identity API, so use it. If you have it, use
it. You get media galleries API, use it. And
if not, degrade gracefully. And this is how
if you build your app, whether it is for Chrome
packaged apps specifically or if you are going
to deploy it on the Web across multiple browsers,
if you do this, you can have one product that
can work on multiple platforms. And on some
platforms, it just has more functionality.
We've done that with Google+ Photos Chrome
app, and we think it is working out really
well.
So I actually think we don't have time for
questions. We only have about a minute left.
But I will be at the office hours bar if you
want to come by and ask any questions you
have. It has been a real pleasure. Thank you
very much for attending, and hope to see you
guys soon.
[ Applause ]