>>Justin Uberti: Hi, everyone. Thanks for
coming to the session on WebRTC for plugin-free
realtime communication. I'm Justin Uberti,
tech lead for WebRTC at Google, and with me
today is -- hey, has anyone seen Sam? -- Sam
Dutton, coming to you live from WebRTC on
Chrome for Android.
[ Applause ]
>>Sam Dutton: On a beautiful Nexus 7.
We got this slow res to cope with the WiFi
here, but it seems to be working pretty well.
>>Justin Uberti: That was quite an entrance.
Why don't you come up here and introduce yourself.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah. Hey, I'm Sam Dutton. I'm
a developer advocate for Chrome.
>>Justin Uberti: So we're here to talk to
you today about the great things that WebRTC
has been working on and how you can use them.
So what is WebRTC?
Well, in a nutshell, it's what we call realtime
communication, RTC. The ability to communicate
live with somebody or something as if you
were right there next to them. And this can
mean audio, video, or even just peer-to-peer
data.
And we think WebRTC is really cool. But there's
a lot of other people who are really excited
about WebRTC as well, and one of the reasons
is that WebRTC fills a critical gap in the
web platform, where previously in a native
proprietary app like Skype could do something
the web just couldn't. But now we've turned
that around and changed that so we have a
web of connected WebRTC devices that can communicate
in real time just by loading a Web page.
So here's what we're trying to do with WebRTC.
To build the key APIs for realtime communication
into the web.
To make an amazing media stack in Chrome so
that developers can build great experiences.
And to use this network of connected WebRTC
devices to create a new communications ecosystem.
And these kind of seem like lofty goals, but
take this quote from the current CTO of the
FCC, who says he sees traditional telephony
fading away as voice just becomes another
Webapp.
So we're trying to live up to that promise,
and right now you can build a single app with
WebRTC that connects Chrome, Chrome for Android,
Firefox, and very soon Opera.
I'm especially excited to announce that as
of this week Firefox 22 has gone to beta,
which is the very first WebRTC-enabled version
of Firefox.
So within a matter of weeks, we will have
over 1 billion users using a WebRTC-enabled
browser.
[ Cheers and applause ]
>>Justin Uberti: And I think that just kind
of gives like a good idea of the size of the
opportunity here.
And we expect that number to grow very significantly
as both Chrome and Firefox get increased adoption.
For places where we don't have WebRTC-enabled
browsers, we're providing native supported
official toolkits on both Android and very
soon iOS that can interoperate with WebRTC
in the browser.
[ Applause ]
>>Justin Uberti: So here are just a handful
of the companies that see the opportunity
in WebRTC and are building their business
around it.
So that's the vision for WebRTC. Now let's
dig into the APIs.
There are three main categories of API that
exist in WebRTC.
First, getting access to input devices. Accessing
the microphone, accessing the webcam, getting
a stream of media from either of them.
Secondly, being able to connect to another
WebRTC endpoint across the Internet and to
send this audio and video in real time.
And third, the ability to do this not just
for audio and video but for arbitrary application
data. And we think this one is especially
interesting.
So because of three categories, we have three
objects, three primary objects in WebRTC to
access this stuff.
The first one, MediaStream, is for getting
access to media, then RTCPeerConnection and
RTCDataChannel. And we'll get into each one
of these individually.
Sam, why don't you tell us about MediaStream.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah. Sure. So MediaStream.
It represents like a single source of synchronized
audio or video or both. Each media stream
contains one or more MediaStream tracks. You
know, for example, on your -- like your laptop,
you've got a webcam and a microphone providing
video and audio streams, and they're synchronized.
We get access to these local devices using
the getUserMedia method of navigator, so we'll
just look at the code for that, just highlight
that.
And you can see the getUserMedia there. It
takes three parameters, three arguments there,
and the first one, if we look at the constraints
argument I've got, you can see I'm just specifying
I want video. That's all I'm saying. "Just
give me video, nothing else."
And then in the success callback, we're setting
the source of the video using the stream that's
returned by getUserMedia.
Now, let's see that in action.
A really simple example here.
And you can see when we fire the getUserMedia
method, we get the allow permissions bar at
the top there.
Now, this means that users have to explicitly
opt in to allowing access to their microphone
and camera.
And yeah, there we have it. Using that code,
we've got video displayed in a video element.
Great.
What really excites me about these APIs, you
know, is when they kind of come up against
each other. Like in this example, what's happening
is that we've got getUserMedia being piped
into a Canvas element, and then the Canvas
element being analyzed and then producing
ASCII, just like that. That might be a good
codec.
>>Justin Uberti: Yeah. That would be a good
codec. You can just compress it. You can use
gzip.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah. Smaller font sizes, higher
resolution.
>>Justin Uberti: Yeah.
>>Sam Dutton: Also another example is from
Facekat. Now what's happening here is that
it's using the head tracker JavaScript library
to track the position of my head. And when
I move around, you can see I'm moving through
the game and trying to stay alive, which is
quite difficult. This is painful. Anyway...
[ Laughter ]
>>Sam Dutton: Whoa! Okay. I think I've flipped
into hyperspace there.
And an old favorite you may well have seen,
Webcam Toy which gives us access to the camera,
kind of a photo booth app, uses WebGL to create
a bunch of slightly psychedelic effects there,
quite like this old movie one. So I'll take
that and, yeah, get a snapshot. And I can
share that with my friends. So beautiful work
from Paul (saying name) there.
Now, you might remember I said that we could
use the constraints object. The simple example
there was just saying, you know, "Use the
video, nothing else."
Well, we can do more interesting things with
constraints than that. We can do stuff like
specify the resolution or the frame rate,
a whole stack of things that we want from
our local devices.
A little example from that. If we go over
here, now this is with the code, actually.
If we go to the DevTools there, you can see
that I've got three different constraints
objects, one for each resolution.
So when I press the buttons, I use the QVGA
constraints, getUserMedia, and then with the
VGA one, I'm getting high-resolution, and
for HD, I'm getting the full 1280 by 720.
We can also use getUserMedia now for input
from our microphone.
In other words, we can use getUserMedia to
provide a source node for Web Audio, and there's
a huge amount of interesting stuff we can
do without processing audio using web audio
from the mic or wherever.
A little example of that here. I'll just allow
access to the mic and you can see I'm getting
a nice little visualization there in the Canvas
element, and I can start to record this, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, and then --
>>> To record this, blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah.
>>Sam Dutton: And, yeah, you can see that's
-- you record a JS to save that locally to
disk.
GetUserMedia also now -- this is kind of experimental,
but we can use getUserMedia to get a screen
capture. In other words, data coming directly
from what we see on screen, not from the audio/video
from the mic and the camera.
Probably the simplest if I show an example
of this.
So, yeah, a little application here and when
I click to make the call, allow, and you can
see there that I get this kind of crazy hall
of mirrors effect because, you know, I'm capturing
the screen that I'm capturing and so on and
so on.
Now, that's quite nice, but it would be really
useful if we could take that screen capture
and then, you know, transmit that to another
computer. And for that, we have RTCPeerConnection.
>>Justin Uberti: Thanks, Sam.
So as the name implies, RTCPeerConnection
is all about making a connection to another
peer. And over this peer connection, we can
actually then go and send audio and video.
And the way we do this is we take the media
streams that we've gotten from getUserMedia
and we plug them into the peer connection
and send them off to the other side.
When the other side receives them, they'll
pop out as a new media stream on their peer
connection and they can then plug that into
a video element to display on the page. And
so both sides have a peer connection, they
both get streams from getUserMedia, they plug
them in and then those media streams pop out
magically encoded and decoded on the other
side.
Now, under the hood, peer connection is doing
a ton of stuff. Signal processing to remove
noise from audio and video. Codec selection
and compression and decompression of the actual
audio and video. Finding the actually peer-to-peer
route, through firewalls, through NATs, through
relays. Encrypting the data so that the user's
data is fully protected at all times. And
then actually managing the bandwidth so that
if you have 2 megabits, we use it, if you
have 200 kilobits, that's all we use. But
we do everything we can to hide this complexity
from that web developer. And so the main thing
is that you get your media streams, you plug
them in via add stream to peer connection,
and off you go. And here's a real example
of that this.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah. So you can see here that
we've created a new RTCPeerConnection, and
then when the stream is received, the callback
for that in GotRemoteStream there attaches
the media we're getting from a video element
to the stream.
Now, at the same time, we're also creating
what's called an offer, giving information
about media and we're setting that as the
local description, and then sending that to
the callee, so that they can set the remote
description. You can see that in the got answer
function there.
Let's have a little look at RTCPeerConnection
on one page. A very simple example here.
So what we've got here is getUserMedia here.
Just start that up. So it's getting video
from the local camera here, displaying it
on the left there.
Now, when I press "call," it's using RTCPeerConnection
to communicate that video to the other -- yeah,
the other video element on the page there.
This is a great place to start to get your
head around RTCPeerConnection.
And if we look in the code there, you can
see that, you know, it's really simple. There's
not a lot of code there to do that, to transmit
video from one peer to another.
>>Justin Uberti: So that's very cool stuff.
You know, a full video chat client in a single
Web page in just about 15 lines of JavaScript.
And we talked a little bit quickly through
the whole thing around how we set up the parameters
for the call, the offers and answers, but
I'll come back to that later.
The next thing I want to talk about is RTCDataChannel,
and this says "If we have a peer connection
which already creates our peer-to-peer link
for us, can we send arbitrary application
data over it?"
And this is the mechanism that we use to do
so.
Now, one example where we would do this would
be in a game. Like take this game. I think
it's called Jank Wars or something. And we
have all these ships floating around the screen.
Now, when a ship moves, we want to make sure
that's communicated to the other player as
quickly as possible, and so we have this little
json object that kind of contains the parameters
and the position and the velocity of the ships,
and we can just take that object and stuff
it into the send method and it will shoot
it across to the other side where it pops
out as on message.
And the other side can do the same thing.
It can call send on its DataChannel and it
works pretty much like a WebSocket. That's
not an accident. You know, we tried to design
it that way so that people familiar with using
WebSockets could also use a similar API for
RTCDataChannel. And the benefit is that here
we have a peer-to-peer connection for the
lowest possible latency for doing this communication.
In addition, RTCDataChannel can be either
unreliable or reliable, and we can think about
this kind of like UDP versus TCP.
If you're doing a game, it's more important
that your packets get there quickly, than
they're guaranteed to get there. Whereas if
you're doing a file transfer, the files are
only any good if the entire file is delivered.
So you can choose this, as the app developer,
which method you want to use, either unreliable
or reliable.
And lastly, everything is fully secure. We
use standard DTLS encryption to make sure
that the packages you sent across the DataChannel
are fully encrypted on their way to the destination.
And you can do this either with audio and
video, or if you want to make a peer connection
for just data, you can do that as well.
So Sam's going to show us how this actually
works.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah. So again, another really
simple example. We're creating a peer connection
here, and once the DataChannel is received,
in the callback to that we're setting the
receive channel using the event.channel object.
Now, when the receive channel gets a message,
kind of like WebSocket, really, we're just
putting some text in a local div there using
event.data.
Now, the send channel is created with create
DataChannel, and then we've got a send button
and when that's clicked, we get the data from
a text area, and we use the send channel to
send that to the other peer.
Again, let's see this in action.
This is, again, a good place to start, a one-page
demo with all the code for RTCDataChannel,
so type in some text, and we hit "send," and
it's transmitting it to the other text area.
A great place to start if you're looking at
RTCDataChannel.
Something a little more useful here, a great
app from sort of Sharefest. Now, Sharefest
is using RTCDataChannel to enable us to do
file sharing. I'm going to select a nice photo
here I've got of some cherries, and it's popeye
is the URL.
Now, Justin is going to try and get that up
on the screen on his side, just to check that
that's gone through.
So like I say, this is doing file sharing
using RTCDataChannel and there's a huge amount
of potential. There we go. There's the --
>>Justin Uberti: I love cherries.
>>Sam Dutton: Good. These are beautiful Mountain
View cherries, actually. They're really, really
nice.
>>Justin Uberti: All this data is being sent
peer to peer, and anybody else who connects
to the same URL will download that data peer
to peer from Sam's machine. And so none of
this has to touch Sharefest servers. And I
think that's pretty interesting, if you think
about things like file transfer, bulk video
distribution.
Okay. So we talked a lot about how we can
do really clever peer-to-peer stuff with RTCPeerConnection,
but it turns out we need servers to kind of
get the process kicked off.
And the first part of it is actually making
sure that both sides can agree to actually
conduct the session. And this is the process
that we call "signaling."
The signaling in WebRTC is abstract, which
means that there's no fully defined protocol
exactly how you do it. The key part is that
you just have to exchange session description
objects, and if you think about this kind
of like a telephone call, when you make a
call to someone, the telephone network sends
a message to the person you're calling telling
them there's an incoming call and the phone
should ring.
Then when they answer the call, they send
a message back that says "The call is now
active." Now, these messages also contain
parameters around like what media format to
use, where the person is on the network. And
the same is true for WebRTC.
And these things, these session description
objects, contain parameters like what codecs
to use, what security keys to use, the network
information for setting up the peer-to-peer
route. And the only important thing is that
you just send it from your side to the other
side and vice versa. You can use any mechanism
you want. WebSockets, Google cloud messaging,
XHR. You can use any protocol. You can just
send it as json or you can use a standard
protocol like SIP or XMTP. And here's a picture
of how this all works.
The app gets a session description from the
browser and sends it across through the cloud
to the other side. Once it gets the message
back from the other side with the other side's
session description, and both session descriptions
are passed down to WebRTC in the browser,
WebRTC can then set up and conduct the media
link peer to peer.
So we do a lot to try to hide the details
of what's inside the RTC session description
because this includes a whole bunch of parameters.
As I said, codecs, network information, all
sorts of stuff. This is just a snippet of
what's contained inside a session description
right now.
Really advanced apps can do complex behaviors
by modifying this, but we've designed the
API so that regular apps just don't have to
think about it.
The other thing that we need service for is
to actually get the peer-to-peer session fully
routed, and in the old days, this wouldn't
be a problem. A long time ago, each side had
a public IP address, they send each other's
IP address to each other through the cloud,
and we make the link directly between the
peers.
Well, in the age of NAT, things are more complicated.
NATs hand out what's called a private IP address,
and these IP addresses are not useful for
communication. There's no way we can make
the link actually peer-to-peer unless we have
a public address.
So this is where we bring a technology called
STUN. The STUN server, we contact from WebRTC,
and we say, "What's my public IP address?"
And basically the request comes in to the
STUN server, it sees the address that that
request came from, puts that address into
the packet and sends it back, so now WebRTC
knows its public IP address and the STUN server
doesn't have to be in the party anymore. It
doesn't have to have media flowing through
it.
So here if we look at this example, each side
is contacted its STUN server to find out what
its public I.P. address is and then sent the
traffic to the other I.P. address through
its NAT and the data still flows peer-to-peer.
So this is kind of magic stuff, and it usually
works.
Usually, we can make sure that, you know,
the data all flows properly peer-to-peer but
not in every case.
And for that, we have a technology called
TURN built into RTC. This turns things around
and provides a cloud fallback when a peer-to-peer
link is impossible. You basically ask for
a relay in the cloud saying, Give me a public
address and because this public address is
in the cloud, anybody can contact it which
means the call always sets up, even if you
are behind a restrictive NAT or even behind
a proxy.
The downside is since the data is actually
being relayed through the server, there is
an operational cost to it, but it does mean
the call works in almost all environments.
Now, on one hand, we have STUN which is super
cheap but doesn't always work. And we have
TURN which always works but has some costs
to it. How do we make sure we get the best
of both worlds?
Here is TURN in action where we tried to use
STUN and STUN didn't work. We couldn't get
the things to actually penetrate the NATs.
So instead we fell back and only then did
we use TURN and sent the media from one peer
through the NAT, through the TURN server and
to the other side. This is all done by technology
called ICE. ICE knows about STUN and TURN
and tries all the things in parallel to figure
out the best path for the call. If it can
do STUN, it does STUN. If it can do TURN,
well, then it will fall to TURN but it will
do so quickly.
We have stats from a deploy WebRTC application
which says 86% of the time we can make things
work with just STUN. So only one out of seven
calls actually have to run through a TURN
server.
How do you deploy TURN for your application?
We have some testing servers, testing STUN
server that you can use. Plus, we make source
code available for our own STUN and TURN servers
as part of the WebRTC code package.
The ting I would really recommend is the long
name but really good product rfc5766-turn-server,
which has Amazon VM images that you can just
take, download, and deploy into the cloud
and you have got your TURN server provision
for all your users right there. You can also
recommend restund, another TURN server that
we have used with excellent results.
One question that comes up around WebRTC is:
How is security handled? And the great thing
is that security has been built into WebRTC
from the very beginning. And so this means
several different things.
It means we have mandatory encryption for
both media and data. So all the data that's
being sent by WebRTC is being encrypted using
standard AES encryption.
We also have secure UI. I mean, the user's
camera and microphone can only be accessed
if they have explicitly opt in to making that
functionality available.
And, last, WebRTC runs inside the Chrome Sandbox.
So even if somebody tries to attack WebRTC
inside of Chrome, the browser and the user
will be fully protected.
So here's what you need to do to take advantage
of the security in WebRTC, is really simple.
Your app just needs to use HTTPS for actually
doing the signaling. As long as the signaling
goes over a security conduit, the data will
be fully secured as well using the standard
protocols of SRTP for media or datagram TLS
for the DataChannel.
One more question that comes up is around
making a multi-party call, a conference call.
How should I architect my application?
In the simple two-party case, it is really
simple -- it is easy. We just have a peer-to-peer
link. But as we start adding more peers into
the mix, things get a bit more complicated
and one approach that people use is a mesh
where basically every peer connects to every
other peer. And this is really simple because
there's no servers or anything involved other
than the signaling stuff. But every peer has
to send a copy of its data to every other
peer. So this has a corresponding CPU and
bandwidth cost. So depending on the media
you are trying to send, for audio, it can
be kind of higher, for video, it is going
to be less, the number of peers you can support
in this topology, you know, is fairly limited
especially if one of the peers is on a mobile
device.
To deal with that, another architecture that
can be used is the star architecture. And
here you can pick the most capable device
to be what we call the focus for the call.
And the focus is the part that's actually
responsible for taking the data and sending
a copy to each of the other end points.
But as we get to handing multiple HD video
streams, the job for a focus becomes pretty
difficult. And so for the most robust conferencing
architecture, we recommend an MCU, our multi-point
control unit. And this is a server that's
custom made for relaying large amounts of
audio and video. It can do various things.
It can do -- select a stream forwarding. It
can actually mix the audio or video data.
It can also do things like recording.
And so if one peer drops out, it doesn't interrupt
the whole conference because the MCU is taking
care of everything.
So WebRTC is made with standards in mind.
So you connect with things that aren't even
WebRTC devices. And one thing that people
might want to talk to you from WebRTC is phones.
There is a bunch of easy things you can drop
into your Web page to make this happen. There
is sipML5, which is a way to talk to various
standard SIP devices, Photo, and what we are
going to show you now, a widget from Zingaya
to make a phone call.
>>Sam Dutton: Okay. So we got a special guest
joining us a little bit later in the presentation.
I just want to give him a call to see if he's
available. So let's use the Zingaya WebRTC
phone app now and you can see it's asking
for access to my microphone. Calling someone.
I hope it is the person I want. We'll see
if he's there.
>>> Hello?
>>Sam Dutton: Hey. Is that you, Chris?
>>> Hey, Sam, how's it going? It is.
>>Sam Dutton: Fantastic. I just wanted to
check if you are ready for your gig later
on?
>>> I'm ready whenever you are.
>>Sam Dutton: That's fantastic. Okay. Speak
to you soon, Chris. Thanks. Bye-bye.
>>> Talk to you soon. Bye.
>>Sam Dutton: Cheers.
>>Justin Uberti: No plug-ins, realtime communication.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah, well, that situation,
we had a guy with a telephone.
You know, something we were thinking about
is situations where there is no telephone
network. Now, Voxio demonstrated this with
something called Tethr, which is disaster
communications in a box. Uses the open VGS
cell framework. You can see it is that little
box there to enable calls between feature
phones via the open PTS cell through WebRTC
to computers.
You can imagine this is kind of fun to get
a license for this in downtown San Francisco,
but this is incredibly useful in situations
where there is no infrastructure. Yeah, this
is like telephony without a carrier. Just
amazing.
>>Justin Uberti: So we have a codelab this
afternoon that I hope you can come to where
we will really go into the details of exactly
how to build a WebRTC application.
But now we are going to talk about some resources
that I think are really useful.
The first one is something called WebRTC internals.
And this is a page you can open up just by
going to this URL while you are in a WebRTC
call. And it will show all sorts of great
statistics about what's actually happening
inside your call. You know, this will be things
like packet loss, bandwidth, video resolution,
and sizes and there is also a full log of
all the calls made to the WebRTC API that
you can download and export.
So if a customer is reporting problems with
their call, you can easily get this debugging
information from them.
Another thing is the WebRTC spec has been
updating fairly rapidly. And so in a given
browser, the API might not always match the
latest spec. Adapter.js is something that's
there to instantly update the Web developer
with the differences between browsers and
the differences between versions.
So we make sure that adapter.js always implements
the latest spec and it thunks down to whatever
the version supports. So as new APIs are added,
we polyfill them to make sure you don't have
to write custom version code or custom browser
code for each browser. And we use this in
our own applications.
>>Sam Dutton: Okay. If all this is too much
for you, good news is we got some fantastic
JavaScript frameworks come up in the last
few months, really great abstraction libraries
to make it really, really simple to build
WebRTC apps, just with a few lines of code.
Example here from SimpleWebRTC, a little bit
of JavaScript there to specify a video element
that represents local video and one that represents
the remote video stream coming in. And then
join a room just by calling the join room
method with a room name. Really, really simple.
Peerjs does something similar for RTC DataChannel.
Create a peer and then on connection, you
can send messages and receive messages. So
really, really easy to use.
>>Justin Uberti: So, JavaScript frameworks
go a long way. They don't cover the production
aspects of the service, the signaling, the
STUN and TURN servers we talked about. Fortunately,
we have things from Opentok and vline which
are turn-key RTC services and they handle
all this stuff for you. You get an API key,
and then you can make calls using their production
infrastructure, which is spread throughout
the entire globe.
They also make UI widgets that can be easily
dropped into your RTC app. So you can get
up and running with WebRTC super fast.
Now we have got a special treat for you today.
Chris Wilson, a colleague of ours a developer
on the original Mosaic browser and an occasional
musician as well, is going to be joining us
courtesy of WebRTC to show off the HD video
quality and full-band audio quality that we
are now able to offer in the latest version
of Chrome.
Take it away, Chris.
>>> Hey, guys.
>>Sam Dutton: Hey, Chris, how's it going?
>>> I'm good. How are you?
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah, good, good. Have you got
some kind of musical instrument with you?
>>> I do. Originally, you asked me for a face-melting
guitar solo.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah, yeah.
>>> I'm a little more relaxed now. I/O is
starting to wind down. You can tell I have
already got my Hawaiian shirt on and I'm ready
for some vacation. So I figured I would bring
my ukulele and hook it up through a nice microphone
here so we can listen to how it sounds.
>>Sam Dutton: Take it away. Melt my face,
Chris.
[ Laughter ]
[ Music ]
>>Sam Dutton: He's pretty good.
>>Justin Uberti: He is pretty good.
>>Sam Dutton: All right. That was beautiful.
Thank you, Chris.
[ Applause ]
>>Justin Uberti: Chris Wilson, everybody.
>>Sam Dutton: The audience is going crazy,
Chris. Thank you very much.
So we have had a fraction of 30 minutes to
cover a really big topic.
There is a great, a lot more information out
there online. Some good stuff on html5rocks
and a really good e-book, too, if you want
to take a look at that. There are several
ways to contact us. There is a great Google
group, discuss WebRTC. You can post your technical
questions. All the kind of new news for WebRTC
comes through on Google+ and Twitter stream.
And, you know, we're really grateful to all
the people, all of you, who have submitted
feature requests and bugs and please keep
them coming. And the URL for that is crbug.com/new.
So thank you for that.
[ Applause ]
>>Justin Uberti: So -- and so we've built
this stuff into the Web platform to make realtime
communication accessible to everyone. And
we're super excited because we can't wait
to see what you all are going to build. So
thank you for coming.
Once again, the slide link. And now if you
have any questions, we will be happy to try
to answer them. Thank you very much.
>>Sam Dutton: Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>>> Hi, my name is Mark.
>>Justin Uberti: Hi, Mark.
>>> I would like to know, because I'm using
Linux and I want to, how, finally, can I get
rid of the talk plug-in for using Hangouts
in Google+?
>>Justin Uberti: So the question was when
can we get rid of the Hangouts plug-in? And
so, unfortunately, like, we can only talk
about WebRTC matters today. That's handled
by another team.
But let's say there are many of us who have
the same feeling.
>>> Okay.
[ Laughter ]
>>> Can you make any comments on Microsoft's
competing standard? Considering they kind
of hold the cards with Skype and how maybe
we can go forward supporting both or maybe
converge the two or just your thoughts on
that.
>>Justin Uberti: So Microsoft has actually
been very -- a great participant in standards.
They have several people they send from their
team. And, you know, although they don't see
things exactly the same way that we do, I
think that the API differences are sort of
theirs is a little more low level, geared
for expert developers. Ours are a little more
high-level, geared for Web developers. I think
really what you can do is you can implement
the high-level one on top of the low-level
one, maybe even vice versa.
So, like, Microsoft, you know, is a little
more secretive about what they do. So we don't
know exactly what their time frame is relative
to IE. They are fully participating, and,
obviously, they are interested in with Skype.
I'm optimistic that we will see a version
of IE that supports this technology in the
not-too-distant future.
>>> Very good to hear. Thank you.
>>> My question would be I think you mentioned
it quickly in the beginning, so if I wanted
to communicate with WebRTC but, one, I'm using
a different environment than the browser,
let's say I want the Web application to speak
to a native Android app, so what would be
the approach to integrate that with WebRTC?
>>Justin Uberti: So as I mentioned earlier,
we have a fully supported, official native
version of PeerConnection, peerconnection.java,
which is open source. And you can download
and you can build that into your native application
and it interoperates.
We have a demo app that interoperates with
our AppRTC demo app.
So, you know, I think that sort of using Chrome
for Android in a Web view is one thing you
can think about. If that doesn't work for
you, we have the native version that works
great.
>>> Okay, thank you.
>>> Hi. My question would be: Are there any
things to be taken care between cross-browser
compatibility for this Firefox, Chrome? Anything
specific that needs to be taken care of?
>>Justin Uberti: There's some minor differences.
I mentioned adapter.js covers some of the
sort of things where the API isn't quite in
sync in both places. One specific thing is
that Firefox only supports, like, the Opus
codec and they only support DTLS Encryption.
They don't support something called SDES that
we also support.
So for right now, you have to set, like, one
parameter in the API. And you can see that
in the -- in our AppRTC source code to make
sure that communication actually uses this
compatible protocol.
We actually have a document, though, on our
Web page. The document is exactly what you
have to do, which is really setting a single
constraint parameter when you are creating
your PeerConnection object.
>>Sam Dutton: If you go to webrtc.org/interop.
>>Justin Uberti: Webrtc.org/interop.
>>> Okay, thank you.
>>> When a PeerConnection is made and it falls
back to TURN, does the TURN server, is it
capable of unencrypting the messages that
go between the two end points?
>>Justin Uberti: No, The TURN server is just
a packet relay. So the stuff is fully encrypted.
It doesn't have the keying information to
do anything to it. So the TURN server just
takes a byte, sends a byte, takes a packet,
sends a packet.
>>> So for keeping data in sync with low latency
between, say, an Android application and the
server, how would the -- both the native and
the HTML5 -- or the Android Chrome implementations
of WebRTC fare in terms of battery life?
>>Justin Uberti: I don't really have a good
answer for that. I wouldn't think there would
be much difference. I mean, the key things
that are going to be driving battery consumption
in this case -- are you talking about data
or are you talking about audio and video?
>>> Data.
>>Justin Uberti: For data, the key drivers
for your power consumption are going to be
the screen and the network. So I think those
should be comparable between Chrome for Android
and in the native application.
>>> Okay, cool. Thanks.
>>> With two computers running Chrome, what
-- have you seen glass-to-glass latency?
>>Justin Uberti: Repeat?
>>> Glass-to-glass latency, so from the camera
to the opacity.
>>Justin Uberti: Oh, yeah. So it depends on
the platform because, like, the camera can
have a large delay built into it itself. And,
also, some things -- some of the audio things
have, you know, higher latencies than others.
But the overall target is 150 milliseconds
end to end. And we've seen lower than 100
milliseconds in best-case solutions for glass-to-glass-type
latency.
>>> Okay. And how are you ensuring priority
of your data across the network?
>>Justin Uberti: Okay. So that's a complex
question with a long answer. But the basic
thing -- are you saying how do we compete
with, like, cat videos?
>>> No. Within the WebRTC, are you -- how
are you tagging your packets?
>>Justin Uberti: Right.
>>> Or otherwise.
>>Justin Uberti: There is something called
DSCP where we can mark QUOS bits. And this
isn't yet implemented in WebRTC, but it is
on the roadmap to be able to tag things like
audio as higher priority than, say, video
and that has a higher priority than cat videos.
>>> So it is not done today, but it will be
done?
>>Justin Uberti: It will be done. We also
have things for doing, like, FEC-type mechanisms
to, you know, protect things at the application
layer. But the expectation is that, you know,
as WebRTC becomes more pervasive, carriers
will support DSCP at least on the bit from
coming off the computer and going onto their
network.
We have seen the DSCP does help going through
WiFi access points because WiFi access points
do give priority to DSCP-marked traffic.
>>> Thank you.
>>> So in Chrome for iOS being limited to
UI Web view and with other restrictions, how
much of WebRTC will you be able to implement?
>>Justin Uberti: So that's a really interesting
question. You know, they haven't made it easy
for us, but the Chrome for iOS team has already
done some amazing things to deliver the Chrome
experience that exists there now. And so we're
pretty optimistic that one way or another,
we can find some way to make that work. No
commitment to time frame, though.
>>> What are the mechanisms for saving video
and audio that's broadcast with WebRTC? Like
record -- like, making video recordings from
it?
>>Justin Uberti: So if you have the media
stream, you can then take the media stream
and plug it into things like the Web audio
API where you can actually get the raw samples
and then make a wav file and then save that
out.
On the video side, you can go into a canvas
and extract the frames from a canvas and you
can save it. There isn't really way to sort
of save it as, like, a .mp4, .webm file yet.
But if you want to make a thing that just
captures audio from the computer and it stores
on the server, you can basically make a custom
server that can do that recording. That's
one option.
>>> So the TURN server is open -- but you
said the TURN server doesn't capture, act
as an end point. Do you have server technology
that acts as an end point?
>>Justin Uberti: There are people building
this sort of stuff. Vline might be one particular
vendor who does this. But there is something
where you can basically have an MCU and the
MCU that receives the media can do things
like compositing or recording of that media.
>>> Presumably, the libraries for Java or
Objective C can be user to create a server
implementation?
>>Justin Uberti: Exactly. That's what they're
doing.
>>> Kind of a two-part question that has to
do around codec specifically on the video
side. Currently VP8, webm. Is there plans
for h.264 and also what's the time line?
>>Justin Uberti: Our plans around the VP family
of codec. So we support VP8 and VP9.
You may have heard that is sort of trying
to finalize the bit stream right now. So we
are very much looking forward to taking advantage
of VP9 with all of its sort of new coding
techniques once it is both finished and also
optimized for realtime average.
>>> And h.264 not really on the plane?
>>Justin Uberti: We think VP9 provides much
better sort of compression and overall performance
than h.264 so we have no plans for h.264 at
this time.
>>> I'm running WebRTC on Chrome for tablets.
How does it compare with native performance
like Hangouts on Android?
>>Justin Uberti: We think that we provide
a comparable performance to any native application
right now. We're always trying to make things
better. We still have Chrome for Android.
The WebRTC is behind a flag because we still
have work to do around improving audio, improving
some of the performance. We think we can deliver
equivalent performance in the Web browser.
And we are also working on taking advantage
of acceleration in cases where there is hardware
encoders like there is on Nexus 10 and making
that so we can get the same sort of down-to-the-metal
performance that you can get from a native
app.
>>> Thanks.
>>> So the Google Talk plug-in is using not
just h.264 but h.264 svc optimized for the
needs of video conferencing. Is VP8 and VP9
going to be similarly optimized, specifically
in an svc-like fashion for videoconferencing
versus just the version used for file encoding?
>>Justin Uberti: So VP8 already supports temporal
scalability and the S part of SVC. VP9 supports
additional scalability modes as well.
So we are very excited about the new coding
techniques that are coming in VP9.
>>> So we want to use WebRTC to do live streaming
from, let's say, cameras, hardware cameras
and one of the things, you know, we should
take care for such kind of an application.
And when you mentioned VP8 and VP9 support,
h.264 is not supported, assuming hardware
support is only h.264, (inaudible) can be
used with Chrome in that case?
>>Justin Uberti: We are building up support
for hardware VP8 and later VP9 encoders.
>>> Okay.
>>Justin Uberti: So, you know, you can make
a media streaming application like you described,
but we're expecting that all the major SSE
vendors are now shipping hardware with built-in
VP8 encoders and decoders.
So as this stuff gets into market, you are
going to see this stuff become, you know,
the most efficient way to record and compress
data.
>>> Okay. So the only way is to support VP8
in hardware right now for us, right?
>>Justin Uberti: If you want hardware -- if
you basically -- if you want hardware compression,
the only -- the only things we support right
now will be VP8 encoders.
>>> That's on the device side, you know, the
camera, which is, you know, is on the remote
computer.
>>Justin Uberti: If you are having encoding
from a device that you want to be decoded
within the browser, I would advise you to
do it in VP8.
>>> Thank you.
>>Justin Uberti: Thank you all for coming.
>>Sam Dutton: Yeah, thank you.
[ Applause ]