>>Pamela Fox: Hello.
>>>Group: Hello.
>>Pamela Fox: How are you? Okay, how are you?
Okay, good. I know this is the time in the
afternoon when you typically sleep. They did
just turn off the lights. I will try to be
as loud and obnoxious as possible to keep
you awake. My name is Pamela Fox. Today I
want to talk about feature detection in the
real world. This shit is going to get real.
You are in a Chrome track. Presumably you
are on the Chrome track and doing web development
stuff. You are probably all pretty excited
about HTML5, right? Whoo! HTML5 is awesome.
It is bringing us all these things that for
years and years we wanted as developers, and
we had to do all these crazy hacks in order
to do them. Finally the browsers are making
it really easy for us, right? I remember once
spending two months implementing rounded corners
on this little gadget back when I was working
at Google and finally getting it to work in
IE6 and then taking it to UX review with Marissa
to find out we didn't do rounded corners at
Google. So stuff like that, right? These days
it would take me one line of code to put a
boarder radius on there and then get it rejected
and life would go on. Right? HTML5 is great
because we get these new features, but we
are getting them incrementally. Right? We
have them in some browsers; we don't have
them in other browsers. We have kind of parts
of the features in some and they don't quite
work. So that means we actually have to worry
about whether particular feature is actually
supported, because most of us probably have
to actually develop things for multiple browsers.
If we could, we would probably just tell all
of our users, like, hey, just use Chrome.
I've tried that. Kind of works. So what do
we do? We think to ourself, all right. I want
to use this feature but first I need to see
if it is supported. How should I do that,
right? The obvious thing to do is to ask the
browser. Like, hey, I want to use this feature.
Do you use that, right? And we do that via
this technique we call feature detection.
Right? We have various ways of actually doing
feature detection. Here's examples, right?
If we want to know if a browser supports some
JavaScript API, we might ask does window.webkit
audio exist. If it does exist, then this browser
presumably this supports that JavaScript API.
If we are trying to see if a particular HTML
element works, right, we create the HTML element
and see if it gets attributes automatically
applied to it in the producers. Right? If
we want to know if a CSS works, we can create
an element and see if that style property
is actually a key on that element. And most
of us probably use Modernizr, which is a library
that does these detections for you behind
the scenes. And then you just ask Modernizr,
hey, does this work, right? So that feature
detection and it sounds like it's actually
really great, right? All we have to do is
say we want to use this feature. Just tell
the browser, hey, tell us if it works. Right?
So it's really, really awesome when it works.
Right? It's a great idea. However, it doesn't
always work. Right? Sometimes it's impossible
to detect a feature. Sometimes you get false
negatives, positive false, whatever you want
to call them, all those things. You need a
different plan. A lot of times what you do
instead is use user agent detection. Right?
And this is where we just look at the navigator.user
agent and we try to understand what device
and what browser a user is using. So a very
basic check here. If I want to know if they
are on a iPad or iPhone, I'm looking for iPhone
or iPod in that user agent doing a RegEx.
This is where we have a lot of RegExs, I hate
RegExs. I will never make one myself. They
get worse. Right? If I want to check for mobile
browsers, maybe the top mobile browsers. Right?
Here's a check that gets a bit more crazier
RegEx that going to get me maybe the top ten
mobile browsers. Right? But it's not that
simple. Right? There's a lot more browsers
out there and devices in the world. Especially
as you go international. I know a lot of you
are from outside of America. I'm sure you
have Android devices that I have never even
heard of, right? So if you really wanted to
check for every mobile browser, you get something
like this. I think this is from mobilebrowsersdetect.com
and as you can see, there's a the lot of mobile
browsers in the world. Right? Do you need
to check for all of them? I don't know. I
don't know what you are doing. This is an
example of how intense users agent sniffing
can be and we usually don't want to do user
agent sniffing for a couple of reasons. Right?
First of all, we have to write RegExs. I don't
know about you, but I don't like RegExs. It
is generally easy to get RegExs wrong. It
is also really easy to get user agents wrong.
User agents, they are this crazy strings that
browsers come up with and browsers are always
trying to fool developers into thinking that
they are not what they used to be, right?
So I think the new IE10 has gotten rid of
something in its user agent string that people
normally sniff for to find out if it is IE
because they don't want you thinking it is
IE because it's cool now, right? You didn't
get that note? And then some browsers, like,
if you are viewing IE with Chrome frame, it
will tell you Chrome in the user agent but
then Chrome frame might not actually be running
on a page. That's kind of confusing. Then,
of course, every user agent string isn't world
has Mozilla. That was the original. So user
agent detection can be really tricky. It also
means when you are detecting user agent, if
that user agent does come to support a feature,
you prematurely blocked it, right? If you
say, hey, Safari doesn't support this feature,
we're not going to use this feature in Safari,
and then Safari tomorrow comes out with a
release that supports that feature, you have
probably moved on to other things. The chance
that you are actually going to update that
bit of code that blocks Safari users is really
small, right? So we don't like user agent
detection because it is often not future thinking,
right? It can really easy leave us in a state
where parts of our site aren't working as
well when they actually could be, because
these browsers do move fast. But it is a tool
that we can use, right? So here's the thing.
We have these two tools, feature detection
and user agent sniffing. A lot of people will
tell you, hey, you've got to use feature detection,
you've got to use feature detection, that's
the only way. I definitely -- I do try to.
But I have run into all these cases where
it hasn't quite worked. I have had to use
other techniques instead. So I wanted to share
those with you so that hopefully when you
guys are working on, you know, using these
fancy new features yourself, you will know
what to look out for and you will know how
to react yourself so that you can spend less
time figuring out how to detect things and
just move time to making stuff happen, which
is what we all want to do, right? So let's
talk about a few cases. Localstorage is this
cool lightweight storage API. It's actually
supported in quite a few browsers now. It's
from the W3C web storage spec. And it's a
very simple key value store that you can access
from JavaScript and use to store and cache
data from your application, right? And I thought
it was really cool. So I wrote a library on
top of localstorage called lschache which
was inspired by mem cache which is a tool
we use on the server and would allow me to
store stuff in a localstorage with a particular
expiration and then they would automatically
get kicked out. In this library I thought
it was -- it would be responsible for of me
to actually check to see if localstorage worked
in the browser before I attempted to store
anything in it, right? So I needed to figure
out how to do this detection. So I started
off with the most basic thing I could do which
is, okay, is localstorage on window and not
null? Therefore, this browser supports the
localstorage API. That was my very naive first
attempt. But what happened is that you can
have localstorage supported by a browser.
It didn't mean you could actually use it.
Because it could be that the browser was currently
in incognito mode and doesn't let you store
localstorage. It could be that the localstorage
was over quota. It could be for whatever reason.
There was one version of iPad where they turned
it off. So the only way you can actually check
to see if localstorage works is to try to
use it the way you want to use it. So my localstorage
check then turned into this, which is, okay,
let's try to set an item in the cache and
remove the item from the cache and if we are
able to do that and we don't get any exceptions
during that time, then, okay, localstorage
works, right? So the only way I could actually
check this was to use it exactly the way I
wanted to be able to use it. Right? I went
to that check. Now, even that caused me some
problems. So I was using this in a mobile
web app. It was a phone gap hybrid app. And
I noticed that my web app was taking a long
time to load and I was trying to get this
load time down. So I profiled it, right? I
put little new date in between all the things
that it did and I tried to figure out why
is it taking so much time just to get to this
main screen. And I found it was actually taking
something like 300 milliseconds on Android
and in order to get through this localstorage
detection check. Because in my code I had,
you know, script stores equals lschache.js.
It would execute that code. And that code
would immediately do the localstorage detection
check. What I realized was, I needed to stop
doing that detection check, you know, on page
load and defer it, only do it later when I
actually needed it. Right? So what I did is
I made a little cache variable to remember
whether localstorage works, because we don't
want to do this check all the time. Right?
We want to do it once. So basically what happens,
every time you try to use lscache, it will
check to see, have we figured out yet that
it works? Okay, if we haven't, let's do that
check. Let's remember it and then next time
they use it, they will remember, right? So
what I learned here is that you have to be
careful when you are checking if something
is supported in API, not that it supports
it, but it supports the way you want to use
it, right? Localstorage, you can actually
be in a mode where you can read it but you
wouldn't be able to right. Maybe you only
care about reading, in which case you should
just check for that, right? So there's a lot
of subtleties to when we say something is
supported or works. It's a bit more complex
than that. You also need to make sure that
you don't let feature detection slow down
your site. Right? It's always simple to do
everything up front, do all your checks up
front and then you know you can always have
it there. But you don't want to sacrifice
the user's loading performance just for simplicity.
Right? This is the unfortunate thing is pretty
much when it comes to performance, your code
can start off beautiful. As soon as you start
worrying about performance, your code is not
going to be beautiful anymore. You're going
to have to implement caching and it's not
going to look very clean. But sometimes we
have to make our code look not as beautiful
in order for users to have a better experience.
Right? We sacrifice developer happiness for
user happiness. That's really hard for us
to give up, but it's important. Along with
this, every time I encountered something with,
you know, with this feature detection, I thought
to myself, okay, what would I want out of
browsers? What could browsers give to me as
a developer that would have made it easier
for me in this case? So here it would have
been awesome if I could just ask the browser,
hey, browser, can I use localstorage in a
read mode? Can I use localstorage in a write
mode? Okay, great. Then the browser could
figure out the most optimal way of checking
and it wouldn't be up to me, right? The good
thing about browsers, having browsers give
us these checks, is that they could do it
in a very fast way, a very efficient way,
ways that I couldn't necessarily do because
I'm not going behind the scenes in the browser
code, right? So I hope that this is something
that browsers do going forward with things
like the storage APIs. I think that index.db
does actually have stuff like this. So they
learn.
All right. Whoo! So then we have this thing
called formdata. Formdata is another addition
to HTML5. It's something that lets you store,
take data from all your form inputs, serialize
it, send it in a XMHTLP request. Right? You
don't have to use Jquery AJAX anymore. Right?
I thought, oh, this is cool, right? I saw
all the Google DevRelers were talking about
how cool formdata was. Man, I want to be cool
like them. I want to use formdata, right?
So I implemented it for a sign-up form on
this web site I made last year so that when
you signed up, you would actually -- it would
go through this code here, which would say,
okay, if window.formdata -- starting with
this basic check. If window.formdata, create
new formdata from the form. Do a new XHR.
Send that formdata to the XHR. If not, then
we just down to our AJAX technique, right?
This is awesome. I have been all proper and
I've implemented the feature detection check.
I've done a fallback technique. I tested it.
And it works, and it's great. I put it out,
there. I tweeted about it. I felt really good.
But then I got all these reports from Safari
users that they weren't able to sign up. I
was like, well, this is not very good, right?
Sign-up is somewhat a crucial part of an application,
right? I was like, what is this? Why can't
they sign up on Safari. It worked fine on
my Safari, right? I realized there was that
there was this particular version of Safari,
it was like 5.1.50 or whatever only on Macs,
maybe on Windows. But this particular version
of Safari, it pretended to work but it didn't
actually work. What happened is that when
you created that formdata object, it created
it and pretended it all worked but there was
nothing in it. Which is kind of horrible because
people would be trying to sign up and there
would be no data going to my server so I couldn't
even find out what email address they put
in in order to tell them, okay, hey, I fixed
it, right? I was I was getting an empty string.
That was pretty bad. And the other bad thing
is that there is no way to actually do a detection
check for this because formdata has no accessors.
You can't ask formdata to tell you what's
in it to say get a key out, give me the link
of what's in there. It's just this blob that
you can't look inside and maybe there's nothing
in it. So I was like, okay, I'm going to have
to just blacklist Safari. I knew it had a
problem and that was my only option, right?
So I ended up coming up with a detection user
agent sniffing for Safari, and I said, okay,
if window.formdata and we're not in Safari,
then let's go set it on, right? And I could
have done, like, the very specific version
of Safari, but I didn't want to -- if they
introduced the bug in one version, who is
to say they are not going to introduce it
in other versions. So I just wanted to move
on with life and get it over with, right?
So what I learned here is that it sounds really
-- these new APIs, they seem really exciting
and if you are around -- if you go to conferences
a lot, like you guys might, you hear about
these new APIs. That's so cool. I'm going
to go home and implement it immediately for
my app. You get really excited. But you've
got to be careful about using new APIs because
the bugs in them are new. They are not documented.
New bugs will come up in recent versions of
the browsers. And especially if you are doing
something -- if it's some mission-critical
part of your site like sign-up, I wouldn't
recommend trying out a new API there, right?
If it is mission-critical part of your site,
then just go with the other techniques. Right?
They might not be as cool but we have had
them for years. People have tested them. People
know what all the bugs are with file upload
in IE7 and they have figured them out in libraries.
So I would say, you know, try and use those
old APIs and libraries that people have written
because they are battle tested and you don't
want to be using something so new and shiny
for something that's so important.
Now, for browsers, we really need accessors
for anything that has storage in it, right?
Like with localstorage, if there was no accessor,
I would have no way of knowing that it actually
successfully stored something. Right? So this
is something they should add to any sort of
API like this.
Okay. So now let's talk a bit about CSS. Because
this is something that you can run into as
well. Because we have a lot of fancy CSS now,
right? We've got shiny animations and transforms.
So I was working on that mobile web app, right,
using phone gap and I had this embedded WebView.
I decided to do it as a mobile web app because
I knew HTML CSS. I will use HTML CSS. I'm
just going to use it to make this app. It
will be great. I don't have to learn something
new. At the time, I was doing it for both
iPhone and Android. Only iPhone had a set
of design guidelines. Android hadn't really
come up with anything yet. So I just followed
the iPhone design guidelines. They were a
lot of like rounded corners and gradients
and look really bubbly. Luckily CSS3 made
it really easy to make something like iPhone-y.
The box shadow, the gradiant, the border radius,
all that. Right? I had my app. It was all
good, and I was feeling good having it out
on the market there. But then what happened
is I was using Android at the time and I would
notice from time to time that the entire screen
would just go completely white, right? And
I would be unable -- there would be nothing
there anymore and I would have to, like, restart
the app and somehow go back. It was useless,
right? You can't use an app that's a white
screen. It's highly unfunctional. So okay,
clearly something is not working in this app
that I need to work out. I kind of had a suspicion
that maybe Android didn't like all this fancy
CSS. I had kind of heard rumors that Android
wasn't so good with new CSS3 stuff. So I suspected
that it was having trouble actually rendering
this. So what I did was I spent an entire
afternoon sitting there commenting out CSS.
Redeploying my APK to my phone. Scrolling
and scrolling and scrolling, waiting to see
if I got a white screen. That was probably
one of the most boring afternoons in my life.
So eventually I did figure out that if I commented
out enough of the fancy CSS, that I wouldn't
get white screens anymore. And I didn't want
to have to sit there and figure out exactly
how much CSS Android can handle because it
was just really boring. So I decided, well,
you know what, I'm going to get rid of all
of it, right? I will take away the border
radius, the gradients, box shadows, and so
it ended up looking really flat.
Then conveniently Android came out with their
design guidelines which were the opposite
of iPhone's and their design guidelines were:
Flat, not gradient, square. And I thought
"Wow, that's perfect. It's like you knew that
you were incapable of handling CSS 3."
[ Laughter ]
>>Pamela Fox: So that worked out really well,
actually. But the thing is that I still wanted
to have the iPhone look and feel for iPhone
users and the Android, you know, look and
feel for the Android users and I was doing
this from the same code base, so I needed
to detect Android. So you can see here the
transformation from the iPhone to the Android.
So to detect Android, it's a little more complex
than you would imagine. I was doing the standard
user agent check for popular Android devices.
I was also using the phone gap API that they
provide for checking device. And I was also
checking the URL parameter because I test
my mobile Webapp in the browser as well, so
I wanted to be able to just fake Android when
I was testing the browser.
But finally, when I decided to add Android,
I add the Android class to the body tag and
then in my CSS, I can just say, "Oh, okay,
if we're looking at a mobile class inside
the Android body class, then just reset all
of these fancy things," right? Box shadow
none, no border radius, get rid of all of
that, reset it all to zero.
And that worked.
So what I learned here is that just because
something is supported does not mean it's
supported well, right?
It's really easy to throw in support for these
things. It's much harder to make them work
really well and be really performant, especially
for this CSS 3 stuff, right?
So you really need a check for that. And especially
if you're using these features in bulk, right?
Part of my problem was that I had a -- kind
of an infinite scrolling interface so there
was potentially lots and lots of these features
that were kind of building up and being used
by the browser. I think if I only had, you
know, a limited amount of usage of it, I probably
could have more easily controlled it and predicted
what it -- how it would perform. But since
I had more and more of this CSS 3 features
building up, I think that contributed to Android
kind of freaking out and going "Ahh, that's
too many!"
I'm just guessing that's what Android does.
[ Laughter ]
>>Pamela Fox: So if you're going to -- if
you have any sort of interfaces which potentially
get, you know, bigger and bigger amounts of
content and don't have a finite cap, really
be careful about your performance there. Right?
I worked on the Google Wave team years ago,
and we had that problem with waves, right?
Waves that got way too long. They just had
too much DOM inside them so we really had
to look at that DOM and say "Okay, we probably
shouldn't be using a table to make all of
our buttons," right?
Because that really, really adds up when you
get these really long waves.
So definitely anyplace where you've got this
scrolling or lots of things adding up, look
out for it.
Now, for browsers, I just want browsers to
know their limits, right?
I would much rather that Android realize that
it couldn't render my fancy CSS and just not
have done it, right?
Instead of pretending it could do it and then
rendering a white screen. Because white screens
are really not easy to use, right?
It's like worse than blue screens. At least
blue screens, you know it's a blue screen
of death. You're like, "Oh, okay, die. I'm
just going to restart it."
White screens, it's like "Hey, I don't know
what's going on here." It's kind of abstract.
So browsers should just know their limits,
right? So should all of us.
[ Laughter ]
>>Pamela Fox: Okay. So finally, I want to
talk about a sign-up process that we have
at Coursera that I helped on a few months
ago.
So we introduced this thing called Signature
Track which is a way of taking courses while
verifying your identity, and there are a few
technical components of Signature Track and
we wanted to make sure that people knew about
these technical requirements before they signed
up, because I didn't want users to get halfway
through this multi-step sign-up process and
then realize that there was no way they would
have been able to complete it and then, you
know, they get all mad, like "Coursera, why
do you tease me like that?"
So these were the -- you know, the requirements
were that you needed to have a physical keyboard
because we do this keystroke biometrics algorithm,
and it doesn't work so well on soft keyboards.
So we wanted you to have a real physical keyboard.
You needed to have a webcam because we took
a picture of your face every time you took
a quiz and when you signed up and so -- to
match it to your ID. So we couldn't have you
do it if you didn't have a webcam.
And you needed to have a modern browser and
also you needed to have Flash because we're
using Flash to get the webcam stuff. I know
that you can do it in HTML5 but it didn't
work so well.
So I needed to figure out how to do checks
for all of these. The first thing was a physical
keyboard, and that was a little tricky because
there's no such thing as asking the browser
if there's a physical keyboard attached.
So we said, "All right. Well, maybe we should
just look to see if it's a touch device."
So we started off with this check here, like,
"Oh, does ontouch start in window or document
touch? Then okay, we're on a touch device."
And we rolled that out but we immediately
got cases where it thought you were on a touch
device and you weren't and vice versa.
And people would actually have physical keyboards
and we're like, "All right. We are just going
to black-list mobile browsers. So basically
you're only going to be able to do this on
your desktop browser, and we'll give you a
link to let us know that if you actually do
have a physical keyboard, we'll give you that
option." Right?
So we ended up doing that, because we needed
something -- I just needed something that
worked to get this out fast. But the thing
is, we do tell -- we would tell people, right?
So for every -- every time I would detect
something about a user, I would let them know
like "Hey, this is the reason that we're not
letting you do it."
So that then they could see and then they
could contact us and say, "Oh, hey, you say
that you blocked me because I didn't have
a hard keyboard but actually I do," and then
we could decide to unblock them or we could
change our blocking process. Right?
We actually -- we haven't gotten any emails
about that check yet, so I guess it's kind
of working.
Now, I just want to give an aside now on touch
events because touch events are really, really
interesting things, and there's been a lot
of very interesting articles lately about
touch events and whether you should be supporting
-- detecting them and how.
So here's -- you know, if we want to look
for touch events, there's a couple things
we have to do across different browsers to
find out if that browser is capable of doing
touch events.
But there's a difference between a browser
supporting touch events and the user actually
using touch events, right?
So if you're on an Android tablet, you could
still connect a mouse to your tablet, right?
And you could actually potentially be using
a Web site and switching between using a mouse
and using your finger on the same Web page,
right?
So that means as a developer you shouldn't
be relying on just the fact that something
is a touch device as meaning that that's actually
-- that you should just be doing everything
reacting to touch, because a lot of times
users can connect these other devices as well.
And I think this is going to become more and
more common that we'll have these devices
that are both.
I mean, we all just got that Chrome Pixel,
right? And the Chrome Pixel is a touchscreen
and a keyboard and you have the little mousey
down there, right?
So this is becoming more and more the reality,
so we have to be really careful that when
we're looking for touch, that we consider
the fact that they could still be using click
events, right?
So the standard way -- or one way that you
could actually not care about this is that
you could listen to a touch event, and if
you get a touch event, you would just trigger
your listener for the click event and basically
they would both do the same thing.
Right?
So that way, the user could go between using
touch and using click and your Web page should
respond exactly the same way.
So if you are doing anything right now or
thinking about doing something where you're
detecting touch events and doing something
different, think to yourself "How would this
work if the user also had a -- a mouse attached?
How would it work if they switched between
the mouse and the touchscreen halfway through
the interaction," right? That's kind of the
-- the trickiest, but it could happen, right?
And there's some really interesting articles
about that there.
Okay. So that's an aside.
Oh, we also need to check the Flash plugin
and I just used the SWF object library for
this, which is -- it's a nice well-supported
library and it will even tell you the Flash
Player versions, in case you want to support
particular versions.
And I also wanted to check for a webcam. Unfortunately,
there is no way to check for a webcam unless
you actually put up the webcam prompt and
ask the user to give permission, right?
And I wanted to check for this before they
even got to the webcam part of the process.
So I gave up, and I just put a -- we put up
a little modal that said "Hey, remember, you
need a webcam," and, you know, presumably
if they saw that and decided to keep going,
even though they didn't have a webcam, well,
that's their prerogative.
So sometimes you just can't detect things
and you have to -- you have to accept that.
So in this case, I learned that, you know,
you can't detect things all the time and you
have to do different things, and if you do
decide to block the users, which, you know,
can be a bad thing, but if you do block them,
tell them why you blocked them, give them
an option to contact you and explain, you
know -- you know, what their -- their particular
setup is, and maybe you'll realize then that
the code you were using could actually be
much improved.
And for browsers, I would really like for
browsers to give us a way to detect those
physical devices and plugins, right? So I
wouldn't have to go through all this effort
to try and figure it out. So something like
is there a physical keyboard, are they using
it right now, do they have a webcam, do they
have Flash. Those would have all made my life
much, much easier.
All right. So to finish up, this is a reminder
of why this all matters. This is a visualization
of browser support for a particular feature
and there's lots more visualizations of this.
But the point is that, yeah, we're going to
have unequal distribution of feature support
for a long time going forward. Basically forever,
right? People will keep coming up with new
things. Browsers will keep not implementing
them at the same rate, keep implementing in
different ways with different performance
concerns, with different attributes supported,
and we're going to just have to keep dealing
with that, right?
So this is something that we're going to have
to think about for years to come.
Now, browsers are aware of this and browsers
are trying to help, so browsers, they did
introduce this CSS conditionals Level 3 spec,
which actually has this @supports rule for
CSS where you can say, "Oh, hey, does this
browser actually support this CSS" and then
you could serve different styles. And they've
got the same in JavaScript, window.supportCSS,
and this is actually supported by three browsers
now.
So the cool thing is that browsers are actually
realizing that, yeah, this is something developers
care about and they're trying to come up with
more ways for us to figure it out, but this
is still -- this is really cutting-edge and
most of you, you know, we won't be able to
use this quite yet, right?
So in the meantime, what should be your strategy?
First of all, don't assume it's going to be
easy, because sometimes it's not, and if you
assume it's easy, you might look for an easy
solution and overlook all the complexities.
Don't just copy the first answer off stackoverflow,
which is something I do a lot but I'm trying
to -- I'm trying to cut back on it.
[ Laughter ]
>>Pamela Fox: Try -- do use the tried-and-true
techniques, right? So use popular and well-tested
libraries. Look at the number of forks, the
number of issues, the number of contributors,
look at how recently the change was. Browse
through the issue tracker and see what people
say about it, right?
And if you're not sure, just ask, right?
When I was trying to figure out the Signature
Track process, I just emailed my buddies on
the Chrome team and said, "Hey, is there anything
I'm not thinking of here?" Right?
And now we don't all have buddies on the Chrome
team but we do have Paul Irish's Twitter account
so I recommend just tweeting at him because
he really likes to answer these things and
he's got the lowdown, so don't be afraid to
ask. There's a lot of people out there that
will answer. And do try feature detection
first, right?
So use Modernizr and you can see all the different
ways of using it.
Also, if you do need to do user agent detection,
use this library called UA parser. It's maintained
by Browser Stack and contributed by Google
and Facebook, so it's got a lot of great well-tested
RegExes in it and it's supported in lots of
different languages.
And you can also mix and match, right? You
can see if something works and then maybe
black-list it for certain browsers that you
know have problems, right? Certain browsers
and versions. That's the best kind of blacklist.
So basically the conclusion here is that we
don't have that. Do you guys know what that
is up there?
Yeah, so that's a sonic screwdriver from Doctor
Who, and basically it can do everything, right?
We don't have something that can do everything.
We don't have the perfect solution in web
development. That's just how it is. But we
do have a lot of tools in our toolbox, and
we can learn how to use those tools and we
can combine them together and we can try to
use the more sophisticated ones first. And
we also have each other, so that we can learn
from each other about how to learn these tools,
right? So we're not alone in it, so when you're
figuring this out, look to each other for
the solutions, document what you find out,
write it up, open-source your code, and then
we'll all learn how to do all this detection
together so that we can fully take advantage
of everything the web has for us today.
Got it?
Done!
[ Applause ]
So questions? Yeah? Anyone have questions?
Speechless. Doctor Who episodes, perhaps?
[ Humming ]
>>Pamela Fox: There's a little microphony
thing there.
>>> Okay. So there seems to be kind of an
underlying theme to all of this, and that
is, you're doing all this checking. It almost
feels like you're trying to implement what
you can when you can, rather than trying to
develop to implement -- or to cover as many
browsers as possible and then dealing with
exceptions. Am I just kind of reading into
that the wrong way or...
>>Pamela Fox: So you're wondering am I trying
to use new things -- am I trying to like overly
hard to use new things versus using the older
things?
>>> No, I wouldn't say "overly hard," but
it seems like -- and not just you. I see a
lot of developers out there feel like there's
this push, this emphasis to use everything
possibly available even if it causes 10 times
the work.
>>Pamela Fox: Right. Yeah. No, I think that's
a good point, right?
>>> You know.
>>Pamela Fox: I think that we see the new
stuff and we get really excited about it and
it makes us feel good to try out the new stuff
because we feel like we're on the cutting
edge.
It's kind of like not-invented-here syndrome,
right? Like it helps us kind of feel like
inventors if we're using the new stuff too
and we're going on this alone. But it's true.
So I -- so nowadays, like at Coursera, most
of the time I will just try and go with the
tried-and-true techniques now because I -- now
that I've had this much experience with trying
the new stuff, you know, I like knowing that
it's there, but I also know that if I'm going
to try it out, I'm probably going to be one
of the first people to really try it out in
a big app and I'm going to have to struggle
with figuring that out. And sometimes I'm
up for that challenge because it can be quite
interesting, but sometimes I just want it
to work.
>>> Okay. So I hadn't quite formed the question
till now that you've said that.
In your experience, these things that are
out there, are they generally stable enough
that it's -- it's okay for the better part
of the user base to try to use them and deal
with them, or should -- if you've got a really
deal with the general public, should you just
stick with those tried-and-true methods?
>>Pamela Fox: It really depends on what they
are. Some of them have been out there for
longer than others. I guess I've experienced,
even with -- even with local storage, that
browsers introduce new bugs and it's even
been around for a couple years.
We use HTML5 video at Coursera and we still
have a lot of problems with it, and it's been
out for a year or so, so we've started defaulting
users to Flash instead.
>>> Okay. That right there says a lot.
>>Pamela Fox: So sometimes there are advantages
to stuff, right? We're using HTML5 video at
Coursera because we get playback, right? We
can use the speedup buttons. So we're using
it there because we're getting a real advantage
to using it. So if there is a real advantage
in terms of performance or productivity -- right?
-- like, you know, border radius I'm going
to use that and just not care if it doesn't
work in other browsers, right? Because I get
a big advantage there and not -- and not a
big decrease, so it's a balance.
>>> Thank you.
>>> Regarding your fancy CSS woes, did you
file any bugs?
>>Pamela Fox: So did I file bugs on the Android
whiteout?
>>> And was it Chrome or was it the Android
browser?
>>Pamela Fox: This was Android Webkit, so
the thing is, when you doing phone gap, you
have to use the embedded Web view, which means
using the Android Webkit, also known as like
the worst Webkit ever. So there -- I mean,
there were a lot of issues with that Webkit.
I think I filed some -- some issues on that,
but I don't know if I filed on the whiteout
in particular, because it's -- it's something
where you'd have to give them the test case
and it's kind of a -- sometimes it can be
really complex to come up with the test cases
for people, and I feel bad reporting bugs
without a really nice test case for it. So
I probably didn't.
>>> I gotcha. Cool. We'd like to help fix
those.
>>Pamela Fox: Nice. Anything else?
All right. How many of you use Modernizr now?
[ Show of hands ]
>>Pamela Fox: Cool.
Any of you guys do UA parser?
[ Show of hands ]
>>Pamela Fox: Oh, yeah, one. Yeah, I actually
had never even heard of it before, so...
>> (Speaker is off microphone.)
>>Pamela Fox: Why doesn't Modernizr have it
in its Flash? So there's a whole issue on
it. So this is what I recommend. Like when
you use Modernizr, you'll find it doesn't
have checks for -- there's lots of things
it doesn't have checks for, right? Many of
the things I check for these days, like playback
rate on the video element, Modernizr doesn't
have that.
But if you look in the issue tracker, you
will often find discussions about it, right?
So anytime you use a library, look in the
issue tracker, right?
So I always look in the issue tracker. So
you've got to, like, look and see what are
the common issues that people are having,
right? To see, "Oh, is that something that's
going to hit me too?"
And also look for interesting discussions,
especially with Modernizr.
And I also look to see just when people respond
to issues, if they're nice or if they're mean,
because if I'm thinking about using a library
and all the responses on the issue tracker
are kind of mean, then I don't use it.
[ Laughter ]
>>Pamela Fox: So I definitely check out -- when
I'm thinking of using a library, I check out
their issue tracker and their code history
fairly thoroughly, right? Because anytime
you use a library, it's an investment because
you'll encounter issues with it.
So they don't have a Flash support but they
do have a long thread about it and I followed
a few links from there, but in the end, SWF
object was the -- the best option. It's the
most accurate.
Cool. All right. You're free to go.
[ Applause ]