>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Hello. Good morning,
everyone. Welcome to the making money on Google
Play session. My name is Ibrahim Elbouchikhi.
I'm project manager for commerce on Google
Play, and Bob Meese over there is my colleague
who is from business development on Google
Play.
Let's get started. Where's the clicker?
Clicker? Here, sorry.
Okay. So first I wanted to start by just saying
thank you. Over the past 12 months we've talked
to a lot of you, got a lot of great feedback
that we baked into the product. A lot of the
features that you will see next have really
been developed in -- by working with you and
getting your feedback. So let's continue that,
let's continue that conversation. Keep sending
the feedback, the good, the bad, the ugly,
and we promise we'll keep working on it and
making things better.
We'll start off with the office hours which
is happening next, so come by the Google Play
office hours section and we'll talk there.
So the agenda for today, we'll first share
some data. These are metrics that we feel
are interesting for you as you build your
business on Google Play.
We'll then give you a product update. These
are features we've launched recently and their
impact as well as features we look forward
to in the midterm.
Finally we'll talk about some case studies
about what some of our most commercially successful
partners are doing.
And finally we'll close out with Q and A in
the office hours by the Google Play section.
So let's get started with some data. Last
year Chris Yerga got on stage, I think exactly
this room, and showed us the growth trajectory
of in-app. It looked something like ridiculous,
well, reverse, like going up to the right.
And we were very excited about that growth.
This year we've actually done something even
more incredible, which is that we've multiplied
in-app revenue by seven. So over the past
12 months -- there are very few industries,
companies, countries, anything that grows
that fast over 12 months, and this is a testament
to all the work you have all been doing.
Users are engaged with the applications you've
been building and they're willing to pay for
them and are really enjoying them. So that's
just incredible.
So we wanted to look beyond the number and
say what is this telling us about the Google
Play and Android user? And one thing we've
learned is we've heard this a lot from our
Japanese partners, which is omotenashi. And
what omotenashi means essentially, it's hospitality,
but it's got a bit of a deeper sense. It's
got more of a personalized experience. It's
almost like not a buyer and seller relationship,
it's a host and a guest.
And what this is, it's essentially what in-app
represents, right? In-app is about getting
the user to enjoy the application, to really
get immersed into it before getting to monetization.
We've heard this a lot in all sorts of saying,
focus on the user experience and the money
will follow. And that's exactly what in-app
represents.
Now, in-app is not for everyone and we've
got very successful subscription partners
as well as paid app developers, but if you're
able to inject some omotenashi into your application,
please try, and that's the message from this
number.
Subscriptions launched about 12 months ago
as well, and since launch we're very excited
that the number of subscribers has doubled
each quarter. Subscriptions have a pretty
high hurdle. The user has to see continuous
value. They have to commit to recurring subscription,
and it's a pretty high hurdle for subscription,
but yet we're seeing more and more users taking
that step and that's again because of the
applications and the content you've all been
creating for our users.
There's no better example today than Pandora,
which is a partner on the top grossing list,
one of the few non-games that's completely
based on subscriptions.
Now, Android is a global platform clearly
and Google Play store is equally global. We
have buyers in 134 markets, so by pushing
that button in the Google Play developer console
and pushing your app for sale you're making
it available to buyers in 134 countries.
This is unprecedented distribution. Never
before has distribution been this easy and
efficient. For you as a developer, wherever
you are in the world, whether you're a solo
developer or a multinational corporation,
we take care of everything for you and we
just have to push that button and get your
application out there.
Now, the countries that we've overlaid on
the map, some of them are probably already
in your mind, they are particularly large,
growing fast, but there are also other countries
that we feel will play a big part of the next
12 months so we're excited about that. We've
launched a lot of features around localization
and translations at I/O so take advantage
of that and map them up to that set of countries,
the 134, and hopefully you will see success
globally.
Tablets have been a big part of Android over
the past 12 months. And the way the conversation
generally goes is that we ask you to optimize
your apps for tablets, and as a business owner
you look at the cost and you say that's additional
cost. Is that where I invest my resources?
And I know you have very limited resources
like everyone else.
And the number I want to share with you today
is a tablet monetizes 1.7 extra rate of a
phone, so that additional cost of optimizing
your tablets, your application for tablets,
is well worthwhile. And we want to see more
of our developers doing just that.
We've launched a lot of features on our end
as well, whether it's the optimization tips
for tablets or the guidelines to help you
do this as well.
The other metric that's interesting is recent
platform releases monetize at 2.2X their prior
versions. What this is telling us is, again,
as you build your application take advantage
of the latest platform features. Whether it's
Google+ sign-in or all of the APIs that launched
at I/O this week, all of that coming together
actually has a tangible impact on your revenue.
It is not just nice to have, they might be
actually required for you and you can more
than double your revenue by actually adopting
those new features.
Next this is a very intuitive message, right,
higher rated applications monetize better.
We wanted to give you a sense of just how
much better.
If you go from 1 to 2 let's not talk about
those, but if you go from 2 to 3-star you
are actually almost doubling your revenue.
And again, if you go from 3 to 4 stars you're
actually almost tripling your revenue. So
a conversation we have around quality and
reply to reviews and fixing bugs and good
customer experience and good support, all
of that has now a tangible impact on your
revenue. And that's what we're going to demonstrate
with these metrics.
Finally, as it was mentioned in the keynote,
over the past year we've more than doubled
average revenue per user. This is even given
the incredible growth that Android itself
has been having, 900 million devices has grown
our pool by 2.5X.
This is the baseline metric that every platform
is measured by. How profitable are we for
you? And this is really exciting for us, this
particular development. It's a testament to
the type of experiences you've been creating
and how engaging and immersive they have been.
So we'll go now into the product update portion.
And I know it might be obvious or it might
be intuitive, but I always like to start with
the baseline understanding of our mission.
We have a bunch of people who work on payments
sprinkled around the room and all of us show
up to work everyday because we want to make
our developers successful, and in the context
of payment we want to make sure we maximize
your income.
So when you work hard and build an application,
an awesome application, we want to make sure
you're getting the most value out of that
work. That's just the baseline understanding.
That's why we show up to work everyday and
a lot of us that's our goal and objective.
So with that in mind I again like to think
of things in terms of frameworks to just simplify
the conversation. In this case I picked a
really simple framework.
We try to maximize your income, which means
we're going to increase your sales and reduce
your costs. So our conversation going forward
is going to be in this context, how are we
maximizing your sales and reducing your cost
in order to maximize your income?
We've also talked to you about what drives
your sales, and you've told us a bunch of
things. One is the number of devices out there.
How many tablets do we have? The other thing
was how many markets you're targeting. So
if we're growing really fast in a particular
region, but you're actually not localizing
to it or tailoring the experience to it, you're
not really benefiting from that.
The aspect is the quality of your application.
We just saw if you go from three to four you're
tripling your revenue. Your aspect is how
many buyers do we have, how many credit cards
do we have on file, how many carrier billing
accounts do we have?
And then the purchase experience, how smooth
is it, how well does it convert? This all
impacts your sales.
And finally, all of these things that happen
after the fact, whether it's cancellations
because of a poor user experience. The user
did not get the item they purchased and they
call and that becomes a poor user experience.
So all of these things drive your sales.
In terms of costs you've told us about three
big buckets. These are things we've talked
about in terms of tablets and optimizing for
them or adopting new platform features. Engineering
work. You've got to have engineers and you've
got to have QA, you have to have back office
and accounting. You have user acquisition
costs. So marketing, paid installs, whatever
it is.
Then you have your support costs. These are
the three buckets that your costs largely
fit into.
So with that in mind I want to share with
you some things we did to help in each of
these areas.
So more forms of payment. This is clearly
comes up all the time. What have we done over
the past 12 months to address that?
First off is the Google Play gift card. It
actually only launched in July of last year.
And since then it's --
[ Applause ]
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Woo, that's right.
>>Bob Meese: Somebody is happy.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: It only launched in
July of last year and since then it's become
incredibly successful for us. And it's omnipresent
in U.S. retail locations, it's in the U.K.
now. You can see us continue to invest in
the Google Play gift card. The whole prepaid
form of payment is critical to us.
The other aspect is we launched campaigns.
And what campaigns are essentially in this
case, if you bought a Galaxy S3 you get a
free Galaxy s3, which is awesome, but also
you got $50 to spend on Google Play.
What this does is, one, it ingests money that
gets spent on your applications. And two,
it lowers the hurdle for users to go from
a free app buyer, consumer to actually a purchaser.
And our experiments have shown that when the
user makes one, two, three purchases, they're
much more likely to make the fourth and fifth
even when their credit is over.
Finally, carrier billing. The exciting number
I want to share with you today is that 50%
of Google Play 30-day actives are now on carriers
that support carrier billing.
What that means is that they are one button
click away from becoming buyers. They don't
have to type numbers, no expiration dates,
they just have to enable it and then they
can start buying. And this is a really critical
number for us.
And as a background, if you're not aware of
what carrier billing is, it's essentially
the ability to put your purchases on your
monthly bill. This is something that's unique
to Google Play and we've invested a lot in
the technology behind it.
So the other thing you said is the purchase
flow. We've heard a lot about our purchase
flow in the past.
I don't know if you've been through the new
store as well as the new purchase flow, but
it's a really exciting development for us
and a lot of the design came in from feedback
you gave us, which was that you wanted the
purchase flow to be contextual. You want it
to be fast and you want it to be simple. So
we did just that.
In addition to that we made it a lot faster.
So in this particular client release that
came out a few weeks ago we have seen a 35%
drop in latency.
In addition to that we're seeing really good
user feedback and we're seeing a pick up in
conversion as well.
Now, let's shift gears to costs. We've heard
a lot from you around accounting and back
office. And if you're a small developer you
might not worry too much about this, but for
our large partners it was a big problem. You
couldn't get your reports on a timely basis,
you couldn't get them programmatically out
of our database, and so we've done just that.
So with the rollout of the Google Wallet merchant
center, now -- if you don't have it you should
get it in a few weeks. You will be able to
use a very simple script to download all of
your monthly reports and ingest them into
your back end and do whatever you want with
them, most likely reconcile.
The other aspect is support costs. And the
thing about support costs is if you look at
the top level costs of lost purchases you
might feel that, well, it's bad, but it's
not terrible, but the impact of support goes
well beyond that.
One is there is a cost of the lost sale and
there's a fixed cost of supporting that call.
So somebody calls 10 minutes to support that
user, that's a lot of money, but the worst
part is you've acquired that buyer with a
certain lifetime value assumption. And what
this does to it is it truncates their lifetime.
It cuts it short. So your math as you're looking
at this it's going to -- does it add for me,
it really gets messed up.
So support, as little as you might not pay
a lot of attention to it, it's actually critical
to your revenue, your cost and sales. And
what's the exciting metric here is IAB V3.
IAB V3 launched in December and since then
Gamevil has seen a drop 90% drop in customer
contact rates for games where they have implemented
IAB V3. There was a talk about it, on Wednesday
about it. Please go watch it on YouTube and
thank that person over there for designing
IAB V3.
So anyways, basically this is really awesome.
You just need to do it.
So in-app order status API. This is another
big ask from you, which is essentially the
ability for you to take the purchase token
that we send you back and turn around and
verify the status of that purchase.
This is for two reasons. You could do it for
either verifying authenticity of the purchase
or just the state.
And we're launching this in a few weeks worldwide.
So all of our developers will have access
to this and it should help a lot with reconciling
your purchases and even preventing fraud.
Okay. The other thing is in-app billing testing.
You probably heard this already, but we're
now simplifying in-app billing testing by
allowing your licensed test accounts, the
one you already configured in the Google Play
developer console to make purchases without
being charged. Everything else is the same,
just no more holds, no bins, no delays, none
of that bad stuff.
We think this is going to be super exciting,
super helpful in streamlining your experience
and testing and making sure that you're not
wasting time stuck in those sorts of things.
When you see that message that says this is
a test purchase you know that you're not actually
being charged as it says in the remainder
sentence.
All right. So to summarize, so for your sales
we've got 50% of our users now on carrier
billing, we have the Google Play gift cards,
we have promo campaigns and we have a faster,
better purchase flow.
For your costs we've got a pragmatic access
to your reports, easy in-app testing, better
user experience with in-app billing V3 and
order status check API to prevent fraud as
well as reconcile your purchases.
So this is the summary list of things we've
done and already doing in the next few weeks
to help you maximize your income.
So looking forward a little bit, you can see
us invest more heavily in Google Play gift
card. We'll push it into our biggest markets
and you will see us continue to do that.
The next thing we'll do is carrier billing.
It's in 12 countries today. See us push that
further over the next few months and over
the next 12 months. Those add up.
And then the purchase experience, right? So
we've already made a huge improvement in our
last release, but we're actually going to
go even further.
The one thing we've done so far -- the one
thing we've done really critically is that
we've instrumented the purchase flow so that
we can analyze it and study it and continue
to improve it very quickly. So look for us
to do a lot more experimentation, lots more
fine tuning, so when you send us a buyer,
when you get a user to commit to making a
purchase on your app, we want to convert as
many of those as possible unless they change
their mind.
And so look for us to do a lot more of that
and look for us to support more forms of payment.
Gift cards are just the beginning.
And finally, seller support in more countries.
We're all -- one of the objectives and missions
of all of us is that anyone, anyone around
the world can make a living on Google Play.
And we want to get there. It's taken a long
time. It's slower than we would like it to
be as well, but we do want to get to that
point where anyone around the planet can code
an awesome app and make a living out of it.
And we'll get there.
So why is it an exciting year ahead? I think
there's a convergence of a few things for
us on play.
First of all, we've got a global payments
reach. We're really getting to the point where
we've got FOBs in many, many countries and
that's going to really help with our conversion.
The next thing is we're seeing higher buyer
engagement, as you've seen in the numbers
before, across the board. Whether it's in-app
subscriptions or paid apps, users are willing
to buy and are willing to pay for the experiences
you're creating, and that's really good news
for us.
Finally, we're really putting the final pieces
together for world class commerce infrastructure
and developer tools. We want to get you back
to doing the things that you do well and do
best, which is building awesome applications.
We want to take you away from spending time
trying to figure out why your account is blocked
for testing purposes or why you have to download
these reports in some way or the other. We
want to do all of that and make sure you do
what you do best, which is build awesome applications.
That's all for me. I'm going to hand it over
to Bob, who is going to cover a few case studies.
>>Bob Meese: Thanks, Ibrahim. And hello, everyone.
So to get the growth rates that we're seeing,
we're clearly doing a lot to help support
that growth, but much of the work is also
being done by our developers. So this section
of the presentation we're really focused on
the work of those great developers and we're
focusing specifically on the most commercially
successful developers. And by commercially
successful I mean the developers that are
not just building great products that their
users love that are being installed in large
numbers in many cases, but these are the developers
that are making money on Google Play.
I'll focus on two key parts in this section,
so one will just be to help you understand
more about what these developers are doing
and then I'd also like to focus on how you
can apply some of these lessons to your own
businesses.
So as Ibrahim says, we've seen a 7X increase
in the last year in-app revenue. Signs of
in-app revenue growth are all over the Play
Store. If you look at the top grossing apps
right now, all of the top grossing apps are
free to play.
But with every rule there's always an exception
and so we have a fun game we like to play
called "Where's Minecraft?"
There it is down there at number 22. So we
are not saying you need to push everything
free to play. Minecraft is an amazing game.
It's an iconic brand with a very loyal following.
We think it will continue to be successful
so we are not asking you to follow the crowd
to do that; however, also recognize the dominant
trend towards free to play. It's very important
to recognize that. The bar for success for
a paid title in the top grossing charts is
very high.
More than anything, the trend that we see
is developers allowing users to defer that
payment decision. We see a three-step funnel
to monetization.
So the first step is really around acquisition.
So this is about expanding this top of the
funnel as wide as you possibly can, getting
as many users as you can to press that install
button.
The install counts on Google Play are public
within a certain band, and just go check out
some of your favorite paid apps and free apps
and check out the large, large difference
in the large number of free installs that
happen on Google Play.
Second, retention.
And we think this is really an underappreciated
part of the funnel. It's part of the omotenashi
that Ibrahim was mentioning earlier. It's
an area where our smartest developers are
spending more and more of their time. And
the thing you need to focus on here is really
on earning, the ability to ask those users
for money. It's not something you can take
for granted.
For example, if I asked all of you to rate
my talk a couple of minutes into it right
now, you might ask for a little bit more time
to see, like, hey, what's this guy actually
going to talk about; right? And the same sort
of principle applies here. How do your users
get into your product, provide value to them,
have them coming back over time. And clearly
we've seen signs that users are more likely
to pay after they've had an experience.
And then finally, obviously pressing that
buy button in monetization. And what we've
found, and it's very important, is there's
a lot of differences in terms of when and
how developers ask users to pay.
And now I'll do a first case study that introduces
these three principles.
So Kiwi is an Android-focused developer lead
by Omar Saddiqui. Omar is actually going to
be joining us for the Office Hours session
afterwards, and Shipwrecked has been their
most successful game on Google Play. It will
also be the subject of the case study in the
following slides.
Kiwi has three other games on Google Play
including Monsterama Park, Brightwood Adventures
and Monsterama Planet, which was recently
released.
And when we spoke with them, they said for
acquisition, really invest in your Play Store
page.
It sounds basic, but the little things matter.
You see here in the description, "Millions
of players agree that Shipwrecked's Lost Island,
an Editor's Choice app, is one of the top
free games on Android."
In just a few words, they communicate a lot
of powerful principles. It's one of the first
experiences that a user has with your application,
and these words really create a powerful impression.
Also, on the right you see videos. We found
that videos is a very powerful way to communicate
the value of your product, and it helps differentiate
you against all of the other products that
do not have videos in the titles.
Second, retention, as we said, is very important.
Here, when you think of retention, thinking
about rewarding those user actions that you
want your users to take. So here on the left,
as you see that, it's very important to have
daily retention, and you see your reward,
a daily login bonus, that rewards those players
for taking the actions you want them to take.
On the right, you see a leveling up. You see
the time and effort that your users are spending
in that application being rewarded through
new content and new features being unlocked
and other rewards happening.
Further on retention, keeping the content
fresh and unlocking big new content -- in
this case, a full new island, Atlantis in
this case -- allows your users to stay engaged
with the game or the application and explore
all of this new content.
Also, you can even think about reinventing
the user experience. When Shipwrecked first
launched, it was really focused around exploration
and collection. After launch, they added a
trading mechanic which users actually loved.
It was a bit of a risk, but the users love
this, and they keep coming back to the game
over and over.
On the topic of monetization, we found that
merchandising really matters. I think this
monkey is great here. He is pointing out this
"arrrsome" deal if you can't see the little
text there. The 24 gold for $2.99, who can
beat that? You can see below it, you can go
to the full store but why not pull out one
of the most attractive offers and put it right
there to make it easy for users to buy.
And so as you saw with Kiwi, acquisition is
about improving your placed lower page. Retention
is about rewarding the user behaviors that
you want to promote and about reinventing
the user experience. And monetization, merchandising
matters.
But it's not just enough to go linearly through
this. What we're seeing the most successful
developers on Google Play do is they create
a virtuous cycle by feeding back to acquisition
several different ways.
So those developers that are able to find
success and make money on Google Play can
reinvest those earnings through paid user
acquisition to feel for future growth of their
products.
Similarly, those developers that have a great
number of retained users can cross promote
those users, especially the developers that
have multiple titles, back into acquisition.
And then finally, those developers that are
fortunate enough to reach the top list, that
becomes a self-fulfilling cycle. You need
a lot of installs to get there, but you get
a lot of installs from being there.
And now I'll talk about some of these concepts
with the other case studies.
The second one we'll introduce today is DeNA,
and the game we'll mostly focus on is their
successful game, Blood Brothers. They have
a couple other hit titles including Marvel,
War of Heroes and Rage of Bahamut, which was
a clear breakout hit through 2012. DeNA also
has six other games in the top 100 top grossing.
So because they have so many successful titles,
they really focus on cross promotion. In this
case, I was playing Blood Brothers on the
left. While I was playing, I received this
promotion, "Play Marvel and receive 50 Mobacoin."
It's a way for them to target a very attractive
user base, the users who are playing their
existing games, and use them to acquire them
for the new games they're launching.
It's also important for retention to provide
very clear objectives. The central objective
in the game Blood Brothers is a card collection
mechanic. It's all around strengthening your
characters, which they call familiars.
All of the core game loops in the game support
this core objective. It's a very powerful
thing. They focus you on a single core objective,
and then you have a game loop of adventuring,
battling, leveling up your characters, all
feeling back into that one objective of strengthening
your characters.
Even as you add more complexity to the game,
when you battle and you win, you capture a
character, there's a variety of ways you can
combine these characters all back towards
that central objective of strengthening your
characters.
And one thing that's particularly worth calling
out is DeNA success with events. So events
are variations on the standard game play that
happen for a very limited amount of time,
a fixed duration, that provide important rewards.
And in this case, they provide rare characters
which are extremely valuable within the context
of the game, again feeding back to strengthening
your characters. But the importance here is
creating that sense of urgency through having
a limited time window and providing something
that's very valuable.
And that combination is very powerful.
You say how powerful is it? The monetization
in that game actually doubles on an average-revenue-per-user
basis during these events. So there's a clear
payoff to finding the ways to make your game
work for users, to create that sense of urgency,
to give the players that great experience,
to provide a slightly different game experience,
to give them a different way to interact with
other users. And clearly there's a financial
reward for doing this within the game.
Next one I'd like to talk about is Kabam,
another very successful developer who moved
just last year from the Web over to mobile.
So in Kabam's case, we're going to focus their
case study on Kings of the Camelot, Battle
for the North.
They also have several other successful titles
on Google Play, including The Hobbit, Arcane
Empires, and the soon to release Fast & Furious
6.
One of the lessons from Kabam was always be
testing. Kabam focuses on core gaming users.
Core gaming users monetize much better than
your average user, and as a result of being
able to earn that revenue, they're able to
reinvest those earnings back into paid user
acquisition. In this case here, they're doing
a split test on several different campaigns.
On the campaign on the left, you can see a
campaign focused around characters and concept.
On the campaign on the right, you can see
a campaign much more focused around a realistic
depiction of game play.
Kabam is always testing, and so based on the
relative success of each of these campaigns,
they can add more resources to one, take them
away from another, and be very flexible in
growing their overall user base.
In terms of retention, as I mentioned, Kabam
recently came from Web over to mobile, and
they quickly realized a difference in those
users.
The mobile sessions were much more frequent.
There were many more sessions through the
course of the day, but they were also shorter,
and so one of the first things they did was
change the way they did the content refreshes
to make them more frequent.
You can also see visually depicted here, on
the left, that's the Web game, and there's
a very rich landscape of game-play elements.
Many of the major elements are spread further
apart. It's really designed to be played with
a mouse and keyboard, obviously. And on the
right, you have a much more streamlined game
experience on mobile. Many of the user actions
are able to be taken right from your thumb
in a very easy way.
Now, monetization. Kabam really focuses on
providing visual consistency. As I said, it's
really important how you ask your users for
payment. In their case, they want to minimize
any confusion, and so here, through all three
screens, you can see the exact identical presentation
throughout.
The final case study today will be on Pandora.
Pandora is a company that's extremely well-known.
It hardly needs an introduction. The leading
Internet radio service.
Kabam is one of those lucky few apps that
has reached the top of the lists, and so from
there -- it's hard to get there, but when
you do, it's quite powerful. But what I really
want to focus on with Pandora that's a recent
change that they've made is around monetization.
And so as Ibrahim alluded to earlier is you
can see in the chart here, something changed
in February. And what was that change?
So the thing that changed in February is Pandora
implemented our in-app billing subscriptions.
Previously, before that time, while the revenue
and payments were much flatter, you had to
go from your mobile device over to Pandora
on Web and sign up for subscription there
to be able to use the subscriptions on mobile.
By reducing all of that payment friction,
by allowing a user to purchase directly from
the mobile device, they saw a big bump in
overall payments.
But it doesn't stop there. It gets even better
the next month, because what happened here?
So at this time, Pandora still allowed users
40 free hours of mobile listening per month.
But for those users who reached those 40 free
hours and still wanted more, Pandora asked
them to pay. And that's what really allows
this. And omotenashi is the theme. It's finding
that mix of you have users. You're providing
a great value to users. For free you're providing
40 free hours of mobile listening per month,
but yet there's so many users who want to
help you build your business, they love your
product so much they're happy to pay at that
time.
So in summary, when you're thinking about
acquisition, think about improving your Play
Store page and investing in your Play Store
page. Consider cross promotion, especially
with multiple different applications.
For those applications that are making money,
reinvest those earnings for paid user acquisition.
And of course everybody wants to get at the
top of the charts.
For retention, really think about rewarding
the user actions that you're trying to promote.
And consider reinventing your user experience.
It's really important to provide clear objectives
to users, and to support those objectives
with the overall user experience.
Design for mobile. It's important, and users
will notice.
In (indiscernible) monetization the way that
you merchandise within your products on mobile
matters. If you change new game play mechanics,
users will notice and you can drive huge success.
Present a consistent visual experience. And
finally, there's still -- there's developers
that have charts like this, and we're looking
forward to even more of these in the coming
year.
And so that concludes the prepared part for
our talk. As we mentioned, following this
talk we'll be taking Q&A in the Office Hour
areas. We'd also like to point out a few other
--
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: We have time to do
the questions.
>>Bob Meese: Yeah, we can do a few now, but
we'd like to specifically point out a few
we thought were particularly noteworthy and
valuable for your time.
And then most importantly, we'd like to say
thank you. We would like to thank you all
of you for your time today. We would like
to thank some of the developers who were part
of this. I see Kabam here in the front row.
Thank you guys very much. And then thank you
to all of the developers on Google Play. It's
been an amazing past year, but the future,
I believe, is even brighter.
>>> I had one quick question. Can I ask now?
[ Applause ]
>>> You said something about the carrier billing,
apart from the gift card. What is that carrier
billing?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: So carrier billing
is basically the ability for a user to put
their purchases on a monthly bill. So the
same bill you get from your provider, you
just put all your purchases on that bill.
And so it just adds up to that.
>>> So if you want to do international calling
or something, is it used for that or for what?
>>Bob Meese: It's just for buying in-app products.
So when you're, let's say, playing a game
or you're even subscribing to Pandora, you
can put your Pandora subscription on your
monthly phone bill.
>>> Oh, that way.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Yeah.
>>> Hello. I'm having a little bit of time
just judging business models and evaluating
business models when I'm thinking about developing
apps. Like, for example, you're talking about
7x improvements, 5x improvements, 2x improvements,
and all that sounds great but zero times five
is still zero.
So the question is what does it mean to be
in the hundred top-grossing apps? Is there
any charts of, like, revenue, actual dollars
per month if you're a certain percentile of
your app in that top-grossing list? I'm having
a really hard time finding useful data in
that direction.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: So I would say that's
probably like partner data. We generally can't
share information like that about how much
revenue people make in our different rankings.
It varies a lot depending what type of application
is up there. Clearly, if you have a $9.99
a month subscription and you are at the top
gross end, that gets you up there faster.
It varies a lot, so it's hard for us to give
a firm number there.
>>> Even if it's completely anonymized statistic,
like if your app is in the top 2% you can
expect, I don't know, $3,000 a month?
>>Bob Meese: You want more just what is the
data behind it.
>>> Just very rough guidelines. Can I expect
to make 30 bucks a month, 3,000 bucks a month,
300,000 bucks a month if I have a top 2% app?
It's just really hard to get a feeling for
this.
>>Bob Meese: Sure. I mean, if you're interested
enough, there's data that's out there. A number
of the developers are publicly traded, and
so there you can get a sense of what their
revenues are.
As Ibrahim said, it's challenging for us to
share our partners' data. We all have confidentiality
agreements.
We've tried as much as possible through this
presentation to be as open, and over time
we've become more and more open. But if you
want to talk more, we can find you at Office
Hours.
>>> Okay. Thanks.
>>> Now with version three of in-app billing,
how soon can we expect to be able to do multiple
purchases of a single item? For instance,
purchase 200 tokens for two bucks and have
Google Play handle the maintenance of that?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: So that's (indiscernible)
configuring one skew that equals 200 tokens.
>>> Yeah.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: It's not in the immediate
roadmap, but it's something we've talked about
in the past. So I'll take that back to the
team and see if we can prioritize it.
And the use case, is it just a maintenance
issue or --
>>> I mean, I can do it right now, but I'll
have to build my own server infrastructure
to manage the consumption of those 200 tokens.
So what I'd really like to do is allow the
user to purchase 200 tokens, and then as they
use them in game, I just tell Google Play
consume one token, consume one token.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Okay. Yeah, that makes
sense.
>>> Hi. Do you have any tip or -- what's better?
To enlighten the pro app or do a light app
in a purchase?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: I'm sorry; I didn't
get that.
>>Bob Meese: You're saying whether you do
two different applications or whether you
do a free app with an in-app purchase?
>>> Yeah.
>>Bob Meese: One error we found is whenever
developers have two different apps, it creates
a lot of overhead. So some of the general
guidance is simplifying, finding one application
to invest all of your resources behind. Otherwise,
it can lead to confusion.
So the general best practice is invest in
a single app, especially for smaller developers.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: And the upgrade experience
is not as nice; right? Because you have to
get them to go install a different app and
buy another app versus just in-app purchase
any upgrade, you unlock the new content immediately
in the app.
>>> Thanks.
>>> Yeah, I was wondering if you are considering
doing promo codes for paid apps? And are you
also considering affiliate programs?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Yeah, those are things
that we've looked into as well. We've launched
the promotional campaigns in terms of promo
codes for money, so you can actually get $50,
as I mentioned, in the earlier Galaxy S3 campaign.
We're looking as well into being able to allow
developers to issue promo codes and have them
redeemed by -- whether it's the press or reviewers
or whomever it is. Yes.
>>> And what about the affiliate programs?
Do you -- Are you going to launch that soon?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: I don't think it will
launch soon, but we'll definitely talk about
them, especially in the content side of Google
Play. But we'll definitely take that back
to the team.
>>> All right. Thanks.
>>> How are you defining what is a top app?
Is it, you know, the top sales that day? That
week? That month?
And are you also doing any editorializing
around that where you're just putting in things
like you like?
>>Bob Meese: No, no. All the top lists are
straight up algorithmic, and there, it's revenue
transacted through Google Play, and it's generally
over a week time frame.
>>> One week time frame?
>>Bob Meese: Yep.
>>> Same thing across free/paid apps -- or
free apps, paid apps, et cetera?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: There was a talk earlier
about discovery that Ankit Jain gave. It's
one of those we've highlighted, and that was
actually all about that, all about discovery
and top lists and those sorts of things.
>>> You had an example about the kind of creative
that works well in the Play Store and what
your listing should contain. Do you have similar
recipes or insights about how to do paid user
acquisition, which you also briefly mentioned?
What works in paid user acquisition?
>>Bob Meese: We observe it. We don't make
recommendations. There's a part of Google's
business which is fully separate from us with,
you know, the ads business, which focuses
more on that.
For us, the conversation today was more around
observing more so than recommending, but there's
plenty of other smart people, either other
developers that are out there that are doing
it or the vendors themselves, that I'm sure
will be happy to educate you.
>>> If I have a paid application with low
download numbers, one way I could boost those
is to offer it free for a period of time,
say a week or a month or even a day. Is that
still not possible, and why?
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Converting a free app
to a paid app.
>>> Other way. I have a paid app now. I want
to make it free for a day or a week.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: And then bring it back.
>>> Mm-hmm.
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: We'll have to take
that back to the Developer Console team. That's
more of how do we manage the skew and what
types of skews are out there, and like each
product and categorization, but I'll bring
that back to the team.
>>Bob Meese: And I think that's it. Our time
is up. So we really appreciate your questions.
Please, follow up with --
>>Ibrahim Elbouchikhi: Yeah, Office Hours.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]