>>Paul Lewis: So this
is device agnostic development and I'm Paul
Lewis. I'm the guy looking confused over on
the left. Mostly on the right right now. I
spend -- I'm on the Chrome developer relations
team. I spend my days at talking about and
rendering performance.
>>Pete Beverloo: I'm Peter Beverloo. I'm a
software engineer on the Chrome team. I work
on Chrome for Android. I mostly spend my time
pushing the web platform forward.
>>Paul Lewis: So we ran a small survey and
we asked developers two questions amongst
many. The questions we asked them were, which
form factors do you support versus prioritize?
Not surprisingly, 96% of people said we support
desktop. Pretty much everybody. Two-thirds
of people went for phone and tablet. As you
can see on the prioritization side, 81% of
the 200 or so developers that we asked said,
you know what, desktop is our top priority.
This leads us to a question, if we prioritize
a single form factor, what happens? The answer
is probably quite obvious, right? We start
to build on the expectations of capability.
We build expecting that we're going to have
desktop-like performance. That we're going
to expect to see big screens, good GPs, good
CPs, a lot of memory. All those kinds of things.
>>Pete Beverloo: So along comes new form factor.
Such as mobile. What does this mean? Well,
we have been creating web sites for desktop
experiences for quite a long time now. Desktop
experiences give us a number of advantages
over more limited platforms such as mobile
devices. As an example, there's this big screen
available to you which has a lot of space
for you to put content on or to put data on.
But on mobile, there's a difference. It's
not just a screen size, which is different.
It's a lot smaller. But it's also in terms
of a number of additional constraints such
computational power. We create web sites using
a lot of JavaScript, for example, for scrolling
or concordance, and while this works fine
and acceptable on a desktop machine, on a
mobile, this will look janky. So along comes
new form factor. It's not just about desktop
and mobile. The web actually goes quite a
bit further than that. This is something we've
only started to see quite recently. Back in
the days, there used to be mobile devices
which were capable of internet using imodes
or similar systems. They weren't really internet.
You could see a web page. You could talk to
a server but the experience was quite limited.
These days, mobile devices such as phones
and tablets, they are basically on par with
desktop devices and they just work just like
a desktop machine. Of course, with a number
of additional constraints. Now, we're see
more and more come to televisions or consoles.
On a television, the screen is a lot bigger
but we also know the user is sitting away
from the screen quite a bit further than is
the case with mobile device and desktop machine.
Which means that as developers we actually
have to change how we create web sites. With
console, be it a portable one or be it a stationary
one next to your television, the story changes
completely altogether again and with portable
devices, such as consoles, they can be similar
to mobile, like a telephone. But they could
be entirely different as well with different
forms of inputs and different types of managing
your data which come with it. We really don't
know. Like what is the next device? We've
got desktops, mobile, televisions, consoles.
What will come next? Are there going to be
wearable computers? Could be anything.
>>Paul Lewis: So the point we are trying to
make with all this is that it's just the web.
Okay? We have this propensity for talking
about the mobile web. We don't talk about
the desktop web or the TV web or the console
web. We just talk about the mobile web. That's
fair enough to some degree. What we need to
start realizing, I think, is it's just the
web. It's consumed through a number different
devices. A good experience matters no matter
what the device. So then, becoming device
agnostic. If we figure we will have people
connecting to size and applications through
a bunch of different devices, how can we start
actually being device agnostic? So the grand
unified theory of devices. Sounds good. We
figured we can actually turn this on its head.
We can actually start figuring out what the
constraints are. Okay? Instead of device capability,
what about looking at the device constraint?
We figured there are these three constraints.
We can assess every device we know about,
and the ones we don't know about, the ones
coming tomorrow, in the same way. Network.
How quickly can it pull stuff down on the
wire? What's the latency? What's the bandwidth?
It it's network constraint, it's going to
be slow.
Compute constraint. So how quickly can it
process information? How much memory has it
got? Is it good at calculating my styles and
laying out my page? What's the CPU like? The
last one is a giant, shiny monkey head. How
quickly can it push pixels around the screen?
Does it have a good GPU? When we start actually
start looking at it from this perspective,
what we can start to realize is if we distance
ourselves from these constraints, if we start
planning for these constraints, then what
we realize is that we are, in effect, becoming
agnostic to them. So that when we hit a device
with one or more of these constraints, that
we are not actually as bothered by it. So
instead of relying on the capabilities of
a desktop, we are now going to spin it on
its head, look at these constraints in turn,
figure out what comes up and how we can distance
ourselves from them.
>>Pete Beverloo: So let's look at a few of
these device types and map them against constraints.
This creates quite an interesting matrix.
I apologize to those of you in the back. It
will be extremely hard to read. I'll just
name what's on the slides. On a desktop machine,
the network will generally be quite good.
You will be connected to your home DSL connection
which will be quite performant. Computational
power will be decent, even for older desktop
machines while they are still better than
mobile. Rendering performance will be decent
because they are multipurpose machines. They
are not just created for a single, streaming
video. So they will be able to display web
sites. And the screen is big. Maybe not as
big as a television in terms of physical size
but often you have a monitor of maybe 20 or
24 inches width and, as a developer, that
gives you a lot of space to play with. On
mobile it's a little bit different. With a
mobile device you can be on the move at any
random time and you cannot rely on a network
connection to always be available. So network
conditions are quite bad. Computational power
can be okay. There's different classes of
mobile devices. Tablets are, of course, entirely
different from phones. But even within a single
class, such as a phone, there can be quite
a lot of differences. We've got phones over
$500, $600. There's phones for $50, and computational
power will rely a lot on the capabilities
of the actual device. Rendering performance
will be quite bad. We are trying to get to
60 frames per second, but it turns out to
be really difficult to get there on any platform.
And the screen is quite small. That's the
physical screen size. While the actual logical
screen size, so the number of pixels which
have to be shown to the user can be a lot
bigger because we have got all these high
resolution fonts. For televisions, well, they
are standing in your house. I don't often
walk around with a television behind my arm.
>>Paul Lewis: What? I do.
>>Pete Beverloo: Okay. So the network conditions
will generally be similar to your normal desktop
computer. Computational power is bad. It's
meant for showing video, not for showing web
sites. Rendering performance will be bad for
the same reasons because the device really
has been made for a single purpose. And the
screen is pretty big but the resolution can
be smaller and in some cases even smaller
than a mobile device. Now, for consoles, it's
quite similar to mobile. It depends on the
kind of console really. You can be on the
move at all times. Computational power, they
are meant for games for interactive imaging
while web sites can be static content. Rendering
performance, again, it really depends on the
device. And the same goes for screen size.
And for the new class of devices, we just
don't know. We have no idea what's it going
to get us.
>>Paul Lewis: Actually, to be fair. If we
take a step back. We actually don't know on
any of these because let's say desktop, take
that for a second, it could be a laptop as
well. Now, we said good Internet network,
but what if you have tethered your phone?
>>Pete Beverloo: Or what if you have a dial-up
Internet connection?
>>Paul Lewis: Yeah. So at this point actually
all bets are off, right? Because on any of
these you can find an exception. Okay?
>>Pete Beverloo: So to set reality is that
everything in this matrix is a maybe. We just
don't know. And the only real way to figure
out what you need to optimize for your web
site is not to just blindly apply all the
best practices you can find around the Internet.
You need to measure and you need to look at
your statistics. Go to whatever statistics
you have. Look at the devices which your visitors
are actually using. Optimize for these devices.
Use the number of available APIs which we
will come back to later in the presentation.
Actually measure what your performance bottlenecks
are. One way of measure what's going on are
your Chrome DevTools. This is built into Google
Chrome in all the release channels. It makes
it entirely possible to accurately measure
any aspect at any time what's happening on
your page in terms of network computational
requirements and rendering as well. We've
got a series of videos available on YouTube.
Called the breakpoints. The screen shot here
is showing Paul Irish on the first few seconds
of a presentation which gives you a video
introduction to a number of the features available
on DevTools. There was a talk yesterday about
Chrome DevTools resolution which will have
shown you about a number of new features which
have recently become available. And we've
recently updated the DevTools documentation
which you can definitely check out as well
and which contains a lot of information about
how to measure exactly what's going on on
your pages.
>>Paul Lewis: Okay. So we've established that
we can be on any device and we can't really
predict exactly what the constraints are going
to be for that device. Now let's step into
network computer rendering. This is actually
essentially a performance talk by the back
door. If you have been up to the third floor
and seen in the Chrome area, we have a performance
area and network computer rendering are in,
in fact, three areas. If you have not been,
you should stop by. But what we are going
do is we are going to step through the common
issues that we see on each of these three
areas and we are going to try to find ways
of distancing ourselves from those constraints
so that irrespective of which device we are
actually hitting, if we have hit that constraint
we have done everything that we possibly can
to try to make that a non-issue.
>>Pete Beverloo: So the first thing to keep
in mind is the page load time. This basically
describes the time it takes for the user to
start a navigation action like clicking on
a link or entering a link interbrowser address
bar until the time that they see the page
and that they are actually able to use it.
Now, you've got all your visitors. If your
page on a mobile device takes more than three
seconds to load, 57% of your visitors will
go away. They will just leave. They will go
elsewhere. They might search for an alternative.
They may know of an alternative and they are
gone for the day basically. Now it gets worse.
For all these visitors, if your page takes
more than three seconds to load, 46% will
not return. They will find a competitor of
yours. They will find an alternative source
of the data or the information which are giving
to them and start preferring the other web
site just because it loads a little bit faster.
And probably the worst statistic is that 22%
of your visitors will tell their friends to
not use your web site. Now, let that sink
in for a little bit. That means that over
one in five visitors of your mobile web site
will tell their friends to not visit your
site if your page takes more than three seconds
to load. That's quite a lot of impact and
one thing to keep in mind here is that the
perceived loading time of a web page is actually
15% higher than the actual loading time. And
it gets worse because when they are talking
to their friends about this, they will remember
loading time which is up to 35% slower of
what it actually was. So while it actually
could have been three seconds, in their memory
it may be up to five seconds or more. So there
are a few things we can do. Probably the biggest
contributor to having a big load time for
your web pages is having a huge number of
requests on your page. Now, for every request
to your page, we can look at costs implied
by it and we can split it up in three different
ones. Firstly, there is the latency cost.
For each of these requests, for the resources
which could be an image or style sheet, we
need to make a connection to the server -- well,
in some cases because in other cases we may
be able to re-use the connection. We need
to request the resource, get a reply and that
could take a little bit of time, especially
if the resource is hosted on a different server,
in which case a DNS lookup might be necessary.
Now, for big resources such as images, bandwidth
may be a constraint. If I am on a 3G connection
and I'm sitting on a train, then it will take
a while for that image to be available on
my mobile device. Of course, there is a financial
cost. This is not just about visitors which
you may lose if your site takes quite a long
time to load. But Paul and I are from the
United Kingdom and if we want to use the mobile
Internet on our normal phones here in the
United States, then it costs us up to $8 per
megabyte. You need to have a really good server
or web site if I want to use it that cost.
So probably the easiest thing to do here is
obsolete a number of these requests. For every
single one of the resources on your page,
ask yourself, do you really need it? Can you
maybe get around by inlining it on the page?
By concatenating style sheets, so having several
style sheets in a single file? Or can you
perhaps minimize them to reduce bandwidth
cost? And making optimizations such as these
will often have a big impact in a base loading
time performance of your web sites.
>>Paul Lewis: Now, a lot of people already
do this one, right? Most people when you speak
to them, they say, yeah, we can concatenate
min files. The next thing we want to talk
about is reducing the image overhead. Statistic
that you may have heard of and if you haven't
and it's the first time, really good one to
put in your head, 60% of web traffic, 60%
of the average web page is images. And that
gives us a huge opportunity for optimizing
our network. Okay, can we change formats?
Now, in the case of WebP, by switching to
it, the Chrome web store saved several terabytes
of transfer every day. Now, it may not be
that it is going to save you that much of
transfer. You can immediately realize that
actually instead of JPEG I should be using
pings or pings instead of JPEG, or gifs maybe
or even WebP. It depends on the actual image
and what you are trying to achieve and so
forth. But spend some time figuring out whether
you can change formats, whether you can change
quality and that will potentially save you
an awful lot of data. The next thing is actually
request images of the size you need. Responsive
web design has become all the rage and it's
really quite cool. But there is this problem
with it which is that people often request
their full-size images and then the user ends
up paying a tax, as it were. We rely on client
side resizing to get it down but we end up
requesting a much larger file in some cases
than we actually need. There are loads of
things you can do on the server side to actually
let you scale down and cache a smaller version
of the image. If you are not doing that, take
a look at that one. The last one is, do you
even need an image? Controversial. You could
get away with SVG in some cases, web fonts
with icon glyphs. Have a look at those and
play around. See if you can actually get rid
of some of your images. 60% of the average
page is going to be images. So if you can
get rid of that, that saves us a ton.
>>Peter Beverloo: One of the solutions available
to you if you have control over your server
itself, is that you can look into using mod
PageSpeed. Mod PageSpeed is a plug-in made
by Google which basically gives you a free
pass to a quicker web site. What it does,
it looks at your web page before sending it
to the user. It will look into ways to optimize
your page by inlining resources, by concatenating
style sheet files together and by doing a
number of number of optimization steps which
just generally make it faster. Of course,
this does require you to be in control of
your web page -- of your web server, I'm sorry.
If you are not, there's another tool available
called PageSpeed insights. Many of you will
work on the front end of a web site and this
tool is as simple as enter the URL of your
page, click on a button, it will start downloading
your page. It will start analyzing it. It
will show up with a number of suggestions
and how to optimize the page itself and make
it faster to load and dissipate to the user.
Now, of course these two tools will only do
-- will only optimize your page to the best
of their abilities. But they do this by looking
at the average space, what they are doing,
and applying these rules of your site. Now,
your web sites are not average. They are special
because, in a way, there is no average web
site, and the only real way optimize the page
itself by doing it yourself and looking at
what pieces of information or resources on
your page actually impact or reduce performance.
Now, we have already spoken a little bit about
DevTools which make it possible for you to
look at exactly which parts are taking a long
time in the loading process of the web page.
But then there are API available to you as
their resource timing API which exposes high-fidelity
information about most of the resources which
you have included on the page itself and gets
you insight into how long it took to actually
look up the DNS for that resource, to connect
to the server or to download to resource.
And especially if you have blocking resources
such as scripts, it can be a great way to
actually figure out which script is blocking
your page from showing up quickly.
>>Paul Lewis: Okay. So we've talked about
the kind of things that you can get into for
actually transferring your sites and apps
down to end users. Now we actually step into
the runtime-y bit. It's actually running.
And this is the bit where we talk about compute.
So we've got everything downloaded or we've
got enough to get going, and now we want to
talk about what that actually involves to
solve for compute.
So the first thing you need to do is define
this term "jank." Now, you've probably heard
it over the course of the last few days. Let's
define it again just in case.
Chrome is synchronized to the refresh rate
of the device. Now, that's 60 hertz. That
means you've got just about 16 1/2 milliseconds
to get everything done. And that includes
Chrome's housekeeping, it includes your code
-- and that's a bunch of things like layout,
recalc style, paint, composite, JavaScript
-- all that stuff. 16 milliseconds. I don't
get much done in 16 milliseconds, but Chrome
really, really does.
We call this the frame budget, and if we don't
hit that frame budget, users notice. It's
kind of this hitching. You know, when they
scroll and it hitches and hiccups? That's
what we call "jank."
So when we talk about "jank" in the coming
slides, that's what we're referring to. We're
talking about busting that frame budget of
most likely 16 1/2 milliseconds.
So the first thing I want to talk about in
the compute area is style recalculations.
Now, it's very common when we do apps that
we change class on the body, okay? And you
do that for maybe state and you maybe even
do it for styling. The problem is, the size
of the tree that's affected can be huge. Now,
you see on the left-hand side -- hopefully
you can see -- I was changing a class on the
body and I was affecting nearly twenty- -- just
over 23,000 elements by doing that. The recalculation
style effort then was 20 milliseconds.
Now, this is Canary that's telling us the
elements affected so if you haven't seen that
feature, it's a really useful thing when you're
trying to figure out kind of what was the
impact.
There's a corresponding one for layout as
well which tells you the scope and the size
of the layout calculation.
So we've changed the body, 23,000 elements,
20 milliseconds.
I knew that I actually wanted to affect 6
and when I did that, it was a fraction of
a millisecond.
Now, it sounds obvious but only change the
things that you need to change. Go and have
a look at your app, see whether you're actually
overdoing your style recalculation.
Layout thrashing. If you've not seen this
one before, this is quite a fascinating one,
really.
So this little bit of JavaScript at the top
allows us to get the target -- a thing called
"target" -- from the DOM, and what we're going
to do is we're going to go through a bunch
of other elements and we're going to ask -- we're
going to set their width to match the target's
width. Pretty trivial stuff to do. What is
that, three lines of code plus a comment?
Okay. The first thing we need to notice is
that asking for offset width is going to cause
Chrome to do a layout.
So it goes off and it says, "All right. What's
the left, the top, the width, the height?
What do I need to know about all the elements
in the page to be able to give you a good
answer on offset width?"
So it goes off and it does that.
The next thing is, that first element gets
its style width value set to the target's
width.
The problem is, by doing that, we just invalidated
the layout calculation that we've just done.
So then the next time around the loop, we
ask Chrome to do a potentially very expensive
layout again.
So we're doing this get, set, get, set, get,
set, get, set, get, set. And the problem is
this adds up really quickly. Especially when
layout is expensive.
What we should be doing is getting once and
setting many. And it probably makes sense
when you hear it in that sense.
The thing is to realize that offset width
is actually going to cause the layout to happen.
And you can Google that, how to not trigger
a layout in Webkit, and you'll see a very
good blog post that will tell you which ones
in Webkit and Blink will cause a layout to
happen.
So avoid layout thrashing.
Two very simple things there: Layout and style
calculations.
>>Peter Beverloo: So a browser has a very
particular set of skills. Skills it has acquired
over a short, but quite eventful, career.
You should not do in JavaScript in an imperative
way what you can do in a declarative way.
Animations and transitions are excellent examples
of that. Five years ago, six years ago, perhaps
even more, we had all these libraries such
as jQuery or Dojo, which are animation libraries,
and it allowed you to animate items on your
page. It allows you to change the left property
from -- from zero to a thousand and move an
element horizontally over your page without
the user having to do anything at all, and
that's awesome.
But this is really costly because every time
the frame does something -- and often a library
internally sets the timer to try and match
the frame budget of the browser -- it needs
to look at the position, it needs to do a
re-layout, and all of these are really expensive
operations.
Now, there are excellent alternatives available
to this in CSS, to do it in a declarative
way, and by using a declarative way, you're
actually saying -- telling the browser what
you want it to do instead of telling the browser
what it has to do.
And by telling the browser your goal, you're
basically saying, "Okay. I want you to do
this effect, but please do it in the best
way you can do it for me." And by using the
CSS transitions module or the CSS animation
module, the browser is actually able to optimize
all this transcript code away from you. It
can do these animations, in some cases, on
a different thread and this will look a lot
better and a lot less janky for the user,
while also taking a lot less CPU and, well,
it doesn't eat away from your frame budget
and it works regardless of many of the constraints
of the device.
Up until a few years ago, fixed position was
unreliable. It kind of could stick around
in the viewport. It could be janky if you
were scrolling. Now, lately, in pretty much
all big mobile browsers, this has been fixed,
and of course it works in all desktop browsers
as well.
So if you have an element which should always
be available in the viewport of the page itself,
just use position ficky -- sticky -- no, position
fixed and don't use JavaScript to keep it
in exactly that position, using the scrolling
position, for example.
>>Paul Lewis: But you could use position sticky.
What would you use position sticky for?
>>Peter Beverloo: Well, position sticky actually
is a new experimental feature in Chrome.
>>Paul Lewis: Really?
>>Peter Beverloo: Yeah. You can go to the
Chrome flex page. You can enable it for Chrome
for Android as well. And position sticky is
somewhat like a fixed position element, but
if the parent element is not inside of the
viewport itself, so if it's scrolled away
somewhere, then it will just be an inflow
element. If the parent element comes in the
page, then it will make sure that the element
is -- that the sticky positioned element is
visible. But if the parent element kind of
moves out of the viewport but still is visible,
then the element will stick around in the
viewport as if it was fixed position. And
an example you might know which uses this
quite a lot is an address book. If you have
a lot of names, then the header which contains
the first letter of the names which are currently
being displayed may stick around at the top
of the viewport for a little while until the
next letter is up.
And the fourth big point is keep your invent
listener code to a minimum. Some event handlers
such as scrolling events will be called many,
many, many times per second, sometimes even
multiple times per frame, and any processing
you do in these handlers will eat away from
your frame budget and this will definitely
limit the time Chrome has to display your
Web page and, as a result, you might miss
frames.
>>Paul Lewis: One thing you can definitely
do with that one is, say you're doing something
in your scroll handler. Just get it to store
the last known value. Okay? And then schedule
up a requestAnimationFrame. Because what will
happen is most of the time you have like four
or five of these running, okay? You get like
four or five in the frame, but you actually
only care about the last one, so you just
store the value and then set a requestAnimationFrame
to actually deal with the last known value.
This is called de-bouncing in some places
or -- yeah, "de-bouncing" is the most common
name for it. And just basically rather than
running that expensive code in your scroll
handler, just keep the value and run one handler
at the end.
Okay. So we've talked about network, we've
talked about compute, so now let's take a
look at some of the stuff that happens inside
of render.
Now, I have DevTools open here and it's captured
something which is quite expensive on the
paint side of things, and if you look, we've
twittled down one of the pane records and
we spent 13 milliseconds decoding a JPEG.
Now, we have 16 milliseconds to do everything,
not just paint. And then we spent a further
71 milliseconds dealing with the resize.
Now, this is what I was talking about before
about responsive web design is that there's
potentially a second tax. And before, we talked
about reducing image overhead but we talked
about it from the network constraint. We also
have a render constraint because we actually
have to process these images.
So actually, just getting the -- the smallest
possible image and in the correct dimensions
is actually extremely advantageous.
So check out DevTools if you've not seen that
feature. That's really useful to actually
find out your decodes and your resizes.
Paint costs. So whenever you scroll or you're
interacting with your page, the things that
change or the things that appear on screen,
they need to get painted. And since painting
is actually quite an expensive thing, depending
on the styles that you apply, we have to keep
it to a minimum.
So there are two things that are actually
involved in reducing paint costs, the first
of which is actually reducing the size of
the area that got painted.
So you see I've got show paint rectangle switched
on here. So you go into DevTools, hit the
cog, switch on show paint rectangles, and
then interact with your page.
Now, as I roll over these elements, you can
see that they're flashing red which is Chrome's
saying, "I repainted those."
But watch there. When I scrolled, the whole
page flashed red. Now, that should be a warning
to you that the entire page needed painting,
and that's potentially an expensive thing
and it's the kind of thing that gives you
those big green bars, okay? Now, there's a
very specific reason for this one, but I'll
let you figure out what that is.
The thing to know is that you're looking for
those smaller areas. The question you should
be asking yourself is, "Am I seeing the bits
that are getting repainted that I thought
were going to get repainted? Is it predictable
to me?" As in, "I rolled over this and I expected
it to repaint. Yes, it did."
When I scrolled, I didn't expect to see the
whole thing flash or the whole screen flash,
right? So there's something to look at there.
The second thing, once we've reduced the size
of the paint areas is to then reduce the complexity
of the paint areas, so we've got this other
tool that's fantastic. It's called -- called
continuous page repainting. And what it does
is it puts Chrome into a mode where it forces
Chrome to repaint the whole page every frame.
Okay? And you see it switched on there. It
puts this little chart in the top right-hand
corner with the number of milliseconds that
it took to paint the page.
Now, what we can do is we start switching
off styles, and in this particular case, switching
off box shadow or border radius is the one
that's actually dropping that time to paint
really far down.
Now, I'd much rather you didn't walk out of
here saying "Box shadow is bad. Border radius
is bad. We shan't do these." That's not what
we want you to do. What we want you to do
is realize that your styles have a corresponding
cost and there is a tool in DevTools that
will let you figure what the cost is.
And you can use that to your advantage to
-- to move away from that constraint so that
you're not render-bound, okay? So reduce the
paint size, then reduce the complexity of
your paints.
>>Peter Beverloo: So far, we've talked about
technical constraints which apply to you as
the developer, but eventually what we really
want is to give the right user experience
to the end user, to the person who is actually
using your page.
Now, one thing to realize is that the user
comes for your content. They come to your
Web site with a specific person -- purpose.
That could be to get information. That could
be to use your service. And they don't really
care about that big image header which you
had at all of the top of your pages, which
basically just means that they have to scroll
the page before they even get to the content.
You, as the developer, have all these constraints,
but the user shouldn't have them.
And the main thing here, the main takeaway,
is that if I, as a user, use my mobile device,
if I use a phone to look at your Web site,
I really don't care about how well it works
on a web -- on a desktop machine because I
use a mobile device. And the other way around,
the same goes.
And while you probably want to offer the same
-- a different user experience, because after
all they are different classes of devices,
you should offer the same functionality.
And what this basically means is that the
content on your page, or the services, it's
fine to refactor them or to reshape them in
a way that's more optimized for the device,
as long as you don't offer that reduced functionality
such as a simple entry page, "Sorry, you can't
use this feature at this time because it's
not optimized for mobile. Please use a desktop."
That just scares away users.
When you develop a Web site for a desktop
computer, you've got all this real estate
available to you. You can put content next
to each other, you can put it on top of each
other, in any form that you want, for -- especially
for text.
You can have a news article, you can have
a bold introduction, you can have related
information about the company or the people
who are mentioned in the article itself.
And this is nice because on a desktop, because
there's all this space, even a relatively
big amount of text looks like moderate and
it doesn't fill up your screen.
Now, for mobile devices, this is a problem.
Or actually for devices with constrained screen
size this is a problem. Because if I look
at exactly the same text, or maybe even one
paragraph of text on my mobile phone, then
my entire screen is filled with text, and
that's quite intimidating.
If I then start to scroll down and I get five
or six more paragraphs, then I have to scroll
for several seconds before the text stops.
Even at relatively high scroll speeds.
And this is intimidating and this could easily
scare away users.
Now, we know that you're not always in control
of your content, so changing the text itself
or changing the images might not always be
a feasible solution, but you can at least
pass on the message that the users care a
lot more about getting an optimized experience
and care about getting the same functionality
than they get for getting all of the text
and all of the site information.
>>Paul Lewis: And one thing to notice here,
just if you can go back, is at the bottom
of that that we've got an image that's kind
of suggesting something is not responsive.
Just bear in mind if you do do this kind of
responsive thing, just watch out for that
tax that I told you about earlier about resizing
images down. Make sure you always request
the images at the right size.
Okay. So we have a couple of suggestions,
as you've just seen, because we think it will
be good to give you a couple of -- couple
of suggestions for your work workflow.
The first one is assign somebody that you
used to like to your team as the sheriff.
They'll probably become unpopular pretty quickly.
However, they perform a very important role
for you.
As you can see, the idea is to clarify and
set some constraints before you start. How
much time are we going to spend in garbage
collection, paint, composite, layout, recalc
style? Where are we going to spend our time,
on the assumption that we've got a network-constrained
device or a render-constrained device. Where
are we actually going to spend our time?
Then that person is going to track it and
they're going to stop you from shipping if
you don't hit it.
Now, the question then becomes, "Well, what
number should we have?" And the honest answer
is: It depends on your application.
But have that person -- a lot of times when
we speak to developers, performance and this
-- this kind of stuff is often a bit like
a unit test. Are we fast? No. Oops.
[ Laughter ]
>>Paul Lewis: What we're talking about is
building it in from the start so that it's
something that you're continually checking
all the way through and there's somebody who's
owning and is responsible for that for you
as a team.
Check out jankfree.org. That's a bunch of
slides. It's a bunch of articles. It's a bunch
of videos. All of which are designed to help
you with these -- the things that we've talked
about and in a lot more detail than we've
been able to cover so that's a fantastic resource
that you can track.
So should we conclude? We should because it
says "Conclusion" on the screen.
>>Peter Beverloo: Yes.
>>Paul Lewis: Super.
>>Peter Beverloo: It's not about the device
which users are able to access your Web sites.
It's about the content and the experience
which you're delivering to them. And while
the content and the functionality should be
the same, you can optimize them to create
a user experience specific to the different
devices.
>>Paul Lewis: The devices you're going to
deal with, they're going to probably have
at least one constraint at some point.
Even on a desktop you might have multiple
processes running. There's no guarantee that
you're going to be good. So you figure out
ways to actually just reduce the load, fight
against those constraints, and you will be
agnostic. Mostly, let the browser do what
it's good at doing. If you're doing stuff
with JavaScript and you don't need to do it,
don't do it. Let the browser do it for you.
>>Peter Beverloo: And just to reiterate on
the content a little bit more, users come
to your page for content. I've said it a number
of times and I just say it again.
Refactor your content in a more direct and
concise way to get it to them in the fastest
way possible, because, after all, that's why
they're there.
>>Paul Lewis: Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
>>Paul Lewis: We have a tiny amount of time
for one or two questions, maybe, so if you
have a question, go up to the mic and we'll
see if we can get through any of them. And
then if you want to find us after, we're going
to be upstairs in the Chrome area, probably
in the -- I'll at the for performance booth,
if you're interested.
>>> I'm curious. The last couple I/Os, we've
seen a lot about getting rid of jank and using
the de-bouncing technique that you guys have
talked to do so, which strikes me as a bug
in the spec because I don't know why anyone
would ever care about getting 200 touch or
scroll events per frame and yet every single
application that any developer here is going
to write means that we have to take all this
data, persist it somewhere, use it in yet
another function and let it be garbage collected
later.
Is that something that we should address at
a lower level than the JavaScript that we
write?
>>Paul Lewis: Well, I think if that's how
you feel, definitely involve yourself in the
spec process for sure. It's something that
we're trying to watch and I'm interested in
it because especially, as I said, I see a
lot of code going to scroll handlers and touch
handlers that doesn't need to be there. So
there's a certain amount of "should this be
spec, should this be developer required."
I haven't got a good use case for multiple
scroll handler -- or multiple calls to the
scroll handler, for example, inside a single
frame, but I wouldn't like to presume that
nobody does, but I'm not saying that they
do either, so I guess it could be something
that should be spec'd, and I'd involve yourself
in the spec process and see if we can hash
it out.
>>Peter Beverloo: Well, a lot of specifications
already keep this in mind by offering asynchronous
functionality rather than synchronous ones.
And even though this is often not the case
for event handlers yet, for -- for getting
many kinds of data, it will allow it to do
on the background thread, not block any other
processing and just come back when everything
is available.
We've gone a little bit over time.
>>Paul Lewis: Yeah. So I'm afraid if you've
got any questions, just come and find us upstairs.
Thank you.