What is PageSpeed Service and how does it
work?
Web pages today contain a lot more than HTML.
They combine stylesheets, images, videos,
Javascript files and other components to give
the rich interactive experience we now expect
on the web.
This means however that to display a web page,
a browser has to make several HTTP requests,
as many as 43 requests for the average web
page, to fetch all these resources from the
server hosting your site.
Many such network requests to fetch files
one after another increases wait time and
slows down the page. Slow web pages can make
visitors to your site less engaged and even
frustrated, leading to lower conversion and
lost revenue.
Google PageSpeed Service is an online service
you can use to automatically speed up your
website. It rewrites web pages dynamically
to apply several performance-improving practices,
and then serves the optimized pages via Google
servers to reduce page load time.
When you first setup PageSpeed Service for
your site, you’ll be guided to change its
DNS entry so that your domain name points
to PageSpeed servers. Once completed, PageSpeed
servers will serve your web pages and intelligently
cache their resources to serve them to users
faster. They’ll also fetch newer content
from your original host server so that the
latest version of your website is always served
to users.
PageSpeed servers are located in Google operated
datacenters distributed around the world.
So your site will benefit from the speed,
efficiency and security of the same infrastructure
that powers all of Google.
PageSpeed rewriters use a combination of techniques
to optimize web pages. One of them is to reduce
the number and size of the resources to be
fetched. PageSpeed Service rewrites web pages
to merge and compress Javascript, stylesheet
and image files, and to parallelize the download
of these files wherever possible. This means
fewer HTTP requests and lower round-trip times,
so your web page gets delivered to the browser
faster.
Another technique is to reduce the perceived
page load time. This is the minimum time that
users have to wait before they can view the
page.
The typical web page today is long and has
many visual elements. But only a small portion
of the page is initially visible in the browser
once the page has loaded.
PageSpeed Service can rewrite a web page so
that the parts of the page that users expect
to see first get downloaded first. This means
users can engage with your site right away,
without having to wait for the full page to
load. The rewriters can also cache parts of
the page that don’t change frequently so
they get delivered to the browser quickly
on future visits to your site.
This combination of advanced rewriter technology
and global serving infrastructure can dramatically
reduce the load time of your web pages, often
by as much as 40%. Faster web pages improve
the experience of visitors to your site and
so can increase both traffic and customer
conversion.
So get started with PageSpeed Service today
and discover how fast your websites can be!