[APPLAUSE]
BEN VINEGAR: Hello?
Test.
This is the Build Process
Panel, which thematically is all
about, how do we take our source
code in whatever form it may be
and transpile preprocess,
minify, optimize, et cetera
until it arrives
in its final form?
So my name's Ben Vinegar.
I'm a lead front
engineer at Disqus.
I also wrote a book called
Third Party JavaScript.
It's pretty terrible.
I have five wonderful
panelists with me.
First there's Kyle
Simpson, who you
may know as the author
of LABjs, a JSON author.
He's writing a book called
"You Don't Know JS."
Nick Fisher, who works at
SoundCloud and he designs
and implements a lot
of the build systems,
SoundCloud being a relatively
large client side applications
with some cool stuff going on.
Addy Osmani, who develops
TodoMVC and Yeoman, which
is a scaffolding tool
working with Grunt,
and he also sorts
on Chrome DevTools.
And then Sebastian
Golasch, who works
for Deutsche Telekom--
I practiced pronouncing
that for a while--
working on a product
there that also uses sort of
older, traditional build tools.
I don't know if "old"
is the right word,
but with Maven combined with
Grunt and some client side
stuff.
And then lastly, I
have Gareth Rushgrove,
who works for the UK government,
working on a big project that
involves modernizing a whole
bunch of UK government websites
and bringing them
into the modern era.
And with that said,
Gareth is just
going to start us off
with a quick presentation.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Your
build process needs you
because it's probably not
as good as it could be.
There it is.
But what is a build process?
What we're talking
about really is
it's a way of sharing common
actions as much as anything
else.
If it's just you doing something
and you're just doing it once,
that's not really
a build process,
but actually storing
it as something
that you can come back
to, or more commonly,
storing it as something that
your team can come back to
is really important
because frankly, people
suck at repetitive tasks.
If I ask someone to do
something over and over again,
they'll probably do
it subtly different.
A build process is always
about standardizing
those repetitive tasks.
And some of that's
to do with the fact
that words can mean different
things to different people.
If I say, can you minimize
this bit of JavaScript for me,
people will do it differently,
and that's probably
no good in an environment where
you're trying to work together.
You end up with
different results.
Someone might take longer.
That's no good.
We need to standardize.
But your build
process is software.
People come to it, certainly,
from engineering and web
development, from lots
of different paths,
and not all of them
will think of themselves
as software developers.
Tough.
You're a software developer.
If you're anywhere
near a build process,
you're a software developer.
Live with it.
But what are we building?
What are the sorts
of types of things
that we're putting
into our build process?
Ben mentioned a few
things that will
be common to lots of people in
the room-- CSS preprocessing,
templating-- Kyle-- bundling,
minification, linting, testing,
optimization, transpiling.
There's lots of things
we're doing with our code
and there's lots of
tools we're using.
Two of the common
ones at the moment,
certainly in the
front end space,
appear to be Gulp and Grunt.
Grunt-- this was a
few days ago, but I
bet it's about the same today.
Maybe it's less today because
we're all in this room
or watching on the video.
30,000 installs
of this every day.
That sounds like quite a lot.
That's a lot of interest.
That's a lot of people.
There's 2,500 Grunt
plug-ins, and I'll
come back to why that might
not be great in a moment.
There's actually
450 Gulp plug-ins,
and that's a tool that's not
been around anywhere near as
long.
But I said I'll come back
to why that might not
be good in a moment.
Contrib-jshint is a Grunt
plug-in, And excellent.
There's one for Gulp.
Brilliant.
And there's grunt-coffee
and gulp-coffee,
and there's
broccoli-coffee as well.
And at some point--
and there definitely
will be someone in this
room, someone watching this,
I'm building another
one, and hoping someone
comes along and builds another
one -coffee, and -jshint,
and everything else.
And we know there's
2,500 Grunt plug-ins.
Do we want 2,500 Gulp
ones and Broccoli ones
and everything else?
I think there's probably
a lot of front end
people in the room.
There's probably people writing
JavaScript, writing CSS,
writing HTML most of their time.
Is that fair to say?
Any people go, I'm basically
just a Java programmer?
[INAUDIBLE]
But we're all working
in environments
where there probably
is a bucket that
might not be written
in JavaScript.
You maybe are using
Node, maybe you're not.
Maybe it's Ruby, maybe it's
Python, maybe it's [INAUDIBLE].
It doesn't matter.
There's a lot of other things
going on around you that also
have build processes,
and there's
loads of build tools,
whether it's Make,
[INAUDIBLE], Maven, [INAUDIBLE].
There's loads of these.
There's a bit at the bottom that
says two points for each tool,
minus five if you
liked using Maven.
Ultimately, building
software isn't new.
It's happening all
over the place,
and standardizing all the
things, standardizing things
in silos probably isn't enough.
Even when it comes
to typical tasks
around front end
engineering, a lot of those
have plug-ins or projects
related to other build tools
that are doing
it, whether that's
[INAUDIBLE] versions of things
like [INAUDIBLE] Compiler
or Compressor versus
Sprockets and Rails
versus [INAUDIBLE] and PHP.
This is spiraling,
massive, all these things
doing fundamentally
the same jobs.
And really, everything
old is new again.
Building software is not new.
It's maybe new to-- these
tools are new, Grunt and Gulp.
There's a lot of interest
around programming
and JavaScript at the moment.
There's a lot of new
tools coming around,
but this isn't fundamentally
a new activity,
and some of the same
mistakes are being made.
Some of the learnings are
not being taken forward.
Make is older than you probably.
I wrote this before turning up.
I think that's broadly true.
Unless you're all 37,
Make is older than you.
There's a few people here who
probably look older than 37,
but I reckon most
of you-- I'm going
to go for Make is
older than you.
Make is a build tool.
If you haven't seen
it, it looks like this.
If you're thinking,
wait a minute.
Where's all the
rest of the code?
You can think, well,
maybe you should
be using Make rather than Grunt.
Do you know how many
Make plug-ins there are?
I don't think there are any.
That's probably going
to be completely untrue,
but basically, there aren't
really Make plug-ins.
There aren't really plug-ins
for LS as a Unix command tool.
The reason is because Unix
pipes are amazing, or rather,
the concept of simply
chaining things
together by sending
information between them.
LS doesn't have a Grep
plug-in or a Sort plug-in.
It's just about Unix
command line tools
being able to be
chained together.
It doesn't matter that
these things could
be written in different
languages by different people
at different times.
We don't have to customize
them all via plug-in models.
Actually, I don't do
a lot for [INAUDIBLE].
I haven't done
for quite a while.
So actually, I did a
whole bunch of research
into what people were
doing to be on this panel,
and I thought, as
a community, it
seems that there's a lot of
effort reinventing the wheel.
This isn't just true
for this community.
That's true of basically
programmers, myself included.
But we invariably invent
things and reinvent things
in our language of
choice and sometimes
in our tool of choice.
But the thing we have
to miss is that's
our language and tool
of choice at the moment,
and that probably
changes over time.
So anything that we
can do to minimize that
is probably a good
thing to think about
because we can
make things better.
And ultimately,
things are better
now than they were before.
Having tools is good.
This is not about,
oh, we shouldn't
have done any of that.
Throw it all away.
It's about, how can we make
it a lot more sustainable?
How can we learn
from 20-odd years,
30-odd years of other
programming communities' build
processes?
What is the most
valuable unit of sharing?
Is it a plug-in?
How can we build
community consensus
and avoid the
plug-in apocalypse?
I think there's a
genuine problem there.
Can we share entire
pipelines as well as tools?
It's fine sharing
the individual bits,
but actually, we probably can
all take a collection of things
together and string it
together to do the same thing.
And actually, can we
share the pipeline?
Is that a better
unit of sharing?
And importantly,
how do we break down
these artificial
programming language silos?
Because even if you're thinking,
well actually, my career is
going to be all about--
for engineering-- it's all
going to be about
JavaScript and CSS and HTML,
and probably they're
going to change,
they're going to evolve,
they're going to better.
The tools around it's
going to get better,
but that's what I'm going to do.
You'll probably
do it in a context
where other people
around you are writing
different programming
languages, and how do we
make it so there's not
that culture clash?
There's not that us versus them?
How do we bring these
things together?
They're just some
of the things that
were in my head and some
of the things I care about.
My other panelists
might violently
disagree with some of that.
With that, we can
go on to the panel.
[APPLAUSE]
BEN VINEGAR: Thanks, Gareth.
I think that was a pretty
good way to start us off.
There's a question I'm
looking for as I browse
this thing that's
been moved around.
I'm going to ask on
Cornell [INAUDIBLE].
And also I just
want to say, I feel
that we've butchered
your question slightly,
and if you would like to
go original with this,
please do so.
AUDIENCE: Is eliminating
a need for a build process
a goal of web standards?
For example, should CSS
adopt all the features
of CSS preprocessors, or should
it avoid duplicating them?
ADDY OSMANI: So one of
the really nice things
about the Extensible
Web Manifesto
has been the community
starts to iterate
on features and
languages like JavaScript
and tools like
JavaScript and so on,
and once we reach a
nice consensus there,
we can then go and move on to
standardizing those features.
So in the case of CSS
and preprocessors,
we've already started to see
things like variables actually
land and go from things
like Sass and LESS
directly into CSS.
The same thing is being
done with mix-ins.
I think that it's
perhaps not necessarily
the browser's responsibility
to provide hooks into your
build process, like a preprocess
step or a post-process step.
That seems to be something
that would be better left up
to additional tools or
something on the server side.
But I think that we currently
have a good system in place
for actually landing things
that the community is doing
and finding useful
patterns directly
inside native
primitives, and I'd
like to see us
continue doing that.
KYLE SIMPSON: I want to
jump in because they asked
me to be on the panel so that
I could disagree with everyone.
I actually think
it's a terrible idea
to standardize all
of these things
into CSS and into
HTML and JavaScript.
For example, I think it
would be an awful world
if the browser had a transpiler
for every one of the 1,000
languages that are out there.
There are things that
belong in our tool sets,
there are things they
belong in our technology,
and there are things that
belong in a build process,
and I draw a very distinct
line between them.
So transpiling, a
lot of things that we
see in CSS preprocessors
are things that I think
aren't necessarily great
to be in the CSS language.
They're things that
tools could do for you.
So I don't think
it's a good idea
at all to go down that slippery
slope of saying, anything
that I can dream up should
just drop into a standard.
I think build processes
are there for a reason,
and I don't see them
going away any day.
GARETH RUSHGROVE:
If anyone's got
a way of just dreaming
stuff up and dropping it
into a standards
process, though,
I'd like to hear about it.
KYLE SIMPSON: That
would be awesome.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: I
think fundamentally,
the fiction around standardizing
things is it takes time
and it's hard but
for good reason.
So actually, I think
the answer is yes,
but realistically, the
rate that that happens
is slow for good reasons.
Until we can broadly
all agree on something,
then it's not going
to get standardized,
and we're definitely
not going to broadly
agree on everything
anytime soon.
So therefore, it's
the stuff that we
can fight about that goes in
our different build processes.
NICK FISHER: I'd agree
with Kyle here as
well that I think one
of the real benefits
and the reason that JavaScript
and CSS got to where it is now
is because it
didn't do that ever.
It is a very bare bones
language, JavaScript,
that has let all
of us then come up
with these new tools
and these new things
to build upon a
very basic level.
And I think that if we decided
to do that, say, 10 years ago,
we might have a very
different language today.
BEN VINEGAR: So I'd
just tack onto this,
which is historically,
have we even done
a good job of when we take
features from other languages
and bring them into
JavaScript or CSS,
people talk to me a lot
about, we shouldn't even
be using jQuery but we
should be doing straight DOM.
But I find that those
API methods are still
pretty verbose and they're
not very fun to use.
So if we went along the path
of bringing a lot of these,
let's say, LESS and
Sass features into CSS,
would we even get it right?
Would it be fun to work with?
KYLE SIMPSON: I think
it's OK for these tools
to inform standards, but I
think we should draw a line
and say just because
somebody can put something
into a build process doesn't
mean that it will ever
belong in a standard.
So there's plenty of good
examples, for better or worse,
that CoffeeScript informed ESX.
I don't like all of
them, but that's good
that we were able
to inform that.
But I don't think it would be
a good idea for CoffeeScript
to natively start
being in the browser.
I think that's a build step.
ADDY OSMANI: So I
think the TLDR of that
is it looks like it's
probably not the best
idea for everything that's
possible inside a build process
today to be baked
into the browser.
We're always going to
fundamentally differ
when it comes to
our tools, and there
are going to be some
patterns that it makes sense
to eventually land
natively, but on the whole,
if we can do something
outside of that process,
let's keep rolling with that.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: And also,
in my opinion, the good part
of using a tool and
a build process,
using processing before
it is in the browser,
is that if it doesn't make
sense, you can throw it away.
Once it's been in the browser,
it's there forever, period,
and that's a huge problem.
That's also why standards
are slow in the common sense,
but it's the right thing.
BEN VINEGAR: So there
was a second part
to Cornell's question,
the original question.
I don't know that he
touched on it exactly.
I was hoping that he
would, but it was about,
should the idea of preprocessing
itself be a standards feature?
We are basically in
agreement that it
seems like most of our code
is being taken from one source
into another.
Is there an idea of
having a preprocess step
versus a runtime step?
I'm looking for a nod from you.
Have I captured that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
was thinking
where CSS should be optimized
for being preprocessed,
whether it should have syntax
or features that are not
for humans to type manually, but
for preprocessors to generate,
for example.
BEN VINEGAR: Any
comments on that?
KYLE SIMPSON: Well, I'll
jump in since I happen
to be experimenting with what I
call CSS templating as opposed
to CSS preprocessing,
and I think
that's a better way to go.
So again, what I
said was there's
several things that we've been
informed by LESS and Sass that
do belong in the CSS
language, and I'm
glad that we've got tools
that have standardized on what
those things are, like for
instance, being able to drop
in a value or for
instance, being
able to nest a rule or
something like that.
But there's a whole
bunch of other stuff
that I think should
be externalized.
So I think we can draw
those distinct lines,
and I think the tools can
standardize on the stuff that
is smart, but that's
obviously a gray area.
I mean, it's hard for
any one person to say,
here's where the line goes.
So the community, I
think, needs to be
more responsible about not just
looking at the new, shiny thing
that somebody dreamed
up but saying, really,
should that actually be
adopted or should that
stay in the user land?
I think we need, as
a community, to be
more responsible
with that decision.
BEN VINEGAR: On
that note, I'm going
to bring us to
our next question.
I'm going to call on from
the audience Ernesto Jimenez?
AUDIENCE: So the question
is, much of the new tools
and preprocessors are growing
within the Node.js community
and depend on the
Node stack and MPM.
Do you think this
dependency might
be limiting in the future?
ADDY OSMANI: Let's talk
about Node for a moment.
So Node has been growing
in popularity quite
extensively over the
last couple of years.
It currently has something
like 35,000 downloads a day.
I think 0.1 was downloaded
something like a million times.
So Node's popularity is
increasing, which is great.
At the same time,
you have to remember
that the long tail--
so not necessarily
the people in this
room, but people
who are still afraid of the
command line, people who
want to be able to optimize
their pages and their apps
and so forth but
don't necessarily
feel like it's a nice place
to go into the command line.
They still feel it's
really, really scary.
It's those people
that we actually
need to come up
with solutions for.
And there do exist tools that
can help with this stuff.
The long tail generally
like working with GUIs,
and we can tie that
stuff back to Node,
whether we're using something
like Node-webkit or additional
tooling so that they just
have to say, here's my project
or here are the directories
I'm working with.
Can you just bind these
to the different tools
that might do preprocessing,
postprocessing, and so forth?
So I don't think
that using Node is
something that's stopping us.
It's just going to be
about improving awareness
of how OK it is to use things
like Node and the command line
when you're actually working.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Coming at
that from a completely different
point as well is that
Node's a runtime,
and yeah, whether
someone's using
command line or
another tail, it's
something that's
actually in our code.
For some environments,
that is a barrier to entry.
They're not going to put
Node on their environment.
That's fine.
That's going to happen.
One thing that is
happening, though,
because there's been a lot
of interest in the tools
that are being built
on top of this,
and there's certainly
some work around basically
embedding a Node
runtime in the JVM
for environments
which are saying,
we're not going to install
this random new tool,
but we are happy with
running all this Java stuff.
So I think that becomes a less
limiting factor over time.
The tools will be able to
be run in different places.
KYLE SIMPSON: So to
build off of that,
I think what it gets to
is I would wholeheartedly
say we should standardize
on JavaScript for driving
these tools, but Node
is the tool right now.
It won't be the tool necessarily
five years from now or 10 years
from now because Node wasn't
the first server side JavaScript
engine and it's
certainly not the last.
We had one from Netscape in the
very early days of JavaScript
that didn't survive,
Rhino, and now [INAUDIBLE].
I mean, we've got a whole
bunch of other environments.
So I think to the extent that
it's possible for a tool author
to build a build process
tool in JavaScript
and try to be as
agnostic as possible,
try to put as few touch
points to the specific host
environment as possible, then
we see that five years from now,
when there's something
that supersedes Node,
it won't be as hard to
convert that tool over.
Most of the logic will survive.
So I think we should
be doing that.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: If you
think back five years ago,
we didn't have Node,
and back then, we
did build scripts with
Ant, this XML Java thingy,
and maybe put a Rhino jar
in there because we only
knew JavaScript and so we
could script something up
that does a little
bit on top of it.
It was hard to configure, and
so with the rise of Node, front
end developers who were
capable of writing JavaScript
and couldn't write some other
languages, or only CSS and HTML
besides.
KYLE SIMPSON: Or didn't want to.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: Or
didn't want to-- just
had the power to tap
into that build process
without just learning
another language
or whatever, or another tool.
So they're now
familiar with the stack
and can embrace this whole
plug-in ecosystem of whatever.
I think that that's
a really good thing.
BEN VINEGAR: I want
to cut you guys off
and actually just bring up the
second part of that question,
which we haven't touched
on at all, which was MPM.
I think everyone seems to
be pretty positive on Node,
but what about this
idea that there's
a huge dependence on MPM
as a package manager,
and the MPM repository,
for which I think
it's fair to say there's
been some bumpiness to it.
PRESENTER: What are
you talking about?
BEN VINEGAR: Well, bumpiness--
to contextualize this,
for example, I
think a month ago,
they changed their security
certificates without notice,
and I think a lot of people
who had depended on Node,
they just couldn't download
packages for a day.
There was no instruction.
There was no communication
about what had happened,
just as an example point.
It's not the only one.
Anyone want to touch on this?
Perhaps I'm going to
start with you, Nick.
NICK FISHER: I
think that's going
to be a problem if you're
relying on any third party
to host the things that you
need for your application.
I don't think it's
unique to MPM.
I think MPM's solving a
really good problem right now,
but if something were to
replace that in the future,
then I think that it shouldn't
be that difficult to actually
transition across to that
or even get rid of that
altogether, like flatten
all your dependencies,
check that in, if
it came to that.
I'm not suggesting
you do that, but I
don't see that MPM
itself is an issue there.
KYLE SIMPSON: Well MPM is
actually, if I understand,
it's sort of like a protocol
that you could theoretically--
and I know companies do-- spin
up their own MPM instances.
So we don't necessarily
have to think of MPM
as the one global,
universal repository.
It can be a way to get your
own company intranet repository
or something like that.
So I think that's
good, but I would also
say Git and GitHub are
pretty awesome for that, too.
We don't have to discount
those as the place
that we keep repositories.
BEN VINEGAR: [INAUDIBLE]
the audience here.
Sorry, I don't know
your name, but do you
have a comment on this?
Oh, your name's on your badge.
Johnathan?
AUDIENCE: We have the issues as
well that a lot of these tools
are now being stored in GitHub.
GitHub's a company and we're
relying a lot on GitHub,
so what should be
done [INAUDIBLE]?
PRESENTER: Don't use GitHub.
Use Git, not GitHub.
Use MPM the protocol,
not MPM the--
PRESENTER: Registry.
BEN VINEGAR: What about the
idea that-- obviously, you
can spin up your own
thing, but MPM now, it's
a private company.
And if you go to other
languages where there's PyPy
and there's Gems,
those are all actually
community efforts sponsored,
as far as I understand.
Does that change the
landscape at all?
No?
KYLE SIMPSON: No.
BEN VINEGAR: All right.
I thought I'd
throw it out there.
KYLE SIMPSON: I'm sure it
does change the landscape.
AUDIENCE: I would love to
hear from Gareth about that.
When you work with
government people,
what do they say when the piece
of software that you rely on
is an 0.1 release, and not
a 1.0, 2.0, 5.0 release
that can be trusted?
GARETH RUSHGROVE: So
the version number thing
is nearly a red
herring because it's
an arbitrary string, basically.
It's only representing value
in the eye of the author,
and so you can just
go-- if someone goes,
oh, it's got to be 1,
if you tell the author,
they might just make it 1.
But ultimately,
different organizations
will have different
risk appetites,
and that's true of--
I work for government,
there's going to
be banks, there's
probably going to
be your new startup.
The thing that kills
your new startup
is probably not a bad dependency
from a third party managed
service, but it
might be something
that has an impact on
a bank because someone
tries to compromise that
service and come back to you.
It's a really hard problem, and
it's not specific JavaScript.
It's specific to third
party packaged services.
Having one per language
was a stupid idea.
It's too late to fix it.
The next new language
that comes around
will probably have an
MPM or a Ruby Gems.
Its a bit of a shame.
The package management systems
within operating systems
solve a lot of the
problems and people
forget about the
problems they're solving.
C Panther Perl does loads
of really interesting stuff
that no one's recreated
in the last 10 years.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: One addition.
I think one thing
that will help us
with at least the security
concerns about using
MPM is when MPM adopts
something like Maven
does with package signing
and stuff like this
so we can assure our clients
that this thing is really
the thing that we said
it's going to be there
and not something different
because someone hijacked it
or something.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: It solves
the man in the middle issue.
It doesn't solve the fact that
someone might have compromised
the person who was uploading
it in the first place.
PRESENTER: But in
general, isn't it--
I find it always fascinating--
BEN VINEGAR: Guys, sorry.
I'm getting thrashed to
get to the new topic.
So we could go to
the audience again.
I think this is a pretty
exciting question.
I guess I'm not going
to the audience.
I guess I'm supposed to ask
Kyle Simpson to ask a question.
KYLE SIMPSON: Like I said,
they put me on the panel
so that I could
stir things up, so I
get the pleasure of
asking this question.
There's a mini browser war
that's going on right now
between Grunt and Gulp, and we
toyed around with having you
all have to stand up and
declare where you are on that,
but we won't.
But there's other several
other would be contenders,
and that sort of betrays
this idea that maybe there
is one right build
tool to rule them all.
So the question is, is that
a realistic idea, that we're
striving towards one great
build tool that we need to find,
or is it just idealistic?
And is it harmful fragmentation
or useful experimentation?
ADDY OSMANI: I think
that traditionally,
having multiple tools is a
good thing because it drives
innovation, and I don't
think that's a bad thing
in this community.
Build tooling on the front
end is still very young
and it's somewhat
in its infancy.
So I don't think it's
necessarily a bad thing.
One thing I would like to
see is us standardizing on
perhaps a task specification.
I know that there's been
some effort from different
build tools to standardize
on the Node task spec, which
talks about things like having
a single way to handle records
or logging or
notifications and so forth.
I think that could actually
help us avoid having
this crazy wheel of
reimplementing things
all the time, but I know
it has its own challenges.
NICK FISHER: I have an
opinion on the Gulp and Grunt
thing, which is I don't care.
I don't use either
of them, and I
see these tools as useful
for certain situations,
but they are glue that sticks
together interesting things.
I think the discussion and
browser war type arguments
going on-- well, I'm
not sure anyone's really
arguing-- but arguments
going on between these things
really distract from why we're
even doing a build process
in the first place.
We're doing it to
get faster websites,
to get better development
time, and so on.
If you use Grunt, if you
use Make, if you use Ant,
I don't care.
It's what we actually
do in the build
process which is
actually important.
But I would personally like to
see less people reimplementing
Grunt-coffee, Gulp-coffee,
whatever, and just have coffee.
Just use that and hook
into it any way you want.
ADDY OSMANI: So you feel like we
should get closer to the grain
and just actually call
the existing tools,
rather than writing
wrappers around them?
It seems to me
what you're saying.
NICK FISHER: I mean, the
wrappers are fine, but just
recognize that they
are just wrappers.
The important thing
is what it's wrapping
and what that actually does, and
how you can plug these things
together is just details.
KYLE SIMPSON: There was a
write up some months ago.
It was kind of tongue
in cheek, but it
was tasks.js, which boiled
down to simply just writing
the JavaScript yourself.
And while it was funny and
interesting from a boilerplate
perspective, I think what
it does miss a little bit,
the reason I write
tools and the reason
I would make a Grunt
plug-in for my tool is not
because that's the only
way to use my tool.
It's because I'm trying to
lower the barrier to entry so
that I get bigger market share.
I'm trying to make it so
there's as little boilerplate
as possible to drop
my template engine in.
Of course, some
people-- and I might
have the same perspective--
but some people
would say, well, it's OK to
raise the barrier a little bit.
If you want to use it, you
have to know how to use it.
Call the API, well
document the API.
I think that's the reason
why plug-ins exist.
Everybody wants to make it so
that their tool is the one that
blows up and gets 10
million stars on GitHub.
BEN VINEGAR: Sebastian,
you had a comment there.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH:
I mean, the thing
is with all these dependencies,
with all these plug-ins, when
we say, OK, we have
a common interface
so we only have one plug-in that
works with all of the systems,
perfect.
In the end, it's a tool
and a tool should help us,
so if I like hammer B better
in my hand than hammer A,
then I use hammer B
because it's better for me.
And the same is true with
Grunt and Gulp and Broccoli
and [INAUDIBLE] or whatever.
I mean, if you're
a Node developer,
Gulp.js feels more familiar
with all the stream stuff,
and so you can write it
because it feels more familiar.
If you're a front end
developer, most of them
like Grunt more because it's
this declarative approach where
you only have to
configure things.
I think it comes down to use
the right tool for the job.
BEN VINEGAR: Can I
go to the audience
here, because there's a
bunch of hands going up.
Just first over here, and Remy.
AUDIENCE: Disclaimer.
Unfortunately, I'm one of
these people who has also
developed another
build tool [INAUDIBLE].
So I agree with
everything we've said
and I think the idea of having
inter-op between plug-ins
is great.
One thing to remember is
that these tools are there
to make it really
easy for people.
We want people who are
scared by the command line
to be able to do the right
thing by default without having
to worry about configuring
crazy paths everywhere.
So to me, the real
question is, what
is a good baseline
for these tasks that
would work in different tools so
that it does the right things?
And just to throw out
a few examples is,
should it be able to produce
source maps currently
for everything by default?
Should it be able
to rebuild partially
so you don't have to rebuild
all your things all the time?
And all these
things, I think need
to fit into what is the common
format for these build tools.
ADDY OSMANI: I think one of
the really big challenges
with coming up with a spec for
build processes in that task
spec is that it's difficult
to create something that
is flexible enough to also
match the architectures
of these different tools so that
they can work behind the scenes
and do what they need to do
without necessarily feeling
overly constrained.
Unfortunately, the
Node task spec idea
that I talked about earlier,
that's actually something that
is currently on hold
because none of the
build tools could
actually reach agreement
on how they should
approach this problem.
It's really, really difficult.
I'm hoping that later on in the
year, they'll come back to it
and think that it's
something worth value.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Sorry.
Are we talking about
something like, oh, it's
good to have multiple tools
because that breeds innovation?
Don't think you can't get
locked into an open source tool,
because you can.
It's not just commercial side.
You talk about lock-in.
You get yourself locked
into something by saying,
you know what?
The barrier to
moving from this tool
is so great, I'm not going
to do it, at which point
you benefit not one bit
from the innovation coming
from other tools.
BEN VINEGAR: OK.
I'm going to get a quick
comment from the audience
here, from Remy [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: I was going to
say I don't personally
use build tools.
That's one step.
The thing is jQuery,
it was the tool that
made working with
JavaScript really,
stupid simple for a
large amount of people,
and suddenly, they were
able to write JavaScripts
without writing JavaScript.
And these build
tools have given me
a way of just adding
minification and getting
that done whereas before,
I wouldn't have done it,
and many other people are
going to be doing that.
You talk about
getting locked in.
I don't think it
matters at this point.
Getting hold of build
tools at this point
was so new for this community.
If we get locked into
Grunt for a few years,
and eventually, there's
standardization in five years'
time, then that's a huge
step forward compared
to just not doing it at all and
just delivering massive images
over the wire,
uncompressed images.
I think we're still at that
very early days of when jQuery
was really spurring the
JavaScript [INAUDIBLE].
ADDY OSMANI: I agree with that.
I feel like this build
tool conversation,
sometimes it skips
over the fact that we
don't talk enough about what's
inside our build process.
We should be caring more about
image optimization, image
compression.
Images are the thing that are
slowing down the web today,
and we need to get more people
caring about those problems
and spending more time talking
about how we can actually
speed up our pages
and less time,
perhaps, on arguing
why you should
be using Gulp versus Grunt.
I mean, they're still
fantastic tools,
but I think Sebastian
said earlier,
people who are more
familiar with Node
are perhaps going to use Gulp
and people who aren't are just
going to use Grunt.
That seems to be working.
BEN VINEGAR: I'm going to cut
you guys off because actually,
the next question I
think, goes into just what
Addy was touching on.
I'm looking for, from the
audience, Peter Muller.
AUDIENCE: I'll have to read
this as well because it's
been changed a bit.
Most build scripts, including
those generated by scaffolding,
are a chain of several
discrete steps.
Do we even need the
complexity of having control
of every one of these
steps, or should we instead
have an opinionated build
chain that just gets us
to the endpoint that
we're interested in?
NICK FISHER: From
my experience, I've
built an opinionated
tool chain for our own
build system that we needed,
and I'm really happy with it.
There's been a lot of work
put into it, obviously,
but I think in the
end, if you really
want to get total
performance out of your
build process, not in
terms of how fast it runs
or anything like that, but in
terms of what actually executes
at the end of your
build process,
then I think that's definitely
a very smart way to go,
and you definitely don't need
any particular tools like Grunt
or Gulp to get you there.
BEN VINEGAR: Kyle had a comment.
KYLE SIMPSON: So
I think going back
to the Unix philosophy, which
certainly informs a lot of what
we're doing, it says have
lots of tiny little tools
that can be woven together.
And I think that's the more
appropriate way of doing this.
When you get to the
point where you've
decided that there
is a particular flow
through those tools
that make sense for you,
you write yourself
a bash script so you
don't have to repeat it again,
and that's all you need.
In the JavaScript world, when
you have a set of API calls
through these different
tools, you just
write yourself a
little Node script
that repeats that
process over and over.
So I don't think we need
to worry so much about, oh,
there's too many details here.
You just wrap a script
around it and then
you don't worry about those
details if you don't want.
GARETH RUSHGROVE:
I think the thing
is you said "for
me" and "I write."
I think actually, sharing
that unit for some people
is really valuable.
Some people in this
room are going to go,
I'm a really good
programmer, and that's
exactly what they're going to
do, and like Remy was saying,
some people in
this room are not.
They're going to, I have no idea
what all these steps are doing,
but I want the magic
from people who
are really smart
to do it for me.
KYLE SIMPSON: So I just make a
Gist and then I tweet it out.
That's my solution
to that problem.
ADDY OSMANI: So one of things
that we tried to do with--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
the non-technical people
in the room.
[LAUGHTER]
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Distributing
really usable software is hard.
Packaging that up
into something that
is just easily
usable off the shelf
by someone who does not
understand what's going on
in the middle is hard
work, but it's valuable.
Instead of these
millions of plug-ins,
there's probably two
or three good ways
that would be good enough
for 80% of the people.
ADDY OSMANI: One
of the things we
tried doing with
Yeoman is actually
trying to provide people
with opinionated workflows,
especially when it comes
to things like performance
and what we think
people should be doing.
Because a lot of
people don't know
exactly what they should be
getting in their build process
to actually keep their
pages fast and so forth,
or what build tasks
they should be
using, whether they're
using Grunt or Gulp.
So there do exist
solutions to help you
with opinionated
stacks for the stuff,
but at the end of
the day, if you
find those too much
and too overbearing,
you can always just use them
for reference in the same way
that people use
HTML5 boilerplate.
Just take what you want.
Delete key friendly the rest.
BEN VINEGAR: Just going
to go back to Peter here.
AUDIENCE: I'd like to touch
on Kyle's point about the Unix
philosophy.
I love the Unix
philosophy, small tools
being able to chain
them together.
The thing is that
Unix pipes work
with text and web
files are not text.
We would need to be
able to pass objects
like we can do in PowerShell.
The thing is some of the
things that are really, really
difficult to do with the
existing build tools-- revving
files, concatenating files,
all that stuff-- are things
that both Grunt and
Gulp do really badly,
actually, because
they're based essentially
on a continuation of the Unix
philosophy or the Make file
philosophy.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: I touched
on earlier, steal things
from things outside
your community,
and one of the things to
steal from is PowerShell.
For those that are familiar
with that Unix philosophy is all
chaining small things
together, PowerShell
adds basically a full object
in between those things,
and you can do a
lot more with that.
KYLE SIMPSON: I don't
think we need that.
Not that it's bad,
but I don't think
we necessarily always need that.
If you look at the flows for
JavaScript tooling-- parsers,
analyzers, transpilers,
code generators,
and that whole flow
and that round trip.
If you look at
that, they decided
we start out with
source code and then we
move to a tree format, and
there's a relatively agreed
upon tree format, the AST.
We're actually working on
a more complete version
of that called a
concrete [INAUDIBLE].
That's the thing that
moves from tool to tool,
and then what you get out
is more compiled code.
I don't think that's
a big problem.
BEN VINEGAR: I feel like we've
gotten a little off track.
We've moved from, is there
merit to having, let's say,
a plug-in like Grunt-awesome
that just does everything,
and now we're getting into the
details of chaining and stuff
like that.
So maybe just to bring us
back, just a comment over here.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
because I think
a lot of the things in the
Unix idea is to chain things
through, sort of in a functional
way, you're taking output
from one thing into
the next thing.
But some of the things
we do-- and there's
one in Yeoman, the
one that transforms.
You can run things.
It can take chunks of
JavaScript and compile them
into different files,
and it keeps state.
So it can do something
at the start,
go through the whole chain, and
then refer back to something
that happened, and that's
the same for revving things.
You have to have some idea of
the state of the whole system
to be able to rev things
later on and go, right,
this is what has appeared.
So this whole idea of just
having chains-- even in Unix,
you do stupid things
where you might temp files
and you get into
all this weird stuff
when you're trying to
do something that just
isn't fundamentally functional.
It always goes back to, I'll
just do it the Unix way,
but there are some
things that just
can't be done that
way very well.
BEN VINEGAR: Any
comments on that?
NICK FISHER: Yeah.
That's what I was saying.
This build script
that we use has
a lot of these things
that at the start,
we find all the
assets, and then we
have a state that is
then used later on.
The downside of that is that
it means that you can't really
share your tools very
easily because it's
very specific and bespoke
to your application.
I know one of the themes
that's coming here
is sharing and helping
people get into community,
but there's the
other side, which
is I want to build the
best app that I can
for me, which might sound a
bit mean, but that's my job.
I'm pretty sure
everyone else here
has got a job very
similar to that as well.
And you shouldn't forget that.
Sometimes, you do have
to just do something
then you can't open source.
That's fine.
BEN VINEGAR: I'm
going to stop there.
That seems like a good
closing point, me, me, me.
So I'm going to call
on the next question.
Looking here from Ian Feather.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
Most of the pain
in build process
occurs at dev iteration.
Would it make sense
to implement things
like Sass and CoffeeScript
as plug-ins for developers,
removing the need
for repetitive build
processes, or even in
the browser itself?
So I think he's talking
about having extensions which
will allow you to
iterate without having
to run the build
process [INAUDIBLE].
BEN VINEGAR: Just to jump ahead
of this before you comment.
This question interested
me because what
I seem to read a
lot about new tools,
like Gulp being produced, is
that the speed of building
is actually becoming
really important to people.
So what if we can just
not have that at all?
Any comments?
ADDY OSMANI:
Generally, I think we
were all in agreement about
things like Sass and Coffee
not necessarily
belonging in the browser.
We agreed on that earlier.
But I think in terms of
your iteration workflow,
Gulp is commonly used by people
because when you're actually
iterating on a project using
Sass, it's a little bit faster.
Whenever you make
a change and you
want to see that
refresh in the browser,
you don't necessarily
have as much of a delay
as you perhaps do with Grunt.
It's not a massive
difference but it's
important enough to
people that they sometimes
consider switching over.
I think that we need to
look at how we can actually
keep our tools lean
and fast where possible
to improve on that.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: It feels
like it's a software thing.
What you're saying is, well,
I have a slow build script,
and I bet those
browser people have
got some really
good coders who can
do exactly the
same thing faster.
It's like, well,
maybe, or you could
find someone else who can
re-engineer your build process
to be faster.
Ultimately, you're
doing the same job,
you're just doing it in a
different place with code.
If Node isn't fast
enough, write ANC.
PRESENTER: [INAUDIBLE].
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: I think
the thing is we're web people,
and we're used to hitting F5
or Control R, and refresh,
and it changes, not
like the Java guys who
could grab a coffee while
their thing is compiling.
I think we should really
embrace that and not
build tools that are watching
in the background a file system
and then doing
something for 10 seconds
before we can see the
change in the browser.
That's not the web and
I think that's totally
heading in the wrong direction.
You have Sass and stuff, OK,
but really don't overdo it.
Just keep it clean and simple.
NICK FISHER: I
think one point here
is to consider your total build
separate to your development
time.
Things like watches can be good,
or running a local server that
compiles these things on
the fly and can give you
a good enough representation
of the production
build while you're developing.
If your build script takes less
than five minutes, that's fine.
Above that is a
problem, but less
than that I wouldn't care, as
long as when you're developing,
that feedback loop
is very short, and do
that through file
watching, serving
individual files on the fly.
If you separate those
two ideas, then I
don't think you
hit this problem.
KYLE SIMPSON: Just
real quick, one area
that definitely needs to
get better with those tools
is the incremental recompile.
So just because I change one
Sass file doesn't mean I really
actually want to recompile
the entire damn directory,
but that's often what happens.
So if we could get smarter
tools that it could understand,
I only need to recompile this
one little part of this one
little file, that
would certainly
speed up a lot of that time.
BEN VINEGAR: A comment
here from Jake Archibald.
He's right in the middle.
People can't decide which
mic he's going to get.
AUDIENCE: Aside from
the performance issue,
if the browser understands
Sass or CoffeeScript,
doesn't that make
tooling better?
We've got source
maps at the moment,
but that is just
a basic mapping.
Wouldn't we get a lot more
if the browser actually
understood the other language?
ADDY OSMANI: When you say
the browser understanding
other languages, I think we need
to realize that it's not just
about Sass and Coffee.
It's about Sass
and LESS and Stylus
and other crazy thing
that's been created
while people are
sitting in this room.
We have to define limits
about how we can actually
go about supporting
these things and what
we support because if the
browser were to support that,
that goes back to one
of the earlier questions
about having some sort
of a preprocess step
where the browser could perhaps
call out to external tools
to actually get the job done.
That's realistically
the only way
I can see it being done without
you baking in support for Sass
into the browser directly.
GARETH RUSHGROVE:
It comes back to the
build process thing as well.
It's still a build process.
It's just you've split it over
the browser and your code.
That could be fine.
And yeah, getting
it into the browser
is probably easier than
getting it into a standard,
but it's not easy as
grabbing a plug-in
or writing some code yourself.
There's this barrier
to entry there.
Yeah, it's not quite the
standards thing, but still,
grabbing like the [INAUDIBLE]
and adding that feature
and getting it through
a process whereby
it's fit for
everyone else to use,
much higher barrier to entry.
KYLE SIMPSON:
Someone earlier said,
and I think it bears repeating,
as soon as you put something
into the browser, now it's
going to move a whole lot slower
in terms of change.
So I don't think we ought
to put Sass in there
until we're really sure
that it's pretty much done,
and I don't think it is, so I
think we need to keep separate.
BEN VINEGAR: First comment
over here from [INAUDIBLE].
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE], when
you said ramping up people,
I think the web started and
became so big because it was
easy to write something, put
it in a browser, and see it.
When I see a lot of people
tweeting, that people look up
to, that tell
people, if you want
to start with web development,
go to the command line,
get a Ruby Gem, do
this, do that, do that.
It's no wonder we're
using new developers
to close platforms
instead of the web.
So could we do a better job in
actually promoting power tools
only to power users rather
than saying start with this?
PRESENTER: I think so.
BEN VINEGAR: Actually, got
one more question coming up
that I think basically
captures this,
so I think we're just going to
jump to that also because we're
running low on time.
I should have queued
this up ahead of time.
This is awkward.
I swear it was here.
KYLE SIMPSON: Let's start
addressing this question
while you look it up.
BEN VINEGAR: It's more finding
the person who speaks it.
PRESENTER: Who's
got that question?
BEN VINEGAR: Let's
go to the audience.
It's a question about,
is tooling taking us away
from these fundamental
building blocks?
You do?
Yeah.
PRESENTER: Crowdsourcing.
ADDY OSMANI: I think that the
fastest iteration loop today
is probably just
sticking directly
with HTML, JavaScript, and CSS.
Only use these power tools
when they're actually
going to be genuinely
useful to you.
That's at the core of
what you're saying,
and I don't think that we
should move away from that.
If you're just hacking
away on something,
there's no reason not to
stick with those tools.
Where all this other
stuff becomes important
is when you're trying to
develop for a large system
or something that's going
to go out to production,
and you want to make
sure that if someone's
accessing something on a
slow network on a phone,
that it's actually still fast.
BEN VINEGAR: Addy,
going to-- also,
can you say your name because
I don't have it in front of me?
AUDIENCE: My name is Florian,
and the question obviously
has been rewritten, but it
covers my question exactly.
As build processors become
more and more complex,
our source code
gets further away
from the fundamental
building blocks of the web--
JavaScript, CSS, and HTML.
How does this affect
future maintainability,
and is this a good thing?
KYLE SIMPSON: Yes,
it's a good thing
because we all pick our
various levels of abstraction.
Some people loved
writing in assembly,
some people didn't, so we picked
a higher level of abstraction.
So all of these extra tools
and things, when you decide-- I
say this all the time.
Source code's not
for the computer.
It's for the developer.
Computer just cares
about ones and zeros.
So you choose ClosureScript
because you like something
about that tool and the way
that allows you to express
your code, and that makes you
a better and faster and more
efficient developer,
so that's a good thing.
BEN VINEGAR: So to play devil's
advocate for a moment, what
about all the resources that
we've put behind HTML and CSS?
MDN doesn't have
CoffeeScript examples.
W3Schools does not
have Sass examples.
We have this huge
base of knowledge,
and are we getting
away from that?
Is that necessarily bad?
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: I
think back in the day,
we looked for
developers for the web,
and they must understand
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
Today, we're looking for
TypeScript developers,
Sass developers, and not--
KYLE SIMPSON: Who's looking
for TypeScript developers?
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Certainly
when we're hiring, we're not.
On the programming side,
we're looking for programmers,
and on the front end
side, we're looking
for people with a really
good understanding of HTML,
CSS, JavaScript.
And the fact is everything
else, they will learn.
We write a lot of Ruby code,
and we've hired actually
a relatively small
number of people
who were proficient
in Ruby to start with,
but they were programmers.
SEBASTIAN GOLASCH: Then
you're doing it right,
but I've seen job descriptions
with lists of tools.
In the end, you don't
need to know all of them
but we just lined them up
because they're so popular
and we want to attract
people to work for us.
That's stupid.
ADDY OSMANI: This is where
you get job descriptions
like 15 years
AngularJS experience.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: But we're
not going to fix that.
NICK FISHER: I think to go
to what Chris was saying
about how scary it is
for a new developer,
I don't think that
should hold us back.
I mean, you can still
have the tutorials.
They're definitely
very worthwhile.
But JavaScript is
where it is now
because we didn't
let it hold us back.
We did start building
upon it and create
really amazing things with it.
And the more that people
do the amazing things,
that's even better.
I don't think necessarily
having a zero level entry
barrier is a goal.
BEN VINEGAR: Just want to get
an update from Florian here.
AUDIENCE: I think
you're not really
addressing my
question because what
I'm worried about it is
I'm writing code today,
and it may be Sass, it
may be CoffeeScript.
And in five years' time,
I go back to that code
and I can't run it anymore
because it's not standardized.
All I can run is my
previously compiled code,
and the output is--
NICK FISHER: I think that should
be a serious consideration
before you choose
one of those tools.
GARETH RUSHGROVE: Different
organizations as well
are going to have different
thresholds for that.
Because if in five years'
time, your startup has either
been sold, at which point you
don't care, or it's gone bust
and you don't care, actually
probably optimizing for right
now is massively important.
Government stuff,
yeah, I'm not going
to choose something
that's not standardized.
ADDY OSMANI: I was
just going to say
that if you're choosing
an abstraction,
you're almost marrying
yourself to it.
You can't expect
Sass necessarily
to be the thing that people
are going to use in five or six
years' time from now.
You can expect
people to still be
using CSS, though, and probably
JavaScript, and probably HTML.
So sometimes, staying
closer to the grain
is not necessarily a bad idea.
But to add to your point, a
lot of the time these days,
people are just trying to
build stuff that works now.
You need something that's
maintainable for right now.
If that makes sense,
sure, use these new tools
to augment your experience
and make it easier
for you to develop.
But I think that
our abstractions
are something that are not
going to be around forever.
BEN VINEGAR: Well,
we're out of time,
so I think that's a
good place to end.
Just want to thank all
these amazing panelists
for their thoughts
and opinions, and I
want to thank you
guys for being here.
[APPLAUSE]