DAN APPELQUIST:
Thank you, Andrew.
Is this thing on?
Yeah?
OK, good.
Hi there.
We are the warm up act
for Jake Archibald.
[LAUGHTER]
And we're going to be
talking about components--
which is OK, by the way.
That's fine.
I'm good with that.
So my name's Dan.
I'm just going to
briefly introduce people,
and then we're going
to have a brief talk,
to get into it.
So my name's Dan Appelquist.
I work for Telefonica, and I
do Firefox stuff, Firefox OS.
And I co-chair
something called the TAG
in W3C, which is kind of the
technical architecture steering
board for W3C.
On our panel today, we have
a panoply of stars here.
We have Nicole Sullivan
from Pivotal Labs, who
is a proponent of
component based systems.
And she's the creator of Object
Oriented CSS, Type-o-matic,
and CSS Lint.
We have Alex
Komoroske from Google,
who's product manager
on Blink and Polymer.
We have Pete Hunt from
Instagram slash Facebook,
member of the React core team.
We have Soledad
Penades from Mozilla,
who's working on things like
Mortar, Brick, and X-Tag.
We have Peter Gasston, who
is a creative technologist
and an author and speaks
about web components.
And we're going to hear
him speak right now.
So without further
ado, I'm going
to ask him to come give
a kind of intro talk.
Tell us about components.
PETER GASSTON:
Thank you very much.
Better log in first, excuse me.
And my screen is locked.
Embarrassing.
But I can get over
it, don't worry.
I'm a professional.
I've done this
thousands of times
before, stood up here
and embarrassed myself
thousands of times before.
Thanks.
So good morning.
I'm here to do a quick
talk about introducing
web components.
I know some of you
know them already.
But I want to kind of give a
little overview for everybody
about basically the why,
the how, and the when
of web components.
Don't use that hashtag.
Oh no, that is
the right hashtag.
I corrected it.
Do use that hashtag.
It's OK.
My name is Peter Gasston.
I tweet @stopsatgreen.
I write for broken-links.com.
And I'm a technologist
and front end
lead, which is a very cumbersome
job title, for an agency
here in London.
So it's kind of my job to
look at new and future web
technologies and evaluate them,
and see when we can use them.
And one of the things I'm most
excited about at the moment
is web components.
So I'll be very much playing
the role of the excited everyman
developer in this panel
of stars we've got here.
Ever since we've been
developing for the web,
we've been copying
other people's stuff.
There's no shame in that.
That's how the web kind of grew.
That's how everybody
got their knowledge.
I learned by copying
other people's stuff.
I'm sure most of you
did here, as well.
The View Page Source is one
of the finest inventions
of the web.
Well done to the original
early browser makers
for making that possible for us.
But as we've done
that, it's kind of
become quite cumbersome to
copy other people's stuff.
It used to be we'd nick a
little line of code here
and a line of code there.
But then it just gets bigger
and bigger and more and more
involved to actually do that.
But we still want to reuse
other people's stuff.
And we want to reuse our own
stuff across our own websites,
as well.
Some of the early efforts
at making this copying
and sharing easy
were Java applets.
If anybody developed for
the web over 10 years ago,
there's a very,
very good chance you
had a photograph of
a house on a lake
with a rippling
lake underneath it.
That would have been
made with a Java applet.
And then we had
Dynamic Drive, which
was the best place to
go to if you wanted
animated stars to follow
your mouse around the window.
But we started becoming kind of
more professional with the way
that we wrote our
code afterwards,
to make it more shareable,
to make it more reusable.
We had fantastic efforts like
Nicole's Object Oriented CSS,
which has become
very, very popular.
Loads of people use it.
And it's been even
more formalized
into things like BEM, languages
or protocols like BEM.
And in terms of
other sharing, we've
even had kind of whole
UI elements, libraries,
grow up, to enable
us to stop having
to code our own
carousel 5,000 times
and instead copy the
carousels of other people.
Efforts like jQuery UI and,
more recently, Bootstrap
have enabled us to do that.
We write our code in a certain
way, and things just happen.
And even bigger, much
more powerful ways
of doing this power some of the
biggest sites on the web today.
We're looking at
things like React,
which is written by
Facebook and Instagram,
who Pete here is going to
talk about later today,
and fantastic hosts.
The Financial Times have their
own version in Fruit Machine.
And these are kind of
template constructors
you put in JavaScript, and it
outputs all the code for you.
And you can power
that through Node.
And you can build whole
very, very powerful,
scalable systems, but just
based on this idea of copying
and reusing other bits
of code, other elements.
So web components is
kind of a formalization
of all these ideas.
It's looked to all the things
we've done in the past.
And it's kind of said, well,
people want to do this.
Let's make a standard
way of doing it.
Let's make an easier
way of doing it
that hooks into the low level
of the APIs, of the browsers,
and makes this much,
much easier to do.
So where the goal
is reusability,
the answer is web components.
There are three core
parts to web components.
Sorry, beg your pardon.
Let me gather my thoughts.
There are three parts
to web components.
The first is what are
known as custom elements.
When I first read
about web components,
I thought they were more
of a background thing.
And Shadow DOM was the big
thing that everybody was really
talking about.
But in fact, as I see
it, as I look at it,
custom elements
are web components.
They are the core thing.
Without anything else, custom
elements are the bit we really,
really want to use.
The idea behind
custom elements is
that basically
everything is an element.
Everything we do and
everything we have on the web
is an element.
That's a core thing that drives
the Polymer project, which
I'm going to talk
about in a little bit,
but custom elements themselves.
For a long time, we've
had elements like image.
And if you provide a source
to that image element,
it puts an image in
the page at that point.
And we've had
things like inputs.
If you say, input type=range,
it outputs for you a UI element
in a consistent way across
all the different browsers.
So we want to do that.
We like having those
consistent UI elements.
But why stop there?
Why not have everything
be an element?
Everything we do all the
time could be an element.
So why not have, for example,
a Google Maps element?
You give it a latitude
and a longitude,
and it outputs a Google map
into your page at that point.
Why not extend
existing elements?
So we can say the video
element, which we generally
have in the page anyway, also
accepts video camera input.
We extend it with WebRTC.
Why not have Ajax
calls be elements?
Why not put them in the page?
We do that all the time.
We want those results.
We want to put those
results in the page
at this consistent place.
So why not make this
into an element, as well?
Creating a custom element
is very, very simple.
You create a new
prototype object.
You can add methods to it.
You then register those
elements into the DOM
by giving it a
unique name, which
has to be hyphenated
like this to make
it compatible with current
and future standardized HTML
elements.
And then you just tell it
which prototype to use.
And that's basically it.
You've registered the
element with the DOM.
You've given it some methods.
You've given it some properties.
And then you can just
include it in your page.
So you can do
anything with that.
That's exceptionally,
exceptionally powerful.
All of those things
I just showed you
before-- Google Maps, the
Ajax calls, the videos--
they all start by
basically doing this.
But once you've
written this, that's
kind of nice that you've
attached all these properties
to this element.
But then you want to
share that element.
You want to make it
shareable everywhere.
So that's where the second part
of web components comes in.
These are called HTML imports.
And they are simplicity itself.
They're just like
including a JavaScript file
or referring to an
external CSS file.
But it's using snippets
of HTML markup,
hopefully with all your
attached behaviors.
So you put a new link
element in the head,
you say it's an import link,
and you give it an href.
And then that allows you
to take your custom element
and apply it to all of
the pages on your site.
But more than that,
it also allows
people to take that
same code that you've
written, that same import,
that same snippet file,
and apply it across
all their sites, too.
So it's immensely reusable,
which is really, really cool.
The final core part of web
components is the Shadow DOM.
Shadow DOM is not vital
to web components,
but it makes them really,
really nice and useful.
And it actually
exists right now.
Many of you might have
seen this already.
If you open up
Chrome, and I think
it's even in Safari still, and
you choose the Show Shadow DOM
option, you can see the markup
inside these UI elements
that we use.
For example, if you have
an input type=range,
if you view the
Shadow DOM of that,
you can see it's actually
built of other elements.
They're just not
exposed to the user.
They're hidden inside that.
And that's what a Shadow DOM is.
It's the DOM inside
the DOM that's
hidden from the user
in most [? instances ?]
that kind of powers the
simplicity of the element.
There are also a
few things which
aren't part of the
web components spec
but are related to it and make
it way, way more extensible
and useful, one of them
being the template element,
which allows you to drop
markup into your document
and not have it rendered
until you explicitly
tell the browser to render it.
We have mutation
observers, which
look for changes in the DOM and
fire an event when they happen.
And we have scoped styles, which
allow you to apply CSS only
to specific elements, as opposed
to being globally scoped,
as they are at the moment.
So who's on board at the moment?
Most of the work is
being done in Chrome.
If you look in Chrome
nightly or the Dev channel,
there's a lot of this
stuff that maybe you
have to enable it through
flags, but it's all in there.
Because of that, a lot of it
comes into Opera, naturally,
as well, as they're based
on the same Blink engine.
Firefox is doing an awful
lot of work in this, as well.
Custom elements are in there.
I know they're working
heavily on the Shadow
DOM and the rest of the suite.
Microsoft we're not sure
about at the moment.
But I think the signs are good.
Because they're involved
in some of the extra stuff,
like mutation observers.
And also, they've
got history in this.
Internet Explorer 5
actually had this thing
called HTML Components, which
is really similar to what
web components do nowadays.
So in this case,
Microsoft is sort
of the proto-hipsters of
the web component scene.
[CHUCKLING]
Finally, there's Safari.
And really, who knows?
[LAUGHTER]
If you want to use them today,
you've got two main choices.
There's these two libraries
called Polymer and X-Tags.
They're both public, but
one's kind of driven by Google
and one kind of
driven by Mozilla.
Polymer has its
Polymer Core, which
is where you do
the registration.
X-Tags has its X-Tag Core.
Polymer has a set of
UI elements on top.
And X-Tags have Brick,
which do the same job.
And they both share this
platform underneath.
They both use the same
platform to polyfill
where these things are
not present natively,
which is really, really
good and makes it-- the fact
that, whether you
choose one or the other,
you're still working
into the same code base
underneath, which is really
helpful for moving forward.
The outcome that we get from
this is meaningful markup.
We get reusable elements.
And hopefully in the future,
who knows, even a consistent UI.
Maybe the web could
have a consistent UI
like native apps have.
That might be something that
we want to move towards,
to make it easier for people.
So we can stop reinventing the
wheel on every site we build.
The challenges are,
to put it politely,
a proliferation of crap.
If we let people
create their own stuff,
they're going to create
some crappy stuff.
But that's not a
reason to move on.
That's not a reason to
stop [? viewing ?] them.
And performance, people
have flagged performance,
accessibility, and
internationalization.
And those are all
the things we're
going to talk about today.
So web components are the
future, for better or worse.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
DAN APPELQUIST: OK, so, given
our-- thank you, first of all,
for that intro.
I think that gives us
a lot to think about.
And I think it nicely intros
us to our first questioner.
I'm going to ask Yoav
Weiss to stand up,
hopefully-- yes,
thank you-- and to ask
the first question of the day.
YOAV WEISS: Hi.
We're all aiming towards
better page load times.
HTML imports can
include other imports.
ES6 modules can
include other modules.
To what extent does
using components
break web performance
by breaking parallelism?
DAN APPELQUIST: So
performance immediately.
So let's, first of all, I'd like
to ask Pete to maybe, as you're
a company that has a strong
emphasis on page performance
and on performance,
what's your view on that?
PETE HUNT: You want to just
get the trolling out early?
DAN APPELQUIST:
Yeah, basically, yes.
PETE HUNT: Well, at
Facebook, we found
that flexibility is the most
important thing, that there's
not a silver bullet to
initial page load performance.
You can actually improve
page load performance
by deferring certain things.
So for example, we found that
actually adding JavaScript
to the page can improve
page load performance
if the JavaScript isn't driving
an important part of the UI.
At the same time, we found that
the raw kind of-- if you want
to just say, what
is the fastest way
to get a UI into
the browser, it's
server-rendered HTML every time.
So for us, we're not going
to adopt a system that
requires you to either server
render or to client render.
I think that the
trendy term for this
is called isomorphic JavaScript.
But every system
that we have, we
need to make sure that
we can choose where
on that spectrum do we want to
server render or client render
and at which point do we want
to push that data down the wire.
Which is one of my big
concerns about web components,
because it's blocked on
the JavaScript execution.
And it's tied tightly
to the DOM APIs.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So I
want to go to that point.
So HTML imports, the top level
import from the main document
does block rendering, just
like a style sheet does.
There is an async attribute
that you can use to say,
do not block anything.
And then within
imports themselves,
which are not blocking the
main page from executing
script or parsing,
that kind of thing,
you might have a
complex interdependency
of different things.
We found it's much better it's
much easier to reason about
if you do block those
contacts as you're
loading the other resources.
However, one thing
to remember too
is that web components
provides a set of new tools
that don't take away any tools.
So there's certain
best practices
that we've discovered
that will remain.
So for example, when
you're doing development,
sure, you might want a bunch
of different HTML components
in separate files.
But when you deploy
a production,
you might want to compress
those and minify those
into one resource.
We've also found that you can
do a lot of interesting things
like using these tools and
using async and some judicious
use of some of the stuff.
You could, for example, define
a very simple component that's
just markup that's actually
in the head of your document
so that it loads very
quickly for the user,
and then load the
more complex component
and use that after it loads.
PETE HUNT: Yeah, I'm actually--
I think I like HTML imports.
They seem pretty good.
They seem like
one of these tools
that you can use to shoot
yourself in the foot or not.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: As with many
tools in the [INAUDIBLE].
PETE HUNT: Yeah.
Like, that's a sign
that it's a good tool.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: It can
be a little bit dangerous
to make sure it's
powerful enough.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: Do
you mean that you
would have multiple versions
of the same component
and load the simpler
version first?
And then layer on a more
complicated version after that?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Again,
it's extra tools.
And one thing that's
interesting in this
is with these extra
tools, we found today
on the web platform,
we've got a set
of tools in the web platform.
Some of them are kind
of janky and busted.
But they're what we've got.
We've added a few
more tools on the end.
What I found is that we
found a lot of best practices
today that we've all
sort of discovered
using this set of
tools that we've got.
And actually, adding a few
new ones brings questions,
opens a possibility for
different best practices
that are actually even better.
And one of the cool
things about this
is I feel like, on the
Polymer team and people
who are using
Polymer and X-Tags,
we're kind of the pioneers.
We're discovering
this stuff and saying,
oh my gosh, that's an
interesting pattern that
looks really crazy
before but actually
now makes a lot of sense.
So a number of folks
have been experimenting
with that kind of stuff.
And we don't know what the best
practices are for every case,
obviously.
DAN APPELQUIST: To come over
to this side of the room,
first of all, I
wanted to ask Soledad,
did you have a performance
related comment?
SOLEDAD PENADES: I
have to say, I mean,
when you need to acquire
kind of a complicated UI,
maybe it's not the
matter of a page.
You're going to be
talking about an app.
You're in a different space.
I don't think you can really
consider the same case.
I don't think it's equivalent.
It's like, I mean, it's
talking about a different case,
I guess.
It's like a hybrid between
an app and sharing content.
But the case we're having
with components is many times,
you're building a complex
app, like with UIs and stuff.
You really need to wait
for the whole thing
to load before you can start.
It has to load.
You can optimize on
everything, but it
has to load at some point.
You need to wait.
PETE HUNT: It's all about
option value, though.
Like, we don't want to
commit to a technology
where you have to say, these are
my performance characteristics.
And the way that we're starting
to think about initial page
load performance now is that
when you open your Mac laptop,
or you open an app
on an iOS device,
you see a static screen shot of
the previous version of the UI
before the real UI
actually initializes.
Now, wouldn't it be great if we
could build all of our web apps
like that?
We could render
it on the server,
send down a static HTML
page that can be cached,
and reanimate it
with JavaScript.
So I'm just--
DAN APPELQUIST: I hate that.
[LAUGHTER]
I would kill the web
if that happened.
PETE HUNT: But you have
the choice, though.
Would you want that choice?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: I
think that's the point
is it's still up
to the developers
to figure out how best
to use these tools
for their particular uses.
PETER GASSTON: So
can I say, as someone
who's not involved in the
high level of creation,
I'm kind of an end user of them,
for us, the choice often comes
down to, is it better
than what we've got now?
So if we want to use something
like jQuery UI or something,
or an existing UI
library, do web components
make that faster or better?
I can't really tell that
until we have them natively
and they're implemented.
Personally, I think
they will be better.
But I can't really test
that until we're all
finished and implemented.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: I
want to come back
to the server side
rendering point you made.
I know React has a
mode where it sort
of ships down the
rendered components
directly in the main body.
We actually have found--
this is an example where
some people have explored
going all web components.
Teams at Google who
are prototyping on this
actually found--
they were people
who were big proponents
of server side rendering--
they actually
found in some cases
that it was actually faster
to just heavily cache
the components client side
and then just ship down
the component based markup
and have it inflate locally.
PETE HUNT: That's pretty similar
to what we found, as well.
But we found that
the best thing is
that you want some
of your components
rendered server side, some
of them rendered client side.
And choosing that mix.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: And does that
depend on mobile, as well?
Because I think the
rendering is going
to take a lot longer
client side on mobile.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Yeah.
The performance
characteristics of how much
CPU you have on the machine,
network speeds, latency,
that kind of stuff will
definitely, I think,
impact your decision.
DAN APPELQUIST: Also, I
wanted to open things up
to the audience here.
And I'm looking over to Andrew.
ANDREW: We're good.
DAN APPELQUIST: OK.
[LAUGHTER]
Just want to make sure.
ALEX KOMOROSKE:
Another thing, too,
is that we found-- again, the
Polymer team in particular
is actually part of
the larger Blink team.
So Polymer, the way I think
of it is almost a means
to an ends.
And making sure
that there's good
feedback going into the
specification process.
Because it's very hard
to design complex specs
in a room in the
midst of a discussion.
But it's also, we're
identifying use cases
that make a lot more sense
in the web components world.
And we'll literally yell
over and be like, hey, Adam,
this is something that
we run into a lot.
This is a very common pattern.
And he'll say, oh
yeah, we can actually,
if that pattern's
going to be common,
we can do optimizations
in the engine.
So I imagine in this
new world you'll
see that different patterns
become more common,
or things will be
optimized by engines.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: It's
sort of interesting,
though, because if you look at
the UI libraries that are out
there, Bootstrap or jQuery UI
or Object Oriented CSS, any
of them, they're solving the
same 50 problems over and over
again.
So while I really
like web components
and that you can do
anything with them,
I think maybe the
browser should have
solved those 50 things,
like tabs and carousel
and some basic stuff that's
on every site in the universe
so that we'd need zero
JavaScript for those things.
PETE HUNT: That's actually
a really good point.
DAN APPELQUIST: So we
actually should move on
to the next topic.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Oh, I really
wanted to talk about that.
DAN APPELQUIST: Maybe you
can bookmark that, save it,
and let's bring it to the
rest of the discussion.
So next, I'm going to ask
Jonathan Fielding to ask
his question.
JONATHAN FIELDING: So how
do components help or hinder
responsive design?
Given that many queries are
often [INAUDIBLE] components,
how do components play well with
responsive design approaches?
DAN APPELQUIST: OK, so I'm
going to hand that one over
to Soledad first.
SOLEDAD PENADES: OK.
I've got mixed
feelings about that.
I think that you shouldn't
be building components
that know too much about the
look and feel of the app.
That, I think, should be
something from the outside.
Like, if you're [? inputing ?]
your component with statics,
maybe you're doing it wrong.
It should be about
functionality,
at least in my view.
And I think it's the
view of everyone else.
I mean, if you have
Shadow DOM and you
have a scoped CSS and
things, you can't really
put too much look and
feel inside the thing.
Because you want to be able
to theme from outside and have
break points and everything.
So if you put everything
into a component,
it's not going to
be reusable, which
is what you are actually--
ALEX KOMOROSKE: And
I think, actually,
there's cases where
you don't want styling
or you don't want to be
too [? opinionated. ?]
There are other cases, I think,
where developers would love--
I think Bootstrap is a
great example, where it's
a well designed set
of things that you
can use that play
together nicely.
And I think there's
a lot of room
here for opinionated
UI components.
But again, people can
choose to use them,
or they can choose to do
those different libraries.
But it's a tool.
And there's going to be a
spectrum of uses, I think.
SOLEDAD PENADES: Yeah,
but you can't really
put the whole set of break
points inside the component.
It's just going
to be, a component
works only for this page.
And it's not going to work
for another set of designs.
That's why I suggest-- I mean,
it could be nice, good enough.
I mean, that's why
we're doing Brick.
Make it look good enough
so that it's not that ugly.
But don't try to assume things
that people are going to want.
Make it decent.
PETER GASSTON: I think web
components put a much stronger
onus onto the developer
now than what's
been from the browser
makers in the past.
People are going to
start seeing how hard it
is to create, for
example, a Select element,
and make it accessible,
and make it responsive,
and make it work
across platforms.
And we don't have these
dedicated teams to do that.
We have to work this
stuff out for ourselves.
We're going to see this
a few more times in some
of the other topics we
talk about, I think.
It's how much more
of a burden that
becomes on us as developers.
But it's also a good
responsibility, the fact
that we are shaping
these things in the way
that we want to use them and we
want them to be in the future.
ALEX KOMOROSKE:
So you say burden,
I say it's empowering
developers.
So to your point earlier,
Nicole, you were talking about,
why don't we just ship carousel,
spec carousel and ship it?
Before, web developers
weren't on the same playing
field as browser vendors.
So we could implement some of
these built-in controls using
things like Shadow DOM
that you guys couldn't use.
And so one thing that we're
excited about on the Polymer
team in particular is this idea
that people can play around.
There's an [? X-desk ?] GIF that
someone was sharing yesterday.
It's really cool.
I don't know if that should
be standardized and shipped
in browsers.
But the cool thing is
that people can use it,
and it feels just like
a built-in element.
And if everyone agrees that
those are the semantics
that we should use
and everyone loves it,
maybe that is a target
for standardization.
Because now developers are
empowered to experiment
and to play around and
explore using the same tools
that browsers have.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: But how
frequently has someone
made a built-in element
for picking some thing,
and in fact, on my mobile
phone, it doesn't work?
Or in some other context
that they haven't tested for.
Or they're really used
to an Android browser,
and so they made it
exactly mimic that.
And so then in
whatever I'm using,
it feels weird and has
this uncanny valley,
like it's sort of that
thing, but it's not really
quite that thing.
PETE HUNT: Yeah,
I think that this
is kind of what we were
touching on earlier
and what I really wanted
to jump in for, is
there's kind of two things
where native apps are
kicking the web's ass.
The first is performance.
And we can go into that forever.
But the other thing is that
the widgets that you implement
on the web don't behave exactly
like they do on native devices.
Or you don't have them, rather.
So you have to
basically polyfill them,
and they don't behave
exactly the same.
So while I kind of believe in
the extensible web manifesto,
where we want these primitives
to build whatever we want,
it's also important to get the
integration with the system
level components.
So your UI table
view actually feels
like a UI table view
on an iOS device.
And the equivalent feels
like the equivalent widget
on Android.
So I'm with you on that.
DAN APPELQUIST: I'm going to go
to the audience a little bit.
We have Remy Sharp somewhere?
REMY SHARP: My question was
for the previous discussion,
so that [INAUDIBLE].
DAN APPELQUIST: All right.
So let's go to Jake.
JAKE: So this is in regards to
the responsive design thing.
Having everything as
components makes total sense.
But don't we have a
fundamental problem
that we don't have a component
model for responsive design?
When we use media queries,
they are to the viewport
and not to the component.
DAN APPELQUIST: So the
question is about--
[LAUGHTER]
I'm trying to restate
it without restating it.
PETER GASSTON: Tab Atkins
wrote a very thoughtful article
on this thing.
Because having
responsive components
that are just responsive
kind of in themselves
and not to the viewport
is a great idea.
And it's been
floated many times.
But there are very, very
hard technical problems
to overcome before that.
I can't actually remember
exactly what he said.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: So
basically, any time
you're going to have rendering,
where the child can influence
the parent and the parent
can influence the child,
you can have loops
in your rendering.
And that can't work.
That can't be a thing
that can be implemented.
And so yeah, it
comes up perennially
that people want to be
able to have a media
query on a particular
element's width.
But we need to let that go.
It cannot work.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Tab has a
very thoughtful post on this.
And I can't remember
his conclusions.
It's been a number
of months now.
But one thing that we found
is, in Polymer, we really
embrace it.
Everything is an element,
almost to an extreme.
You build your app.
You're like, oh, I'm always
going to top the whole thing.
And then next week,
you write another app
that has tabs with different
applications inside of it.
And so it's important
as a component author
to think not just
how am I using this,
but what other context
could I be used in?
And some of the tools,
like media queries
might make more sense
for elements, as well.
But again, there are some
challenges to deal with there.
DAN APPELQUIST: Good.
Before we move on
to the next topic,
we have-- sorry if
I'm mispronouncing
your name-- but
Narciso Jaramillo.
NARCISO JARAMILLO: I just
wanted to echo and amplify
what Soledad and
Nicole were saying.
I used to work on Flash with
this component architect.
It's Flash, which is--
it's Flash, whatever.
But we tried to solve
the same problem.
What we found, especially in
highly designed applications,
is that it's really
important to preserve
the separation between
functionality and appearance.
The components should be about
the behavior of the component.
And people should be able to
customize their appearance so
that it fits with
whatever they want.
And I think that the more
people put things like specific
[INAUDIBLE] Shadow DOM, the
less the component is really
going to be usable for
people [INAUDIBLE] devices.
So is there anything
architecturally
in web components that makes it
easier for a component author
to just worry about
the behavior and not
make too many assumptions about
[INAUDIBLE] is going to be?
DAN APPELQUIST:
Alex, quick thoughts?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: It's up
to the component author
to do what they want.
There's going to be a spectrum
of opinionated UI components
that are themable and ones
that have no opinion on UI.
PETE HUNT: There's scoped
style, which helps with this.
But also, I think that that only
gets you to a certain point.
At some point, the
appearance of your element
has to be coupled with
changes in behavior, as well.
So I think really focusing on
the composition of elements
and how, if I've got
a component-- like,
do I want that full
drop down functionality?
What if I want to add separators
inside the drop down element
and the developer
didn't think of it?
So you need to think it really
in terms of composition,
not only of styling,
but also of behavior,
and the way that data flows
between components, as well.
DAN APPELQUIST: So before we
move on to the next thing,
I just want to--
Jonathan, you're
on the queue, quick comment?
JONATHAN FIELDING: So if
you've got some [INAUDIBLE]
onto the mobile,
[INAUDIBLE] mobile,
[INAUDIBLE] responsive
sites, would you
show and hide
different components?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: It's going
to be up to the developers
in different cases.
We play around with,
on the Polymer side,
most of the UI elements we
have now are just expirations.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: Well, and just
like building the UI libraries
that have come up
until now, I think
there are UI libraries
that are very opinionated,
like this thing is going
to be exactly this width.
And it means you can only use
it when, magically, that's
the width you need.
And the better UI libraries
and the ones that have emerged
are the ones that build tabs
that fill in whatever space
is available.
And that's still going to
be true in the web component
world.
PETER GASSTON: There was also,
as part of the earlier web
component suite, there was an
idea of these things called
decorators, which are HTML
markup applied with CSS.
So you could apply
different markup
and use your media
queries in that way.
But again, there were
insurmountable technical
problems in doing that.
And that's had to be dropped.
So I don't think
this is something
that's going to be
easily achieved.
DAN APPELQUIST: So I'm going
to have to cut it off there,
because we need to move on
to the next thing, which
is Joshua Peek.
Can you please speak your mind?
Can we get him a mic?
JOSHUA PEEK: Hi.
I've done a lot of work
on GitHub's implementation
of content security policy.
I'm wondering how web
components fit into CSP.
Polymer and other polyfills make
use of eval and HTML imports
[INAUDIBLE] declare
the scripts in line.
In general, how
will web components
become another attack vector?
And what's the general story
for security in web components?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So again,
we're adding some new tools.
We're not taking others away.
It is possible to
use web components
within a very restrictive
CSP environment.
For example, Chrome apps
has a very restrictive CSP
environment.
And although by
default, with Polymer,
we recommend people define
their scripts right in line
with the templates, there's a
version of our Vulcanize tool
that will allow you to actually
have those as external scripts
that will obey a
CSP policy and not
be eval in the main
context of the page.
DAN APPELQUIST: Other thoughts
on security in general,
as well?
Like, it really
occurred to me when
I was reading this
question about, I think
I added the thing about,
can web components
be a vector for
attack in some way?
Thoughts on that from
any of the panel?
Have you thought about that?
SOLEDAD PENADES: I
think we should be fine.
I mean, you can still have the
same content or [INAUDIBLE]
restrictions.
It's just through JavaScript.
It's not different JavaScript.
This is still a thing that
is running the same way
that all the other
JavaScript is running.
So you should still
get your browser angry
if you do something
inappropriate.
So we should be fine.
Haven't tried to break it yet.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: And there are
a number of attack vectors
if you use third party content.
For example, if you don't use
CSP [INAUDIBLE] effectively,
there's attack vectors
on the web today.
This isn't changing that.
If you're using someone else's
hosting of the components,
sure.
To be clear, by
the way, Shadow DOM
does not provide a
security boundary.
That's a misconception that
sometimes we see from people.
We have iframes for
the security boundary.
But Shadow DOM just provides
a much stronger style
encapsulation.
But ultimately it's
a boundary that
can be crossed in the page.
DAN APPELQUIST: Any other
thoughts on security or CSP?
PETER GASSTON: That's
really not my area at all.
DAN APPELQUIST: No?
OK.
Maybe we move on then, actually.
So now I'm going
to ask Stewart Cox.
Can we get Stewart a mic?
STEWART COX: So do you
think web components
open the door for developers
to abandon semantics?
Are we going to end up with
a million different homegrown
select widgets, and what is
the meaning of an attack name
if that happens?
DAN APPELQUIST: So I'm going to
ask Nicole to field that one.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: So
I'm probably going
to give a little bit of an
unpopular point of view here.
I like semantics on a gut level.
But when I'm making a decision
about what to do for a project,
I try to keep in mind
what I'm actually
trying to get out of it and
what semantics actually give me.
Because in a lot of
cases, we give way
too much weight to semantics.
And we aren't getting enough out
of it for basically the value
that we're trying for.
So basically, I
think that there's
semantic value in accessibility.
And we get that from ARIA roles.
And what I think is great about
ARIA roles is that they're
divorced from whatever markup
you happened to have used.
And so we're no longer relying
on some implicit connection.
But instead, we're basically
getting the semantic value
from something we can
tag onto anything.
So I think that
that's important.
And then the other
value that we get
is sort of developer
maintenance and how developers
will understand our code later.
Because those are basically
the only two things
that use semantics.
And I think that actually
being able to write custom tags
has a chance to
make it-- and being
able to hide a bunch of junkie
markup gives us a fairly good--
not junkie, but presentational
markup, basically,
gives us a chance to be able to
have cleaner HTML that contains
just the things that are
relevant to understanding
what's going on.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: When you
say abandon semantics,
I mean, we've
abandoned semantics.
If you open up the Dev
Tools Inspector on any page,
you see a whole bunch of
stuff that's meaningless.
The cool thing
about Shadow DOM is
you can take that
presentational gunk that's
required and sort of
store it off to the side.
And so if you look at pages
that are written in a web
components-y style, you look at
it and you can understand it.
Like, it actually
makes sense reading it.
I also think that we
abandoned semantics
because the
components that we're
shipping in the browser,
things like input and select,
they're great.
But there weren't that many
of them, as you were saying.
There's no carousel
built into the browser.
And so this allows us
to create that carousel.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: Maybe for the
carousel there shouldn't be.
Just because it's
an awful UI pattern.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: But
I'm saying, this
allows us to create
those things and actually
represent them more semantically
in ways in the [INAUDIBLE].
DAN APPELQUIST: I got
Remy in the queue.
I just wanted to pull him in.
Can we get Remy a mic up here?
REMY SHARP: So we're rushing
to make all these libraries,
Brick, Polymer, and so on, we're
rushing great web components.
And this kind of hangs a little
bit off the blocking thing,
but we're making old mistakes.
We're repeating old mistakes.
Like, local storage is a good
example of new technology
that came out a few years ago.
There was a big throw of arms,
and it's not asynchronous.
And we're warned
against using it.
But we're repeating
the same mistakes
when we've got the opportunity
with new technology
to not make these mistakes
and make sure that everything
is good for going forward,
since it's effectively
a clean slate, right?
NICOLE SULLIVAN: But there's
no such thing, is there?
Like, we are always
going to make mistakes.
Like, we're going
to totally screw up.
REMY SHARP: Sure, sure.
No, I agree.
Unknown mistakes
that we're going
to create in the first
place, but knowingly
develop against mistakes.
PETE HUNT: I think that a lot of
those mistakes come from this.
We're not sure if the browser
is an SDK or a run time.
Right?
So it wouldn't make
any sense for you
to have your OpenGL
calls be semantic, right?
But OpenGL's a very
performant API.
So why do the data
structures that we've
rendered to the rendering engine
we have available to us, which
is the DOM, why do those
have to be semantic?
Why do we even think about that?
Why do we think about
like, we talk about,
we need to make this
performant and expressive.
And sometimes those are
at odds with each other.
So I think that
the reason why you
get things like
synchronous local storage
is because the fast
API, the fast primitive,
is an asynchronous call.
But the easy API
is a blocking call.
And so we need to basically
make a decision, like,
are we going to make
the browser in SDK?
Are we going to make
it like Visual Basic?
Or are we going to
make it like libc?
And it's still this kind of
Frankenstein environment.
REMY SHARP: The thing is,
we, the web community,
prefer the easier solution.
We'll always take
the shortest route
to actually getting
the thing live.
So if it means we kill the
performance in the browser,
we'll take that, as a community.
Because we're great
at Copy and Paste.
Or we're great at just ripping
off other people's code.
So if you have the
opportunity to-- the baseline
doesn't have those kind
of blocks built into it,
or mistakes built
into it, then that
seems like the right thing.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Remy, this
is a very complex topic.
And I'm not going to pretend
to know all the details.
I've watched this be argued
many, many times by people
much smarter than
me on this issue.
And inevitably, after
hours of discussion,
everyone goes, oh, I get it now.
But it's one of those things
that's very hard to explain.
Like, I can't do it effectively.
DAN APPELQUIST:
Maybe we have some
of those smart
people in the room.
[LAUGHTER]
So first of all, [? Floran ?]
[? Edgar? ?] Can we get him
a mic?
AUDIENCE: I wonder if we are
not hiding a lot of stuff
in abstractions when we're
using web components.
Doesn't it affect
maintainability
and actually hurt reuse?
Because we are building, again,
100 different Select boxes.
Because we all have just a
little bit different use cases.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: I think,
using web components,
it's very clear, it makes your
code much more maintainable
because you can think more
in your local context.
You don't have to worry about
what someone else elsewhere
in the page has done,
what kind of styles
they've put in the
global style sheet.
Because you have scoped
styles, because you
have this nice
encapsulation mechanism,
you can think much more locally.
And it's really
freeing as a developer
to be able to think like that.
Because today, if you have
more than three people working
on a site together,
they have to coordinate.
And they have to say,
well, don't do this thing.
And please make sure your
selectors don't accidentally
select over into my area.
And actually, my
personal experience
and a lot of people who have
used web components so far has
been it's actually far,
far, far more maintainable.
I don't know if anyone else--
PETER GASSTON: It's like, as
I mentioned before, it's like,
is it better than
what we have now?
What we do now is we
just get a load of divs
with classes attached to them
and attach the things to that.
And it's all put directly
into the markup of the page.
It's all in the DOM tree.
Now, I think that what
web components bring
through encapsulation,
through scoped styles,
I think that makes that
better and more maintainable.
It's not going to stop
people from writing,
as I said, a
proliferation of crap.
That's never going to end.
That's what we do until we
find that maybe we settled--
DAN APPELQUIST: That's the
web, proliferation of crap.
PETER GASSTON: Until
maybe we settle
on something like Brick or
Polymer or the two of them
together, come up with
something that we're
all so enamored with.
And we decide to, let's
be mature about this,
and stop reinventing
everything all the time.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: When have
we ever settled on anything?
PETER GASSTON: Right.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: But
one thing that I think
is very important about
this is that web components,
to the extent they
pretend that they're just
other elements, to the
extent that they take
in configuration through
attributes or methods
and properties on the prototype,
and that they admit events
when interesting
things happen, it
doesn't matter how they're
implemented on the inside.
So you can use an
X-Tag component
right next to a
Polymer component
or within one another,
and it just works.
PETE HUNT: So I
agree with the spirit
of abstraction
and encapsulation.
But web components deals
primarily with scoped style.
And honestly, Nicole solved
that a couple years ago
with Object Oriented CSS.
So I think that that's solving--
NICOLE SULLIVAN:
Well, except that,
in order to make Object
Oriented CSS work,
you have to have a lot
of developer rigor.
And everybody has to be on the
same page about making sure.
And it isn't even
on the same page.
When someone's
just learning CSS,
they're going to make 1,000
mistakes before they're
ready to write something
that's really encapsulated.
And then there
are other problems
where you can't
encapsulate it, right?
Styles are going to flow
through to children.
You can't help it.
PETE HUNT: I'm speaking from
a very Facebook-specific
perspective, where we can
control our engineering
organization.
But the problem is that
that's the easy part.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: But also,
that's hard for just even
a large organization,
where everyone's
being paid by the same person.
We run into this at
Google all the time.
PETE HUNT: Well, we have a
rule of like, single class name
for--
DAN APPELQUIST: Before
we move on to the next--
SOLEDAD PENADES: Can I
say something quickly?
I have experience
of building things
with components, reusable
things, and they work great.
If you want, I can show you.
If you can trust, all
these guys are like--
DAN APPELQUIST:
Wait for the break.
One more comment maybe from
the audience before we-- yeah,
Guy from Akamai?
Can we get, just a brief?
GUY PODJARNY: I mostly wanted to
highlight some of the comments
that Remy was getting to.
So when you look at
the existing successes
we have, like Node, one
of its claims to fame
is that it forces you
to be asynchronous.
A lot of the
problems that we have
on the flip side of
that, if you look
at the async widgets,
anything that didn't ship
as async widget before,
Google [INAUDIBLE],
Facebook, or Twitter, we're
stuck with those things now.
So I do think that there's
strong merit in taking away
some flexibility in
favor of performance
or in favor of making it a
little bit harder to shoot
yourself in the foot.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: To be
clear, HTML imports
don't block the script and
parsing of the main document.
They do block rendering, just
like style sheets do today.
But again, if you want
to render something fast,
you can put things
directly in your document.
You don't have to use HTML
imports for everything.
PETER GASSTON: [INAUDIBLE]
PETE HUNT: The recurring theme
within Facebook engineering
is one word.
And it's predictability.
It's like, you
want to know what's
going to happen when
you do something.
With Node, you
know everything is
going to be async
out of the box,
unless you're using a
weird, like, C extension.
With the DOM, yes,
there is a fast path.
But it's so easy to
fall off the fast path.
Like, you don't know
what's going to happen.
You have no way
to predict what's
going to happen because
you have to reason
about the entire system
as a whole, which I think
is an argument for
building abstractions
on top of fast,
underlying primitives,
like you talked about.
And I think that's
the way forward.
I don't think baking
more functionality
into this unpredictable
DOM is the way forward.
DAN APPELQUIST: We're
going to move on.
I'm sorry, Christian, but you'll
have a chance to talk later.
The next topic is going to
be introduced by [? Cormel ?]
[? Lasinski. ?]
AUDIENCE: Hi.
What's the story of
internationalization
of components?
Does the user of the
component inject strengths
in the component, or
does the component
have to have hooks for
internationalization?
ALEX KOMOROSKE:
Again, this is an area
where the best practices--
people are still
being pioneers in this space
and see what these new tools do.
In different cases, it
will depend, I think.
But we are experimenting
with a number
of approaches on Polymer.
I think that it will depend
for different code bases,
potentially.
PETE HUNT: I can't
speak to the spec,
but we've been building
component architectures
at Facebook for a long time.
And it's made
internationalization
a lot easier.
Because your components--
you basically
say, hey, this is my
internationalized text label
component.
And you drop that
in wherever you
need internationalized text.
And within that, you can
have tokens, like, oh, this
is my user's gender component.
And it'll know, it'll
look at the user object,
and it'll say, oh, is
this male or female?
And put the right
string in there.
And so when you build with
a component architecture,
the composition
possibilities make
internationalization
a lot easier.
And we built tooling around
that for our own systems,
including React and XHP,
that people don't even
really think about it so much.
They just wrap their
strings in the right text.
PETER GASSTON: This will
be one where I think,
sorry to bang on
the same drum again,
but it puts more of the emphasis
on you doing the right thing.
If you make UI elements--
and I think mostly,
if I'm not mistaken,
all of the UI elements
we have at the moment don't
include any text by default.
So you just drop your
own values into that.
But if you create a UI element
that does have text in there
by default, the onus is on
you to put something in there
to make that internationalized.
Or make your work open
source and let other people
do that for you.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So one
metapoint I want to make
is that because web components
get this interoperability
very cheaply-- I think
X-Tags and Brick interopting
with Polymer is a great proof
point for that-- it means
that it's different
than what happens today.
So today, as a developer,
you pick a framework.
At the beginning, you say,
OK, well, this framework
has 20 widgets that look
pretty good, I guess.
But then you get to them, and
maybe their calendar widget
isn't accessible or isn't
internationalizable.
And because the competition
is on the framework level,
you don't necessarily
get the framework
at the component level.
Whereas with web
components, it's easier.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: Well, sure.
But thinking of the
frameworks that we
have today, the amount of stuff
you have to pull in in order
to make anyone-- I mean, you
could pick and choose and take
one piece from one framework
and one bit from another,
but the amount you have
to pull in in order
to do that, my worry is
that each component is going
to depend on a whole
bunch of dependencies.
And they're going
to end up actually
pulling in way too much.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: And part of the
reason that's the case today
is because we have to create
our own parallel universes
and use the DOM just as
sort of the rendering layer,
and that's it.
Actually, one of the
cool things about Polymer
is most of the code
size is that layer
of polyfills, which is
completely unnecessary
if the browser
you're using ships
Shadow DOM, custom elements,
HTML imports, et cetera.
So it goes way, way,
way down in size
as browsers ship those natively.
SOLEDAD PENADES:
Back to the topic.
I think custom elements
are just DOM elements.
So you can just use
your current libraries
for internationalization.
DAN APPELQUIST: Say [INAUDIBLE].
SOLEDAD PENADES: Yeah.
Or [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, so I've been
running some tests.
And it works great with
mobile and everything.
You just add your
custom data [INAUDIBLE]
to translate things.
And it translates things.
I mean, it's just
another element, so.
It's just that
once you create it,
but it works like any
other thing works.
DAN APPELQUIST:
Any other comments?
Nicole, did you want to-- no?
OK.
So I think, given
that, we'll move on
to our next possibly
related topic, which
is going to be asked
by George Thomas.
GEORGE THOMAS: Hi.
How could web components be
used to enhance accessibility?
Can shared standards
for interaction
be developed and agreed
upon for common components?
ALEX KOMOROSKE:
So accessibility's
incredibly important.
Actually, Alice
Boxhall, who's going
to be speaking on one of
the later panels, who's
on the Chrome
accessibility team,
has been working very closely
with some folks on the Polymer
team and the web
components standards folks.
DAN APPELQUIST: And we
shouldn't rathole too much
into general
accessibility issues
because we're going to have
a whole panel on that later.
So I was almost
reluctant to field
this question in the panel.
But what are the web
component specific issues
that have cropped up
around accessibility?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So our
understanding, our belief,
and Alice can correct
me if I'm wrong here,
is that actually,
we think that it
should be possible to
make things just as
accessible as before.
But in addition,
because there can
be competition on the
level of components,
there'll be much more
pressure on component authors
to create accessible,
internationalizable components.
And so actually,
accessibility is
one of those hard
things for developers
to wrap their heads
around sometimes.
It's one of those things
they put off until the end.
But if you use a component
that's already made accessible,
that's actually great for users.
Because it's more
likely that you
don't have to do all
that thinking yourself
every single time you use it.
So I'm actually more hopeful
that the accessibility story
will get better in
the components world.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: It's hard
to see it getting better
than native UI controls, though.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So
the best practices
of using native UI
controls where necessary
or where relevant
makes sense in the ARIA
as a fallback if for
some reason [INAUDIBLE].
PETE HUNT: So I'm the world's
biggest DOM hater here,
and I'm excited
about Shadow DOM.
Because being able to
style a select component
is like the prime example of how
awesome Shadow DOM is, I think.
Because we have our custom
select element component
at Facebook that matches
our interface guidelines,
and it's like a zillion lines
of code, and then a zillion
extra lines of
code on top of that
to get the tab behavior
right for accessibility.
Now, the browser and
the operating system
have already done all that
work for each platform.
So we can leverage
that with Shadow DOM.
So I'm really
excited about that.
Additionally, the way that we
use a component architecture
at Facebook, we don't use
the web component standard,
but we use the same kind
of ideas of encapsulated UI
elements rather than
templates or traditional MVC
is we have a library that has
been developed that is already
accessible and ready to go.
And people who don't know
much about accessibility just
go in, pull a component
off the shelf, drop it in.
PETER GASSTON: Yeah,
we've been talking a lot
about creating your own totally
bespoke custom elements.
But we shouldn't forget that
that's a big part of it,
as well, is extending existing
elements becomes very, very
easy through web
components, as well.
You can take your
Select box, which
we seem to be using as the
default go-to for whenever
we talk about it, and just
add your own things to it.
But the markup inside that,
inside the Shadow DOM,
still remains as accessible
as it was before.
When we are creating
our own elements,
again, we have to bake
the accessibility into it.
But you can put ARIA
roles onto these things.
You can do all that.
If you view the Shadow DOM of
any element that exists out
there, you'll see that they've
got ARIA roles in there
already.
We should be using that as
a model of best practice.
But it is a concern.
Because people--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] question.
Because there's a
lot of accessibility
thrown around here
by non-experts.
I'm very scared of what's
going on here right now.
We have a whole
session on that later.
DAN APPELQUIST: And we're
going to talk about ARIA
later, actually, I think.
Yeah.
I do notice that we have zero
people connected to the system.
AUDIENCE: It's down again.
DAN APPELQUIST: OK,
that's what I thought.
So if there's somebody who
wants to ask a question
related to this--
OK, yes, Jeremy.
JEREMY: So yes, this is related
to accessibility and semantics
as well, as you
pointed out, Nicole.
It's one of the reasons
for semantics to exist,
is exposing hooks, for example,
to assistive technology.
But to say then,
we're all sorted
because we've got
ARIA, so no problem.
First of all, ARIA is intended
as a stopgap solution working
towards native semantics.
That's the end goal.
ARIA is to get us there.
Also, if the whole
point of web components
is that we can invent these new
browser elements, effectively,
but then in order to
make them accessible,
we are restricted
to what ARIA can do,
then we're just passing
the buck to ARIA.
And unless there is a
concept of ARIA components,
then web components
will always be
using a small pool of
accessibility hooks, which
limits their scope,
which kind of goes
against the whole point
of web components.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: I
agree with the person
that I'm not an expert
in accessibility,
and I guess maybe
this is best deferred
to the accessibility panel.
PETE HUNT: Well, you just need
to make the primitives you have
for composition as expressive
as possible, right?
Like, the only way
to solve this problem
is to be able to compose
more complex things out
of simpler things
that are accessible
and somehow make the system
as a whole accessible.
So web components need to be, or
whatever component architecture
you use, need to be as
expressive as possible.
And it's not just
ARIA attributes.
And it's not just styling.
It's behavior.
And I think you have
to be able to compose
with the full power of a
real programming language
to do that.
And you need to be
able to override
specific bits of functionality.
So part of it is kind
of the architecture
of the system you're
using, and part of it
is the power of the
primitives that you have,
which is why I think composing
with DOM elements isn't
powerful enough.
I think you have to
compose with like, Turing
complete programming
languages to do this.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: I think
you're also bringing up
something important, which is
that the whole web community is
suffering with the fact that
the accessibility side of web
standards and the web and
other side of web standards
don't talk to each
other nearly enough,
and haven't figured
out how it's supposed
to work together very neatly.
And so I think a lot of
this we don't actually
have answers for.
I mean, yes, we're not
accessibility experts.
But also, we don't know how
it's supposed to work together.
And the standards
teams themselves
aren't really working together.
DAN APPELQUIST: Other
gentleman in the front row,
can you introduce
yourself, as well?
AUDIENCE: Hey, Matt [? Bonn. ?]
The question was kind of
phrased like, you have
accessibility on the web today.
How does that apply
to Polymer components?
Is there anything Polymer
and just web components
in general can do
that would basically
make accessibility better?
In other words,
ignore what today is.
If you could change it and
make web components successful,
ignoring everything
now, what would you do?
Like for me, you could add
life cycle events saying,
you're going to get focus.
Deal with it.
Like, that should be part
of the web component,
that they have to deal
with that at that point.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Not an
accessibility expert,
so I guess that's--
PETE HUNT: I mean, this
is kind of what the Shadow
DOM's trying to solve, right?
Like, Select boxes seem
to be pretty accessible.
At least, they do
the same semantics
that the operating system does.
One of the things, and Nicole
had mentioned this before,
is the more native UI you
expose in the browser,
the more you can reuse from
the experts that have actually
implemented it right.
DAN APPELQUIST: Remy,
I see your hand up,
but we are going to move on.
And we are going to pick
up this topic hopefully
in Christian's accessibility
panel, as well.
So I hope that we
revisit this, as well.
Our last question of
this topic, some guy
named Andrew Betts
possibly needs to ask this.
It's a long-y.
ANDREW BETTS: Until web
components are more widely
supported, in what
use cases would
you consider polyfills
like Polymer or X-Tags
over alternative
component frameworks?
To what extent do the
existence of polyfills
hinder or slow down
the implementation
of web components?
NICOLE SULLIVAN: I
couldn't hear that.
DAN APPELQUIST: Polyfills.
So the question is really
related to polyfills.
And I think the crux of it is,
are the existence of polyfills
going to hinder or help the
adoption or the implementation
of web components within
browsers in general
in the developer community?
Any thoughts on that?
ALEX KOMOROSKE: I
think it will help.
It'll help the adoption
in other browser vendors.
Because it allows developers
to use the technologies today
in a way that actually
works quite well.
It's just when the native
implementation is there,
it's much faster.
And so like Shadow
DOM, for example,
is a very complicated
thing to polyfill.
And it's not possible
to do it 100% perfectly.
CSS in particular is very hard
to polyfill correctly there.
And then when it's
supported natively,
it's just much, much faster
[INAUDIBLE] done in script.
DAN APPELQUIST: I see somebody
who might know something
about polyfills
asking a question.
AUDIENCE: It's not
specifically polyfills.
But when we get to the day
when we're including Polymer,
and we're including this
other web component that
comes from another
website, and another web
component from another
website, and all
the magic is kind of tucked
away between my X-gif tag,
those web components
are going to be carrying
all their own
JavaScript, for instance.
What if they all pull in their
own jQuery library or polyfills
library for all--
NICOLE SULLIVAN: And
different versions of jQuery.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, different
versions of jQuery.
The version's not a
problem, because they're
going to be
sandboxed off, right?
I assume.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: Sure, but
that's a lot of components.
AUDIENCE: The overhead for
having four or five web
components where they're
all pulling in JavaScript--
there is jQuery, but from
different locations--
how do we deal with that?
How do we not end up returning
to the days of [INAUDIBLE]
drive, where we're just
slapping in big blocks of code
and going, fuck it, it works.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: So one of
the cool things about HTML
imports, too, is they can do
deduping of those resources.
So different components
can rely on the same thing,
and it won't be
re-downloaded twice.
And of course, if you use
some kind of minification step
before you push
to production, you
can make sure that
you take care of that.
But of course, if you have
different versions of jQuery,
you're going to want to
avoid that as a developer,
just like you do today.
You don't want to use--
AUDIENCE: What I'm
talking about is,
like I'm using Brick
and Polymer together,
because you've got
different web components,
and I want to use both of them.
How does that even
get surfaced to me?
DAN APPELQUIST: Let's get
X-Tag's perspective on this.
SOLEDAD PENADES: I think
it's pretty much the same.
I mean, you have
to be responsible.
You have to be
minifying just choosing
the components you want.
It's just like if you just
load the whole jQuery UI,
they're huge.
And it's the same with Brick.
If you download the whole
thing, it's not that huge.
But it's still a lot of
things you might not want.
But you can choose, build
your own distribution.
I mean, you've got script
for backend things,
like as they do.
I think we call
it smush in a way.
PETE HUNT: Is this like
a fundamental problem
with software, though?
SOLEDAD PENADES:
It's a big process.
PETE HUNT: If you
coded in the '90s,
you know DLL hell and
that kind of thing.
So I think that the pipe dream
of like pulling components
off the shelf and
dropping them in
is way more nuanced than
people normally say it is.
For us, we just run it
through a build system
and we dedupe and alert when
there's different versions.
AUDIENCE: You're using
your own web components.
So you're not using
anyone else's?
PETE HUNT: Well, we have a
component based architecture
that we own the whole stack, so.
NICOLE SULLIVAN:
And they also have
a backend that is
component based
and matches up exactly with
the front end part of it.
So that changes it.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Also,
practically today,
Polymer and X-Tags use the
same layer of polyfills below.
And remember, that's
where the bulk of the code
is, in Polymer in particular.
And remember, that goes to
zero over time, is the idea.
NICOLE SULLIVAN: I don't
see how that's true, though.
Like yeah, that's true in
a really simple component.
But as the components want to
do all these widgety things,
it's going to have the
same amount of code
that any library that would have
done the same thing has now.
ALEX KOMOROSKE: Not necessarily.
Because to the extent that
today, a number of frameworks
have no other choice
but to retreat to script
and to create their own
world that uses, again,
DOM as just a sort of
dumb rendering service.
In a world where you're
working more closely with DOM,
you don't have
that overhead where
you have to create
your own world,
create your own concepts.
There's parallel
hierarchy in the script.
DAN APPELQUIST: In a world.
[LAUGHTER]
All right, so I'm being
told from the front row
that we need to wrap up.
I think my personal
closing statement might be,
a web component, some
assembly required.
What is it, vague
but interesting?
Maybe.
So we'll leave it at that.
Thanks very much.
And thanks to our panel.