CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Here's the panel
that you've been waiting
for after we had it hinted
in every other panel so far, and
the lots of questions and lots
of quick solutions
being thrown around.
Like the last session,
for example-- when
will voice recognition
be the norm?
Just easy-- take people's
eyes out, take their arms off,
and they have to use
voice recognition.
A lot of things that we
actually think is coming
had to be used in accessibility
for years and years already.
I always see accessibility as
a hard core usability testing.
It's something that people
need and not something
that we just want to have.
But Derek is going to
do a better job in that.
My job is right now not to
talk but to introduce people.
So to first make
fun of the Germans,
let's have a family
name like Lewthwaite.
Sarah is here.
She's from King's College.
And she's an academic
researcher and writer bridging
the gap between critical
disability theory
and accessibility
practice, something
that was on our mind
for a long, long time,
and we've been discussing a
lot between us, hopefully.
Andrew Ronskley over
here is from the RNIB.
And he's an accessibility
and usability specialist
focused on the web
and mobile platforms.
He's also contributed to the
Surf Right standards, which
was an interesting
thing to look at.
Alice Boxhall is
from Google, but she
knows about accessibility.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, that was unfair.
But it was so good,
because everybody else
I talked to, she's
like, and here's Alice.
She's going to talk to you
later about accessibility.
So no pressure-- you have
to answer all the questions
right now.
She works on the
Accessibility Developer Tools
extension and library.
And that's something
like we used in the past.
We had performance tools
for developer tools.
But now we have accessibility
testers in there
as well, which are great,
and absolutely necessary
for things like a
Chromebook where
you only have Chrome
on it and nothing else.
And Matthew Tylee Atkinson from
the Paciello Group over there
is from the Paciello Group,
a tester, screen magnifier,
and occasional text
to speech user.
And he works on
web accessibility,
accessible gaming, which is an
interesting topic, especially
when you think about these
kinds of Kinect things, level
editing, and
supporting older users.
Old users-- is that a
political correct term?
I'm not sure.
So speaking of people that have
been around for a longer time,
I'm going to introduce you
now to Derek Featherstone, who
has been with me in
the accessibility world
for a long, long time and
worked on the first book
that we both had chapters in,
the web accessibility book
that two or four people read
and followed up later on.
So without further
ado, over to Derek.
[APPLAUSE]
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
So I'm here today
to talk about accessibility.
And most people think
of accessibility
in very technical terms.
And the number one point
that I want everybody
to walk away from
this today with
is that accessibility
is all about people.
It has to be about people.
Because if it's
not about people,
we end up doing the wrong
thing even though we're
meaning to do the right thing.
So all of us that are up
here have a background
in doing this stuff for people.
So Christian actually
started his first foray
into understanding
accessibility when
he was working with
people with disabilities
when he worked
for the Red Cross.
Sarah is a researcher.
She actually works with real
people on accessibility issues.
Alice is putting ARIA
support into Chrome.
And that's for
people to use, right?
We cannot forget this.
Andrew actually
works with people,
taking smartphones to them
to show them and demonstrate
all the different accessibility
features of smartphones
and how those
things can actually
have an impact on
their day to day life.
And Matthew started changing
the authoring environment
for gaming so that that
could be accessible to people
that were blind.
And I do, too.
I work with people
with accessibility
with disabilities every day.
We do research and
testing and try
to figure out what UX is for
people with disabilities,
right?
What does UX mean to them?
And so hearing all the
things that everybody's
talking about this
morning and this afternoon
has been absolutely fascinating.
Because we're talking about
it at very technical levels.
But at the end of the day,
people have to use those tools.
And that to me is what
accessibility is all about.
We tend to simplify things.
And you probably
have heard of all
of these different conditions
or things that people have,
that people are blind or they
have low vision, they have
hearing difficulties,
or that they
have a mobility or a
dexterity impairment.
And when you start to think
of all of these things,
even those things seem
to be very physical.
But what about the
cognitive side of things?
And those are
traditionally the things
that we're thinking about when
we think about accessibility.
But there's a whole
other realm that we
need to start to get
into and explore.
How many of you
have heard of things
like vestibular disorders?
So there's a whole
group of people
that have some kind of
vestibular disorder--
and I don't even like the
word "disorder," but issues
with their balance.
And so when they're looking at
a screen with all your fancy CSS
animations and your
parallax effects,
that actually makes
them nauseous, right?
It actually causes migraines.
So when you're
scrolling down the page,
and you have a car
that you've animated
with CSS that's going like this
across the page, that actually
makes somebody nauseous, right?
These are new things that
aren't sort of in the mainstream
accessibility.
And we need to start to take
those things into account.
Things like speech--
the very last panel
was talking about,
well, what about speech?
And as Christian pointed out,
voice recognition software
was originally invented for
people with disabilities.
So on the speech side
of things-- and this
is I think an absolutely
critical thing for us
to keep in mind as
we move forward.
Speech is just one
modality, right?
What happens if we
create interfaces
that use that as
the only modality?
And what does that
do for somebody
that speaks a different
language, that
has a stutter, that
maybe has cerebral palsy
and has difficulty
speaking, right?
We need to create interfaces
that are entirely flexible.
And one of the other
panels earlier,
the pointers-- what
about custom gestures?
Well, what about the fact that--
and so here's a custom gesture,
move up and to the left.
Well, that custom
gesture is already
being used on Android for
screen reader users that
are using the talk back
screen reader on Android.
So what happens when
that custom gesture
that you've created and built
into your page conflicts
with the custom gesture that is
required for the screen reader?
So we need to think about
flexible alternatives.
So when I move up and left
in TalkBack in Android,
that means something to me.
And that gives functionality.
So even though you
create a custom gesture
like that in your
app or in your page,
you need to consider that maybe
that's not the only way that we
should be able to
instantiate that action.
Maybe we need some other
method or a backup mechanism
to do that.
We need to think about all
of these different things.
We tend to put people in
boxes and say, you're blind
or you're not blind, right?
You have a disability
or your don't.
But that is not reality.
We have a scenario-- and this
is a very standard Gaussian
binomial bell
curve distribution,
whatever you want to call it.
And we have people
that live at one
end of the extreme or another.
And this one's talking
about people's size.
But think of it in
terms of any ability.
So you have people on one end
that have maybe completely
normal vision, on the other
end people that have no vision.
And then, you have people
everywhere in between.
This is not a binary
all or nothing scenario.
And we need to think
about that all the time.
Today's assistive technology
is really advanced.
We've moved from a point where
solutions that we used to think
were completely
untenable, like ARIA.
So ARIA stands for Accessible
Rich Internet Applications.
And it's a tool that we
can use to add to our code
to provide programmatic
accessibility where it just
didn't exist before.
Screen readers for over
the last five years
have really advanced
and really done
a great job of getting ARIA
support into that technology.
But we have to ask this
kind of a question.
What if a brand new
version of a certain type
of assistive technology
just isn't modern?
And I'll give you an example.
This is a suite of
assistive technology tools.
We've got voice
recognition up there.
We've got tools
built into browsers.
NV Access is a screen reader
for the Windows platform that's
free, VoiceOver on the Mac.
ZoomText on Windows is
a magnifier and reader
combination.
Now, all of the screen
readers on there,
they have done a pretty
good job of keeping up
with modern technology.
But some other tools
don't necessarily keep up.
And so I'm not going to name
any names or single anybody out.
But Dragon NaturallySpeaking
is a great tool.
But it doesn't keep
up with the standards.
They haven't implemented
any support for ARIA.
And that's something that all
the screen readers have done.
I'll give you an example of
why that's actually important.
This is a very, very new
version of a Google map.
And these things on the
interface, the search button
and the zoom in
and the zoom out,
those things all used to be
divs with on-click handlers--
pretty straightforward
practice, very typical.
This is something where we
could actually improve that by
instead of just having
a div with an on-click,
we could actually give
that a role of button
so that a screen reader or other
piece of assistive technology
in theory could recognize that
that's a button so that there's
a more natural affordance
there that, hey, I can actually
click on this instead of it
just being a div in the page.
The beautiful
thing about this is
that-- and I just
literally saw this
with this new revision
of Google Maps--
there are actually now
buttons, like actual buttons.
Holy crap, there are
actually buttons.
And that totally
gets a gold star.
Because all the
semantics of a button
are already in that
native element, right?
This button could be used
by Dragon NaturallySpeaking.
The div with the role of
button can't be, right?
So there's a question about
whose responsibility is this.
There's a lot of people that are
pointing the finger at Dragon
and saying, you guys are wrong.
And I want you to
think about this.
From an ARIA perspective,
this is-- the last time
I stayed in London, I had
this in my hotel room.
This was a king size bed.
And so I had a sleep apparatus
with the role of king size bed.
But it was two twins with
a break in the middle.
Now, I complained.
I'm Canadian.
I don't complain.
So this was a big deal to me.
So I complain, and
I got a new room.
And I got a new bed.
And so in that bed, I
had a sleep apparatus.
And it was a king
with a class of posh.
I thought everything was great
until I dug a little further.
And I had a sleep apparatus with
the role of king size bed, two
twins with a break,
but the break
was styled to be display none.
If you remember nothing
else about ARIA,
remember that what's under the
sheets actually matters, right?
The tools and the code
that you use actually
have a huge impact on how
assistive technology can
interpret it and
work with it, right?
So thinking about
those kinds of things,
and thinking about
Dragon and how it works,
is it our job to be
responsible, even though we
have a tool like ARIA that
could really change your app?
Do we have a responsibility
to make some better choices
and actually use things
like real buttons,
or just better code in general?
My vote is yes.
But you'll find that out
in the next little while.
The other thing that people
are asking quite a lot
about these days is stuff about
detecting assistive technology.
And I want to know--
and as a developer,
you probably want to know.
I've heard it all morning.
I'd really like to
know, is this HTTP 1?
Is it HTTP 2?
Is it whatever?
Do we have the
capability to know?
And my question to you is,
if you could detect a screen
reader, what would you even
do with that information?
And there's some
real slippery slopes
that we go down when we do
that kind of stuff and say--
and I'll give you one example,
and then I'll shut up.
If we use a screen reader,
if we detect a screen reader,
we might inject a whole bunch
of extra hidden headings
that give some extra
context to a screen reader
user, which is kind
of a neat idea.
I think there's
some merit to that.
But we have to remember
that the only people that
use screen readers
aren't just blind.
There's all kinds
of people that use
screen readers for
literacy reasons.
And what's the impact on them if
they have a learning difficulty
if you're having a screen
reader read hidden headings
that they can't see
on the page, right?
So we need to think bigger.
We'll address a lot of
those kinds of questions
and more during the
panel-- thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Splendid, so we're
back to bed components instead
of web components-- not bad.
So we have a lot
of experts here.
We have seven questions
that we cut down on.
I'm supposed to get these
questions on some list here.
But that's not going
up at the moment.
What's going on there?
So-- oh, it's a tablet.
Look at that-- wonderful.
Touch interface-- and really
small and not resizable.
OK, so the first
question that we have
was a post by Andrew Betts.
But he doesn't want to
do it, so Melanie Lang.
MELANIE LANG: So it is,
what are the main offenders
of modern websites in
terms of accessibility?
What are the main offenders
of modern websites in terms
of accessibility and what
can be done to fix that?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
So the question
is, like in many
cases, web developers,
we do things that
look beautiful.
And it's a barrier
for accessibility
without us even knowing it.
So I think we're going to
send that off to Matthew.
So Matthew, what have
you seen in your day
to day browsing
that drives you nuts
although people
think it's amazing?
MATTHEW TYLEE ATKINSON:
There's a few things.
I'm sure that
there's going to be
many examples from
the rest of the panel.
But I suppose a
personal [INAUDIBLE]
for me is disabling pinch
to zoom on mobile sites.
Because it just renders them
completely useless to me,
personally.
I'm vision impaired.
I can see well enough
to use the device,
but only if I've got control
of the size of things on it.
So that's a personal one.
I think something
to bear in mind
is that somebody that's using an
assistive technology to browse
a website, say, for
example, a screen reader,
but it doesn't limit it
to just a screen reader,
they can only perceive
one element at a time.
So they go through the
whole thing one element
by the next element until
they get to the end.
And a lot of stuff
in accessibility
is providing information such
that the assistive technology
can help the user get to the
bit of the page they want
to get to as
quickly as possible.
So a lot of stuff is
about saving the user time
and making sure that the
structure of the page
is conveyed, the
semantics are conveyed,
so that the user saves time and
can get to the bit they need.
So things like lack of skip
links, lack of headings--
visually, you can see
the layout beautifully.
But there's just no
semantic information
or no structural
information there.
That's very frustrating.
Because it might actually
be-- a trend on modern sites
is towards things
like simpler language,
fewer words on the
page, more focused.
It could be really good.
But sometimes people
forget the basics,
which is, just make sure that
you use HTML headings and lists
and stuff like that,
ARIA if necessary,
excuse me, and native
controls where possible,
so things that save people time.
And there is also an
article I read recently
about things that
just have to go away,
things like when you're asked
to enter a credit card number,
and you're asked, what
type of credit card is it,
and please remember
to put the dashes in,
or don't put dashes
in, or put spaces in,
telling the user
to do this stuff.
OK, for all of us,
that's really annoying.
It shouldn't be necessary.
It's just a number.
But for accessibility, people
facing extra accessibility
barriers, that sort
of stuff, having
to go back and correct it
because the instructions
weren't necessarily
there or correct,
that can really
take a lot of time.
And it's very frustrating.
So it's going back to
using sensible HTML,
building things the
way they used to work.
I remember when
browsers were bad,
you had to use the right
HTML or otherwise they
wouldn't show up.
Because there was
no CSS to a degree.
We don't use tables for
different weird things,
but that's a different story.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: So Alice,
the shockingly innovative way
of using buttons instead of
divs with on-click handlers,
do you have to fight for
these kinds of things?
Is there a way that
developers are actually
assuming that things
work in the browser,
because the browser
fixes it for them,
and do we have to remind people
how to make things accessible?
ALICE BOXHALL: Well, yeah, if
you're using standard widgets,
by and large, it
should be accessible.
One of the big problems we
see is that people just simply
aren't using the
standard widgets.
And yeah, I'd very much
like to understand why.
My hypothesis is that you can't
style them the way you want.
So two problems-- one, you can't
style them the way you want,
or they don't behave
the way you want.
So one thing I
would like to see is
making it easier to style
custom elements the way
that we want to.
Because it's quite
difficult today.
It's a very simple
problem to solve, I think.
Secondly, make it easier for
developers to actually apply
that ARIA metadata
semantic information.
How can we get that
on the golden path
that we've been talking about
today, or the pit of success?
How can we make that
easier for developers?
I think that web
components possibly
has a big role to play here.
And I knew the team
is working on that.
Another idea would be to put
it into the developer tools
that we're all using.
So how can we expose the
accessibility information such
that it's impossible to ignore?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
Wouldn't it be better
to make it harder to
put ARIA on stuff?
ALICE BOXHALL: How do you mean?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
Well, ARIA is
a great solution
for screen readers.
But it's not right
now for Dragon.
And I know in good conscience
that we don't use ARIA
unless we know that it's going
to get really good support,
and that we look for
other ways to do things
while we're building things.
I almost would like
to make it better
to just use a button
than to add role
equals button on something.
ALICE BOXHALL: Yeah,
I completely agree.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
We're coming back
to ARIA in an extra
question later on.
And I agree.
It's a tricky thing to actually
turn something into something
that it isn't when
there is something
that is already something.
But that's a different story.
So Andrew, what do
you see as crimes
that are happening that
actually make things
inaccessible on mobile
devices when people use HTML?
I found it interesting,
for example,
the unsightly Select box that
people hated on the desktop
and always wanted to style
is awesome on mobile devices.
ANDREW RONKSLEY: Yeah,
I think on mobile,
I think Matthew's
already covered it.
The biggest one is
disabling pinch to zoom.
I've had so many users come
to me with that problem.
I'm asking you,
why does my pinch
to zoom not work
on this website?
And it comes down
to the way we use it
in the meta viewport tag.
And we're all
using it to get rid
of the 300 millisecond delay,
which-- I guess in the past,
my advice would
be to developers,
think about how you use that.
But I guess now, going
forward, I'm thinking,
should people like myself
be getting more involved
with browser vendors
to say, OK, developers
are doing this-- Is there a
way that we can kind of cater
to both scenarios?
Rather than say to
developers, don't do that,
is there a way that
we can kind of get
this fixed through bugs for
the browsers, basically?
So that's probably
the biggest one.
I think on desktop,
the best bit of advice
I could give to
you guys would be,
try using the things you
build with a keyboard only.
So just recently, I was
working with someone
who's having a huge problem
with their online banking
where they couldn't complete
a payment to somebody.
Because it was using an overlay.
And whoever had built
that had clearly
thought about the
interaction with a mouse.
Things behind the
overlay were disabled.
You couldn't click on them.
Well, because this user
was using the keyboards,
their interaction was
going wildly wrong.
And if the developer had
thought, OK, maybe what
if someone's not using
a mouse, they probably
would have found that
problem quite quickly
and could have done
something about it.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: I'm very
excited that Jake Archebald has
a question, but we have to
move onto our next topic.
[LAUGHTER]
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: So Ross
Green has a question for us.
AUDIENCE: I've got it.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
You're not Ross Green.
AUDIENCE: I'm not Ross Green.
But Ross Green is not attending.
So he asked me to
ask the question.
And I'm also going to answer it,
because I've got a microphone.
Accessibility expectations
and requirements
are vastly different depending
on the user's world region.
What more could be
done to align them?
Example-- most EU rules
say don't autoplay media.
However, most US
media will autoplay.
The answer is don't
autoplay the media.
[LAUGHTER]
AUDIENCE: And a slight
snark is, well, EU rules
could be more widely
promulgated if the EU government
websites actually
obeyed their own rules.
But anyway, what
could be done to align
the different
territories' regulations
about accessibility?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
So the good news
is that this was
hard to understand.
The question is-- basically
there's two folds to that.
There's differences between
accessibility guidelines
in Europe and in America.
And you have to--
for example, when
you do government websites,
when you do any website that
faces a lot of audience,
you have to apply with them.
You have to basically
apply the rules.
And they're different
from Europe to America.
As this world wide web
of ours is worldwide,
it's kind of confusing
to which ones to follow.
So are there ways to actually
get the legal requirements
more aligned with each other?
So maybe Sara, you could
tell us something about that.
SARAH LEWTHWAITE:The thing I
find interesting about this
question is it
refers to geography,
which I think is
really important.
Obviously, we know devices vary.
Our tools vary, and so forth.
But also, it's worth
understanding and thinking
about how disability varies
globally and internationally.
So we've already heard
a little bit about, say,
the nature of
disability and how we
might want to conceptualize it.
But it's worth also, I think,
recognizing that disability
means different things in
different parts of the world.
Levels and types of
disabilities vary
depending on where you
are by locale, region,
as well as by nation.
So personally, I think
there's a bit of attention
in terms of picking a standard
to apply in all situations.
I think the great thing about
WCAG is that it's a guideline.
And when it's applied
as a guideline,
it allows perhaps for more of
that indigenous reflection--
the expertise of
local developers
to come into play as well.
So they can account, maybe,
for indigenous populations
with low literacy levels.
Or perhaps you have less
assistive technologies.
At the moment, there's
not a great deal
of data globally in terms
of the kinds of technologies
that disabled people are using.
But obviously,
WCAG in particular
is being picked up
because the UN convention
on the rights of persons
with disabilities
is being taken up by
more and more countries.
And people have this
kind of policy vacuum
in terms of information and
communication technologies
that are referred to
in the UN convention.
And people want to make sure
that the policy is picking that
up.
So WCAG is being
applied more and more
as the kind of
verbatim standard.
But I think there is
a bit of attention
in terms of knowing what that
means, say, in Nepal or Uganda,
or more regionally.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: It
is kind of confusing.
Because being an ex-German
developer and now living here,
there's different guidelines
even in Europe from country
to country.
So maybe in point
of the RNIB, I guess
you work with a lot of
people that come to say,
I don't want to be sued.
What can I do for people
with disabilities--
which is the awful, awful
question we keep getting.
What is your answer to that?
How do you get people to
understand that just applying
with the law does
not necessarily
make an accessible interface?
ANDREW RONKSLEY:
So I think for me,
there is a business case
behind accessibility,
which we'll often talk
to companies about,
around some potential
SEO benefits,
potentially opening
up to new markets.
And I think when I first
got into that sector,
or this sector,
sorry, I really did
believe in that business case.
And I still do.
But at the same time, it's
a little bit theoretical.
Because you don't have
many cases to back it up.
So Derek's point about, what
if we could detect a screen
reader-- I think
I'm with you, Derek.
I don't think it's a good
idea to detect a screen
reader if you're
going to do something
with that information
in terms of the website.
But I'd really like that
feature as part of analytics
so that we can say, OK, we made
some changes to the website.
And we can now see, perhaps,
screen reader users are not
dropping out midway through
the process of checking out,
or something like that.
So I'd really like
that kind of stuff.
Because we don't have
many good case studies.
So while we can say, yeah,
maybe you can get more visitors,
we don't have any figures
really to back that up.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Yeah, Derek, you
used to work on that
for a long time as well,
like back in [INAUDIBLE] days
and things with like-- I mean,
we had guidelines
that said, you have
to have a certain kind of access
key on the page, for example.
And that was unenforceable
or usable, really.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: Yeah,
there's a lot of things
in-- you have to remember
that especially when you
talk about guidelines,
accessibility guidelines,
and then talk about giving
them the force of legislation,
you're taking something that
is designed to be necessarily
fuzzy and putting it
into something that
becomes absolute
black and white.
And I would even
respond to Bruce.
We all said-- everybody laughed.
He said, well, the simple
answer is do not autoplay.
And I would counter that
by saying that autoplay
can actually be useful for
certain types of people,
including people that have
mobility difficulties.
It may be actually
much easier for them
if you do autoplay so that when
you go to a new video page,
it actually does play for them.
They don't have to try and
work hard to actually get
it to play.
So when we're
embedding a YouTube
video or a whatever
video on a site of ours,
we always recommend,
have it embedded
and don't autoplay that one.
But also, link to the
YouTube page outside.
Because then, the
user has a preference
to set it up so that my videos
on YouTube always autoplay.
So we're kind of catering
for both things there.
So the edicts like,
do not autoplay,
they sound really good.
But they don't necessarily
always make sense.
Autoplay is bad for everyone
except for the people
that need it.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
OK, we have a question
from Christopher Emery.
CHRISTOPHER EMERY: I just
wanted to kind of chime
in just with regards to
going about our differences
between EU law and
US law-- so yeah,
the difference between
the EU and US law.
Just with regards
to my experience,
I found that it's actually
even more complicated.
Because the requirements
suggest we don't just
live in the government
legislature.
For example, when you
get to a client who
reaches a level where
they're now rolling out
in different markets,
they will then
have their own accessibility
requirements layer
within that which typically
will be based on one market,
even though they're
rolling out local.
I mean, that's my
experience, even
though they're
rolling out globally.
So we've actually
encounter situations
whereby we're using,
in one example, the EU
accessibility guidelines,
even though we're rolling out
in the UAE or in China
and things like that.
And that becomes a very
weird, strange situation.
Because the document
a lot of times
that the accessibility was kind
of created at the companies in
was, check off a
box to say, yes,
we have accessibility
guidelines.
But they didn't roll it
out to the market level.
So I just wanted to say, on top
of the government legislature,
there's the actual
corporate layer as well.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: It's a
super tricky all-in-all problem.
And the issue is a lot of
people try to sell accessibility
as something you could be
sued if you don't do it right.
But then, we don't have the
answer how to do it right.
It's like getting
someone's attention
by kicking them in the shins.
Yeah, you have their attention
but not their support.
So Shane Hudson has
a question for us
on this, not the
kicking but general.
He's there, the man
in the striped shirt.
SHANE HUDSON: So
are the WCAG-- I
have trouble saying
that-- guidelines
redundant in a world of
smartphones and tablets?
Are accessibility laws trying
to fix an outdated world?
It's kind of been touched upon.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah, kind
of-- so basically, the question
is, the WCAG guidelines
define a lot of stuff,
for example, keyboard
accessibility, which
is on a touch device a bit
of a weird thing to enforce.
So do they need to be upgraded?
Do we need to think about
different form factors?
I think the best would be
just-- Sarah, what do you think?
SARAH LEWTHWAITE:
I think this is
a problem with the
nature of standards.
And there's quite a
lot of interesting
writing about what
standards do outside
of development communities.
So for example, they
offer a fixed perspective,
which is what I think
some of us are struggling
with in the sense
that disability
is so heterogenic that
it needs to sort of be
as inclusive as possible.
And a standard rather than
a guideline is difficult.
So I think, yeah, there are
these problems about how
it keeps abreast
of new developments
which we can't
necessarily foresee.
But I think one of the things
which I find interesting
is that standards also
convey certain values.
And as I say, when they're
being picked up internationally,
it's useful to
recognize that they also
promote the rights of
people with disabilities.
And they promote their
access to technology
and raise a kind
of whole argument
about human rights, disability
rights, which isn't necessarily
reflected in all the communities
that these standards touch
upon.
So that's one of
the things, I think,
which we need to also
keep front and center.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Matthew, in terms of gaming,
the Paciello Group does a great
job in explaining on their blog
how to apply WCAG guidelines,
how to apply best technologies.
And most people start
with a blank canvas
with no keyboard accessibility
whatsoever for their game.
So do you think that
the WCAG is outdated?
Are we fixing the web from 1997
rather than the web from 2005?
MATTHEW TYLEE ATKINSON: A
couple of things-- first of all,
the gaming stuff is
separate to my TPG stuff.
But I'm very happy to
talk about it, of course.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah,
don't get fired over it.
MATTHEW TYLEE ATKINSON: Sarah
made a really good point
last night, which I just
wanted to make sure came up,
which is that a
screen reader could
be a person next to
you reading what's
on the screen in a
particular place.
You were saying about
different countries have
different social views of
accessibility and different
access to ATs.
And therefore, screen
reader detection
would have to encompass
reading glasses
and people sat next
to you as well,
and both of these at
the same time, perhaps.
Anyway, moving on to answering
the actual question--
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Thanks.
[LAUGHTER]
MATTHEW TYLEE ATKINSON:
A couple of points-- one
of them is that if
you look at WCAG--
and there's a lot to read.
But the central point
that it's trying
to get across, and the
values that Sarah mentioned,
they're actually
written down in there.
They are the POUR principles
that your content needs
to be Perceivable, Operable,
Understandable, and Robust.
And you can look
up what those are,
but you get the general idea.
You can apply those kinds
of principles to any medium.
Now, some of the
WCAG stuff might
be less appropriate
on mobile, some
of the very specific
technical stuff.
But a lot of the guidelines--
in fact, all of them--
are written with those
four principles in mind.
And you can apply
those to any medium.
So in terms of
game accessibility,
that is about making sure
that you know what information
is important to someone to
be able to play this game.
What is the best way to present
it to the particular audience
that you're thinking about?
In our case, it
was blind people.
So it was making a lot of
visual cues auditory instead.
Understandable--
well, it's got to be
understandable to be able
to be enjoyable in the case
of a game.
And in the case of
a banking website,
it's got to be understandable
in order to be able to use it.
And robust-- that covers
the kind of security
and reliability stuff on
the website side of things.
And on the game
side of things, you
don't want it to crash
just before you're
going to complete the level.
So very briefly, that is
a very glib high level
trying to demonstrate
you can apply
these things to multiple areas.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
So Alice, when
you put that into the Developer
Tools Accessibility panel--
those of us who have been
in accessibility long enough
remember Bobby Approved and
people putting triple A badges
on their website,
which ironically
didn't have an alternative text.
[LAUGHTER]
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: What
are the testing tools
that you have in there?
Do you get, this doesn't
apply with that guideline?
Or is it more of a
transcription of the perceivable
and-- the ideas of it?
Because it's easy for
a developer to say,
oh, I'm now accessible,
because I tick all the boxes.
But what does it really mean?
What kind of a test
would help people there?
ALICE BOXHALL: So one
point that I always
try to make with the
accessibility developer tool
is that passing a mechanical
accessibility audit
does not in any way
guarantee that you're
completely accessible.
It's only looking at
the things that we
can test programmatically,
which is a subset.
That said, what it does look at
are things like color contrast.
It tries to look
for click targets
and suggests that you should use
an ARIA role and a [INAUDIBLE].
It also looks for
valid ARIA use.
Yeah, so those are
sort of the main things
that it's looking at.
Yeah, but one point I did
want to make just to follow on
is that the robust in
perceivable, optimal,
understandable, robust
actually encapsulates
working in different modalities,
which actually implies that it
should work on
different devices.
So when we're talking about
mobile, tablet, even something
like Google Glass
or TV or a Leap,
robust encapsulates all of that.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Good,
Matthew, you had a question,
or you're pulling it?
She covered everything you do?
I just want to show that
somebody from Google
has something to say
about accessibility.
MATTHEW: No, I was going to
ask, since you're all there--
[LAUGHTER]
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
As I have you here.
MATTHEW: So I once
made a comment
about changing an outline in
CSS and basically changing
the background
color for the focus.
I got slated immediately
on [INAUDIBLE] for this.
It's not accessible.
And I'm fine with that.
And I'm kind of like, well,
what is the right way to do it?
And there's a part of
me that's like, well,
can't I apply filters to
my site that say, this
is what a screen
reader will see?
Or what should I be doing in my
workflow that basically helps
me as a developer make my
site more accessible, I guess?
Are there tools?
Is there something
you'd recommend?
Or is it just a case of,
use native components,
use the accessibility
thing, and use that?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: So
using-- 75% of all statistics
are made up.
So you can get probably--
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: 2 out
of 7 people know that.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: Yeah,
you can get 80 to 90%
of the way accessible by testing
everything with a keyboard.
And you have to
manually test that.
Because that's interaction.
There's no way to test
it other than that.
But dealing with straight up
good, solid semantic markup--
just writing good HTML and not
screwing up keyboard access
gets you 80 to 90%
of the way there,
straight up, honest truth.
Now, using it with a keyboard
is going to show you stuff
about your outline
changes, right?
You're going to go
through and you're
going to say, shit,
I can see the cursor.
I have no idea where I am.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: I have to
stop this cursing right now,
actually.
And this is a longer
topic that we could go on.
So I'm moving on to
actually Ed Soden, which
is actually covering this a bit.
So Ed Soden has a question.
ED SODEN: I'm reading this one.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah,
Mr. Snowden, ah, Soden--
was I not allowed to say it?
ED SODEN: So as developers, we
often try and make our sites
work well for screen readers.
But is there anything else we
can do besides screen readers
when we're designing our
sites to make them better
for accessibility?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: That is an
incredibly interesting question
that we haven't quite covered
yet, or just did, or tried.
So Andrew, what do you think?
The big screen reader
debate, every developer
I talk to like, it works
from the screen reader,
because that's something I can
test with-- what else should we
be thinking about?
ANDREW RONKSLEY: No,
it's a great question.
And I could make up some stats
now, but I'm not going to.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Go ahead.
ANDREW RONKSLEY:
In the UK, there's
around 2 million
people that have
some kind of
sight-related issue.
And the vast majority
of those have
some residual useful vision.
So the thing you can
take away from that
is quite a small percentage
of those 2 million people
are using the screen reader.
The rest of them are making
some kind of visual adaptations
to the page.
And I think you can extrapolate
that to around the world
issues.
So I think around the
world it's something
like 280 million people have
some sight-related issue.
So things that you
can do that are not
related to a screen
reader-- and this kind of
applies to all of us.
You think about using a
website out and about,
color contrast, the
size of your font,
how much white space
is between controls.
So when he's using
a screen magnifier--
I'll see sites sometimes
where there's a form.
And maybe, there's two buttons
at the end, Next and Previous.
They're really far
apart from each other.
If someone's using
a screen magnifier--
I think Matt kind of
touched on this before.
It's a little bit different
with a screen magnifier.
But you see a portion of
the screen at any one time.
Those of you-- everyone
pretty much has Macs here.
You'll all have a screen
magnifier built-in, Windows
as well.
So you can try this
out if you want.
Another way to think about it is
if you imagine sliding a credit
card around your screen, just
imagine that was your viewport.
So if the buttons are far apart,
there's potential to miss them.
So just that kind of stuff
is worth thinking about.
And that's nothing to do
with screen readers at all.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah,
and that's a very good point.
I love the credit card thing.
I didn't think about that yet.
My favorite is always when
people-- now everything
comes with screen
readers, which is
great for accessibility
for people.
But it also is kind of bad.
Because developers think they
know how these things work now.
The amount of people I see using
a screen reader with their eyes
open is amazing.
And that defeats the purpose.
Because of course you can
understand your system.
So James [INAUDIBLE]
has a question,
or was that already
about the last topic?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, that was
about the last topic.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: OK, good,
so do you have another one?
MELANIE LANG: I was
wondering if maybe we
need to be more creative
and maybe go back to roots
and test-- I don't know--
[INAUDIBLE], for example,
the test set aside
for old people.
I think they put
Vaseline on glasses
and put gloves on to
simulate arthrosis.
Yeah, so maybe, do we need
to go back and just do that,
maybe, and go this extra mile?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Testing
this kind of way works.
I gave people broken
mice to actually use
the website, for example, with.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: Yeah,
there's tons of things
that you can do like
that to simulate
different types of disability.
And I believe that
all those things
are great emulating what a
user with a particular type
of disability would be.
You want to see what
it's like for somebody
that has a tremor in
their hand to use a mouse,
turn your mouse sideways and try
to manipulate it on the screen,
or use the wrong hand.
There's all kinds of
things that you can do.
One thing that I would point
out-- and I think those
are great things to do.
The WCAG guidelines are designed
specifically because we know--
and I say "we" like I was
involved or something.
But we can't all go and
test with real people.
And so those guidelines
are all in place
because they're based on
years and years of people
actually working with
people with disabilities.
So those are absolutely
valuable and useful.
And everybody should do it.
But if you can't
do that, then you
have guidelines as your sort
of first point of advice.
And absolutely go back to it.
But if you can't, just feel
at least partially confident
that those guidelines
are there to replace
the fact that everybody
can't do that.
ALICE BOXHALL: Actually-- oh.
SARAH LEWTHWAITE: I
completely understand
where you're coming from.
But I also feel that's a bit
of a cop-out in terms of-- I
think sometimes
standards step in,
and people want to learn
the standard because that's
the easy thing to do.
And they want to turn the mouse
and do that when sometimes,
they have disabled populations
sitting right under their nose.
So for example, in
the university sector,
there are hundreds
of disabled students
at King's College, London.
How many are involved
in testing our systems?
They're right there.
We could easily
engage with them.
So I think it's important
to be creative and think
about drawing people
into this conversation.
So if you're doing
usability testing at large,
don't be afraid of contacting,
say, disabled people's
organizations or
putting a call out
for people to get involved
in testing your systems.
Because they will
give you much richer
feedback about how
your interfaces work.
And they're going
to bring up things
that you just would not
have imagined possible.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: It
would be interesting to see
what kind of-- I mean, you
can take the glasses away
from your colleagues,
for example.
Or you can read out
your text on the screen
to somebody on the phone.
If it then makes sense, you
know it's an accessible text.
If you need to think to see to
understand it, then you don't.
It would be
interesting to set up
a wiki or something about these
little accessibility hacks
to simulate different things.
But outreach to real
people with disabilities--
hard core users that know how
to use something is amazing.
I learned most working next
to a PHP developer, who
was blind, for like four years.
And that was just incredible.
Because he coded faster
than me, which is annoying.
Now, with a sense of dread,
Patrick Lauke has a question.
[LAUGHTER]
PATRICK LAUKE: No, I
haven't got a question.
I've got a lengthy statement.
No, just a quick note--
I wanted to pick up just
on something that was mentioned
at the start there about,
I did something to my
outline, and I was immediately
jumped upon by an
accessibility lynch mob.
The dirty kind of truth, even
within the Paciello Group--
I can say that
hopefully openly--
is that you get three
accessibility experts,
you get five different opinions.
We disagree even on sometimes
very fundamental things,
like very first
guideline of WCAG,
having appropriate alt text.
We could have discussions
for days about,
what is the most appropriate
alt text for this?
And you'll get fierce debates
in the accessibility community
about, every image should
have this kind of alt,
or no image should have alt.
And so I just wanted to
kind of temper the whole--
when you get some
people jumping on you
and immediately shouting,
oh, that's not accessible,
they may be right.
Or they may not be right.
And as Derek mentioned
towards the start,
it is not a binary thing.
It's not always, it's either
accessible or inaccessible.
There are certainly
things that you
can do that completely
screw everybody over that
can't see the screen
perfectly and use their mouse.
But beyond that, there's lots
of shades of grey on that one.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah,
also, stop arguing on Twitter.
140 characters are not
good to actually bring
emotions or facts in.
We've got [INAUDIBLE]
here, because Christopher
has said too many
things already.
AUDIENCE: So basically, I
did a bit of a stat check.
And I checked that there
are about 2.7 million people
in Britain who have
color blindness.
And I haven't seen that
mention in this talk yet.
Do we consider people who are
color blind to be disabled,
or are there any things
that people in general
can do to improve their pages
to improve the looks for color
blind?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
Did you say stable?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: I met a
few unstable color blind people
in my past.
I think your tools,
Alice-- you talked
about the color distance.
But also, color blindness
is one of the simulators
in there, isn't it?
ALICE BOXHALL: No, not
in my tool, actually.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Well, that can be fixed.
ALICE BOXHALL: Sure, you want
to send me a [INAUDIBLE]?
There are extensions
certainly for Chrome, probably
for other browsers
as well, which
will simulate color blindness.
And contrast ratio has a color
blindness implication in that,
say, if you have red on white,
if you view that as grey,
it may not be a high
enough contrast ratio.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Derek, you were twitching?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
A little-- there's
a great tool,
Color Oracle, which
you can install at
the desktop level.
And it will
transform everything.
And you can simulate things.
Two challenges with
color blindness-- and I'm
saying this as a very
blanket statement.
So there's probably
more challenges.
But one is a color
contrast issue.
The other is the way
that you're using color
to convey information, right?
If you're relying on color, then
you need to-- we're not saying,
don't rely on color.
Use color as much as you want.
But use other mechanisms
to indicate things as well.
So it could be that you're
using pattern with color.
Or instead of just
using color, think
of a line graph that has
a legend at the bottom.
Instead of putting a
legend at the bottom,
change your graph so that each
one of the individual legend
pieces is actually
up beside the line
so that you can then
follow the line.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: This also
ties into internationalization.
My favorite is when people
just use red as a warning,
whereas in China,
it means good luck.
Good luck, we lost
your emails, wonderful.
[LAUGHTER]
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Oh
god, lots of questions.
So let's have one here,
the man in the loud shirt.
AUDIENCE: Sorry about my shirt.
I was just thinking,
we've talked
a lot today about
web performance
and things like that, and about,
how does the whole performance
piece fit into accessibility?
We'll see one kind of coming
to mind as things being too
fast where we're constantly
working to speed things up.
Is there cases in
accessibility where we actually
need to slow it down?
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: So
I have a few thoughts
when listening to all the
other performance things.
And one of the
things that I heard
was, what's in the
first 15 kilobytes?
And I started to think, what
should be in the first 15
kilobytes for somebody
that has a particular type
of disability?
And I don't know the
answer to that question.
I think that's a great one.
I'm not sure about
slowing things down.
Most technology, most
screen reading technology
and other technologies, they
work on top of browsers.
They're not their own
thing, generally speaking.
AUDIENCE: Where I'm
kind of coming from
is about the thought
of perception,
if something changes on
the screen too quickly,
and it becomes harder for
visually impaired people
to actually detect that change.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: So are
you talking about in response
to some event that's
happened on the page,
or like an initial load?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Is it more
like UX problems, isn't it?
I think like drop-down--
AUDIENCE: Something
like a carousel.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, just a
case of stuff changing,
either naturally in a carousel,
which is kind of automated,
or in response to an action.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE:
So on a carousel,
for example, if
it autoplays, you
have to be able to turn it off.
And you have to be able
to start it up again.
So I'm not sure that that's
really slowing it down
from a performance perspective.
But you should definitely
allow for somebody
to manually go
through the carousel
if you have to have
one on your page.
We also do things like if
the carousel container-- when
you detect keyboard usage
within that container,
we automatically
stop it from rotating
so that it immediately becomes
a manual thing if you're
moving through it
with a keyboard
so that you basically take
a screen reader that's
on that content.
If it's suddenly whisked away,
quite often what happens,
if the node is just slidden--
"slidden," nice word.
If the node slides
out to the side,
that's different than if
the node is destroyed.
And in some of these cases,
screen reader focus is lost.
And they have to start over
at the top of the page.
So that's something where
we want to kind of give them
a little bit more control and--
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: I think
we're running the danger here
of getting into implementations
and explaining to you how
to do a certain widget.
And we are open to
discussion for that.
It would be wonderful to ask,
get a few questions sorted.
And then we could
answer offline.
Because [INAUDIBLE] would
be like, do it like this,
or do it like that.
ALICE BOXHALL: To answer the
broader question about timing,
there's language in WCAG about
how long things should take,
how much time you
should allow for things.
So that maybe gets a bit
more at your question.
And also, to me, it raises a
bit of a broader question, which
is, I'm curious how many
web developers have even
looked look at WCAG here?
Quite a few-- cool.
To me, it seems like it's
a great set of guidelines
for creating good
user interfaces.
So for example, things like
allowing error correction
in forms-- do we
not all want that?
Do we not all want the form
to lose all of our data
if we make a single mistake?
So yeah, I think the web
would be better for everybody
if we all followed WCAG.
And this is an
example of something
which is in there which we could
learn about just from reading
the guidelines.
And of course, there's more.
There's stuff
that's not in there.
Or there's stuff that
needs more information.
But it's a really
great place to start.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: OK, we're
running out of time here a bit.
So we're skipping one of the
questions that I've ceded,
sadly enough.
We have one from
Aralia Moser here.
ARALIA MOSER: OK,
you skipped a person.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: I
skipped Dan Appelquist.
He can deal with it.
ARALIA MOSER: OK,
so I'm wondering,
how do you prioritize
accessibility in your workflow?
And right now, it
seems that reactive
is something you need to do.
So how can we make it
just the thing to do?
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN: It's
the old question of,
where's the
accessibility plug-in
that I can put at the
end of my workflow?
How do you get accessibility
into the workflow
from the very beginning in
a cutthroat environment that
has not much time?
Derek.
DEREK FEATHERSTONE: It's
got to be moved earlier
in the process.
If it gets to the
end, and you're
finding accessibility issues
for the first time in QA
or as you're preparing
it for QA, it's too late.
It has to be done
at the design level.
And I think if you focus very
loosely on design, development,
and QA as kind of
three important pieces,
not thinking about the business
side-- that's important.
But the focusing
on the transition
points I think is critical.
So having designers talk with
developers and spec-ing things
out-- not like as in
the spec, but here's
what my intent is
with this design.
And so a design can
specify things like,
here's how the
keyboard flow should
work for this particular
widget, or for this page.
Even working on it
together, here's
the most logical source order.
Looking at this wire frame
and the hierarchy of content,
here's the most logical
source order for that.
And having that stuff passed
all the way down the chain
is, to me, one of the
most critical things that
would help address that
so that it happens earlier
and we don't get to the
end and say, I forgot.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
Andrew, what do you think?
ANDREW RONKSLEY: This is
someone else's point of view.
I can't remember
who exactly it was.
But it was talking about how
the first time you do something,
it is difficult, and it
takes you longer to do it.
So if you guys can remember the
first time you built a website,
it was probably hard.
And it took you a long time.
The first time you
built a responsive site,
your mind might have
been a bit blown
like, this is taking
me a long time.
But then, the next time
you do it, it's easier.
The next time you do
it, again, it's easier.
And then, it just
becomes normal.
And it's kind of like
that with accessibility.
It only seems hard
because it's not
something you'll do day to day.
But if you do invest a
bit of time and effort
into doing it a couple of times,
your workflow will change.
And it just will become
something you do naturally.
I can't remember whose
opinion that was.
But I really liked
it when I read it.
MATTHEW TYLEE ATKINSON: I
completely agree with that.
And I completely agree
with various things
that have been said
before, like for example,
just try it out with a
keyboard as you're doing it.
The most important thing
is, as Derek pointed out,
to do it from the very start,
from the design process.
But you're all
going to be dealing
with stuff that already exists.
And there are some
things-- I think
Alice mentioned
accessibility testing.
You can't do it
all mechanically.
But some of it you can.
And perhaps this is going
to sound odd coming from me.
Because I'm very much reliant
on me going to look at a site
and finding accessibility
problems with it.
But there are a
whole range of things
that you can test mechanically.
For example, does every
image have an Alt attribute?
It's a very simple thing.
Now, one of my
colleagues is working on
or has developed a
tool, an API in fact.
It's going to be in beta soon.
It's called [INAUDIBLE]-- which
can perform these tests that
can be automated.
And it will go away
and perform them.
And because it's a
command line thing,
you can make it part
of your build process.
So if there were two
biggest things I would say
is perhaps look at that,
see what it can do for you.
Because it can be part
of your build process.
A human being does not
need to waste their time
on some of this stuff.
And the other
thing is, make sure
that you can challenge yourself
to, like Christian said,
take away the mouse
for a while and see
if you can still use your site.
Some stuff like
that you can really
reduce the amount
of time and effort
it takes by making it
part of your process.
And as much as
possible, please do
try and consider it
from the design stage,
from the absolute get-go.
And then, there's the
other sorts of advice
that you've heard just generally
sprinkled through about testing
things with a keyboard
and stuff like that.
SARAH LEWTHWAITE: I'd
like to just interject
a little bit of sociology.
Because I know that
part of the issue
is that it has to be a team
effort across your entire team.
Some people are going to value
accessibility more than others.
And I think it's trying
to position accessibility
as part of a norm,
which is understanding
that disabled people
aren't an out group.
They're part of your in group.
So at the moment, there's
a term, aversive disablism.
So most people believe
they're quite liberal.
They don't discriminate
against disabled people.
But if you're designing
for your group,
and that group doesn't
include disabled people,
then you might as well be
making disablist judgments.
Because you're still excluding.
The outputs are still the same.
So in that sense, it's
important to sort of expand
the concept of who
a normal user is
to include disabled
people of who we know.
CHRISTIAN HEILMANN:
OK, we have to wrap up.
So I have to thank the panel.
And I am incredibly excited
about all of your interest.
Because having worked
in accessibility
and having to shout
at people for years
to consider
accessibility, it's great
that there's a new way there.
It's kind of
disheartening that we
have to remind people
about something.
There seems to be
a communication
gap between the accessibility
evangelists and the developers
out there.
And a lot of things
can be repeated
and have been said a few times.
So I'm really happy about this.
So take this idea, take this
enthusiasm about it out there,
and pester as many
people as possible
who know about accessibility.
And if you get grumpy
answers, as Patrick said,
we're just people, too.
So that just happens.
So thanks very much again,
and thanks everyone.
[APPLAUSE]